
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">575</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">parasitvect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101462774</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &amp; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10734124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10734124.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10734124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10734124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38124152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-023-06075-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6075</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RETRACTED ARTICLE: csi-miR-96-5p delivered by <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> extracellular vesicles promotes intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma proliferation and migration via the ferroptosis-related PTEN/SLC7A11/GPX4 axis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names initials="LJ">Li-Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names initials="JG">Ji-Gang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="YX">Yong-Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="JX">Ji-Xue</given-names></name><address><email>jixue@jlu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/034haf133</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430605.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1758 4110</institution-id><institution>Department of Pediatric Surgery, </institution><institution>The First Hospital of Jilin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changchun, 130021 Jilin China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00js3aw79</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.64924.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 5735</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory for Diagnosis and Treatment of Severe Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, Key Laboratory for Zoonosis Research of the Ministry of Education, Institute of Zoonosis, College of Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>Jilin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changchun, 130062 Jilin China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/034haf133</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430605.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1758 4110</institution-id><institution>Department of Hepatobiliary and Pancreatic Surgery, General Surgery Center, </institution><institution>The First Hospital of Jilin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changchun, 130021 Jilin China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">424971</issue-id><elocation-id>465</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-23 00:25:13.430"><day>23</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13071_2023_Article_6075.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="17" journal-id="Parasit Vectors" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11256693"><article-title>Retraction Note: csi-miR-96-5p delivered by <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> extracellular vesicles promotes intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma proliferation and migration via the ferroptosis-related PTEN/SLC7A11/GPX4 axis</article-title><volume>17</volume><date><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><elocation-id>309</elocation-id><source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-024-06408-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11256693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39026290</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>) is classified as a group 1 carcinogen and can cause intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma (ICC). <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> extracellular vesicles (CsEVs) play important roles in mediating communication between parasitic helminths and humans. Ferroptosis is a novel cell death mechanism that is mainly induced by lipid peroxidation and iron overload. However, the role of CsEVs in the regulation of ferroptosis in ICC remains unclear. This study aimed to explore the role of <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-secreted miR-96-5p (csi-miR-96-5p) delivered by CsEVs in ICC progression and ferroptosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Tissue samples were collected from ICC patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection (<italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC) or without <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection (NC-ICC). The levels of csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN gene were determined by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) and western blotting, and survival analysis was performed. CsEVs were isolated and identified by ultracentrifugation and transmission electron microscopy. Lentiviruses were used to establish stable cell lines with csi-miR-96-5p mimic expression, PTEN overexpression (PTEN-EXO) and PTEN CRISPR/Cas9-based knockout (PTEN-KO) and their respective negative controls. Cell proliferation was assessed by performing Cell Counting Kit-8 assays in vitro and in a tumor xenograft model in vivo, and cell migration was assessed by performing Transwell assays. Erastin is used to induce ferroptosis. Ferroptosis levels were evaluated using biomarkers.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">High csi-miR-96-5p and low PTEN expression was observed in <italic toggle="yes">CS-</italic>ICC tissues and was associated with poor overall survival. csi-miR-96-5p was highly enriched in CsEVs and was taken up by ICC cells. csi-miR-96-5p mimics or PTEN-KO significantly promoted the growth and migration of ICC cells in vitro and in vivo, whereas PTEN-EXO exerted the opposite effect. Mechanistically, csi-miR-96-5p mimics or PTEN-KO inhibited erastin-induced ferroptosis, including reducing the accumulation of Fe<sup>2+</sup>, lipid reactive oxygen species, and malondialdehyde, increasing the GSH/GSSG ratio and levels of SLC7A11 and GPX4, whereas PTEN-EXOs exerted the opposite effect.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">csi-miR-96-5p delivered by CsEVs reduced ferroptosis by regulating the expression of the PTEN/SLC7A11/GPX4 axis, thereby promoting ICC proliferation and migration. For the first time to our knowledge, we found that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> miRNAs could promote tumor development through ferroptosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p id="Par05">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" id="MO50" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Figa_HTML.jpg"/></p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13071-023-06075-7.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic></kwd><kwd>Extracellular vesicle</kwd><kwd>miRNA</kwd><kwd>Cholangiocarcinoma</kwd><kwd>Ferroptosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The Science and Technology Development Program of Jilin Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>20200201584JC</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">Intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma (ICC) is the second most common primary liver cancer, accounting for 10–20% of all primary liver cancers. Its incidence and mortality rates have increased in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. ICC is characterized by insidious onset, difficulty in early diagnosis, high malignancy rate, rapid progression, and poor overall prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Multiple factors can lead to ICC occurrence, among which liver fluke infection (<italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> CS</italic>) is defined as a group 1 carcinogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Recent clinical studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] indicate that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection not only promotes the occurrence of cholangiocarcinoma but also increases its malignant progression.</p><p id="Par12">Extracellular vesicles (EVs) are all structures that cells release into their environment. Considering that these “cellular trash cans” have no biological functions, EVs are now recognized as an important medium for intercellular communication by transferring molecular signals, including proteins, nucleic acids, and lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. EVs play multiple roles in maintaining normal physiological functions and are involved in the pathological environment, particularly in tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that parasite-derived EVs, especially the abundant miRNA cargo in EVs, can be taken up by host cells and notably affect the disease phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">As a new cancer treatment strategy, ferroptosis has not been reported between <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> and host cells, but it may be critical for understanding liver fluke-host interactions. Ferroptosis is a type of programmed cell death first discovered in 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Unlike apoptosis, necrosis, and autophagy, ferroptosis is driven by iron-dependent lipid peroxidation. The disruption of iron and lipid metabolism induces reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and accumulation, leading to mitochondrial damage, membrane integrity breakdown, and ultimately cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Alterations in the ferroptosis regulatory network can lead to the development of various diseases including cancer. Evidence suggests that ferroptosis is suppressed in cancer cells, allowing them to survive and progress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Whether parasitic worms can cause or inhibit ferroptosis in host cells and the related molecular mechanisms is yet to be explored but is crucial for understanding the malignant progression of tumors caused by <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>.</p><p id="Par14">Studies have found that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-secreted miR-96-5p (csi-miR-96-5p) is highly expressed in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> adult worms and <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-secreted EVs (CsEVs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In the present study, we performed quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) to analyze the abundance of csi-miR-96-5p and western blotting (WB) to analyze the expression of PTEN in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC tissues and studied the molecular mechanism by which csi-miR-96-5p promotes ICC malignant transformation, providing new insights into the prevention and treatment of ICC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Human tissue samples</title><p id="Par15">The preoperative diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> mainly relies on stool microscopy, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay, or endoscopy. Fresh liver and intrahepatic bile duct specimens were collected from ICC patients with (<italic toggle="yes">CS-</italic>ICC group) and without (NC-ICC group) <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection during partial hepatectomy at the First Hospital of Jilin University. Tumor tissues and adjacent normal tissues were preserved. Three patients without the disease who underwent hepatic segment resection because of trauma were also enrolled. The clinical and pathological characteristics were recorded. This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the First Hospital of Jilin University (permit no. 19K041-001) and conducted in strict accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from all the participants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Animals</title><p id="Par16">Six-week-old nude mice were purchased from the Animal Center of Jilin University and bred in a specific pathogen-free animal laboratory. All the animals were provided with food and water ad libitum. The animal study protocol was approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of the First Hospital of Jilin University (permit no. 20210526).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par17">A human ICC cell line (HuCCT1 cells) and normal bile duct cells were purchased from the cell bank of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China). The cells were cultured in the RPMI-1640 medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 100 U/ml penicillin/streptomycin solution (Sigma) at 37 °C in a humidified incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>miRNA transfection, gene knockdown, and gene overexpression</title><p id="Par18">csi-miR-96-5p mimics and a negative control (Shanghai Genchem Co., Ltd.) were transfected into cells using Lipofectamine 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.). To create stable cell lines, recombinant lentivirus (LV) vectors containing csi-miR-96-5p mimics (Shanghai Genchem Co., Ltd.), a PTEN overexpression plasmid (PTEN-EXO) (Sino Biological, China), and a PTEN CRISPR/Cas9 based knockout (PTEN-KO) plasmid (Shanghai Genchem Co., Ltd.) were constructed. HuCCT1 cells were infected with the above recombinant LV vectors and selected in the presence of 1.5 μg/ml puromycin (Sigma) over 14 days. To explore the effects of csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN on ferroptosis, HuCCT1 cells were treated with the ferroptosis activator erastin (1 μM) (MCE, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>CsEV isolation and identification</title><p id="Par19">The method of CsEV separation is as described above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Eight weeks after <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection, Sprague-Dawley rats were killed under deep ether anesthesia, the liver was removed, and adult worms were collected from the bile canals. The worms were washed five times with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing 1% penicillin/streptomycin at 37 °C and then incubated in the RPMI-1640 medium for 24 h. The supernatant from the first 2 h of culture was discarded as it contained many host components. CsEVs were isolated by differential centrifugation. The culture solution was pooled and centrifuged for 15 min at 3000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> and then at 10,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 30 min to remove cellular debris, worm eggs, and sperm, after which it was filtered through a 0.22-µm filter (Steriflip; Millipore). Finally, the supernatant was centrifuged twice at 100,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 90 min, and the cell pellets, which contained CsEVs, were resuspended in 50 µl PBS and stored at − 80 °C.</p><p id="Par20">Anti-CD63 and anti-TSG101 protein markers of CsEVs were detected by WB. For transmission electron microscopy (TEM) characterization, CsEVs were placed on a mesh in thin layers, to which a 2% uranyl acetate aqueous solution was added, and the mesh was subsequently dried overnight. To verify whether CsEVs could be taken up by HuCCT1 cells, CsEVs were labeled with a PKH67 green fluorescent labeling kit (Sigma) and cultured with HuCCT1 cells for 24 h. The cells were then observed using a confocal microscope (FV1200, Olympus).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Dual-luciferase reporter activity assay</title><p id="Par21">Dual-luciferase assay was performed according to standard protocol (Promega, USA). The luciferase gene was cloned downstream of the wild-type or mutant region of the PTEN and co-transfected into HuCCT1 cells with the csi-miR-96-5p mimics or negative control. Forty-eight hours after transfection, the cells were lysed and the firefly luciferase activity was measured using a dual-luciferase assay kit (Promega, USA) following the manufacturer’s instructions. Renilla luciferase was used as the internal reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>RNA isolation, reverse transcription, and quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR)</title><p id="Par22">For RNA isolation, Trizol reagent (Takara, China) and miRNA isolation kit (Tiangen, China) were used to extract total RNA and small RNA (20–200 nt) from cells, tumor samples, or <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> according to the manufacturer's instructions, respectively. For RNA reverse transcription, mRNAs were reverse transcribed into cDNA using PrimeScript RT Master Mix reagent kit (Takara, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. miRNAs were reverse transcribed into cDNA using Reverse Transcriptase M-MLV kit (Takara, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. For qPCR, SYBR green assay kit (Takara, China) was used, and the procedures were performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. GAPDH was used as internal control for mRNA, U6 was used as internal control for miRNA, and csi-miR-96-5p in three disease-free normal samples was normalized as control. The relative expression was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup> method. As csi-miR-96-5p and hsa-miR-96-5p had the same seed sequence, two set of species-specific primers were designed; all primers used for reverse transcription and qPCR are listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Western blot</title><p id="Par23">Cells or tissues were lysed in radio immunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) buffer with protease inhibitor (Beyotime Biotechnology, China); the lysate was centrifuged at 15,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C. Then, proteins were heated at 95 °C for 5 min followed by fractionation in 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes. The membranes were blocked in 5% BSA in TBST buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl at pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl and 0.05% Tween-20) for 2 h and then incubated with primary antibodies at 4 °C overnight. The primary antibodies were as follows: PTEN (1:1000, Abclonal, China), GPX4 (1:1000, Abcam), SLC7A11 (1:10,000, Abclonal, China), and GAPDH (1:50,000, Abclonal, China). After three washes with TBST, the membranes were incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA) and visualized using an electrochemiluminescence reagent (Beyotime Biotechnology, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Establishment of tumor xenografts in vivo</title><p id="Par24">Male BALB/c nude mice (4 weeks) were obtained from the Central Laboratory of Animal Science of Jilin University. HuCCT1 cells (5 × 10<sup>6</sup>) stably transfected with csi-miR-96-5 mimics or PTEN-KO and their empty vector were injected into the nude mice for in situ implantation. Tumor size was measured every week. After 4 weeks, the mice were killed, and the tumors were removed for weight measurement.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Cell proliferation assay</title><p id="Par25">The Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) assay kit (MCE, China) was used to quantify the number of HuCCT1 cells. The cells were seeded in a 96-well plate. After overnight incubation at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, 10 μl of the CCK-8 solution was added to the cells in each well, and the cells were incubated again for 3 h. Absorbance at 450 nm was measured at 0, 24, 48, 72, and 96 h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Transwell migration assays</title><p id="Par26">A 12-well plate was purchased from Corning, and assays were performed according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Briefly, the cells were resuspended with serum-free Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) for a total of 100 μl (1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells) and added to the upper chamber, and the lower chamber was supplemented with 500 μl DMEM containing 20% FBS. The cells were incubated for 72 h. The cells were rinsed with PBS three times, and the non-migrated cells in the upper chamber were removed using a cotton swab. The cells were fixed with 4% polyformaldehyde for 20 min, stained with 1% crystal violet for 15 min, rinsed with PBS three times, and allowed to dry. Five randomly selected areas were examined and photographed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Malondialdehyde (MDA) and glutathione (GSH)/GSH disulfide (GSSG) ratio assays</title><p id="Par27">Assay kits to measure MDA (Beyotime, China) and GSH/GSSG count (Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, China) were purchased. The assays were conducted according to the manufacturer’s protocols. Briefly, cells samples (1 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells) were lysed by 0.1 ml lysate and then centrifuged at 12,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min; the supernatant was used for absorbance measurement. The OD value was measured at 532 nm or 412 nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><bold><italic toggle="yes">Ferrous iron (Fe</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></bold>+</sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">) assay</italic></bold></title><p id="Par28">Assay kit to measure Fe<sup>2+</sup> (Solarbio, China) was purchased. The assays were conducted according to the manufacturer’s protocols. Briefly, cell samples (1 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells) were lysed by 0.1 ml lysate and broken by ultrasound (200 W, last 3 s and interval 7 s, repeat 30 times) and then centrifuged at 8000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min; the supernatant was used for absorbance measurement. The OD value was measured at 510 nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>miRNA target prediction</title><p id="Par29">miRNA target gene prediction and analysis were performed using TargetScan (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</ext-link>), PicTar (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pictar.mdc-berlin.de/">http://pictar.mdc-berlin.de/</ext-link>), and miRanda (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microrna.org/">http://www.microrna.org/</ext-link>). To find target genes associated with ferroptosis, the ferroptosis-associated FerrDb database was searched [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par30">All data were processed using IBM SPSS 20.0. Count data were compared by performing the chi-square test. The Kaplan-Meier method was used for survival analysis, and the log-rank test was used to compare differences between groups. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>Samples from humans</title><p id="Par31">We collected data from 46 ICC patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection (<italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC group) and 46 ICC patients without <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection (NC-ICC group). Another three patients who underwent hepatic segment resection because of trauma were also enrolled as controls. The basic and pathological characteristics of the patients are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection increased serum total bilirubin, tumor TNM stage, and tumor differentiation degree in patients with cholangiocarcinoma (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical and pathological characteristics of ICC patients with or without <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 46)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NC-ICC (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 46)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.1 ± 9.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.3 ± 8.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex, male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.9 ± 2.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.3 ± 2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Length of stenosis, mm</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7 ± 6.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.0 ± 7.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total bilirubin, mmol/l</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">260.1 ± 76.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">150.3 ± 69.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Tumor location</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Left IBD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Right IBD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Cancer stage by AJCC, 7th</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> I–II</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> III–IV</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor differentiation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Well/moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Poorly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are expressed as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> or mean ± SD</p><p>ICC, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">CS-ICC</italic>, ICC with <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection; <italic toggle="yes">NC-ICC</italic>, ICC without <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection; BMI, body mass index; IBD, intrahepatic bile duct; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>, number of patients</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Identification and validation of the abundant presence of csi-miR-96-5p in CS-ICC patients</title><p id="Par32">The specificity of the two sets of primers designed for human (hsa-miR-96-5p) and <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> worms (csi-miR-96-5p) was examined first (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Total small RNA from <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> worms and HuCCT1 cells were extracted and used for reverse transcription. The results showed the <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> set of primers successfully generated the csi-miR-96-5p from samples of CS worms but not HuCCT1 cells, whereas the human set of primers successfully generated the hsa-miR-96-5p from samples of HuCCT1 cells but not <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> worms (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b, c). Therefore, the above results proved that the two set of primers can effectively distinguish between each other and have strong specificity.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Detection of csi-miR-96-5p in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-infected patients with ICC. <bold>a</bold> Design and validation of cross-species primers for csi-miR-96-5p and hsa-miR-96-5p. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Verifying the specificity of csi-miR-96-5p and hsa-miR-96-5p primers. Total RNA samples for <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> worms and HuCCT1 cells were 500 ng. The same qPCR conditions were used for the two groups. <bold>c</bold> Expression of csi-miR-96-5p and hsa-miR-96-5p in patients with ICC. The control group refers to disease-free tissues from patients who underwent hepatectomy because of trauma. Data are presented as the mean ± SD from three replicates, *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01. ICC, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">NC</italic>, negative control without <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection; <italic toggle="yes">AD</italic>, tumor-adjacent normal tissue; <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>, standard deviation; <italic toggle="yes">qPCR</italic>, quantitative polymerase chain reaction</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">Next, we investigated the expression of csi-miR-96-5p and hsa-miR-96-5p in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC patients and NC-ICC patients. The results showed that the level of csi-miR-96-5p in <italic toggle="yes">CS-</italic>ICC tumors (6.27 ± 1.65) was prominently higher than that in adjacent normal tissues (2.17 ± 0.54, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and was also significantly higher than that of hsa-miR-96-5p in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC tumors (1.51 ± 0.38) and adjacent normal tissues (1.24 ± 0.25), indicating the abundant presence of csi-miR-96-5p in patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Prediction and identification of the PTEN gene as the target of csi-miR-96-5p</title><p id="Par34">To further analyze the targets of csi-miR-96-5p, the miRDB, PicTar, and TargetScan databases were used to predict the downstream genes. Finally, twenty-six target genes of csi-miR-96-5p were mached, and by comparing the genes with the ferroptosis-associated FerrDb database, PTEN was identified as the single target associated with ferroptosis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Previous study had found that PTEN could potentially affect tumor survival, migration, and proliferation in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The luciferase assay showed that the cells transfected with csi-miR-96-5p mimics significantly inhibited luciferase activity, which was shown by those transfected with the recombinant plasmid incorporating in the 3′ untranslated region of wild-type PTEN but not by mutant PTEN (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). By performing qPCR and WB, we analyzed PTEN expression in the HuCCT1 cells transfected with the csi-miR-96-5p mimics. The results showed that csi-miR-96-5p was successfully overexpressed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, d) and PTEN mRNA and protein levels were significantly reduced (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e–g). To further verify this regulatory relationship, we analyzed the expression of csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN in patients with ICC. All patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC were divided into high and low csi-miR-96-5p expression groups based on the median value. In the <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC group, a high level of csi-miR-96-5p was associated with a lower PTEN level, and Pearson’s correlation test showed that PTEN was negatively correlated with csi-miR-96-5p (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> =  − 0.833) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>h). Therefore, there is ample evidence suggesting that csi-miR-96-5p directly inhibits PTEN expression.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Prediction and validation of PTEN as a csi-miR-96-5p target gene. <bold>a</bold> The putative binding region of csi-miR-96-5p for PTEN. <bold>b</bold> The luciferase reporter gene method was used to determine the PTEN gene reporter activity. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> csi-miR-96-5p mimics were successfully transfected into HuCCT1 cells. <bold>e</bold>–<bold>g</bold> PTEN mRNA and protein levels after transfection with csi-miR-96-5p mimics or NC mimics were detected using qPCR and WB, respectively. <bold>h</bold> Pearson correlation analysis of csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN levels in tissues from patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS-</italic>ICC. Data are presented as the mean ± SD from three replicates, *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01. ICC, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>, standard deviation; <italic toggle="yes">ns</italic>, no statistical difference; <italic toggle="yes">qPCR</italic>, quantitative polymerase chain reaction</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>csi-miR-96-5p/PTEN axis was associated with a dismal overall survival (OS)</title><p id="Par35">We performed a survival analysis based on long-term postoperative follow-up. The Kaplan-Meier curves showed that the OS of the <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC group was prominently lower than that of the NC-ICC group, with a median OS of 26.9 months and 33.6 months, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). In the <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC group, the Kaplan-Meier curves showed that patients with high levels of csi-miR-96-5p had shorter OS than patients with low levels of csi-miR-96-5p (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). A low level of PTEN was also associated with shorter OS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier curves for OS of patients with ICC based on csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN expression. Patients were divided into high and low csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN expression groups according to the average value. <bold>a</bold> Kaplan-Meier analysis of OS between the <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC and NC-ICC groups. <bold>b</bold> Kaplan-Meier analysis of OS in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC patients with high or low csi-miR-96-5p expression. <bold>c</bold> Kaplan-Meier analysis of OS in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC patients with high or low PTEN expression. <italic toggle="yes">OS</italic>, overall survival; <italic toggle="yes">ICC</italic>, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>csi-miR-96-5p was delivered into ICC cells by CsEVs</title><p id="Par36">To verify whether csi-miR-96-5p in host tissues was delivered by CsEVs, we isolated CsEVs. The culture medium of adult worms in the RPMI-1640 medium at 37 °C for 24 h was collected. CsEVs were isolated from the excretory-secretory products (ESPs) by ultracentrifugation. Under TEM, vesicle morphological characteristics were observed and displayed as a “double-layer saucer,” which is consistent with the typical EV morphology (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Nanoparticle tracking analysis indicated that the median particle size of the extracted exosomes was 112.1 nm and that the CsEV concentration was 1.1 × 10<sup>12</sup> particles/ml (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). WB showed that characteristic EV proteins such as CD63 and TSG101 were present in the CsEVs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Extraction and validation of csi-miR-96-5p in CsEVs. <bold>a</bold> Transmission electron microscopy analysis of CsEVs. <bold>b</bold> Nanoparticle tracking analysis of the sizes of CsEVs. <bold>c</bold> Western blot analysis of characteristic CsEV proteins (CD63 and TSG101). <bold>d</bold> CsEVs labeled with PKH-67 can be taken up by HuCCT1 cells. <bold>e</bold> qPCR analysis of the level of csi-miR-96-5p in cells treated with CsEVs. CsEVs, <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> secreted extracellular vesicles; <italic toggle="yes">qPCR</italic>, quantitative polymerase chain reaction. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">To verify whether CsEVs could be taken up by host cells, the isolated CsEVs (50 uM) were stained with PKH67 (Sigma) and further co-cultured with HuCCT1 for 24 h. Green fluorescence staining was observed in HuCCT1 cells, and qRT-PCR showed the presence of csi-miR-96-5p in HuCCT1 cells, confirming that CsEVs can act as carriers to transport miRNAs into recipient cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d, e).</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>csi-miR-96-5p promoted ICC proliferation and migration</title><p id="Par38">To explore the role of csi-miR-96-5p in ICC progression, csi-miR-96-5p mimics or control miRNA mimics were transfected into HuCCT1 cells. These mimics significantly promoted the proliferation of HuCCT1 cells, as determined by the CCK-8 assay in vitro, and the tumor size in xenograft tumor models in vivo (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, b). Furthermore, compared with NC, transfection with the miRNA mimics led to higher migration tendencies (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). These results suggest that csi-miR-96-5p promotes the proliferation and migration of ICC cells.<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>csi-miR-96-5p promoted ICC proliferation and migration via a ferroptosis mechanism. <bold>a</bold> Cell proliferation was measured by CCK-8 assay in vitro. <bold>b</bold> Cell proliferation was measured by tumor xenograft in vivo. <bold>c</bold> Cell migration was measured by transwell assay. <bold>d</bold> Cell GSH/GSSG radio assay. <bold>e</bold> Cell Fe<sup>2+</sup> assay. <bold>f</bold> Cell MDA assay. <bold>g</bold>, <bold>h</bold> Cell WB assay of SLC7A11 and GPX4. <italic toggle="yes">ICC</italic>, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">WB</italic>, western blotting; <italic toggle="yes">GSH</italic>, glutathione; <italic toggle="yes">GSSG</italic>, GSH disulfide; <italic toggle="yes">MDA</italic>, malondialdehyde. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>csi-miR-96-5p positively regulates ICC progression via ferroptosis</title><p id="Par39">To determine whether csi-miR-96-5p promoted ICC progression by regulating ferroptosis, miRNA mimics or control miRNA was transfected into HuCCT1 cells; then, the cells were cultured in the presence of the ferroptosis activator erastin (1 μM). Several ferroptosis markers and molecules were assayed to explore the potential mechanisms of action. Cells transfected with the csi-miR-96-5p mimics exhibited significantly fewer ferroptosis-related abnormalities, including a remarkably higher GSH/GSSG ratio (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d) and decreased accumulation of Fe<sup>2+</sup> and toxic active aldehydes (MDA) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e, f). The expression of ferroptosis regulatory proteins was confirmed by WB and qPCR. The results showed that the csi-miR-96-5p mimics positively upregulated the expression of SLC7A11 and GPX4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>g, h). These data show that the abundant presence of csi-miR-96-5p promotes ICC cell progression in vitro and in vivo by inhibiting ferroptosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>PTEN inhibited ICC proliferation and migration</title><p id="Par40">To explore the molecular mechanism of PTEN in ICC, LV vectors were used to construct HuCCT1 cells for stably expressing PTEN (PTEN-EXO) or CRISPR/Cas9-based (PTEN-KO), and the empty vector (PTEN-EXO NC) and NC LV (PTEN-KO NC) were used as controls. PTEN overexpression and silencing in HUCCT1 cells were confirmed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). PTEN-EXOs caused a prominent decrease in cell growth in vitro as determined by CCK-8 and in vivo as determined using xenograft tumor models (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, c). Furthermore, the PTEN-EXOs exhibited lower migration tendencies (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d). In contrast, the PTEN-KOs exhibited increased proliferation and migration tendencies. These results showed that PTEN could play a role as a tumor suppressor gene in ICC in vitro and in vivo.<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>PTEN inhibited ICC proliferation and migration via a ferroptosis mechanism. <bold>a</bold> Stable PTEN overexpression (PTEN-EXO) or CRISPR/Cas9-based knockout (PTEN-KO) HuCCT1 cell lines were established; the scale shown is 100 um. <bold>b</bold> Cell proliferation was measured by CCK-8 assay in vitro. <bold>c</bold> Cell proliferation was measured by tumor xenograft in vivo. <bold>d</bold> Cell migration was measured by transwell assay. <bold>e</bold> Cell GSH/GSSG radio assay. <bold>f</bold> Cell Fe<sup>2+</sup> assay. <bold>g</bold> Cell MDA assay. <bold>h</bold>, <bold>i</bold> Cell WB assay of SLC7A11 and GPX4. <italic toggle="yes">ICC</italic>, intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma; <italic toggle="yes">WB</italic>, western blotting; <italic toggle="yes">GSH</italic>, glutathione; <italic toggle="yes">GSSG</italic>, GSH disulfide; <italic toggle="yes">MDA</italic>, malondialdehyde. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>PTEN inhibited tumor progression via a ferroptosis-promoting mechanism</title><p id="Par41">To explore whether PTEN inhibited ICC progression by regulating ferroptosis, stable PTEN-EXO and PTEN-KO HuCCT1 cell lines were constructed; then, the cells were cultured in the presence of erastin (1 μM). Compared with PTEN-EXO NC cells, PTEN-EXO cells showed more ferroptosis-related abnormalities, including a lower GSH/GSSG ratio and higher accumulation of MDA and Fe<sup>2+</sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>e–g). The detection of ferroptosis markers indicated that PTEN-EXOs substantially downregulated the expression of SLC7A11T and GPX4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>h, i). In contrast, PTEN-KO cells exhibited the opposite ferroptotic mechanism. These results indicated that PTEN could promote ferroptosis by regulating related molecules.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>PTEN rescues the effect of csi-miR-96-5p on ICC</title><p id="Par42">To determine the top-down relationship between the csi-miR-96-5p/PTEN axis and ICC, we designed a functional co-transfection rescue experiment. We cotransfected csi-miR-96-5p mimics and PTEN-EXOs into the cells. These results indicated that PTEN-EXOs rescued the tumor-promoting effect of csi-miR-96-5p, thereby inhibiting ICC cell proliferation and migration (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, b).<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Co-transfect functional rescue experiment of csi-miR-96-5p and PTEN-EXO. <bold>a</bold> Cell proliferation was measured by CCK-8 assay in vitro. <bold>b</bold> Transwell assay of migration. <italic toggle="yes">CCK-8</italic>, cell counting kit-8; <italic toggle="yes">PTEN-EXO</italic>, PTEN overexpression. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO7" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par43">Adult <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> live in the human hepatobiliary duct, and their excretions, metabolites, and mechanical stimulation can damage the human bile duct epithelium and submucosal blood vessels, causing bile duct dilatation, epithelial hyperplasia, cholecystitis, gallstones, and ICC. Both clinical epidemiological studies and clinicopathological analyses suggest that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> infection is closely associated with ICC incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Studies have reported that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> excretions are involved in the carcinogenesis of the bile duct epithelium; however, these studies did not clarify whether this carcinogenic effect was caused by ESPs or CsEVs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. EVs secreted by helminths have been shown to interactively enter host cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Some studies have confirmed the roles of helminth miRNAs in host pathogenesis and related molecular mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. hsa-miR-96-5p is a carcinogenic factor that promotes the viability, proliferation, and migration of various cancer cells, such as hepatocellular carcinoma, lung adenocarcinoma, and breast cancer. Multiple signaling-related genes, such as PTEN, caspase-9, and BNIP3/FAK, are involved in the molecular mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Our study identified a conserved miR-96-5p from <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>, csi-miR-96-5p, which has the same seed sequence as hsa-miR-96-5p, despite differences in the remaining miRNA sequences between the species. We demonstrated that csi-miR-96-5p was present in host ICC cells and was delivered by CsEVs. Transfection with csi-miR-96-5p mimics promoted ICC cell proliferation and migration. In addition, csi-miR-96-5p promoted tumor growth in a xenograft animal model of ICC. The analysis of the molecular mechanism showed that csi-miR-96-5p played a role in regulating cell proliferation and invasion by targeting the PTEN gene.</p><p id="Par44">PTEN is a tumor suppressor gene identified after the discovery of the p53 gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Many studies have shown that PTEN plays an important role in cell growth, apoptosis, adhesion, migration, and infiltration and is closely associated with the tumorigenesis process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In recent years, some highly expressed ectopic miRNAs have been found to directly downregulate PTEN expression in the liver and biliary system and play cancer-promoting roles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The results of this study showed that PTEN expression in <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC tumor tissues was lower than that in normal tissues and that the level of csi-miR-96-5p was negatively correlated with PTEN expression. Low levels of csi-miR-96-5p and high levels of SLC7A11 were associated with increased TNM stage, lymph node metastasis, deeper muscle infiltration, and increased Ki-67 expression. These results indicate that the csi-miR-96-5p/PTEN axis promotes ICC progression in patients, in vitro and in vivo.</p><p id="Par45">Ferroptosis is a newly identified type of programmed cell death mainly caused by iron overload and the accumulation of intracellular lipid ROS. GSH/GPX4 is a classical ferroptosis pathway. The key executor of this pathway is System Xc- (also known as the cystine/glutamate anti-transporter), which is composed of the catalytic subunit SLC7A11 and the chaperone subunit SL3A2. SLC7A11 exhibits important transport activities and is highly specific to cysteine and glutamate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. System Xc- takes up cystine at a ratio of 1:1 and exchanges glutamic acid. Cystine transported into the cell is rapidly reduced to cysteine, which participates in GSH synthesis. As an important antioxidant and free radical scavenger, GSH can inhibit ferroptosis. SLC7A11 is highly expressed in various malignant tumors, and tumor cells can maintain high levels of GSH by upregulating SLC7A11 expression to counteract oxidative stress caused by increased metabolic rate, a process that is positively correlated with cancer progression because of its antioxidant function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Our study showed that PTEN loss by csi-miR-96-5p upregulated SLC7A11 in ICC cell lines and patient tumor samples, promoting cystine input and GSH production, thereby protecting cells from ferroptosis. A recent study also demonstrated that PTEN loss desensitized cells to ferroptosis induced by erastin and cystine deprivation. In this mechanism, the loss of PTEN activated AKT kinase to inhibit GSK3b and increases the transcription of NF-E2 P45-associated factor 2 (NRF2) and one of its known target genes encoding SLC7A11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par46">Our study demonstrated that csi-miR-96-5p delivered by CsEVs and PTEN regulated ICC development by modulating ferroptosis. This study has several advantages. First, we are the first to our knowldge to explore and demonstrate ferroptosis in parasitic helminth-host interactions, which is essential for refining our understanding of the effect of parasitic worm-host interactions and providing targeted treatments for cancer. Second, we collected sufficient clinical samples and confirmed the reliability of the csi-miR-96-5p/PTEN/SLC7A11/GPX4 axis through in vitro and in vivo cell and animal experiments. Third, we up- and downregulated PTEN to fully verify multiple possible pathways of ferroptosis and performed functional rescue experiments to verify the role of the csi-miR-96-5p/PTEN axis.</p><p id="Par47">However, in the present study, therapy targeting csi-miR-96-5p or PTEN has not been tested in clinical trials, and more clinical studies are needed to explore the feasibility of targeting this axis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par48">The results of this study demonstrate that csi-miR-96-5p delivered by CsEVs is abundant in patients with <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC and downregulates PTEN, thus promoting the proliferation and migration of ICC through the SLC7A11/GPX4 ferroptosis axis. We are the first to our knowledge to find that <italic toggle="yes">CS</italic> miRNAs can promote ICC tumor development through ferroptosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec32"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13071_2023_6075_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Sequences of primers used for reverse transcription and qPCR.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">CS</italic></term><def><p id="Par5">
<italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EVs</term><def><p id="Par6">Extracellular vesicles</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ICC</term><def><p id="Par7">Intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">CS</italic>-ICC</term><def><p id="Par8">ICC with <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NC-ICC</term><def><p id="Par9">ICC without <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p id="Par10">Quantitative polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p>This article has been retracted. Please see
the retraction notice for more detail:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-024-06408-0">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13071-024-06408-0</ext-link></p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>7/18/2024</p><p>This article has been retracted. Please see the Retraction Notice for more detail: 10.1186/s13071-024-06408-0</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>LJW, JGY, and JXZ conceived and designed the study. LJW, YXW, and JXZ performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript. YXW and KL collected the specimens and clinical data. LJW and JXZ contributed materials and analytical tools. JGY, KL, and JXZ critically revised the manuscript. All the authors have read and approved the final version of this manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Science and Technology Development Program of Jilin Province (Grant No. 20200201584JC).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All datasets are available within the paper.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Ethics Committee of the First Hospital of Jilin University (permit no. 19K041-001). The animal study protocol was approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of First Hospital of Jilin University (permit no. 20210526). Informed consent was obtained from all the participants.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par50">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gores</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis, diagnosis, and management of cholangiocarcinoma</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2013</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24140396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3862291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobrial</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma</article-title><source>J Clin Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2368</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10112368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34072277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8198953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Cholangiocarcinoma</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection: a case-control study in Korea</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2005.11.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16480786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Severe hepatobiliary morbidity is associated with <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> infection: The evidence from a cross-sectional community study</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e9116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0009116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7880442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33507969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> co-infection could affect the disease state and treatment response of HBV patients</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e4806</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4922651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic>-associated cholangiocarcinoma: a large-scale, single-center study</article-title><source>Front Med (Lausanne)</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>675207</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2021.675207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34124104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8193222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thebaud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exosomes: cell garbage can, therapeutic carrier, or trojan horse?</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2012</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>2553</fpage><lpage>2555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.146738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23114790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Record</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carayon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poirot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silvente-Poirot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exosomes as new vesicular lipid transporters involved in cell-cell communication and various pathophysiologies</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2014</year><volume>1841</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2013.10.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24140720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanez-Mo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siljander</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavec</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borras</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buzas</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological properties of extracellular vesicles and their physiological functions</article-title><source>J Extracell Vesicles</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>27066</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jev.v4.27066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25979354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4433489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Andaloussi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mager</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breakefield</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular vesicles: biology and emerging therapeutic opportunities</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd3978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23584393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Torre-Escudero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular vesicle biogenesis in helminths: more than one route to the surface?</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2016.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27720334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of exosome-like vesicles from <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola gigantica</italic> adult worm provides support for new vaccine targets against fascioliasis</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13071-023-05659-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9921414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36765398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma japonicum</italic> extracellular vesicle miRNA cargo regulates host macrophage functions facilitating parasitism</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e1007817</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6548406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31163079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Csi-let-7a-5p delivered by extracellular vesicles from a liver fluke activates M1-like macrophages and exacerbates biliary injuries</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2021</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>e2102206118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2102206118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34772807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8609646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemberg</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamprecht</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skouta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaitsev</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gleason</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ferroptosis: an iron-dependent form of nonapoptotic cell death</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.03.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22632970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3367386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncoding RNAs in cancer ferroptosis: from biology to clinical opportunity</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2023</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>115053</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37379641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferroptosis: molecular mechanisms and health implications</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-00441-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33268902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8026611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differences in the secretory exosomes of <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> adults at different incubation times</article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>106604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2022.106604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35820469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FerrDb V2: update of the manually curated database of ferroptosis regulators and ferroptosis-disease associations</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>D571</fpage><lpage>D582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36305834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functions and regulation of the PTEN tumor suppressor: new modes and prospects</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-018-0015-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29858604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The global epidemiology of clonorchiasis and its relation with cholangiocarcinoma</article-title><source>Infect Dis Poverty</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-9957-1-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23849183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3710150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fürst</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utzinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of human food-borne trematodiasis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(11)70294-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22108757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> combined with Hepatitis B virus infection on the prognosis of patients with Hepatocellular Carcinoma following Hepatectomy</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2023</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>e0011012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0011012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36638133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9879467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of PSMD10, CDK4, and Tumor suppressors in development of intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma of syrian golden hamsters induced by <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-nitrosodimethylamine</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e0004008</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26313366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4551803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and analysis of the tegument protein and excretory-secretory products of the carcinogenic liver fluke <italic toggle="yes">Clonorchis sinensis</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>555730</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.555730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33072014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7538622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonglitthipagon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Easley</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The miRNAome of <italic toggle="yes">Opisthorchis viverrini</italic> induced intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma</article-title><source>Genom Data</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gdata.2014.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26484108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4535865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma japonicum</italic> MiRNA-7-5p inhibits the growth and migration of hepatoma cells via cross-species regulation of S-phase kinase-associated protein 2</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>175</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2019.00175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30967999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6443022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pulito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacconi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donzelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Andrea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manciocco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>miR-96-5p targets PTEN expression affecting radio-chemosensitivity of HNSCC cells</article-title><source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-019-1119-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30925916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6440033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitaichi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oncogenic miR-96-5p inhibits apoptosis by targeting the caspase-9 gene in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29658604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2018.4369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-96-5p regulates wound healing by targeting BNIP3/FAK pathway</article-title><source>J Cell Biochem</source><year>2019</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>12904</fpage><lpage>12911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.28561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30883918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Álvarez-Garcia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tawil</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of PTEN loss in cancer: it's all about diversity</article-title><source>Semin Cancer Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcancer.2019.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30738865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murchie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PTEN loss mediates clinical cross-resistance to CDK4/6 and PI3Kα Inhibitors in breast cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-18-0830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31594766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouw</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damiano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bainer</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakins</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acerbi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tissue mechanics modulate microRNA-dependent PTEN expression to regulate malignant progression</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24633304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3981899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sbodio</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cysteine metabolism in neuronal redox homeostasis</article-title><source>Trends Pharmacol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2018.02.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29530337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5912966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koppula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cystine transporter SLC7A11/xCT in cancer: ferroptosis, nutrient dependency, and cancer therapy</article-title><source>Protein Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13238-020-00789-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33000412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8310547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahuzac</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoenfeld</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AKT activation because of PTEN loss upregulates xCT via GSK3beta/NRF2, leading to inhibition of ferroptosis in PTEN-mutant tumor cells</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>112536</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2023.112536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37210723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10558134</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>