
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101672560</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10020002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10020002.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10020002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10020002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36938448</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e14265</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(23)01472-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e14265</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MiR-1281 is involved in depression disorder and the antidepressant effects of Kai-Xin-San by targeting ADCY1 and DVL1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="C">Chao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="YJ">Yuan-jie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="SR">Shang-rong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="XH">Xiao-hui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="DH">Dai-hong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="XJ">Xiao-jiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="WY">Wei-yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names initials="AD">Ai-Dong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names initials="QR">Qing-Rong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="XZ">Xian-Zhe</given-names></name><email>dongxianzhe@163.com</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="P">Ping</given-names></name><email>liup_301@126.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">∗∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Pharmacy, Medical Supplies Center of PLA General Hospital, Beijing 100853, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Psychiatry, The 984th Hospital of Chinese People's Liberation Army, Beijing 100094, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Pharmacy, Xijing Hospital of Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, 710032, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Psychiatry, Xijing Hospital of Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, 710032, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Pharmacy, Xuanwu Hospital of Capital Medical University, Beijing 100853, People's Republic of China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. Department of Pharmacy, Xuanwu Hospital of Capital Medical University, 45 Changchun Road, Xicheng District, Beijing 100053, China. <email>dongxianzhe@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>Corresponding author.Department of Pharmacy, the General Hospital of the People's Liberation Army, Beijing 100853, China. <email>liup_301@126.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Chao Chen and Yuan-jie Xu contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">429787</issue-id><elocation-id>e14265</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-05 04:25:13.100"><day>05</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Kai-Xin-San (KXS) is a Chinese medicine formulation that is commonly used to treat depression caused by dual deficiencies in the heart and spleen. Recent studies indicated that miRNAs were involved in the pathophysiology of depression. However, there have been few studies on the mechanism underlying the miRNAs directly mediating antidepressant at clinical level, especially in nature drugs and TCM compound. In this study, we identified circulating miRNAs defferentially expressed among the depression patients (DPs), DPs who underwent 8weeks of KXS treatment and health controls (HCs). A total of 45 miRNAs (17 were up-regulated and 28 were down-regulated) were significantly differentially expressed among three groups. Subsequently, qRT-PCR was used to verify 10 differentially expressed candidate miRNAs in more serum samples, and the results showed that 6 miRNAs (miR-1281, miR-365a-3p, miR-2861, miR-16-5p, miR-1202 and miR-451a) were consistent with the results of microarray. Among them, miR-1281, was the novel dynamically altered and appeared to be specifically related to depression and antidepressant effects of KXS. MicroRNA-gene-pathway-net analysis showed that miR-1281-regulated genes are mostly key nodes in the classical signaling pathway related to depression. Additionally, our data suggest that ADCY1 and DVL1 were the targets of miR-1281. Thus, based on the discovery of miRNA expression profiles in vivo, our findings suggest a new role for miR-1281 related to depression and demonstrated in vitro that KXS may activate cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin signal transduction pathways by down-regulating miR-1281 that targets ADCY1 and DVL1 to achieve its role in neuronal cell protection.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Depression</kwd><kwd>Kai-Xin-San</kwd><kwd>miR-1281</kwd><kwd>ADCY1</kwd><kwd>DVL1</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Depression is a multifaceted condition caused by diverse factors and is among the most prevalent of mental disorders. At present, monoamine neurotransmitters are widely used as targets in first-line antidepressants. However, these conventional antidepressants fail to help at least 40% of depression patients and may have severe side effects [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The research and development of antidepressants have been stagnant for several years, and the development of drugs that have therapeutic effects on multiple pathogeneses at the same time is an urgent need. Due to its multicomponent and multitarget characteristics, traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) has shown high reliability to treat emotional diseases with complex mechanisms and symptoms. Therefore, increasing attention has been given to TCM worldwide [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">In addition, recent studies have found that more than half of the detectable miRNAs are abundantly expressed in the mammalian nervous system [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>]. Preclinical evidence suggests that miRNAs play an important role in the pathogenesis of depressive disorders, especially in synaptic plasticity, neurogenesis and the regulation of key elements of signal transduction pathways [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For example, conditional dicer deficiency in excitatory forebrain neurons can significantly reduce dendritic branching refinement and increase dendritic spine length [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; miR-132, miR-134 and miR-let-7 affect the formation of dendrites in neurons, and BDNF can be regulated by multiple miRNAs [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], such as miR-182, miR-30a-5p and miR-195. A large number of studies have reported that microRNAs are involved in regulating monoamine transmitters [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], stress responses [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], glucocorticoids [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and circadian rhythms [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>]. However, many miRNA expression profile studies have discovered systemic changes in depression patients compared to healthy people [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>], but few of them focused on identifying the biological changes upon antidepressant treatment, and most of these researches focused on first-line therapeutic drugs, including 5-hydroxytryptamine reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and 5-hydroxytryptamine/norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>]. Especially for anti-depression treatment with TCM, no miRNA study has been carried out on human patients.</p><p id="p0020">Kai-Xin-San (KXS), which was recorded in Qian-Jin-Yao-Fang by Sun Si-Miao in the Tang Dynasty and consists of ginseng, hoelen, polygala and acorus at a ratio of 3:3:2:2, has been widely used to treat depression and deficiencies in learning and memory for thousands of years [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Its antidepressant effects at the animal level have been systematically and thoroughly studied by our group using many classical models (forced swimming test, small tail suspension model, and unpredictable chronic stress model) [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>]. Thus far, the potential targets of KXS have not been investigated in patients. Therefore, we developed a KXS tablet and performed a randomized double-blind clinical trial, which also included a positive parallel control, to assess the efficacy and safety of KXS in the treatment of mild/moderate depression in patients who also have traditional Chinese medicine diagnosis of heart and spleen deficiency [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Further proteomic analysis in peripheral blood samples from this clinical trial demonstrated that KXS exerts its regulating effect on peripheral platelet function and lipid metabolism, which might become a new therapeutic target of antidepression via improving depression-related biological pathways and their functions [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">As mentioned above, in the present study, to uncover miRNAs associated with the pathophysiology of depression and elucidate the mechanisms of KXS on depression, we collected serum samples from responsive patients in the clinical trial (these patients were considered “cured” or “showing an obvious clinical response” based on clinical efficacy standards) and used these samples for the following microarray study. Moreover, we screened and verified potential miRNA biomarkers for depression and identified novel miRNA as potential antidepressant targets of KXS in functional experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="p0030">The experimental protocols involving human subjects were approved by the Ethics Committee of the Fourth Military Medical University (Xi'an, China). All experiments were conducted according to the related guidelines and regulations. Written informed consent was obtained from all the participants after they were provided a detailed explanation of the entire study. All procedures met the requirements established in the Declaration of Helsinki. The ethical clearance number is YS20150507-4.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Drug preparation</title><p id="p0035">The KXS tablets for participants were prepared as previously described [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The KXS preparation in vitro included the following steps: All medicines formulating KXS (<italic toggle="yes">Panax ginseng</italic> C.A. Mey (No. 17022602); <italic toggle="yes">Smilax glabra</italic> Roxb, (No. 17080101), <italic toggle="yes">Polygala tenuifolia</italic> willd (No. 17082501), and <italic toggle="yes">Acorus gramineus</italic> Aiton (No. 18011304)), which are controlled by the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2010) and authenticated by Professor Ping Liu. The voucher specimen of each plant was registered under the numbers NU-90111, NU-82003, NU-79015, and NU-59012 and deposited in the Herbarium of Traditional Chinese Medicinal Pharmacy. KXS was supplied in the form of a dried powder that was manufactured as an aqueous extract of a mixture of ginseng, hoelen, polygala and Acorus. The aqueous extract was prepared as previously described [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and 1 g of the yielded powder equaled 4.83 g of total original herbs. KXS is mainly composed of saponins, oligosaccharides, polysaccharides and volatile oils [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. We identified 97 compounds from KXS, and the chemical profile is shown in our previous publication [<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Human blood samples</title><p id="p0040">Depressed patients (DPs) were ascertained in the Department of Psychiatry at No. 261 Chinese People's Liberation Army (PLA) Hospital (which is now renamed No. 984). To identify the molecules related to the pathogenesis of depression, we set up healthy control (HC) groups enrolled from the Medical Examination Center. A structured clinical interview based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders IV (DSM-IV) was performed with each participant. The inclusion and exclusion criteria were performed as described in our previous study [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p id="p0045">The clinical trial was an 8-week long, randomized double-blind, positive-controlled, parallel-group trial to evaluate the efficacy of KXS treatment in patients diagnosed with mild/moderate depression [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Patients and investigators were blinded. The patients were randomly divided into the following two groups using a random number chart: the trial group (KXS plus fluoxetine placebo) and the control group (fluoxetine plus KXS placebo). All the drugs were orally administered, and the dosages were 20 mg/day for fluoxetine or fluoxetine placebo and 3.2 g/day for KXS (approximately 13.336 g original herbs) or KXS placebo. The HAMD and Traditional Chinese Medicine Syndrome Score Scale (TCMSSS) were used to assess the severity of the illness. According to the HAMD and TCMSSS scores, the therapeutic efficacy was evaluated and scored at baseline and after 0, 4 and 8 weeks of treatment. A clinical response was defined as a decrease of no less than 25% in the HAMD score and a decrease of 30% in the TCMSSS score after 8 weeks of drug administration compared with the baseline level.</p><p id="p0050">Blood samples were collected into plastic serum-separating tube (SST) between 8:30 and 11:30 a.m. by venipuncture after an overnight fast (at least 12 h), followed by a 30-min incubation at room temperature. Subsequently, blood samples underwent centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 15 min at 4 °C. The upper phase (serum) was transferred into Eppendorf tubes and stored at −80 °C for further analysis.</p><p id="p0055"><bold>Patient sample selection</bold>: The clinical trial showed that KXS has efficacy and safety profile in treatment of patients with mild to moderate depression [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A total of 66 samples were selected, including 21 (7 in each group) for subsequent microarray analysis and 45 (15 in each group) for expanded samples of RT-PCR validation. Sserum samples in KSX group were selected from patients who exhibited the best response after 8 weeks of KXS administration, these patients showed a decrease of 75% in the HAMD score (clinically cured based on Western Medicine standards) and a decrease of 70% in the TCMSSS score (clinically responsive and cured based on Chinese Medicine standards).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Microarray analysis</title><p id="p0060">Total RNA was extracted from 21 serum samples (7 in the HC group, 7 in the DP group and 7 in the KXS group) using TRIzol reagent (mirVana PARIS Kit, Ambion-1556) according to a standard protocol. The concentration and integrity of purified RNA were determined by a NanoDrop ND-2100 and an Agilent 2100, respectively. Samples with an RNA integrity number (RIN) less than 7 were excluded to ensure the reliability of the analysis. Determine whether high-level hemolysis occurs by observing the serum color，if the color of the serum is pink rather than yellow, hemolysis is considered to have occurred and the sample is excluded. One sample in KXS group was rejected due to unqualified quality inspection. Cyanine-3-CTP (Cy3)-labeled RNA was used to prepare a hybridization reaction system (17 μL sample/1 μL Hyb Spike-In/4.5 μL 10-GE Blocking Agent/22.5 μL 2-Hi-RPM Hybridization Buffer) with dephosphorylated RNA. The 45-mu hybridization solution was immediately centrifuged and injected into the Agilent Human miRNA Array (8*60 K, Design ID: 070156), and the sample feeding port was sealed with stickers and hybridized in a hybridization oven for 20 h. The hybridization conditions were 55 °C and 20 rpm. The corresponding parameters were scanned by an Agilent scanner to generate data.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Bioinformatic studies</title><p id="p0065">Feature Extraction software (version 10.7.1.1, Agilent Technologies) was used to process the original images and extract the original data. GeneSpring software (version 12.5; Agilent Technologies) was used for quantile standardization and subsequent data processing.The screening criteria for differential expression of miRNAs was that the miRNAs are up or down regulated ≥1.5 folds and with P values &lt; 0.05 among groups.</p><p id="p0070">The TargetScan, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microRNA.org" id="intref0010">microRNA.org</ext-link> and Pita databases were used to predict target genes of differentially expressed miRNAs. The base complementation analysis followed four rules: (1) the 2nd-4th bases of miRNAs were accurately matched with the 3′UTR of the target RNA; (2) the 3rd-12th base mismatch of miRNAs was less than or equal to five; (3) the 9th-25th bases had at least five bases; and (4) the last five base mismatches of miRNAs were not more than two. In addition, the same base sequence was required in the 3′UTR sequence alignment of multiple species.</p><p id="p0075">Based on the KEGG and Reactome databases, Gene Ontology (GO) and signal pathway enrichment analyses of target genes were performed to determine the biological functions or related pathways of differentially expressed miRNAs, and key network nodes were identified.</p><p id="p0080">A microRNA-gene-pathway network was constructed for the differentially expressed miRNAs after qRT-PCR validation. The microRNA-gene-pathway network was constructed by combining important pathways and target gene functions related to depression. The network reflected the core functions and important pathways regulated by target miRNAs (network eigenvalues were calculated to determine pivotal positions).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>qRT–PCR validation of miRNA expression in serum samples</title><p id="p0085">Total RNA was extracted from 45 serum samples (15 in the HC group, 15 in the DP group and 15 in the KXS group) by using a miRNeasy Serum/Plasma Kit (Qiagen/217184) according to the manufacturer's instructions, 100 μL serum of each sample was used for miRNA profiling. cDNA was synthesized with a miRcute Plus miRNA First-Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (TIANGEN/Cat No. KR211,Beijing, China), and qRT–PCR was performed using a miRcute Plus miRNA qPCR Detection Kit (SYBR Green) (TIANGEN/Cat No. FP411,Beijing, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 1 μg of total RNA per sample was used for cDNA synthesis, and 20 μL of cDNA were obtained. 1 μL of cDNA was added in 20 μL of reaction system for real time PCR. Ce-miR-39-3p, an exogenous miRNA from nematode was used as the exogenous control for miRNAs, up to 30 Cts was considered acceptable for amplification.</p><p id="p0090">Ten of the 45 differentially expressed miRNAs were selected from the three groups in the previous microarray experiment and verified by using qRT–PCR in a larger number of samples. The sequences of the primers are shown in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. The screening criteria included: (1) miRNAs with significant differences and high fold change in microarray results; (2) miRNAs have been reported to be associated with depression or psychiatric disorders; (3) through the Pita/Micrornaorg/Targetscan three library prediction, can control more key target genes associated with depression.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Cell culture</title><p id="p0095">SH-SY5Y cells were maintained in high-glucose DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/mL penicillin and 100 U/mL streptomycin at 37 °C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. When the SH-SY5Y cells grew to logarithmic phase, the cells were digested with 0.25% trypsin for 2 min, followed by centrifugation at 1,000 rpm for 3 min, and the supernatant was discarded. The cell pellet was resuspended in DMEM medium. Subsequently, 100 μL of cell suspension containing 5,000–8,000 cells was added to each well of a 96-well plate, followed by incubation at 37 °C for 24 h, and then the cells were exposed to different treatments. Cells in the control group were treated with culture medium only. Cells in the corticosterone-treated group [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] were exposed to 0.1 mM corticosterone for 24 h. Cells in the low-dose KXS group were exposed to 0.1 mM corticosterone and 10 μg/mL KXS for 24 h. Cells in the medium-dose KXS group were exposed to 0.1 mM corticosterone and 100 μg/mL KXS for 24 h. Cells in the high-dose KXS group were exposed to 0.1 mM corticosterone and 500 μg/mL KXS for 24 h. Subsequently, 10 μL CCK-8 reagent was added to each well, followed by incubation at 37 °C for 4 h. The absorbance at a wavelength of 450 nm was determined by the enzyme labeling method. The experiment was performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Construction of the miR-1281 lentiviral expression vector and KXS intervention</title><p id="p0100">HEK293 cells were inoculated into 6-well plates (1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) and cultured in 2 mL medium for 24 h. The cell culture supernatant was discarded, and 1 mL fresh DMEM containing 10% FBS was added. Lentivirus expressing miR-1281 was added to the medium, followed by the addition of 5 g/mL polybrene. Fresh medium was added 24 h later. At 96 h after transfection, the fluorescence density was detected to determine the transfection efficiency of the expression vector.</p><p id="p0105">After 72 h of transfection, drugs were added. The miR-1281 overexpression group (transfected with the miR-1281 lentiviral expression vector, referred to as the OE group), the negative control group (transfected with lentiviral vector expressing a nonsense sequence, referred to as the NC group), the blank control group (in the presence of equal amounts of culture medium, referred to as the CON group), the OE+10 μg/mL KXS group, the OE+100 μg/mL KXS group and the OE+500 μg/mL KXS were set up. Five wells were designated for each group. qRT–PCR was used to detect the expression of miR-1281 in cells transfected with miR-1281 and cells after KXS intervention.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Detection of survival rate by CCK8 and apoptosis by flow cytometry (FCM)</title><p id="p0110">SH-SY5Y cells in the logarithmic growth phase were inoculated into 6-well plates and divided into a miR-1281 overexpression group (transfected with lentiviral expression vector of miR-1281, referred to as the OE group), a negative control group (transfected with lentiviral expression vector with nonsense sequence, referred to as the NC group), a blank control group (in the presence of equal amount of culture medium, referred to as the CON group), the OE+10 μg/mL KXS group, the OE+100 μg/mL KXS group, and the OE+500 μg/mL KXS group, and there were three wells for each group. The cell culture medium was collected into a suitable centrifuge tube. The adherent cells were washed with PBS once and digested with trypsin cell digestion solution. Next, 1-5 x 10<sup>5</sup> cells were centrifuged at 1,000×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 5 min. The supernatant was discarded, and the cell pellet was gently resuspended in 500 μL binding solution. Subsequently, 5 μL Annexin V-PerCP-Cy5.5 was gently mixed with the cell suspension, and 5 μL propidium iodide was added, followed by incubation at room temperature (20–25 °C) for 10 min. Finally, apoptosis was detected by FCM.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Luciferase reporter assay</title><p id="p0115">miR-1281 mimics (an overexpression plasmid) were designed and synthesized in our lab. The wild-type reporter gene expression plasmid of ADCY1 and the mutant reporter gene plasmid of ADCY1 (the sites of miR-1281 binding to ADCY1 were mutated.) were constructed. A treated single-cell suspension of HEK293 cells was inoculated into a 24-well plate at a density of 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. The reporter gene plasmid containing the wild-type/mutant ADCY1 sequence was transfected into HEK293 cells by the liposome transfection reagent Lipofectamine 2000. The cells were cultured for 2 days, followed by the detection of intracellular fluorescence.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>qRT–PCR assay for miRNA and mRNAs expression in SY5Y cells</title><p id="p0120">RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, USA). Purified RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA using SYBR Green I (10 × ) Reverse Transcription Kit (Genview, USA). PCR was conducted according to the previously described protocol [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. All primers used in the study can be found in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><label>2.12</label><title>Western blotting analysis</title><p id="p0125">SDS–PAGE (10% and 4% gels) and Western blotting analysis were used in the present study. The immunoreactive bands were visualized by ECL solution, and the images were quantified by a UVP gel imager. The primary antibodies used were as follows: anti-Erk1 (pT202/pY204) + Erk2 (pT185/pY187) (Abcam, USA, mouse, 1/100,00), anti-CREB (phospho S133) (Abcam, USA, rabbit, 1/5,000); anti-CREB (Abcam, USA, rabbit, 1/500), anti-BDNF (Abcam, USA, mouse, 0.2–2 μg/mL); anti-β catenin (Abcam, USA, rabbit, 1/5,000), anti-GSK3β (Abcam, USA, mouse, 1/500); anti-GSK3β (phospho Y216) (Abcam, USA, rabbit, 1/500), and anti-PKA (Abcam, USA, rabbit, 1/500).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><label>2.13</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0130">All data were analyzed by SPSS 16.0 software and are presented as the means ± SD except for the microarray analysis. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used in the data analysis, followed by the least significant difference (LSD) test. The standard statistical function of hypergeometric distribution, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and FDR were performed for differentially expressed genes in microarray analysis and KEGG pathway analysis. p &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Clinical characteristics of subjects</title><p id="p0135"><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the detailed baseline parameters of the subjects. There were no significant differences in age, sex or body mass index (BMI) between DPs and HCs (p &gt; 0.05), while the HAMD scores of the two groups were 18.20 ± 0.33 and 0, respectively. After 8 weeks of KXS administration, the HAMD score was significantly decreased (p &lt; 0.0001).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and clinical features of the recruited subjects.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0095">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">HCs</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">DPs</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">KXS</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">DP/HC<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">KXS/DP<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">p value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">p value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Microarray analysis and RT–PCR validation</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sample size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex (M/F)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6/16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5/16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.33 ± 2.76</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.93 ± 2.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.93 ± 2.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3621</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.90 ± 0.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.86 ± 0.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.86 ± 0.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3878</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HAMD score</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.20 ± 0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73 ± 0.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Two-tailed Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was performed to calculate the statistical significance of the differences in the continuous variables (age, BMI, and HAMD scores); chi-square analysis was performed to calculate the statistical significance of the differences in the categorical variables (sex). HCs: healthy controls, DPs: depressed patients, KXS: depressive patients treated with KXS.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Differential expression of miRNAs between groups</title><p id="p0140">Compared with HCs, 112 differentially expressed miRNAs were identified in DPs. Moreover, 46 differentially expressed miRNAs were identified in the KXS group compared with DPs. The expression levels of 45 miRNAs were both significantly different between HC <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> DP and DP <italic toggle="yes">vs.</italic> KXS, of which 17 were upregulated and 28 were downregulated (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>); these miRNAs might be both depression biomarkers and antidepressant targets of KXS. The target genes of the 45 differentially expressed miRNAs were predicted based on the KEGG database, GO and pathway enrichment analyses of the target genes were conducted.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Differential expression of miRNAs in the HC, DP, and KXS groups.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0100">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">miRNA</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">DP/HC<hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">KXS/DP<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regulation</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Log2（FC）</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regulation</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Log2（FC）</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1202<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.8755</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0058</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2750</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0248</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1207-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.6629</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0050</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3066</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0251</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1225-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.7541</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0048</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0269</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-16-5p<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.0896</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0067</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3451</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0386</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1915-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.9118</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1289</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-19b-3p<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.0472</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1500</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0424</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-2861</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.5563</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0046</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5566</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0403</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-3665</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.7841</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0047</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6221</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4270</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.2450</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0058</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8320</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0369</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−8.5824</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0255</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4516</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−8.1277</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4400</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0259</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4687-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.9509</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0131</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4880</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0206</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4787-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.3609</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9044</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0081</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-486-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.1571</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0356</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0260</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6087</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.0764</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0469</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2374</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0395</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6088</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.2317</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0095</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2699</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0080</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6089</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.3100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0210</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6389</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0332</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6125</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.6308</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0161</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8265</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0132</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-638</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.2467</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2197</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6510-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.9221</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0325</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0731</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0364</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6800-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.9002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0027</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.9518</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0485</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6821-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.8987</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7715</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6869-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1747</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-7107-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.8287</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6535</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0271</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-7110-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−5.9046</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9544</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0048</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-7704</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.1497</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8279</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0051</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-8069</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.0136</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0136</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7565</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0044</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-451a<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.7815</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0069</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4378</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-let-7f-1-3p<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4135</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.6562</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0086</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5452</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.6613</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0192</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-129-1-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0070</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.3047</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-129-2-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6468</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.5718</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-3162-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7388</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0057</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.2361</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0428</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-365a-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5785</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0028</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.3683</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0351</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-4649-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4766</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0063</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.2087</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0410</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6508-5p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2904</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0057</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.0109</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0172</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6515-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0869</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.4675</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0400</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6785-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4162</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0037</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.4377</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0195</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6792-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1939</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0007</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.7494</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0357</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6797-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2976</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.7769</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0078</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6865-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4458</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0055</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.8617</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6870-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1631</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0391</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.5101</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0130</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-6889-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8578</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−4.8114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-766-3p</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5868</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.3489</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0235</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-940</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">up</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2681</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">down</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.3167</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0194</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">Depression-related miRNAs reported in the literature.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0145">By predicting the target genes in the three databases, we found that there were 3,249 probable target genes of the miRNAs which differentially expressed in the DP group compared to the HC group; they were located in the cytoplasm, nucleus, synapse, postsynaptic dense region and cell junctions and were associated with protein binding, chromatin binding, transcription factor binding and histone methyltransferase activity. Their biological effects and functions were mainly involved in RNA polymerase II promoter transcription regulation, axon orientation, DNA template transcription, mitotic cell cycle regulation, peptide tyrosine phosphorylation, gene transport and other biological processes(<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). The enriched pathways were mainly the following: focal adhesion, signaling pathways regulating pluripotency of stem cells, MAPK signaling pathway, axon guidance, PI3K-Akt signaling pathway, Rap1 signaling pathway, neurotrophin signaling pathway, and cAMP signaling pathway (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>Significant gene functions and signaling pathways enriched for differentially expressed genes.</bold> (A) Significant gene functions of DP/HC differential gene enrichment; (B) Significant gene functions of KXS/DP differential gene enrichment; (C) Significant signaling pathways of DP/HC differential gene enrichment; (D) Significant signaling pathways of KXS/DP differential gene enrichment.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0150">In the KXS/DP group, there were 1,943 probable target genes of differentially expressed miRNAs, which were located in the cytoplasm, synapse, postsynaptic dense area, nucleus, cell junction, neuron synapse and growth cone, and their biological effects and functions were related to protein binding, transcription activator, phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase, calcium binding and tyrosine protein kinase. The biological processes involved included transcriptional regulation, neurogenesis, multicellular biological development, DNA template transcription, protein autophosphorylation, protein phosphorylation signal transduction, and angiogenesis/neurodifferentiation of the NA polymerase II promoter(<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). The enriched pathways were mainly as follows: axon guidance, focal adhesion, cGMP-PKG signaling pathway, signaling pathways regulating pluripotency of stem cells, EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor resistance, adrenergic signaling in cardiomyocytes, Rap1 signaling pathway, FoxO signaling pathway, endocrine resistance, PI3K-Akt signaling pathway, longevity regulating pathway, AMPK signaling pathway, neurotrophin signaling pathway, insulin signaling pathway, cAMP signaling pathway, Ras signaling pathway, ErbB signaling pathway, phosphatidylinositol signaling system, and oxytocin signaling pathway (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>D).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>PCR and gene regulatory network</title><p id="p0155">The expression levels of miR-1281 (DPs/HCs P = 0.0002) and <underline>miR-365a-3p</underline> (DP/HC P = 0.0087) were up-regulated in the serum of DPs compared with HCs, and miR-1281 (KXS/DPs P = 0.0003) was down-regulated after 8 weeks of KXS treatment. Compared with HCs, the expression levels of miR-2861 (DP/HC P = 0.0029) and miR-16-5p (DP/HC P &lt; 0.0001) were down-regulated in the serum of DPs, and miR-2861 (KXS/DP P = 0.0164) and miR-451a (KXS/DP P = 0.0185) were up-regulated after 8 weeks of KXS treatment. In addition, miR-940 (DP/HC P = 0.0002) and miR-766-3p (DP/HC P &lt; 0.0001) were down-regulated in the serum of DPs, and miR-940 (KXS/DP P = 0.0059) was up-regulated after 8 weeks of KXS treatment, not consistent with the results of previous microarray screening experiments. (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>Verification of the expression levels of eight differentially expressed miRNAs in three groups of serum samples by PCR</bold>. (A) Quantitative real-time PCR was used to detect the expression levels of several differentially expressed miRNAs obtained from the previous microarray screening in healthy controls, depressed patients, and the KXS-treated groups after 8 weeks of administration. The relative expression levels of miRNAs in serum samples were calculated by the 2-ΔΔCt method with Ce_miR-39_1 as the internal reference gene. (B) A microRNA–gene-pathway network analysis of 4 preselected target miRNAs. Compared between groups, *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001; ****P &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0160">Based on the PCR results, we selected miR-1281, miRNA-2861 and miRNA-940, which had significant differences in the changes in expression levels among the HC, DP and KXS groups, and miR-1202, which was not differentially expressed among the three groups (DP/HC P = 0.1838, KXS/DP P = 0.1126), but has been reported to be specific to depression in primates, was chosen for further bioinformatic analysis. A microRNA–gene-pathway network based on KEGG and Reactome dual libraries was constructed (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B).</p><p id="p0165">By comparing network eigenvalues, we found that all four miRNAs could regulate the core functions and important pathways related to depression and cognition. We selected miR-1281 as a target miRNA that may be related to the pathogenesis of depression and the antidepressant effect of KXS for further in vitro biological function study. The screening principles are as follows: (1)The results of PCR experiments showed that the expression levels of miR-1281 were consistent with the results of the previous microarray screening, and there were significant differences among the three groups. (2) miR-1281 interacts with more proteins in the signaling pathway network, and the predicted target genes of miR-1281 (ADCY1, CACNA1C, PRKCA, PRKCG, PRKACA, DVL1, etc.) are key node genes in the classical signaling pathways related to depression, such as cAMP, Wnt, CaMK, ErbB, mTOR, Long-term potentiation, and Axon guidance)(3)The literature suggests that the disorder of miR-1281 may be related to schizophrenia without insight [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], but it has not been reported to be related to depression. Therefore, as a new miRNA that may be related to depression and the antidepressant effect of KXS, miR-1281 has the value of in-depth research.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Prediction and validation of the target genes of miR-1281</title><p id="p0170">Bioinformatic and prediction analyses (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) identified the top four target genes with the strongest complementary binding to miR-1281, which were further validated for the top two target genes ADCY1 and DVL1. ADCY1 is a type I adenylate cyclase that catalyzes the production of cAMP. It is preferentially enriched in postsynaptic densities. Because ADCY1 activity can be dynamically regulated by calcium and neuron stimulation, its function is related to the regulation of neuronal development and synaptic plasticity [<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The cAMP pathway regulated by ADCY1 is a classical pathway related to depression, and it plays an important role in emotional regulation [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. DVL1 is another target gene regulated by miR-1281, and it belongs to the Dishevelled gene family, which plays an important role in the Wingless/Integrated (Wnt) signaling pathway [<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>]. The Wnt signaling pathway mediated by Wnt plays an important role in antidepressant therapy [<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>].<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Complementary binding of miR-1281 to predicted target genes.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0105">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">miRNA</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">gene_symbol</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">align_score</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">energy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">alignment</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">relevance</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADCY1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−28.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">|:|||| |||||||</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DVL1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−29.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">:|:||||||||||</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PRKCA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−30.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">|:|||:|||||||</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hsa-miR-1281</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PRKCG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−22.21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">|| |||:|||||||</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">negative</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Align score: complementary scores of miRNA and gene; Energy: thermal stability of free energy; Alignment: complementary regions of miRNAs and target genes; Relevance: correlation between miRNAs and the expression levels of target genes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0175">The wild-type ADCY1 and DVL1 reporter gene plasmids and the mutant ADCY1 and DVL1 reporter gene plasmids lacking the miR-1281 binding site were constructed and transfected into HEK293 cells(<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A–B). The expression levels of ADCY1 and DVL1 in the transfected cells were detected by chemiluminescence, and the binding to and regulation of ADCY1 and DVL1 by miR-1281 were studied. The results showed that the expression levels of ADCY1 and DVL1 in cells transfected with mutant ADCY1 and DVL1 plasmids were significantly higher than those in cells transfected with wild-type ADCY1 and DVL1 plasmids(<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C–D), indicating that wild-type ADCY1 and DVL1 could specifically bind to miR-1281 and be targeted by miR-1281. ADCY1 and DVL1 with mutant binding sites could not specifically bind to miR-1281. Overall, ADCY1 and DVL1 were target genes of miR-1281.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of miR-1281 on the expression levels of wild-type and mutant ADCY1/DVL1-transfected cells</bold>. (A–B) ADCY1 and DVL1 mutation sites. (C–D) The miR-1281 overexpression plasmid was cotransfected with the ADCY1 or DVL1 wild-type/mutant reporter plasmid into HEK293 human embryonic kidney cells. A dual-luciferase reporter assay was used to detect the levels of the ADCY1 or DVL1 reporter after transfection. Compared with the miR-1281-NC-ADCY1/DVL1 wild-type group and miR-1281-mimics-ADCY1/DVL1 wild-type group, ####P &lt; 0.0001, Compared with the miR-1281-mimics-ADCY1/DVL1 mutant type group and miR-1281-mimics-ADCY1/DVL1 wild-type group, ***P &lt; 0.001, ****P &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0180">The effect of KXS on the survival rate of SH-SY5Y cells and the expression of miR-1281, ADCY1 and DVL1 in corticosterone-injured SH-SY5Y cells</p><p id="p0185">The survival rate of SH-SY5Y cells in the corticosterone-treated group was significantly lower than that in the control group (p &lt; 0.0001). Compared with that of the corticosterone-treated group, the survival rates of SH-SY5Y cells in the KXS groups were significantly increased (p &lt; 0.0001 and p &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). The expression of miR-1281 was upregulated in the corticosterone-treated group, while ADCY1 and DVL1 expression levels were downregulated. After KXS administration, the expression of miR-1281 was downregulated, while ADCY1 and DVL1 expression levels were upregulated. There were significant differences between the groups (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>B–D).<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>Expression levels of miR-1281, ADCY1 and DVL1 in corticosterone-injured SH-SY5Y cells and after KXS treatment.</bold> Compared with the control group, #P &lt; 0.05, ##P &lt; 0.01, ###P &lt; 0.001, ####P &lt; 0.0001 compared with the corticosterone-injured group, *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001, ****P &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0190">The effect of KXS on cell proliferation and apoptosis and the modulation of miR-1281, ADCY1 and DVL1 expression in SH-SY5Y cells overexpressing miR-1281</p><p id="p0195">The transfection efficiency of the miR-1281 lentiviral expression vector in SH-SY5Y cells was as high as 90%(<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A<sub>1</sub>-A<sub>2</sub>). The expression of intracellular miR-1281 was detected by PCR after transfection with the lentiviral expression vector of miR-1281 and intervention with KXS at different doses. The method was the same as previously described. Compared with that in the negative control group, the expression of intracellular miR-1281 was significantly increased after transfection of the lentiviral expression vector, and it was significantly decreased in a concentration-dependent manner after KXS administration (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A<sub>3</sub>).<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of KXS on the viability and apoptosis of miR-1281-overexpressing SH-SY5Y cells and the relative expression levels of miR-1281 and target genes.</bold> (A) A-1 is a virus-infected cell; A-2 is a DAPI-labeled nucleus, and the image magnification is 200X. The expression levels of miR-1281 in the negative control vector and the miR-1281 lentiviral expression vector after transfection and in each group of cells after drug administration were determined by PCR and are shown in A-3. U6 was used as an internal control, and the relative expression level of miR-1281 was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> formula. The expression of the negative control (NC) group in the experiment was set as 1, and the relative expression levels of the other groups were compared to that of the NC group. (B–D) Effect of overexpressing miR-1281 on the phenotype of SH-SY5Y cells and the effect of KXS treatment. The CCK-8 method and flow cytometry were used to detect cell proliferation and apoptosis after miR-1281 was upregulated in SH-SY5Y cells and after treatment with KXS. (E) The effects of overexpressing miR-1281 on the expression levels of ADCY1 and DVL1. GAPDH was used as an internal reference, and the relative expression of each gene was compared using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> formula. Compared with NC, ##P &lt; 0.01, ###P &lt; 0.001; compared with the OE group, *P &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0085">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0200">The CCK-8 assay showed that there was no significant difference in cell proliferation between the negative control group and the normal control group (without intervention). However, the survival rate of SH-SY5Y cells was significantly reduced after transfection with the miR-1281 overexpression vector, which was significantly different from that of the negative control group (p &lt; 0.0001). The cell survival rates of the KXS groups were significantly increased in a dose-dependent manner (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>B).</p><p id="p0205"><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C<sub>1-6</sub>-D shows that after transfection with the negative control vector, the proportion of apoptotic cells was not significantly different from that of the normal control group. However, after transfection with the miR-1281 overexpression vector, the proportion of apoptotic cells was significantly increased compared with that in the normal control group (p &lt; 0.01). After intervention with 100 μg/mL and 500 μg/mL KXS, the proportion of apoptotic cells induced by overexpression of miR-1281 was significantly decreased.</p><p id="p0210"><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>E shows that the expression levels of ADCY1 and DVL1 in SH-SY5Y cells were significantly lower than those in the negative control group, while the expression levels of ADCY1 and DVL1 in the KXS groups were significantly higher after intervention with 100 μg/mL and 500 μg/mL KXS. Taken together, the abovementioned findings suggested that ADCY1 and DVL1 were the target genes of miR-1281.</p><p id="p0215">The regulatory effect of KXS on the classical depression pathways cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin in SH-SY5Y cells overexpressing miR-1281</p><p id="p0220"><xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A–F shows that after transfection of the miR-1281 overexpression vector, the expression levels of the key downstream target proteins PKA, pERK1/2, CREB, pCREB and BDNF in the ADCY1-mediated classical depression pathway (cAMP pathway) were significantly lower than those in the negative control group, while their expression levels were increased after KXS intervention. The expression levels of pGSK-3β and β-catenin, the key target proteins in the classical depression pathway Wnt, downstream of DVL, were significantly decreased after transfection of the miR-1281 overexpression vector, while they were significantly increased after KXS intervention (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>G–J).<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of KXS on the cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathways in cells after miR-1281 overexpression</bold>. Western blot was used to detect the effects of miR-1281 overexpression on cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin signal transduction pathways. (A–F) The effects of KXS on the expression levels of PKA, pERK1/2, CREB, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-CREB and BDNF proteins in the cAMP signaling pathway in cells after miR-1281 overexpression.(G–J) The effects of KXS on the expression levels of GSK-3β, pGSK-3β and β-catenin proteins in the Wnt signaling pathway in cells after miR-1281 overexpression. The expression of the negative control (NC) group in the experiment was set as 1, and the relative expression levels of the other groups were compared to that of the NC group. Compared with NC, ##P &lt; 0.01; compared with the OE group, *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0090">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0225">The expression of miRNAs related to depression has been confirmed at the clinical level (brain tissue, cerebrospinal fluid and peripheral blood of DPs). Compared with those in cadaveric brain tissue and cerebrospinal fluid, miRNAs in peripheral blood are the most promising biomarkers for the diagnosis of central nervous system diseases [<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. However, there has been no report on the regulatory effects of natural drugs and TCM compound antidepressants on the expression of miRNAs at the clinical level.</p><p id="p0230">A randomized, double-blind, double-dummy, parallel-controlled clinical trial was conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety of KXS in the treatment of mild/moderate depression. Blood samples from HCs, DPs and patients with definite efficacy after KXS administration were systematically studied at the molecular level. We analyzed serum samples from HCs and DPs, assessed the treatment efficiency of KXS by miRNA microarray, and identified differentially expressed miRNAs. The expression levels of 45 miRNAs were dynamically altered among the three groups, indicating that they might be both biomarkers of depression and targets of the antidepressant effect of KXS. GO classification showed that the differentially expressed miRNAs in this study mainly regulated the biological processes of RNA transcription, neurodevelopment, axon orientation, angiogenesis, neurodifferentiation and multicellular biological development. Pathway analysis further explored the relationship between the dysregulated miRNAs and the pathogenesis of depression and the molecular mechanism underlying the antidepressant effects of KXS. Our results suggested that multiple signaling pathways were closely related to depression, including the cAMP and MAPK signaling pathways, axon guidance, and the ErbB and neurotrophin signaling pathways.</p><p id="p0235">Subsequently, qRT–PCR was used to verify 10 differentially expressed candidate miRNAs in more serum samples, and the results showed that 6 miRNAs (miR-1281, miR-2861, miR-16-5p, miR-1202, miR-365a-3p and miR-451a) were consistent with the microarray results. These results suggest that KXS plays an antidepressant role by regulating multiple miRNAs at the epigenetic level. Of these differentially expressed genes, three miRNAs have been reported to be related to depression, and three have been associated with schizophrenia or neurological diseases [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Among them, miR-16 has been reported most frequently. It can participate in the regulation of the serotonin system and is involved in the molecular mechanism of antidepressant treatment. In previous animal experiments, our team also found that KXS significantly upregulated the expression of miR-16 in the rat hippocampus and injured neurons and significantly reduced serotonin transporter (SERT) expression [<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In the present study, we found that miR-16 was significantly downregulated in the serum of depressed patients but showed an upregulation trend after 8 weeks of KXS administration, which was consistent with a previous report in the literature and with the results of preliminary research at the animal and cellular levels by our research group, confirming the regulatory effect of KXS on miR-16 at the clinical level. MiR-1202 is the first miRNA that has been demonstrated to be abnormally expressed in both cadaver brain tissue and peripheral blood in patients with depression. Lopez et al. [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] compared miRNAs in the brain tissues of six species and found that miR-1202 was a primate-specific miRNA enriched in the human brain that was significantly downregulated in patients with depression. The results of the present study revealed a change in the expression level of miR-1202 before and after treatment with KXS, indicating that KXS may also exert antidepressant effects by regulating the glutamate system at the clinical level. Furthermore, these results were consistent with the test results at the brain neurotransmitter level obtained with the EEG tide fluctuation chart instrument in earlier clinical trials of KXS. The results of the changes in the transmitter parameters are shown before and after drug treatment compared with those of the control group fluoxetine. Compared to the control group, fluoxetine could only increase 5-hydroxytryptamine (5-HT) levels, while KXS was capable of simultaneously regulating a variety of neurotransmitter levels, including significantly reducing glutamate levels in patient brains [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p id="p0240">Moreover, there were significant differences in the dynamic changes in miR-1281 and miR-2861 expression among the three groups, and the expression trends were stable. Therefore, in view of the uniqueness of miR-1202, the novelty of miR-1281/2861, and the characteristics of the largest number of target genes regulated by miR-940, we reanalyzed the gene regulation networks of these four miRNAs and found that the important pathways regulated by these miRNAs are all closely related to depression and cognition.</p><p id="p0245">In particular, the network potential of miR-1281 was high, and miR-1281-regulated genes were mostly key nodes in the classical signaling pathway related to depression, suggesting that the abnormal regulation of miR-1281 may be related to the onset of depression and the antidepressant effect of KXS. Finally, we comprehensively considered the relevant studies reported in the literature, PCR verification results, regulatory network assignments, gene functions, and efficacy indicators of the previous clinical study conducted by our team and selected miR-1281 for further research as a new miRNA that may be related to the onset of depression and the antidepressant effect of KXS.</p><p id="p0250">Until now, only few studies have been published in which authors had identiﬁed miR-1281 as a potential biomarker in human diseases. Among these disease states were abdominal aortic aneurysm [<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], coronary heart disease and pulmonary arterial hypertension [<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], chronic nephropathy [<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], immune thrombocytopenic purpura [<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], malignant pleural mesothelioma [<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], diabetic retinopathy [<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], bladder cancer [<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and osteosarcoma [<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Our ﬁndings in the present work are consistent with these studies, implicating miR-1281 as a potential biomarker to track disease progression. In addition, it has been reported that miR-1281 is highly expressed in patients with schizophrenia without insight, and it shows a significant downward trend in the cured group. The difference between the onset group and the cured group is significant, and it is speculated that the differential expression of miR-1281 may be related to the symptoms of schizophrenia without insight [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. It shows a correlation with the phenotype of mental disorders. Our results here in indicate, for the ﬁrst time, that miR-1281 could indeed be a potential novel biomarker of depression and antidepressant treatment.</p><p id="p0255">We carried out in vitro experiments to study the neuronal function of miR-1281 and the regulatory mechanism of KXS treatment. The expression of miR-1281 in corticosterone-injured SH-SY5Y cells was increased, while the expression levels of its predicted target genes ADCY1 and DVL1 were decreased. miR-1281 could bind to the 3′ noncoding sequences of ADCY1 and DVL1, and the expression of ADCY1 and DVL1 was inhibited in miR-1281-overexpressing SH-SY5Y cells, suggesting that ADCY1 and DVL1 were the target genes of miR-1281. In addition, the survival rate of SH-SY5Y cells was reduced, and the apoptosis rate was obviously increased after transfection with miR-1281, which was blocked by KXS treatment, suggesting that KXS may exert neuroprotective effects by targeting miR-1281.</p><p id="p0260">Adcy1-type adenylate cyclase (ADCY1) is a neural-specific protein that catalyzes the production of cAMP and is preferentially enriched in the postsynaptic dense substance. The large increase in ADCY1 protein in the hippocampus of newborn rats in ADCY1 knockout mice destroyed LTP in cerebellar long-term enhancement [<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], and cAMP-producing ADCY1 is an integrated neuronal signaling pathway and participates in learning. It is a key molecule in memory processes [<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Previous studies have shown that the activity of ADCY1 is decreased in the cardiac tissues of patients with severe depression, and the cAMP pathway regulated by ADCY1 is also a classic pathway related to depression and plays an important role in emotion regulation [<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. DVL1 is another target gene regulated by miR-1281 and belongs to the Dishevelled gene family. The protein encoded by the Dishevelled gene is a cytoplasmic phosphoprotein that plays an important role in the Wingless/Integrated (Wnt) signaling pathway [<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Studies have shown that Dishevelled gene family defects lead to developmental abnormalities, and the DVL1 gene is involved in the regulation of sensorimotor and social behaviors in mice [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The Wnt signaling pathway mediated by DVL1 plays a very important role in antidepressant treatment, and gSK-3β, the downstream effector of DVL1, has become an important target of antidepressant mechanism research [<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Therefore, we continued to observe the influence of KXS on proteins expression in ADCY1 and DVL1 related signaling pathways. In this study, miR-1281 could inhibit its target genes ADCY1 and DVL1, and KXS could upregulate the expression of ADCY1 and DVL1 mRNAs and proteins, activate cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin signal pathways.</p><p id="p0265">The findings of this study must be interpreted in light of its limitations. First, our lack of a non-responsive group as a control allowed the differentially expressed miRNAs we studied to serve only as markers associated with the antidepressant effects of KXS, rather than as response markers. Second, the generalizability of these findings is limited as the samples were obtained from clinical trials, so that the results about the role of miR-1281 related to depression and antidepressant treatment of KXS need to be proved in stronger evidence studies. Last, this study also omitted to check and eliminate samples with low-level hemolysis. Release of microRNA content of blood cells upon hemolysis alters the microRNA profile in blood, potentially affecting levels of proposed biomarker microRNAs and, consequently, accuracy of serum-based tests, lead to false discovery of disease-associated biomarkers. The impact of hemolysis has been investigated for some microRNAs, such as the red blood cell (RBC)- enriched miRs-16 and -451. Further verification research is necessary, and quality control of hemolysis of serum samples can be conducted by spectrophotometric method, which could detect down to 0.004% hemolysis [<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0270">Collectively, based on the discovery of clinical-level miRNA expression profiles, the biological function of miR-1281 was elucidated in vitro from the perspective of posttranscriptional regulation. We found that the target genes of miR-1281 (ADCY1 and DVL1) were closely related to the occurrence and development of depression. It was demonstrated in vitro that KXS may activate the cAMP/PKA/ERK/CREB and Wnt/β-catenin signal transduction pathways by downregulating miR-1281, which targets ADCY1 and DVL1, to achieve its role in neuronal cell protection. These results provide a novel way of perceiving depression disorder, shedding light on the development of new therapeutic approaches.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0275">Chao Chen: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0280">Yuan-jie Xu: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0285">Shang-rong Zhang; Xiao-hui Wang; Yuan Hu; Dai-hong Guo; Xiao-jiang Zhou; Wei-yu Zhu; Ai-Dong Wen; Qing-Rong Tan: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0290">XianZhe Dong: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0295">Ping Liu: Conceived and designed the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0300">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">National Natural Science Foundation</funding-source> [81673877, 81373996, and 81173430].</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec8"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0305">Data will be made available on request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec9"><title>Declaration of interest’s statement</title><p id="p0310">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>IRB statement</title><p id="p0315">The experimental protocols involving human subjects were approved by the Ethics Committee of the Fourth Military Medical University (Xi'an, China). All experiments were conducted according to the related guidelines and regulations. Written informed consent was obtained from all the participants after they were provided a detailed explanation of the entire study. All procedures met the requirements established in the Declaration of Helsinki. The ethical clearance number is YS20150507-4.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savarino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Operskalski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suicide risk during antidepressant treatment</article-title><source>Am. J. Psychiatr.</source><volume>163</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.163.1.41</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromet</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of depression across cultures</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Publ. Health</source><volume>34</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031912-114409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4100461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23514317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serretti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lattuada</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smeraldi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depressive syndrome in major psychoses: a study on 1351 subjects</article-title><source>Psychiatr. Res.</source><volume>127</volume><issue>1–2</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2003.12.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15261708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A role of Yueju in fast-onset antidepressant action on major depressive disorder and serum BDNF expression: a randomly double-blind, fluoxetine-adjunct, placebo-controlled, pilot clinical study</article-title><source>Neuropsychiatric Dis. Treat.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>2013</fpage><lpage>2021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/ndt.s86585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4532216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26273204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The central dogma decentralized: new perspectives on RNA function and local translation in neurons</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>80</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.10.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24183017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3820025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jobe</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McQuate</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk among epigenetic pathways regulates neurogenesis</article-title><source>Front. Neurosci.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2012.00059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22586361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3347638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenkala</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamazon</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LaCroix</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Im</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA biogenesis and cellular proliferation</article-title><source>Transl. Res.</source><volume>166</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trsl.2015.01.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25724890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4509805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olde Loohuis</surname><given-names>N.F.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>G.J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Bokhoven</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadif Kasri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschrafi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA networks direct neuronal development and plasticity</article-title><source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-011-0788-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3249201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenetic and therapeutic applications of microRNAs in major depressive disorder</article-title><source>Prog. Neuro-Psychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry</source><volume>64</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2015.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4537399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25689819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouillet-Richard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs and depression</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Dis.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2011.12.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22226785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuellar</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harfe</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conditional loss of Dicer disrupts cellular and tissue morphogenesis in the cortex and hippocampus</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>4322</fpage><lpage>4330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.4815-07.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18434510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3844796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Carroll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Llinas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cerebellar neurodegeneration in the absence of microRNAs</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>204</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1553</fpage><lpage>1558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20070823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17606634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2118654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castrén</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rantamäki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of BDNF and its receptors in depression and antidepressant drug action: reactivation of developmental plasticity</article-title><source>Dev. Neurobiol.</source><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dneu.20758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20186711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor: role in depression and suicide</article-title><source>Neuropsychiatric Dis. Treat.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/ndt.s5700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2732010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19721723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouillet-Richard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-16 targets the serotonin transporter: a new facet for adaptive responses to antidepressants</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>329</volume><issue>5998</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1193692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouillet-Richard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Raphe-mediated signals control the hippocampal response to SRI antidepressants via miR-16</article-title><source>Transl. Psychiatry</source><volume>1</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>e56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2011.54</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22833211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3309472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA dysregulation in schizophrenia</article-title><source>Neurobiol. Dis.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbd.2011.12.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22207190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>A.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel microRNA and transcription factor mediated regulatory network in schizophrenia</article-title><source>BMC Syst. Biol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-4-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2834616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verissimo</surname><given-names>C.S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamphorst</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zweers</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA 18 and 124a down-regulate the glucocorticoid receptor: implications for glucocorticoid responsiveness in the brain</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>150</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2220</fpage><lpage>2228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2008-1335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Saavedra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoun</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanagiya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliva-Hernandez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornejo-Palma</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Iratxeta</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>miRNA-132 orchestrates chromatin remodeling and translational control of the circadian clock</article-title><source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddq519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3115667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clijsters</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agami</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The miRNA-192/194 cluster regulates the Period gene family and the circadian clock</article-title><source>FEBS J.</source><volume>276</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>5447</fpage><lpage>5455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2009.07229.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19682069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saus</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soria</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escaramís</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivarelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagerbauer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic variants and abnormal processing of pre-miR-182, a circadian clock modulator, in major depression patients with late insomnia</article-title><source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>4017</fpage><lpage>4025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddq316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20656788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belzeaux</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanjean</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loriod</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Formisano-Tréziny</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verrier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Responder and nonresponder patients exhibit different peripheral transcriptional signatures during major depressive episode</article-title><source>Transl. Psychiatry</source><volume>2</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>e185</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2012.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23149449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3565773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camkurt</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>Ş.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coşkun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Güneş</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Güneş</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yılmaz</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of plasma MicroRNA levels in drug naive, first episode depressed patients and healthy controls</article-title><source>J. Psychiatr. Res.</source><volume>69</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2015.07.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26343596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H.-m.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.-y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>A.-f.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of microRNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cells as specific biomarker for major depressive disorder patients</article-title><source>J. Psychiatr. Res.</source><volume>59</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2014.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25201637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MiR-335 is involved in major depression disorder and antidepressant treatment through targeting GRM4</article-title><source>Neurosci. Lett.</source><volume>606</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2015.08.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26314506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alterations of serum levels of BDNF-related miRNAs in patients with depression</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e63648</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2015.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3660391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23704927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M.-F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>J.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CSF miR-16 is decreased in major depression patients and its neutralization in rats induces depression-like behaviors via a serotonin transmitter system</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><volume>178</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2015.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25779937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preliminary comparison of plasma notch-associated microRNA-34b and -34c levels in drug naive, first episode depressed patients and healthy controls</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><volume>194</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2016.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26807671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedelius</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmér</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundquist</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating microRNA-144-5p is associated with depressive disorders</article-title><source>Clin. Epigenet.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13148-015-0099-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4509564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26199675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocchio-Chiavetto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maffioletti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bettinsoli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovannini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bignotti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tardito</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blood microRNA changes in depressed patients during antidepressant treatment</article-title><source>Eur. Neuropsychopharmacol</source><volume>23</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2012.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22925464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiori</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard-Devantoy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chachamovich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jollant</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of miR-1202, miR-135a, and miR-16 in major depressive disorder and antidepressant response</article-title><source>Int. J. Neuropsychopharmacol.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ijnp/pyx034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28520926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5570004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruceanu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crapper</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labonte</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>miR-1202 is a primate-specific and brain-enriched microRNA involved in major depression and antidepressant treatment</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24908571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4087015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preventive action of Kai Xin San aqueous extract on depressive-like symptoms and cognition deficit induced by chronic mild stress</article-title><source>Exp. Biol. Med.</source><volume>234</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3181/0812-rm-354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.-q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A representative prescription for emotional disease, Ding-Zhi-Xiao-Wan restores 5-HT system deficit through interfering the synthesis and transshipment in chronic mild stress-induced depressive rats</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2013.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H.-B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A bioactive compound from Polygala tenuifolia regulates efficiency of chronic stress on hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis</article-title><source>Pharmazie</source><volume>64</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1691/ph.2009.9580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19827305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai-Hong</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.-X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Behavioral and biochemical effects of Kaixin-San, a traditional Chinese medicinal empirical formula</article-title><source>Drug Dev. Res.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ddr.20252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.-B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antidepressant and neuroprotective effect of the Chinese herb kaixinsan against lentiviral shRNA knockdown brain-derived neurotrophic factor-induced injury in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Neuropsychobiology</source><volume>69</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000358089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24776773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidepressant-like effect of the extracted of Kai Xin San, a traditional Chinese herbal prescription, is explained by modulation of the central monoaminergic neurotransmitter system in mouse</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>139</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2011.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind study on the effects of SZL on patients with mild to moderate depressive disorder with comparison to fluoxetine</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>281</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">114549</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2021.114549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34438029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of the antidepressant effects of shen-zhi-ling in depressed patients: identification of proteins associated with platelet activation and lipid metabolism</article-title><source>Cell. Mol. Neurobiol.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10571-018-0582-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29564590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11481999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-depressive effects of Kai-Xin-San on lipid metabolism in depressed patients and CUMS rats using metabolomic analysis</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>252</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">112615</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.112615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31991203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z.-X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and subchronic oral toxicity assessment of the herbal formula Kai-Xin-San</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>138</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2011.08.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21884776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucca</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smeraldi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukine-6 serum levels correlate with response to antidepressant sleep deprivation and sleep phase advance</article-title><source>Prog. Neuro-Psychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry</source><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0278-5846(02)00255-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12452541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.-W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.-L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UPLC-Q-TOF-MS(E) analysis of the constituents of Ding-Zhi-Xiao-Wan, a traditional Chinese antidepressant, in normal and depressive rats</article-title><source>J. Chromatogr., B: Anal. Technol. Biomed. Life Sci.</source><volume>1026</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2015.07.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26320983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosterone-mediated regulation and functions of miR-218-5p in rat brain</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-03863-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34996981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8742130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.-R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LncRNA COL1A1-014 is involved in the progression of gastric cancer via regulating CXCL12-CXCR4 axis</article-title><source>Gastric Cancer</source><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10120-019-01011-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31650323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Investigation the Differentially Expressed microRNA in Serum from the Patients without Insight Schizophrenia</part-title><year>2014</year><publisher-name>Luzhou Medical College</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sichuan</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akkentli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erzurumlu</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Region-specific disruption of adenylate cyclase type 1 gene differentially affects somatosensorimotor behaviors in mice</article-title><source>eNeuro</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><comment>10.1523%2FENEURO.0007-14.2014</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4443438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26023682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethna</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced expression of ADCY1 underlies aberrant neuronal signalling and behaviour in a syndromic autism model</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14359</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms14359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5321753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28218269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almuedo-Castillo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saló</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dishevelled is essential for neural connectivity and planar cell polarity in planarians</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>108</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>2813</fpage><lpage>2818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1012090108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3041082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in development and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>127</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17081971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lijam</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paylor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrup</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Social interaction and sensorimotor gating abnormalities in mice lacking Dvl1</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>90</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)80354-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9298901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of glycogen synthase kinase 3 promotes axonal growth and recovery in the CNS</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>36</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>8914</fpage><lpage>8928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/jneurosci.1178-08.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18768685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6670875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jope</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>M.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase-3 (GSK3) in psychiatric diseases and therapeutic interventions</article-title><source>Curr. Drug Targets</source><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>1421</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389450110607011421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17100582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1850891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.-Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedhar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snider</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NGF-induced axon growth is mediated by localized inactivation of GSK-3beta and functions of the microtubule plus end binding protein APC</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2004.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15207235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.-F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating microRNAs: a novel class of potential biomarkers for diagnosing and prognosing central nervous system diseases</article-title><source>Cell. Mol. Neurobiol.</source><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10571-013-9940-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23633081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11497935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuai</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>D.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>W.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of differentially expressed microRNA profile in serum of patients with schizophrenia</article-title><source>J. Hosp. Grad. Stud.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1290</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16571/j.cnki.1008-8199.2014.12.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Effect of Dingzhi Xiaowan on miR-16 expression and 5-HT reuptake]</article-title><source>Zhongguo Zhongyao Zazhi</source><volume>43</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>3513</fpage><lpage>3518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19540/j.cnki.cjcmm.20180614.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30347920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasma microRNAs serve as potential biomarkers for abdominal aortic aneurysm</article-title><source>Clin. Biochem.</source><volume>48</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiochem.2015.04.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25916817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-DNA methyltransferase 1-miR-1281-Histone deacetylase 4 regulatory Axis mediates platelet-derived growth factor-induced proliferation and migration of pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>J. Am. Heart Assoc.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/jaha.117.007572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5907547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29514810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muralidharan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramezani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knoblach</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastav</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karandish</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extracellular microRNA signature in chronic kidney disease</article-title><source>Am. J. Physiol. Ren. Physiol.</source><volume>312</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>F982</fpage><lpage>F991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.00569.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5495885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasma microRNAs characterising patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title><source>Thromb. Haemostasis</source><volume>117</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1420</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1160/th-16-06-0481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28424819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bononi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puozzo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stendardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boschetto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orecchia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circulating microRNAs found dysregulated in ex-exposed asbestos workers and pleural mesothelioma patients as potential new biomarkers</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>7</volume><issue>50</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>82700</fpage><lpage>82711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.12408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27716620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5347725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiefari</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Accattato</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corigliano</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arcidiacono</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirabelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-1281 as a novel circulating biomarker in patients with diabetic retinopathy</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>528</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2020.00528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7417427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32849308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of non-invasive biomarkers for predicting the radiosensitivity of nasopharyngeal carcinoma from serum microRNAs</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>5161</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-61958-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32198434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7083955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MiR-1281, a p53-responsive microRNA, impairs the survival of human osteosarcoma cells upon ER stress via targeting USP39</article-title><source>Am. J. Canc. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1764</fpage><lpage>1774</lpage><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30323969" id="intref0020">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30323969</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6176178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smalheiser</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lugli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizavi</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torvik</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turecki</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA expression is down-regulated and reorganized in prefrontal cortex of depressed suicide subjects</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e33201</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3302855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22427989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smalheiser</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enoxacin elevates MicroRNA levels in rat frontal cortex and prevents learned helplessness</article-title><source>Front. Psychiatr.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2014.00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3918929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24575053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowburn</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcusson</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiehager</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenylyl cyclase activity and G-protein subunit levels in postmortem frontal cortex of suicide victims</article-title><source>Brain Res.</source><volume>633</volume><issue>1–2</issue><year>1994</year><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(94)91552-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8137164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maussion</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yerko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mechawar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of a truncated form of tropomyosin-related kinase B (TrkB) by Hsa-miR-185* in frontal cortex of suicide completers</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2012</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e39301</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3382618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22802923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cogswell</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of miRNA changes in Alzheimer's disease brain and CSF yields putative biomarkers and insights into disease pathways</article-title><source>J. Alzheimers Dis.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/jad-2008-14103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18525125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mumford</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Towler</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pashler</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilleard</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating MicroRNA biomarkers in melanoma: tools and challenges in personalised medicine</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom8020021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6022922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29701682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>J.J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>S.C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallely</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Zandwijk</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of hemolysis on cell-free microRNA biomarkers</article-title><source>Front. Genet.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2013.00094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23745127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3663194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soon</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of methodologies to detect low levels of hemolysis in serum for accurate assessment of serum microRNAs</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0153200</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4824492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27054342</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0320">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs2</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs3</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs3</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs4</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs4.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs4</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs5</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs5.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs5</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs6</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs6.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs6</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs7</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs7.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs7</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs8</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs8.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs8</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs9</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs9.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs9</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="figs10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>figs10</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmcfigs10.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>figs10</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0325">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e14265" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e14265</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>