
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sustain Chem Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sustain Chem Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3815</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">pheelsevier</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101748785</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sustainable Chemistry and Pharmacy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-5541</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Elsevier - PMC COVID-19 Collection</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10239909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10239909.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10239909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10239909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37333050</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scp.2023.101136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2352-5541(23)00170-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101136</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Green and rapid and instrumental one-pot method for the synthesis of imidazolines having potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 main protease activity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azimi</surname><given-names initials="S">Sabikeh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">∗∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merza</surname><given-names initials="MS">Muna S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names initials="F">Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhahi</surname><given-names initials="HA">Hasan Ali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baradarbarjastehbaf</surname><given-names initials="F">Farid</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moosavi</surname><given-names initials="M">Mehdi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kargar</surname><given-names initials="PG">Pouya Ghamari</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Len</surname><given-names initials="C">Christophe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Sciences, University of Birjand, Birjand, 97175-615, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Prosthetic Dental Techniques Department, Al-Mustaqbal University College, Babylon, 51001, Iraq</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>MSC in Software Engineering, Kowsar, The Institute of Higher Education, Ministry of Science, Research and Technology, Computer Engineering Department, Qazvin, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>National University of Science and Technology, Dhi Qar, Iraq</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Faculty of Pharmacy, Department of Pharmaceutical Technology and Biopharmacy, University of Pécs, Pécs, Hungary</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Chemistry, Mazandaran University, Babolsar, Iran</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Chimie ParisTech, PSL University, CNRS, Institute of Chemistry for Life and Health Sciences, 11 Rue Pierre et Marie Curie, F-75005, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Sorbonne Universités, Universite de Technologie de Compiegne, F- 60200, Compiegne, France</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. Chimie ParisTech, PSL University, CNRS, Institute of Chemistry for Life and Health Sciences, 11 rue Pierre et Marie Curie, F-75005, Paris, France.</corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">437373</issue-id><fpage>101136</fpage><lpage>101136</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-07-07 00:25:16.960"><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2023 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="44" journal-id="Sustain Chem Pharm" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC13325711"><article-title>Retraction notice to “Green and rapid and instrumental one-pot
method for the synthesis of imidazolines having potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 main protease
activity” [Sustain. Chem. Pharm. 34 (2023) 101136]</article-title><volume>44</volume><date><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><elocation-id>101920</elocation-id><source>Sustainable Chemistry and Pharmacy</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scp.2025.101920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13325711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">42394959</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome CoronaVirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is responsible for ongoing epidemics in humans and some other mammals and has been declared a public health emergency of international concern. In this project, several small non-peptide molecules were synthesized to inhibit the major proteinase (M<sup>pro</sup>) of SARS-CoV-2 using rational strategies of drug design and medicinal chemistry. M<sup>pro</sup> is a key enzyme of coronaviruses and plays an essential role in mediating viral replication and transcription in human lung epithelial and stem cells, making it an attractive drug target for SARS-CoV. The antiviral potential of imidazoline derivatives as inhibitors of (SARS-CoV-2) M<sup>pro</sup> was evaluated using <italic toggle="yes">in-silico</italic> techniques such as molecular docking simulation, molecular dynamics (MD), and ADMET prediction. The docking scores of these imidazoline derivatives were compared to that of the N3 crystal inhibitor and showed that most of these compounds, particularly compound <bold>E07</bold>, interacted satisfactorily in the active site of the coronavirus and strongly interacted with the residues (Met 165, Gln 166, Met 165, His 41, and Gln 189). Furthermore, the results were confirmed by MD simulations after exposure to long-term MD simulations and ADMET predictions.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ga1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2) M<sup>pro</sup></kwd><kwd>Imidazolines</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Bromosaccharin (NBSac)</kwd><kwd>In-silico studies</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0010">Handling Editor: Fabio Aricò</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0035">In December 2019, SARS-CoV-2 was identified as the cause of acute respiratory syndrome. By January 12, 2020, the World Health Organization (WHO) has declared a new pandemic in humans caused by nCoV 2019 (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Oran and Topol, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Saniasiaya et al., 2021</xref>). On February 11, 2020, the WHO warned that SARS-CoV-2 could lead to severe complications, such as septic shock and multiple organ failure, and could be fatal for in high-risk individuals, such as those with weakened immune systems, cancer, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and chronic respiratory diseases. Common symptoms of COVID-19 include fever, cough, and shortness of breath, while severe cases can result in pneumonia, acute respiratory syndrome, limb failure, and death. SARS-CoV-2, a severe acute respiratory syndrome beta-corona virus, is the virus responsible of causing COVID-19 (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Phan, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Ghamari Kargar et al., 2021</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">SARS-CoV-2 possesses four crucial proteins: membrane glycoproteins (M), spike proteins (S), coat proteins (E), and nucleocapsid proteins (N) (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Thomas, 2020</xref>). While the first three are located within a lipid bilayer, the N-positive viral protein covers the single-stranded RNA and plays an important role in virus transcription and translation (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Boopathi et al., 2020</xref>). The S protein is situated on the virus surface and facilitates SARS-CoV-2's entry into human cells by binding to the host cell (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2021</xref>). The packaging of new virions is then processed through proteolysis, controlled by two protease enzymes, the main coronavirus protease (M<sup>pro</sup>) and the papain-like protease (PL<sup>pro</sup>). M<sup>pro</sup> is often referred to as the "Achilles heel" of the virus and is considered one of the most attractive targets for drug development against SARS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Pillaiyar et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Gorbalenya et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Báez-Santos et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2005</xref>). GC376 is a peptide inhibitor that covalently alters the active site of Cys 145 and inhibits M<sup>pro</sup>, thereby preventing viral replication in infected cells (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Xu, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Huff et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">In recent times, numerous studies have been conducted to investigate SARS-CoV-2 inhibitors using in-silico techniques. Among these investigations, researchers have performed robust molecular dynamics (MD) simulations using GROMACS 4.6.7 and calculated thermodynamic binding free energy through Poisson-Boltzmann surface area analysis (MM-PBSA) of molecular mechanics against activity NSP16 SARS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2022</xref>), (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Ghamari kargar et al., 2022</xref>). Aditionally, <italic toggle="yes">in-silico</italic> therapeutic calculation, such as molecular binding site determination, MD simulation, and end-state thermodynamics, have been used to inhibit the S-RBD of SARS-CoV-2 by natural plant molecules (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2021b</xref>). Researchers have also used robust MD simulations to discover new protein inhibitors SARS-CoV-2 Nsp1 and investigate thermodynamic free energy calculations of the ligand-protein and strong interactions with the binding site (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2021a</xref>). In addition, a MD simulation study was conducted on the main components of saffron, including crocin, safranal, and picrocrocin to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 by calculating the binding energies between drug molecules and spike protein and viral protease. Researchers used Leonard Jones calculations and electrostatic potentials for this purpose (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kordzadeh et al., 2020</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Finally, in-silico</italic> studies based on docking and MD simulations, along with binding energy calculation using the Poisson-Boltzmann surface area approach (MM-PBSA), were conducted on the molecular mechanics of extraction alkaloids derived from 500 medicinal plants and sponges to contain SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Mohseni et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">In recent studies, imidazolines and their derivatives have been found to possess several medicinal properties, such vasodepressor activity (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Ernsberger et al., 1997</xref>), antihistaminic effects (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Ren and Cai, 2008</xref>), α-adrenergic inhibition (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Yokota et al., 2013</xref>), antitumor activity (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2015</xref>), histamine-like effects (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Krasavin, 2015</xref>), cholinomimetic activity (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Jakubowski et al., 2020</xref>), anti-inflammatory effects (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Regunathan et al., 1999</xref>), sympathomimetic effects (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Scholz, 1945</xref>), antinociceptive effects (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aglawe et al., 2014</xref>), antioxidant effects (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Faillace et al., 2020</xref>), and anticancer activities (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Ghomashi et al., 2022</xref>) making them useful in pharmaceutical applications. Therefore, the synthesis of imidazolines and their role in treating acute and dangerous diseases such as COVID-19 could be highly significant and effective. Previously, the production of imidazolines required the use of complex synthetic catalysts and challenging temperature conditions, which was time-consuming (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Kazemi et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Ortín and Dixon, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Shao et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">de la Campa et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Kok et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 2016</xref>). However, more recent studies have demonstrated the use of silver salt (AgF) as a catalyst for the preparation of biologically active 2-imidazolines under optimized conditions. These conditions included the asymmetric [3 + 2]-cycloaddition reaction of chiral <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-phosphonyl imines with methyl iso-cyanoacetate in a nonpolar medium at room temperature (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bagherzade et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Qiao et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bakhshi et al., 2021</xref>). Silver salts have been utilized as catalysts along with DBU as a base in an efficient catalytic system for the [3 + 1+1] annulation of iso-cyanoacetate with nitroarene as demonstrated by <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al. (2018)</xref>. However, DBU is an expensive base for synthesizing derivatives of 2-imidazolines. Therefore, implementing easy, fast, cheap and eco-friendly synthesis methods could greatly aid in the production of important drugs for treating dangerous diseases.</p><p id="p0055">To this end, our project aimed to develop a practical and streamlined one-pot synthesis of imidazolines under eco-friendly conditions, which could serve as potent inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>. Employing structure-based drug design strategies, we conducted rigorous and prolonged MD simulations (100 ns) and assessed the results of molecular docking, ultimately selecting the most promising compounds for the synthesis of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitors.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Experimental</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials and reagents</title><p id="p0060">All the solvents and reagents were procurement from commercial sources Merck and used without further refinement. Reaction advance checked out by thin-layer chromatography (TLC) using Merck silica gel 60 F254. Melting points were measured with an electrothermal melting point apparatus (Stafford, UK) and were uncorrected. <sup>1</sup>HNMR spectra were determined at 300 MHz (DMSO-d<sup>6</sup>, TMS) on a Bruker FT-300 MHz instrument (Karlsruhe, Germany). The purification of the compounds was realized with high-performance thin layer chromatography (HPTLC) model: CAMAG. CHNS Elemental Analyzer model: Costech ECS 4010.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>General procedure for the preparation of N-Bromosaccharin</title><p id="p0065"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Bromosaccharin (NBSac) was synthesized according to references (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Olszewski et al., 2019</xref>). In a 500 mL double-walled round bottom balloon equipped with a magnetic stirrer and ice bath, firstly 250 mL of distilled water and then sodium saccharin (10.25 g, 50 mmol), sodium carbonate (2.65 g, 25 mmol), and potassium bromide (3.78 g, 50 mmol) were added. After the material is completely dissolved in water at 0 °C, the oxone (30.75 g, 50 mmol) is dissolved in 30 mL of distilled water and slowly added to the solution. After stirring at room temperature for 24 h, successive filtration of the resulting milky precipitate with a Buchner funnel, wash of the precipitate with distilled water (2 × 50 mL), and dry of the solid in a vacuum oven at 50 °C furnished the pure NBSac as a white solid in 92% efficiency (with HPLC). The purity was confirmed by determining the melting point of 166 °C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>General synthetic method of functionalized imidazoline E01-E18</title><p id="p0070">A mixture of aldehydes (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), NBSac (1.0 mmol), and dry CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) was put into a dried round-bottomed flask was stirred for a particular time at room temperature. The reaction progress was monitored by TLC (eluent: n-Hexane-EtOAc, 4:1, v/v). After completion of the reaction, the mixture was diluted with H<sub>2</sub>O (10 mL), and then the reaction was quenched by the addition of saturated aqueous Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, aqueous NaOH (10%) or saturated aqueous NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (for 2- and 4-hydroxybenzaldehyde). The mixture was extracted with EtOAc or CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (3 × 10 mL). The organic layer was dried with anhydrous Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and concentrated under reduced pressure to give a crude product. Purification of compounds <bold>E01-E18</bold> was realized with high-performance thin layer chromatography (HPTLC).</p><p id="p0075">2-Phenyl-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E01</bold>). A solution of benzaldehyde (106 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E01</bold> as a white solid (140.2 mg) in 96% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.86–4.00 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.43 (s, 1H, NH), 6.92–7.09 (m, 3H, Hm,p-Ar), 7.84–7.88 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>10</sub>N<sub>2</sub>: C, 73.94; H, 6.89; N, 19.16; found: C, 73.52; H, 7.51; N, 18.97. mp 96–100 °C (mp 100–101 °C (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nikoofar and Dizgarani, 2017</xref>)).</p><p id="p0080">2-(4-Methoxyphenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E02</bold>). A solution of 4-methoxybenzaldhyde (136 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E02</bold> as a white solid (144.3 mg) in 82% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.42–3.64 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 3.81 (s, 3H, CH<sub>3</sub>–O), 6.40 (s, 1H, NH), 7.91–7.98 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 9.01–9.08 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 68.16; H, 6.86; N, 15.90; O, 9.08; found: C, 68.01; H, 6.90; N, 15.73. mp 136–138 °C (mp 139–140 °C (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nikoofar and Dizgarani, 2017</xref>)).</p><p id="p0085">2-(2-Methoxyphenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E03</bold>). A solution of 2-methoxybenzaldhyde (136 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E03</bold> as a white solid (140.0 mg) in 80% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.74–3.92 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 4.32 (s, 3H, CH<sub>3</sub>–O), 6.49 (s, 1H, NH), 7.1–7.17 (t, 1H, Hm-Ar), 7.34–7.36 (d, 1H, Hm-Ar), 7.61–7.67 (t, 1H, Hp-Ar), 7.94–7.96 (d, 1H, Hp-Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 68.16; H, 6.86; N, 15.90; O, 9.08; found: C, 68.11; H, 6.85; N, 15.88. mp 60–62 °C (mp 60–64 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0090">2-(p-Tolyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E04</bold>). A solution of 4-methylbenzaldhyde (120 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E04</bold> as a white solid (136.0 mg) in 85% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 2.47 (s, 3H, CH<sub>3</sub>-Ar), 3.87–3.97 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.45 (s, 1H, NH), 7.16–7.19 (d of d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 7.59–7.63 (d of d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>2</sub>: C, 74.97; H, 7.55; N, 17.48; found: C, 74.85; H, 7.60; N, 17.55. mp 176–178 °C (mp 177–179 °C (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nikoofar and Dizgarani, 2017</xref>)).</p><p id="p0095">4-(4,5-Dihydro-1H-imidazole-2-yl) phenol (<bold>E05</bold>). A solution of 4-hydroxybenzaldhyde (122 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E05</bold> as a white solid (132.9 mg) in 82% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.86–4.00 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.49 (s, 1H, NH), 6.83–6.89 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 7.31–7.39 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar), 9.67 (s, 1H, OH). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>10</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 66.65; H, 6.21; N, 17.27; O, 9.86; found: C, 66.51; H, 6.25; N, 16.98. mp 293–294 °C (mp 295–296 °C (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2008</xref>)).</p><p id="p0100">2-(4,5-Dihydro-1H-imidazole-2-yl) phenol (<bold>E06</bold>). A solution of 2-hydroxybenzaldhyde (122 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E06</bold> as white solid (129.6 mg) in 80% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.74–3.92 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.64 (s, 1H, NH), 6.92–6.97 (d, 1H, Hm-Ar), 7.03–7.12 (t, 1H, Hm-Ar), 7.30–7.41 (t, 1H, Hp-Ar), 7.78–7.79 (d, 1H, Ho–Ar), 10.27 (s, 1H, OH). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>10</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 66.65; H, 6.21; N, 17.27; O, 9.86; found: C, 66.65; H, 6.16; N, 17.25. mp 200–203 °C (mp 200–202 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0105">4-(4,5-Dihydro-1H-imidazole-2-yl) benzonitrile (<bold>E07</bold>). A solution of 4-cyanobenzaldehyde (131 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E07</bold> as a white solid (164.2 mg) in 96% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.82–3.96 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.55 (s, 1H, NH), 7.28–7.33 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 7.56–7.61 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>: C, 70.16; H, 5.30; N, 24.54; found: C, 70.10; H, 5.36; N, 24.54. mp 197–198 °C (mp 195–196 °C (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ishihara and Togo, 2007b</xref>)).</p><p id="p0110">2-(2-Nitrophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E08</bold>). A solution of 2-nitrobenzaldehyde (151 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E08</bold> as a white solid (171.9 mg) in 90% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.57–3.76 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.58 (s, 1H, NH), 7.59–7.66 (t, 1H, Hp-Ar), 7.79–7.84 (t, 1H, Hm-Ar), 7.94–7.98 (d, 1H, Hm-Ar), 8.12–8.18 (d, 1H, Hm-Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub>: C, 56.54; H, 4.75; N, 21.98; O, 16.74; found: C, 56.55; H, 4.89; N, 21.51. mp 95–97 °C (mp 98 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0115">2-(4-Nitrophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E09</bold>). A solution of 4-nitrobenzaldehyde (151 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E09</bold> as a white solid (181.5 mg) in 95% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.83–3.94 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.45 (s, 1H, NH), 8.12–8.15 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 8.47–8.50 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub>: C, 56.54; H, 4.75; N, 21.98; O, 16.74; found: C, 56.60; H, 4.80; N, 21.90. mp 240–242 °C (mp 232–234 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0120">2-(2-Chlorophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E10</bold>)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> A solution of 2-chlorobenzaldehyde (140 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E10</bold> as a white solid (162.0 mg) in 90% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.74–3.92 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>–CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.67 (s, 1H, NH), 7.37–7.91 (m, 4H, H–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>: C, 59.84; H, 5.02; Cl, 19.63; N, 15.51; found: C, 59.81; H, 5.11; N, 15.60. mp 68–70 °C (mp 69–70 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0125">2-(4-Chlorophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E11</bold>). A solution of 4-chlorobenzaldehyde (140 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E11</bold> as a white solid (153.0 mg) in 85% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.82–3.96 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>– CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.55 (s, 1H, NH), 7.28–7.33 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 7.56–7.61 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>: C, 59.84; H, 5.02; Cl, 19.63; N, 15.51; found: C, 59.85; H, 5.05; N, 15.50. mp 178–180 °C (mp 188 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0130">2-(3-Chlorophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E12</bold>). A solution of 3-chlorobenzaldehyde (140 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E12</bold> as a white solid (149.4 mg) in 83% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.76–3.89 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>– CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.66 (s, 1H, NH), 7.52–7.59 (m, 2H, Hm,p-Ar), 7.63–7.65 (d, 1H, Ho–Ar), 7.94 (s, 1H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>: C, 59.84; H, 5.02; Cl, 19.63; N, 15.51; found: C, 59.92; H, 4.96; N, 15.53. mp 136–138 °C (mp 136–137 °C (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2011</xref>)).</p><p id="p0135">2-(4-Bromophenyl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E13</bold>). A solution of 4-bromobenzaldehyde (185 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E13</bold> as a white solid (202.7 mg) in 90% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 3.79–3.97 (t, t, 4H, CH<sub>2</sub>– CH<sub>2</sub>), 6.47 (s, 1H, NH), 7.53–7.56 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 7.61–7.63 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>9</sub>BrN<sub>2</sub>: C, 48.03; H, 4.03; Br, 35.50; N, 12.45; found: C, 47.89; H, 4.05; N, 12.44. mp 244–246 °C (mp 243–245 °C (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nikoofar and Dizgarani, 2017</xref>)).</p><p id="p0140">4-(4,5-Dihydro-1H-imidazole-2-yl) pyridine (<bold>E14</bold>). A solution of 4-pyridinecarboxaldehyde (107 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E14</bold> as a white solid (135.3 mg) in 92% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 1.74–1.83 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>-imine), 3.29–3.39 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>–NH), 6.76 (s, 1H, NH), 8.15–8.20 (d, 2H, Hm-Ar), 8.63–8.66 (d, 2H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>: C, 65.29; H, 6.16; N, 28.55; found: C, 65.31; H, 6.14; N, 28.55. mp 194–196 °C.</p><p id="p0145">2-(4,5-Dihydro-1H-imidazole-2-yl) pyridine (<bold>E15</bold>). A solution of 2-pyridinecarboxaldehyde (107 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E15</bold> as a white solid (132.3 mg) in 90% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 1.69–1.83 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>-imine), 3.45–3.54 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>–NH), 6.87 (s, 1H, NH), 7.40–7.45 (t, 1H, Hp-Ar), 8.32–8.37 (t, 1H, Hm-Ar), 8.47–8.50 (d, 1H, Hm-Ar), 8.70–8.73 (d, 1H, Ho–Ar). Anal. calc for C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>: C, 65.29; H, 6.16; N, 28.55; found: C, 65.22; H, 6.16; N, 28.62. mp 98–100 °C (mp 102–103 °C (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nikoofar and Dizgarani, 2017</xref>)).</p><p id="p0150">2-(1H-Pyrrol-2-yl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E16</bold>). A solution of pyrrole-2-carboxaldehyde (95 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E16</bold> as a white solid (121.5 mg) in 90% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 1.28–1.43 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>-imine), 3.42–3.56 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>–NH), 6.14–6.19 (t, 1H, H-pyrrole), 6.52–6.56 (m, 2H, NH, H-pyrrole), 6.92–6.94 (t, 1H, H-pyrrole), 11.13 (s, 1H, NH-pyrrole). Anal. calc for C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>9</sub>N<sub>3</sub>: C, 62.20; H, 6.71; N, 31.09; found: C, 62.25; H, 6.70; N, 31.05. Yield: 90%; mp 211–213 °C (mp 212–213 °C (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">George and Papadopoulos, 1977</xref>)).</p><p id="p0155">2-(Thiophen-2-yl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E17</bold>). A solution of 2-thiophene-2-carboxaldehyde (112 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E17</bold> as a white solid (121.6 mg) in 80% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 1.31–1.43 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>-imine), 3.45–3.56 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>–NH), 6.48 (s, 1H, NH), 6.94–7.00 (t, 1H, H-thiophen), 7.29–7.34 (d, 1H, H-thiophen), 7.70–7.75 (s, 1H, H-thiophen). Anal. calc for C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>S: C, 55.24; H, 5.30; N, 18.40; S, 21.06; found: C, 55.20; H, 5.32; N, 14.37. mp 180–182 °C (mp 175–177 °C (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">George and Papadopoulos, 1977</xref>)).</p><p id="p0160">2-(Furan-2-yl)-4,5-dihydro-1H-imidazole (<bold>E18</bold>). A solution of furan-2-carboxaldehyde (96 mg, 1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (288 mg, 3.0 mmol), NBSac (300 mg, 1.0 mmol) in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) gave compound <bold>E18</bold> as a white solid (115.6 mg) in 85% yield. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>, 300 MHz): <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> (ppm) = 1.31–1.43 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>-imine), 3.45–3.56 (t, 2H, CH<sub>2</sub>–NH), 6.42 (s, 1H, NH), 6.86–6.92 (t, 1H, H-furan), 7.17–7.22 (d, 1H, H-furan), 8.08–8.14 (s, 1H, H-furan). Anal. calc for C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O: C, 61.75; H, 5.92; N, 20.58; O, 11.75; found: C, 61.80; H, 6.00; N, 20.58. mp 170–171 °C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Molecular docking studies</title><p id="p0165">Molecular docking studies are used to determine the optimal ligand orientation with the lowest energy in the protein's active site, which indicates a strong affinity for the substrate for the enzyme. In this study, we used the Molecular Operation Environment (MOE) 2019 software for docking studies. The ligands' PDB file and the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> crystal structure (PDB ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0010">6LU7</ext-link>) for docking studies were obtained from the RCSB Protein Data Bank (RCSB PDB) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org" id="intref0015"><italic toggle="yes">http://www.rcsb.org</italic></ext-link>). Following the MOE 2019, we removed the extra chains of the protein, and added polar hydrogens. We then used the triangle matcher method to identify the optimal placement and selected the londen ΔG algorithm as the scoring matrix. We generated 100 poses and selected the top 30 based on the lowest ΔG after refining the results. We evaluated the docking scores based on the ligand's orientation in the protein's active site (Gly 143, Phe 140, His 164, Met 165, Glu166, His 172, Gln189, Thr 190) as well as the minimum ΔG energy resulting from its interaction with the receptor.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Molecular dynamic studies</title><p id="p0170">MD simulations have become a standard tool for studying biomolecules and complementing experimental techniques, enhancing our understanding of biochemical processes, and providing dynamic dimensions to structural data. This technique enables exploration of structural space, including in ligand docking programs, and allows chemists to perform simulations that are not feasible in a laboratory, bridging the gap between theory and experiment. Comparing simulation and experimental test data, assessing the accuracy of calculated results, and improving laboratory methods are critical steps in this field. In this study, we used GROMACS software (5.1.2 version) and CHARMM36 force field (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Omidkhah et al., 2022</xref>) to simulate MD. We created a topology file (Topol. top) for the protein and ligand (imidazoline derivatives). The MD simulations were performed in a virtual cubic box filled with explicit water (SPC/E), with the protein located at the center of the box and a distance of 1 nm from the neighboring box. The system was neutralized by adding ions, and after performing the minimization steps, the system reached equilibrium for temperature and pressure (300 K, 100 ns, and 1 atm). The results were analyzed using Visual Molecular Dynamics (VMD) and PyMOL software. We calculated the root-mean-square deviation (RMSD), root-mean-square fluctuation (RMSF), radius of gyration (Rg), and hydrogen bonds (H bonds) using MD calculation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Synthesis of NBSac and imidazoline derivatives</title><p id="p0175">The reagent chosen for the imidazoline synthesis was <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Bromosaccharin (NBSac) using a conventional method (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Olszewski et al., 2019</xref>). To prepare NBSac, an aqueous solution of oxone was added dropwise to a mixture of sodium saccharin, sodium carbonate, and potassium bromide at 0 °C (<xref rid="sch1" ref-type="fig">Scheme 1</xref>
). After the reaction was completed, pure NBSac was obtained as a white solid with 92% efficiency (determined by HPLC).<fig id="sch1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption><p>Synthesis of NBSac.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Scheme 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sc1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0180">After obtaining NBSAc, we conducted a model reaction to synthesize imidazoline using benzaldehyde and ethylenediamine, while varying different reaction parameters such as solvent type, temperature, and NBSac quantity. For the entire study, we purified the imidazoline derivatives using high-performance thin layer chromatography (HPTLC). When we mixed a solution of benzaldehyde (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), and dry CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) for 120 min without NBSac or in the presence of saccharin as a pioneer salt (1.0 mmol), the transformation was low, as expected. We attempted a solvent-free reaction to make the process more cost-effective and environmentally friendly but were unsuccessful. To optimize the reaction conditions, we tested different solvents (THF, CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>3</sub>CN, Et<sub>2</sub>O) under mild conditions. The use of CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> under similar conditions resulted in 96% yield of the target imidazoline after just 20 min (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
). However, when we used other solvents such as THF, CH<sub>3</sub>CN, and Et<sub>2</sub>O, the yields of imidazole were low and the reaction times were longer.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Effect of solvents on the synthesis of 2-phenyl-2-imidazoline <bold>E01</bold> in the presence of NBSac at room temperature. Reaction conditions: benzaldehyde (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), NBSac (1.0 mmol), and solvent (5 mL) at room temperature.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0185">In the second step, we tested two temperatures (25 and 40 °C) using CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> as the solvent. However, increasing the temperature from 20 °C to 40 °C did not improve the yield or productivity. Next, we studied the role of NBSac in the reaction rate and product efficiency (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
). We investigated the effect of increasing the amount of NBSac from 0 to 1.5 mmol. As the concentration increased from 0 to 1.5 mmol, the yield of <bold>E01</bold> also increased proportionally until it reached a maximum of 96% at a concentration of 1.0 mmol. With our optimized reaction condition (aldehyde (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), NBSac (1.0 mmol), and CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) at room temperature for an appropriate amount of time), we screened a range of aromatic and heterocyclic aldehydes with varying electronic and steric demands.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Variation of the amount of NBSac on the synthesis of 2-phenyl-2-imidazoline <bold>E01</bold>. Reaction conditions: benzaldehyde (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), NBSac (0–1.5 mmol), and CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) at room temperature for 20 min.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0190">Both electron-donating (EDG) and electron-withdrawing (EWG) groups on the phenyl ring of imidazoline derivatives were found to be suitable for the reaction. Aromatic aldehydes <bold>E02-E06</bold> with EDG groups were converted to the corresponding imidazolines in similar or longer reaction times (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
, entries 2–6), while aromatic aldehydes <bold>E07-E09</bold> containing EWG groups were transformed to the corresponding imidazolines in shorter reaction times (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, entries 7–9). In case where a chloride atom was present, the reaction time was 20 min and imidazolines were obtained in yields of 83–90% (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, entries 10–12). Similar results were obtained when the chloride atom was substituted by a bromide atom (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, entries 11 and 13). When heteroaromatic moieties were presented in the starting material, the imidazoline synthesis gave the corresponding chemicals in yields of 80–92% yields after 15–30 min (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, entries 14–18).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>NBSac helped the formation of imidazolines derivatives <bold>E01-E18</bold> and docking scores. <xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Entry</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Structure of R</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time (min)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yield (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ΔG (Kcal mol<sup>−1</sup>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">K<sub>i</sub> (μM)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Residues</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bond distances (Ǻ)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0055">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E01</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">96</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−6.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0060">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E02</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−7.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx4_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0065">Image 4</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>E03</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">−7.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">5.39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx5_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0070">Image 5</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E04</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">85</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−7.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx6_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0075">Image 6</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>E05</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx7_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0080">Image 7</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>E06</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx8_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0085">Image 8</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>E07</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">96</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">−8.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">98.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asn 142</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gly 143</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx9_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0090">Image 9</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E08</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−7.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx10_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0095">Image 10</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E09</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">95</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−7.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">6.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx11_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0100">Image 11</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E10</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−6.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx12_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0105">Image 12</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E11</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">85</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−6.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thr 190</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx13_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0110">Image 13</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>E12</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">−7.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">6.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx14_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0115">Image 14</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>E13</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx15_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0120">Image 15</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E14</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">92</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−6.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 166</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx16_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0125">Image 16</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>E15</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">−6.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx17_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0130">Image 17</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><bold>E16</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">−6.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arg 188</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx18_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0135">Image 18</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1"><bold>E17</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">−7.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">5.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 164</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">His 164</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met 149</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fx19_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0140">Image 19</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>E18</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−6.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gln 189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.92</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fx1_lrg.jpg"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0010">Reaction conditions: aldehyde (1.0 mmol), ethylenediamine (3.0 mmol), NBSac (1.0 mmol), and CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (5 mL) at room temperature.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0195">Furthermore, aliphatic aldehydes were also used for the synthesis of corresponding imidazolines with appropriate reaction times and high to excellent yields (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, entries 20, 21). These results demonstrate the generality and scope of the reaction for various aromatic, aliphatic, and heterocyclic aldehydes.</p><p id="p0200">Based on these results, a plausible mechanism for the synthesis of imidazoline can be proposed (<xref rid="sch2" ref-type="fig">Scheme 2</xref>
). In CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>, the aldehyde and ethylenediamine first generate the imine, which subsequently forms the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetal. The nitrogen atom of the nucleophilic ethylenediamine attacks the electrophilic carbon atom of the formyl group <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> an addition reaction without the need for an acid catalyst. After rearrangement, the hemiaminal leads to the corresponding imine. Similarly, the nitrogen atom of the primary amine attacks the electrophilic carbon atom of the imine, and after rearrangement, the corresponding imidazolidine is obtained. In the presence of NBSac, the hydrogen atom of the imidazolidine is substituted by the bromine atom of NBSac, which affords the corresponding 1-bromoimidazolidine. Then, conventional elimination furnishes the target imidazoline (<xref rid="sch2" ref-type="fig">Scheme 2</xref>). This reaction has several advantages, such as mild reaction conditions, low reaction temperature, and the use of an almost neutral reagent (NBSac).<fig id="sch2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Scheme 2</label><caption><p>Mechanistic pathway for the synthesis of imidazoline using NBSac.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Scheme 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sc2_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0205">After our study, various methods for preparing imidazolines from aldehydes were investigated, and the results were reported in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
. Most reactions required a temperature higher than room temperature. Among the reactions carried out at room temperature, two used NBS or NBSac in dichloromethane. Our optimized method allows for the synthesis of imidazoline derivatives from the parent aldehyde at room temperature in just 20 min with high efficiency, without requiring strong acidic and alkaline conditions.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the methods of synthesis of imidazolines based on reactions of benzaldehyde and ethylenediamine.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0145">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Entry</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reagent</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Solvent</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Temp. (<sup>o</sup>C)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time (min)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yields (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, NaI, MgSO<sub>4</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t-BuOH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., (2011)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K<sub>4</sub>Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r.t</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Shaikh et al. (2012)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref> HPW, <xref rid="tbl2fnb" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref> TBAB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2019)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="tbl2fnc" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref> NBS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dry TBME or CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Fujioka et al. (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I<sub>2</sub>/KI/K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gogoi and Konwar, 2006</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I<sub>2</sub>,K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t-BuOH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Ishihara and Togo (2007a)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="tbl2fnd" ref-type="table-fn">d</xref> CAN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dry-CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reflux</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Joshi (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NBS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65–70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Sant’ Anna et al., 2009</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NBSac</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">r.t</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>This work</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">Tungstophosphoric acid.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnb"><label>b</label><p id="ntpara0020">Tetrabutylammonium bromide.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnc"><label>c</label><p id="ntpara0025">N-bromosuccinimide.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnd"><label>d</label><p id="ntpara0030">Ceric ammonium nitrate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Recognize the imidazolines as a type of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitors with <italic toggle="yes">in-silico</italic> studies</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Molecular docking studies</title><p id="p0210">Docking was performed using MOE 2019 software on SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> structure (PDB ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0020">6LU7</ext-link>). The binding scores, inhibition constant (Ki), and bond distances (Ǻ) were recorded in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> based on the orientation of the ligand in the active site of the protein (Gly 143, Phe 140, His 164, Met 165, Glu166, His 172, Gln189, Thr 190). Several compounds (<bold>E01</bold>, <bold>E08</bold>, <bold>E12</bold>, <bold>E14</bold>, <bold>E15</bold>) were founded to form hydrogen bonds with Met 165 and also have π-π stacking interaction with catalytic His41. Compound <bold>E17</bold> formed two hydrogen bonds with the backbone of His 164 and the side chain of Gln189. The interaction of <bold>E16</bold> with SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> showed a hydrogen bond with Met165 and Gln189 and Arg188, while also exhibiting π-π stacking interaction between His41 and the ligand. Other compounds (<bold>E10</bold>, <bold>E09</bold>, <bold>E02</bold>, <bold>E03</bold>, <bold>E04</bold>, <bold>E11</bold>) were found to form hydrogen bonds with Met165 and interact with Glu166, Gln189 and Thr190 protein residues. Compound <bold>E07</bold> formed hydrogen bonds with Asn142 and Gly143 while maintaining π-π interaction with catalytic His41. Compounds <bold>E05</bold> and <bold>E18</bold> managed to form a hydrogen bond with the side chain of Gln189. Based on the docking result, compound <bold>E07</bold> had the lowest binding energy (−8.19 kcal/mol) and performed better than the other compounds. The binding score was close to the reference structure crystal (N3) with the lowest binding energy (−9.56 kcal/mol) in the cavity of the active site (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(a) 2D representation of the docking result of (<bold>E07</bold>) into the tunnel-like binding site of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>. (b) 2D representation of the docking result of N<sub>3</sub>. (c) 3D representation of the docking poses of <bold>E07</bold> into the tunnel-like binding site of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>. (d) 3D representation of docking poses of N<sub>3</sub> into the tunnel-like binding site of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Molecular dynamic simulation</title><p id="p0215">The study utilized MD simulation to investigate the structural changes, stability, and flexibility of the protein in the presence of compound <bold>E07</bold>. The root-mean-square deviation (RMSD), root-mean-square fluctuation (RMSF), and radius of gyration (Rg) were calculated to asses these properties. The results indicate that compound <bold>E07</bold> remains in the active site and binds to amino acids Glu192, Thr190, and Asp187, resulting in maximum protein stability (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
).<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Close-up view of the binding interactions of compound (<bold>E07</bold>) with SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins after MD simulation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0220"><italic toggle="yes">Analysis of hydrogen bonds.</italic> Hydrogen bonds are one of the fundamental bonds in biological systems and are responsible for molecular interactions. The binding of a ligand to a protein in an aqueous medium requires hydrogen bonds. The results of this study show that, on average, three hydrogen bonds were formed during the simulation, demonstrating the stability of protein-ligand interactions within the active site of SARS-CoV-2. The hydrogen bonding of compound <bold>E07</bold> is shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
(a).<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>(a) Hydrogen bond numbers of compound <bold>E07</bold>, during 100 ns MD simulation. (b) Plot of RMSD alpha carbon of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins in green and SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins with compound <bold>E07</bold> in purple during 100 ns simulation. (c) Graph of RMSF changes of alpha carbon SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins in green and SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins with compound <bold>E07</bold> in purple during 100 ns simulation. (d) Plot of changes of alpha carbon SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> proteins in green and in the presence of compound <bold>E07</bold> in blue in during 100 ns simulation. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5_lrg.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0225"><italic toggle="yes">Root-mean-square deviation (RMSD).</italic> RMSD values are used to evaluate the stability of a ligand-protein complex compared to the non-protein binding state. For the apo-form of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>, the average RMSD of alpha carbon was found to be 0.21 ± 0.040 nm), whereas in the presence of compound <bold>E07</bold>, the average RMSD was 0.27 ± 0.031 nm (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> (b)). Starting from 40 ns, the protein stability increased to a satisfactory relative strength. The ligand remained stable during the simulation, as indicated by the average RMSD value. However, the change of RMSD was slightly larger than that of the apo-form of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>, suggesting that ligand binding may have increased the compound's flexibility (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abdizadeh et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0230"><italic toggle="yes">Root means square fluctuation (RMSF).</italic> RMSF is a measure of the ratio of fluctuations in amino acid levels and is crucial for predicting the structural stability of proteins. Low RMSF values are associated with high levels of structural stability, and relatively stronger binding of the ligand to the active site residues, resulting in less flexibility. High fluctuating residues are typically far from the active site in protein rings or terminals. After 100 ns of simulation, the mean RMSF changes in the complex compound <bold>E07</bold>-protein and protein alone were obtained, yielding values of 0.11 ± 0.078 nm and 0.12 ± 0.077 nm, respectively. These mean RMSF values were lower in the complex state than in the protein state. As shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> (c) on the RMSF plot, the N and C terminals of the protein exhibit greater oscillation than other regions involved in ligand binding. The results indicate that compound <bold>E07</bold> forms a stable and well-fitted complex with the protein.</p><p id="p0235"><italic toggle="yes">The radius of gyration (Rg).</italic> The radius of gyration (Rg) is a measure of the compactness, shape, and folding of a protein structure. It refers to the mass-weighted root-mean-square distance of a set of atoms from their common center of mass. The average Rg value calculated for the protein was 1.74 ± 0.29 nm. In the presence of compound <bold>E07</bold>, The Rg value was 1.69 ± 0.25 nm after 100 ns of simulation, as shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> (d). The highest Rg plot suggests a looser packing of amino acids, whereas the lowest Rg value indicates a highly compact conformation of the ligand complex without any change to the overall structure and folding of the protein.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>ADMET studies</title><p id="p0240">The ADMET parameter was utilized for <italic toggle="yes">in-silico</italic> studies of the pharmacokinetic properties of synthetic imidazole derivatives through the pkCSM-pharmacokinetics online server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biosig.unime%20lb.edu.au/pkcsm/prediction" id="intref0035">http://biosig.unime lb.edu.au/pkcsm/prediction</ext-link>). ADMET is a descriptor that encompasses absorption, distribution, metabolism, excretion, and toxicity. The canonical SMILES of the compounds were extracted from PubChem (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" id="intref0025"><italic toggle="yes">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</italic></ext-link>) to calculate the ADMET parameters. In this section, we investigated parameters such as intestinal absorption (human) (HIA), blood-brain barrier (BBB) penetration, hepatotoxicity and CYP2D6 enzyme, water solubility, polar surface area (PSA), and lipophilicity (LogPo/w). The pharmacokinetic property analysis results are presented in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
. Based on the results and water solubility (log (mol L<sup>−1</sup>)): insoluble &lt; −10 &lt; poorly soluble &lt; −6 &lt; moderately &lt; - 4 &lt; soluble &lt; −2 &lt; very soluble &lt;0 &lt; highly soluble, compounds (<bold>E03</bold>, <bold>E04</bold>, <bold>E05</bold>, <bold>E06</bold>, <bold>E07</bold>, <bold>E08</bold>, <bold>E09</bold>, <bold>E10</bold>, <bold>E11</bold>, <bold>E12</bold>, <bold>E13</bold>) demonstrated good solubility in water, which reduces dehydration and binding to lipophilic targets in cells, thus decreasing the toxicity of the compounds. The lipophilicity of the drug and the permeability of the membrane is expressed by logP (octanol-water partition coefficient) (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Omidkhah et al., 2022</xref>), (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Abdizadeh et al., 2022</xref>). The intestinal absorption (human) (HIA) of most of the compounds is over 90%, which is a favorable characteristic for the synthesis of oral drugs. The blood-brain barrier (BBB) penetration of the compounds, with the exception of <bold>E01</bold>, <bold>E03</bold>, <bold>E10</bold>, <bold>E11</bold>, <bold>E12</bold>, <bold>E13</bold>, and <bold>E17</bold> was predicted to be poor.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">In-silico</italic> ADMET prediction of the imidazolines derivatives.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0150">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Compound name</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Absorbtion<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Distribution<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metabolism<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toxicity<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Solubility (log mol/L)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intestinal absorption (human)<break/>(% Absorbed)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">BBB<break/>Permeability (log BB)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CPY2D6</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatotoxicity</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Log P</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.074</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.49</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.327</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.187</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.219</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.219</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.70</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.159</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.66</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.127</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.55</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.158</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.201</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.197</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.271</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.83</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.93</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.219</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.76</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0245">Regarding metabolism, these compounds may undergo metabolism by CYP2D6. In the toxicity screening, most of the hepatotoxic compounds did not exhibit toxicity, and the polar surface area (PSA) of all compounds was &lt;.140 Å<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Shanmugarajan et al., 2020</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0250">To establish an enzymatic mechanism of inhibition and design compounds with potent antiviral activity, we employed drug chemistry methods and sound drug design principles for the main protease of SARS-CoV-2. We present a class of imidazoline compounds synthesized efficiently using a cheap, non-metallic, and readily available catalyst under mild reaction conditions with high to excellent efficiency, short reaction time, no metal, and exceptionally compatible conditions. We identified hazardous organic solvents that can be avoided to minimize the impact on the environment and the potential interaction with SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>.</p><p id="p0255">The imidazoline derivatives were characterized using various methods such as <sup>1</sup>HNMR and CHN analysis, allowing the synthesis of a wide range of pharmaceutical compounds. Docking and MD simulation and ADMET prediction showed that some synthetic imidazoline compounds possess the inhibitory power of M<sup>pro</sup>. It remains to be seen whether the imidazoline derivatives presented in this study could also inhibit additional protease such as papain protease like SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup>, which is a promising drug target due to its crucial role in viral propagation and replication and its ability to promote immune escape via the isolated gene 15 protein (ISG15). Future studies should use animal models to assess the toxicity and efficacy of this class of imidazoline compounds, which could potentially be used for Covid-19 therapy.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0260"><italic toggle="yes">S. Azimi</italic>: Methodology, Conducting the experiment, Writing–original draft, Writing–review &amp; editing. <italic toggle="yes">M.S Merza</italic>: Conceptualization, Investigation. <italic toggle="yes">Fatemeh Ghasemi</italic>: Software. <italic toggle="yes">H. A. Dhahid</italic>: Investigation. <italic toggle="yes">F. Baradarbarjastehbaf</italic>: Data curation, Methodology. <italic toggle="yes">M. Moosavi</italic>: Conducting the experiment. <italic toggle="yes">P. Ghamari kargar</italic>: Writing–original draft, Writing–review &amp; editing. <italic toggle="yes">C. Len</italic>: Supervision, Revised and review manuscript (final draft and revised version).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0265">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdizadeh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalani</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abnous</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayarani-Najaran</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khashyarmanesh</surname><given-names>B.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdizadeh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghodsi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadizadeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design, synthesis and biological evaluation of novel coumarin-based benzamides as potent histone deacetylase inhibitors and anticancer agents</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>132</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2017.03.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdizadeh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadizadeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdizadeh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico analysis and identification of antiviral coumarin derivatives against 3-chymotrypsin-like main protease of the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Mol. Divers.</source><volume>26</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11030-021-10230-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34213728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8251691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aglawe</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taksande</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuldhariya</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopde</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umekar</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotagale</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Participation of central imidazoline binding sites in antinociceptive effect of ethanol and nicotine in rats</article-title><source>Fundam. Clin. Pharmacol.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/fcp.12034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23600743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Báez-Santos</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St John</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesecar</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SARS-coronavirus papain-like protease: structure, function and inhibition by designed antiviral compounds</article-title><source>Antivir. Res.</source><volume>115</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.12.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25554382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5896749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagherzade</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhshi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>kargar</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of organic nanocomposite using Pistacia Vera L. Hull: an efficient antimicrobial agent</article-title><source>Medbiotech J</source><volume>5</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22034/MBT.2021.135222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8286193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34335708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A facile and efficient synthesis of 2-imidazolines from aldehydes using hydrogen peroxide and substoichiometric sodium iodide</article-title><source>Synthesis</source><year>2011</year><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1259992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhshi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagherzade</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghamari kargar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of organic nanocomposite using Pistacia vera L. Hull: an efficient antimicrobial agent</article-title><source>Bioinorgan. Chem. Appl.</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2021/4105853</pub-id><comment>2021</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8286193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34335708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boopathi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poma</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolandaivel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel 2019 coronavirus structure, mechanism of action, antiviral drug promises and rule out against its treatment</article-title><source>J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn.</source><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07391102.2020.1758788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7196923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32306836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Campa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gammack Yamagata</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortín</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franchino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic enantio- and diastereoselective Mannich reaction of α-substituted isocyanoacetates and ketimines</article-title><source>Chem. Commun.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>10632</fpage><lpage>10635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6CC04132A</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27500289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernsberger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koletsky</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The I1-imidazoline receptor</article-title><source>J. Hypertens.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>S9</fpage><lpage>S23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004872-199715011-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1351308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9050981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faillace</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves Borges Leal</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muratori da Costa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peláez</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sulfated and oxygenated imidazoline derivatives: synthesis, antioxidant activity and light‐mediated antibacterial activity</article-title><source>ChemMedChem</source><volume>15</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cmdc.202000048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32144846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silver-promoted [3+1+1] annulation of isocyanoacetates with nitrosoarenes</article-title><source>Asian J. Org. Chem.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajoc.201800172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-pot synthesis of imidazolines from aldehydes: detailed study about solvents and substrates</article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><volume>63</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tet.2006.11.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterocycles from N-ethoxycarbonylthioamides and dinucleophilic reagents. 2. Five-membered rings containing two heteroatoms at 1,3 positions</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem.</source><volume>42</volume><year>1977</year><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo00423a011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghamari Kargar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noorian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagherzade</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiani</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, characterization and cytotoxicity evaluation of a novel magnetic nanocomposite with iron oxide deposited on cellulose nanofibers with nickel (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>@NFC@ONSM-Ni)</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>17413</fpage><lpage>17430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D1RA01256H</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35479678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9032764</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10767719"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghamari kargar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagherzade</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyzaei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arghavani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BioMOF-Mn: an antimicrobial agent and an efficient nanocatalyst for domino one-pot preparation of xanthene derivatives</article-title><source>Inorg. Chem.</source><volume>61</volume><issue>28</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>10678</fpage><lpage>10693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.inorgchem.2c00819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35793458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghomashi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghomashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aghaei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massah</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in biological active sulfonamide-based hybrid compounds Part C: multicomponent sulfonamide hybrids</article-title><source>Curr. Med. Chem.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867330666221128142730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36443978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogoi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konwar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient and one-pot synthesis of imidazolines and benzimidazoles via anaerobic oxidation of carbon–nitrogen bonds in water</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tetlet.2005.10.134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorbalenya</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziebuhr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virus-encoded proteinases and proteolytic processing in the Nidovirales</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol.</source><volume>81</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-81-4-853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kummetha</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huante</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Endsley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery and mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 main protease inhibitors</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>2879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c00566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34570513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8491550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Togo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct oxidative conversion of aldehydes and alcohols to 2-imidazolines and 2-oxazolines using molecular iodine</article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><volume>63</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1474</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tet.2006.11.077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Togo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facile preparation of 2-imidazolines from aldehydes with tert -butyl hypochlorite</article-title><source>Synthesis</source><year>2007</year><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2007-983726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakubowski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turek-Jakubowska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szahidewicz-Krupska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawrys</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawrys</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doroszko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling the endothelial function using both peripheral artery tonometry (EndoPAT) and laser Doppler flowmetry (LD) - complementary studies or waste of time?</article-title><source>Microvasc. Res.</source><volume>130</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104008</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mvr.2020.104008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32330479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazemi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cobalt ferrite nanoparticles (CoFe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> MNPs) as catalyst and support: magnetically recoverable nanocatalysts in organic synthesis</article-title><source>Nanotechnol. Rev.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/ntrev-2017-0138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>G.P.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>P.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>S.N.F.B.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergent, enantioselective synthesis of pyrroles, 3H-pyrroles and bicyclic imidazolines by Ag- or P-catalyzed [3+2] cycloaddition of allenoates with activated isocyanides</article-title><source>Chem. Eur J.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>10513</fpage><lpage>10520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.201801768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29774613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kordzadeh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramazani Saadatabadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation on penetration of saffron components through lipid bilayer bound to spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 using steered molecular dynamics simulation</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>6</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e05681</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7733551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33344790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krasavin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biologically active compounds based on the privileged 2-imidazoline scaffold: the world beyond adrenergic/imidazoline receptor modulators</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>97</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2014.11.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mild and efficient one pot synthesis of imidazolinesand benzimidazoles from aldehydes</article-title><source>E-J. Chem.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2007</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">756267</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.-W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherney</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huitema</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>M.N.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structures of the main peptidase from the SARS coronavirus inhibited by a substrate-like aza-peptide epoxide</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>353</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2005.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16219322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of SARS coronavirus spike receptor-binding domain complexed with receptor</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>309</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1864</fpage><lpage>1868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green synthesis of 2‐substituted imidazolines using hydrogen peroxide catalyzed by tungstophosphoric acid and tetrabutylammonium bromide in water</article-title><source>J. Heterocycl. Chem.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jhet.3482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohseni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahrami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farajmand</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amanlou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salehabadi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indole alkaloids as potential candidates against COVID-19: an in silico study</article-title><source>J. Mol. Model.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00894-022-05137-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35546368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9094126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enantioselective construction of imidazolines having vicinal tetra-substituted stereocenters by direct Mannich reaction of α-substituted α-isocyanoacetates with ketimines</article-title><source>Chem. Commun.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>7462</fpage><lpage>7465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6CC02911F</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27159156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikoofar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dizgarani</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HNO<sub>3</sub> @nano SiO<sub>2</sub> : an efficient catalytic system for the synthesis of multi-substituted imidazoles under solvent-free conditions</article-title><source>J. Saudi Chem. Soc.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jscs.2015.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grison</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bio-based catalysts from biomass issued after decontamination of effluents rich in copper—an innovative approach towards greener copper-based catalysis</article-title><source>Catalysts</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/catal9030214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Omidkhah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadizadeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abnous</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghodsi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, structure activity relationship and biological evaluation of a novel series of quinoline–based benzamide derivatives as anticancer agents and histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors</article-title><source>J. Mol. Struct.</source><volume>1267</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">133599</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molstruc.2022.133599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oran</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The proportion of SARS-CoV-2 infections that are asymptomatic</article-title><source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source><volume>174</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-6976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7839426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortín</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct catalytic enantio- and diastereoselective Mannich reaction of isocyanoacetates and ketimines</article-title><source>Angew. Chem.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>3530</fpage><lpage>3533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ange.201309719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel coronavirus: from discovery to clinical diagnostics</article-title><source>Infect. Genet. Evol.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104211</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2020.104211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7129799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32007627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillaiyar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manickam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of severe acute respiratory syndrome–coronavirus (SARS-CoV) 3CL protease inhibitors: peptidomimetics and small molecule chemotherapy</article-title><source>J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>59</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>6595</fpage><lpage>6628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.5b01461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26878082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7075650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asymmetric [3 + 2] cycloaddition of chiral N-phosphonyl imines with methyl isocyanoacetate for accessing 2-imidazolines with switchable stereoselectivity</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem.</source><volume>82</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2992</fpage><lpage>2999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.joc.6b03068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28249385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Q.-P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S.-F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and antitumor mechanisms of a copper(II) complex of anthracene-9-imidazoline hydrazone (9-AIH)</article-title><source>Metallomics</source><volume>7</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1124</fpage><lpage>1136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5MT00027K</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regunathan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-proliferative and anti-inflammatory actions of imidazoline agents: are imidazoline receptors involved?</article-title><source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source><volume>881</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1999.tb09389.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10415945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iodine as an efficient catalyst for the synthesis of benzimidazoles from primary alcohols and diamines</article-title><source>Org. Prep. Proced. Int.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00304940809356644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saniasiaya</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and characteristics of taste disorders in cases of COVID‐19: a meta‐analysis of 29,349 patients</article-title><source>Otolaryngol. Neck Surg.</source><volume>165</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599820981018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33320033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sant’ Anna</surname><given-names>G. da S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauzem</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacorso</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanatta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>M.A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound promoted synthesis of 2-imidazolines in water: a greener approach toward monoamine oxidase inhibitors</article-title><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2008.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19064321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imidazole derivatives with sympathomimetic activity</article-title><source>Ind. Eng. Chem.</source><volume>37</volume><year>1945</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ie50422a006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient and convenient synthesis of imidazolines and benzimidazoles via oxidation of carbon-nitrogen bond in water media</article-title><source>Chin. J. Chem.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cjoc.201100210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugarajan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>B.R.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin to inhibit binding of spike glycoprotein to ACE2 receptors: computational modelling, simulations, and ADMET studies to explore curcuminoids against novel SARS-CoV-2 targets</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>31385</fpage><lpage>31399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D0RA03167D</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35520671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9056388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>P.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly diastereo- and enantioselective silver-catalyzed double [3+2] cyclization of α-imino esters with isocyanoacetate</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>5435</fpage><lpage>5439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201402788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24756902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A computational approach for rational discovery of inhibitors for non-structural protein 1 of SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source><volume>135</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104555</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2021.104555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8184359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34144270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of potential plant bioactive as SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and human ACE2 fusion inhibitors</article-title><source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source><volume>136</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104631</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2021.104631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8264305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-silico evaluation of bioactive compounds from tea as potential SARS-CoV-2 nonstructural protein 16 inhibitors</article-title><source>J. Tradit. Complement. Med.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcme.2021.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34099976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8172245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.-T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.-G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mild and efficient one-pot synthesis of 2-imidazolines from nitriles using sodium hydrosulfide as catalyst</article-title><source>Synth. Commun.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>3151</fpage><lpage>3158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00397910802109232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of the membrane protein of SARS-CoV-2 resembles the sugar transporter semiSWEET</article-title><source>Pathog. Immun.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>342</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20411/pai.v5i1.377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33154981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7608487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AXL is a candidate receptor for SARS-CoV-2 that promotes infection of pulmonary and bronchial epithelial cells</article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-00460-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33420426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7791157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular model of SARS coronavirus polymerase: implications for biochemical functions and drug design</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>7117</fpage><lpage>7130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC291860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hikasa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of imidazoline and non-imidazoline α-adrenergic agents on rabbit platelet aggregation</article-title><source>Pharmacology</source><volume>91</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000346269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23364471</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="da0010"><title>Data availability</title><p id="p0030">No data was used for the research described in the article.</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0270">We gratefully acknowledge the financial and scientific support of the Research Council of <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004748</institution-id><institution>Mashhad University of Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> and Mazandaran University, and Birjand University for the partial support of this work.</p></ack></back></article>