
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2797604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2797604.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2797604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2797604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066037</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-14431</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Microbiology/Medical Microbiology</subject><subject>Microbiology/Microbial Growth and Development</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Novel Role of Phosphorylation-Dependent Interaction between FtsZ and FipA in Mycobacterial Cell Division</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">FipA in Cell Division</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sureka</surname><given-names initials="K">Kamakshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names initials="T">Tofajjen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names initials="P">Partha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names initials="P">Paramita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names initials="P">Pratik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names initials="M">Manikuntala</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names initials="J">Joyoti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Department of Chemistry, Bose Institute, Kolkata, India</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names initials="N">Niyaz</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Hyderabad, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>joyoti@vsnl.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MK JB. Performed the experiments: KS TH PM PC PD. Analyzed the data: KS MK JB. Wrote the paper: MK JB.</p></fn><fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: Public Health Research Institute Center, New Jersey Medical School, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey, United States of America</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">183607</issue-id><elocation-id>e8590</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-09-02 15:25:14.960"><day>02</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Sureka et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0008590.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="17" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8870568"><article-title>Retraction: Novel Role of Phosphorylation-Dependent Interaction between FtsZ and FipA in Mycobacterial Cell Division</article-title><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><date><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2022</year></date><elocation-id>e0264672</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0264672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8870568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35202441</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The bacterial divisome is a multiprotein complex. Specific protein-protein interactions specify whether cell division occurs optimally, or whether division is arrested. Little is known about these protein-protein interactions and their regulation in mycobacteria. We have investigated the interrelationship between the products of the <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> gene cluster <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c-Rv0019c</italic>, namely PknA (encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c</italic>) and <underline>F</underline>tsZ-<underline>i</underline>nteracting <underline>p</underline>rotein A, FipA (encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic>) and the products of the division cell wall (<italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic>) cluster, namely FtsZ and FtsQ. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> strains depleted in components of the two gene clusters have been complemented with orthologs of the respective genes of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. Here we identify FipA as an interacting partner of FtsZ and FtsQ and establish that PknA-dependent phosphorylation of FipA on T77 and FtsZ on T343 is required for cell division under oxidative stress. A <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> knockout strain of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> is less capable of withstanding oxidative stress than the wild type and showed elongation of cells due to a defect in septum formation. Localization of FtsQ, FtsZ and FipA at mid-cell was also compromised. Growth and survival defects under oxidative stress could be functionally complemented by <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> but not its T77A mutant. Merodiploid strains of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> expressing the FtsZ(T343A) showed inhibition of FtsZ-FipA interaction and Z ring formation under oxidative stress. Knockdown of FipA led to elongation of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> cells grown in macrophages and reduced intramacrophage growth. These data reveal a novel role of phosphorylation-dependent protein-protein interactions involving FipA, in the sustenance of mycobacterial cell division under oxidative stress.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cell growth and division involves exquisite temporal and spatial regulation of a succession of events which include choice of the site of division, positioning of the Z-ring at mid-cell, and formation of the septum <xref rid="pone.0008590-Adams1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0008590-Rothfield1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The fidelity of cell division occurring at mid-cell depends on the assembly of a macromolecular complex at the site of division involving recruitment of proteins in a hierarchial manner <xref rid="pone.0008590-Goehring1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0008590-Goehring3" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In most Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria, genes whose products are involved in cell division, cluster in a chromosomal region termed the <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> (<underline>d</underline>ivision and <underline>c</underline>ell <underline>w</underline>all) cluster <xref rid="pone.0008590-Vicente1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The principal player in driving cytokinesis is FtsZ, a GTP-binding protein considered to be the bacterial counterpart of eukaryotic tubulin <xref rid="pone.0008590-deBoer1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-RayChaudhuri1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. It is encoded by a gene within the <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> cluster. It forms the Z-ring <xref rid="pone.0008590-Bramhill1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> which serves as a cytoskeletal scaffold for the sequential recruitment and assembly of the multiprotein complex that comprises the divisome <xref rid="pone.0008590-DiLallo1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Katis1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Mycobacteria share many components of the cell division machinery identified in other bacteria. However, it is likely that there are several unique features in the mechanism of cell division in mycobacteria, considering that assisters of Z ring formation such as FtsA and ZipA have not been identified, nor have counterparts of the MinCD system which ensures that division occurs at midcell. For example, it is possible that direct interaction between FtsZ and FtsW stabilizes FtsZ at the membrane and links cell division to septal peptidoglycan biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0008590-Datta1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Datta2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p>A family of 11 serine/threonine protein kinases (STPKs) are likely sensors of environmental signals in mycobacteria <xref rid="pone.0008590-AvGay1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Wehenkel1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. In spite of an interest in this family of kinases in recent years, there is limited understanding of the signals that they sense and the consequences of such sensing. The STPKs of mycobacteria with the exception of PknG and PknK, have extracellular C-terminal sensory domains and intracellular N-terminal kinase domains. Cell wall biogenesis, cell division, central metabolic processes such as the TCA cycle and gene expression, are among the growing body of processes that are regulated by STPK-mediated phosphorylation in mycobacteria <xref rid="pone.0008590-Wehenkel1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0008590-Villarino1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.</p><p>Both PknA and PknB are involved in regulation of cell shape <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. These two kinases reside in a genomic region (encompassing the ORFs Rv0014c-Rv0019c in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv) that is conserved across all species of mycobacteria for which genome sequences are available. This region also encodes PstP, the cognate phosphatase of PknA and PknB; PBPA, a penicillin-binding transpeptidase <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, and RodA, a putative player in cell shape maintenance. PknA and PknB phosphorylate Wag31<xref rid="pone.0008590-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, and PknB phosphorylates PBPA (Dasgupta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006). A phosphorylation-defective mutant of PBPA fails to localize to the site of division. In <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, this conserved gene cluster containing morphogenetic genes, also harbours the genes <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rv0020c</italic>, encoding two forkhead-associated domain (FHA) proteins. The FHA domain is a phosphopeptide recognition motif spanning 80 to 100 amino acid residues folded in an 11-stranded beta sandwich which recognizes phosphopeptide <xref rid="pone.0008590-Durocher1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Hofmann1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. PknB phosphorylates Rv0020c <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-Grundner1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. As of now, the functional role of Rv0020c remains unclear.</p><p>Key to regulated cell division are proteins which inhibit or stabilize assembly of the divisome at mid-cell. In mycobacteria, some of the above findings have suggested that serine/threonine kinases such as PknA and PknB fine tune the process of cell division, and it is tempting to speculate that accessory proteins unique to mycobacteria, as well as dynamic protein phosphorylation could play vital roles in controlling cell septation, particularly under conditions of stress. We have tested the possibility molecular interactions among proteins encoded by genes of the <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> cluster and those encoded by the cluster <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c-Rv0019c</italic> regulate cell division in mycobcteria. This report focuses on the forkhead-associated domain (FHA)-containing protein encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic>. A role for this gene product in cell division was tested by knocking out its counterpart in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>. The increased susceptibility of the mutant to oxidative stress and the altered cell morphology, further supported our contention that this particular FHA-domain-containing protein could regulate cell division. Using a variety of biochemical and genetic approaches, we demonstrate that in mycobacteria, FtsZ, FtsQ and the product of the ORF <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic>, form a ternary complex. In view of its ability to interact with FtsZ, we name this gene product, <underline>F</underline>tsZ-<underline>i</underline>nteracting <underline>p</underline>rotein A (FipA). The FipA-FtsZ interaction is dependent on PknA which phosphorylates FipA on amino acid residue T77 and FtsZ on T343. We demonstrate that knock down of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> impairs the formation of the FtsZ-FtsQ-FipA complex. FtsZ fails to localize at mid-cell in <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> knock out <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> cells under oxidative stress and localization is rescued by complementation with FipA<sub>MTB</sub>. An important role of FipA is further suggested by the fact that depletion of FipA leads to reduced growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> in macrophages.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Effect of Inactivation of FipA<sub>MSMEG</sub> and Knock Down of FipA in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>
</title><p>The genomic region encompassing the ORFs <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s001">Figure S1A</xref>) of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, is conserved across mycobacterial species. Its role in cell division and the function of some of the genes encoded by this region has been conjectured over the years. The genes <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c-Rv0018c</italic> are organized in an operon. The ORF <italic toggle="yes">Rv0016c</italic> encodes PBPA, a transpeptidase that regulates cell morphology in a manner dependent on phosphorylation by the product of the ORF <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c</italic>, PknB <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The product of the ORF <italic toggle="yes">Rv0015c</italic>, PknA phosphorylates Wag31 thereby regulating cell morphology <xref rid="pone.0008590-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Rv0018c</italic> encodes PstP, a phosphatase which dephosphorylates substrates such as phospho-PBPA. The function of FipA (the product of the adjacent transcriptional unit <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic>), a putative FHA protein, remains obscure. Computational analysis of genome-wide functional linkages, suggests that FipA has a role in cell envelope biosynthesis in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-Strong1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Considering that FipA is conserved across pathogenic and non-pathogenic mycobacterial species, we chose <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>, the fast-growing non-pathogenic strain in order to understand the role of FipA in mycobacterial physiology. The deduced amino acid sequences of FipA<sub>MSMEG</sub> and FipA<sub>MTB</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s001">Figure S1B</xref>) show that the proteins are 88% identical in amino acid sequence. To test the role of FipA in cell growth and division, <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> was inactivated at its native locus in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>. The absence of FipA was confirmed by Western blotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s002">Figure S2A</xref>). We also confirmed by Western blotting that the expression of PknB, PknA, PBPA and PstP encoded by neighboring genes, was not affected (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s002">Fig. S2A</xref>). The mutated strain will be referred to as FipA-KO. The morphology and the growth rates of wild type <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 and FipA-KO were compared. FipA-KO exhibited reduced growth compared to the wild type in Middle Brook 7H9 broth supplemented with Tween 80. The wild type reached mid-log phase at 20 h, whereas the mutant reached mid-log phase at 24 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). At stationary phase, the growth of the mutant was lower than that of the wild type. Considering the lowered growth of the mutant particularly at stationary phase, we speculated that it was possibly less capable of handling stressful conditions than the wild type. We tested its susceptibility to conditions of stress. FipA-KO was more susceptible to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress than the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). In order to test whether FipA is required for cell division under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress, we determined cell lengths in the wild type and FipA-KO. In the absence of exogenous stress, cells of the wild type and FipA-KO were of similar length. However, approximately 40% of the cells were &gt;6 µm in length in the knockout strain subjected to oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). In comparison, &lt;5% of the wild type cells were &gt;6 µm in length under similar oxidative stress. These results suggest that FipA is required to sustain cell division in bacteria subjected to oxidative stress. In order to assess the ability of FipA of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> to complement FipA-KO, a single copy of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> was integrated into the chromosome of FipA-KO. Complementation of FipA was confirmed by Western blotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s002">Fig. S2A</xref>). FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub>, was visualized by microscopy before and after subjecting to oxidative stress. Complementation with <italic toggle="yes">fipA<sub>MTB</sub></italic> restored the cell length of FipA-KO to resemble that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). In addition, growth defect was rescued (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>), and the complemented strain could withstand oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>) to an extent similar to the wild type. This also confirmed that the difference in phenotypic behavior between the wild type and FipA-KO was attributable specifically to the absence of FipA.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>FipA regulates growth and cell division.</title><p>A. Growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 (WT), FipA-KO (KO) or FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (WT) or its <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB(T77A)</sub> [complemented (T77A)], was followed by monitoring cfu at different periods of time. B. Cultures were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as described under “<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>.” Growth was monitored by determining cfu. Percent survival was determined with respect to the cfu of untreated cells (100%). C. Cell length measurements of wild type <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (WT), or FipA-KO (KO), or FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA<sub>MTB</sub></italic> (complemented) after treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as described under “<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>.” At least 100 cells from each set were measured. D. Western blotting of lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> expressing an antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter, with anti-FipA antibody. The blot was reprobed with anti-FtsW as loading control. E. THP1 cells were infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> harbouring vector alone or an antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> at an MOI of 2 for 90 min; washed with fresh medium and grown for different periods of time. Internalized bacteria were released by lysing the macrophages followed by determination of cfu. <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> harbouring vector alone, -▵-; or antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>, -•-. F, G. THP-1 cells were infected and intracellular bacteria were obtained by lysing the macrophages, as in (E). Cell length measurements were done for intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> harbouring vector alone (F) or expressing an antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter (G) after 1, 3, 5, or 6 days of growth in THP1 cells. At least 100 cells from each set were measured.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The division defect occurring after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in FipA-KO could possibly be due to induction of the SOS response. RecA and LexA are two principal proteins involved in the SOS response <xref rid="pone.0008590-Walker1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0008590-Witkin1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. We checked the transcription levels of <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">lexA</italic> after treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. No increase in <italic toggle="yes">lexA</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> was observed in either the wild type or FipA-KO or FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s002">Figure S2B</xref>, C). O' Sullivan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-OSullivan1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> have reported that <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">lexA</italic> transcription increases after exposure of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> to mitomycin C, a compound that alkylates and crosslinks DNA and induces the SOS response. Mitomycin C exposure was therefore used as a positive control for induction of the SOS response. In this case, <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">lexA</italic> transcription increased in the wild type, FipA-KO and FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s002">Figure S2B</xref>, C). Taken together, this suggests that the division defect in FipA-KO cells after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment is not due to induction of the SOS response.</p><p>In order to assess the role of FipA in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growing in macrophages, we knocked down <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). This knock down compromised the ability of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> to multiply within macrophages after two days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1E</xref>). This argued in favor of a role of FipA in mycobacterial multiplication in macrophages. A defect in cell division in the <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>-knocked down cells in macrophages was confirmed by the observation that the percentage of macrophage-grown cells over 6 µm in size was consistently higher in <italic toggle="yes">fipA-</italic> knocked down cells compared to the wild type over a period of 6 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1F, G</xref>). This suggests that FipA is required to sustain mycobacterial cell division in macrophages.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>FipA Interacts with FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">In Vivo</italic>
</title><p>In view of the fact that FtsZ provides the driving force of cytokinesis by forming the Z-ring at the septum <xref rid="pone.0008590-Adams1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, and that knock out of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> is associated with a septation defect, we tested the possibility that FtsZ and FipA are interacting partners <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. In order to analyze the interaction of FipA with FtsZ, FtsZ was immunoprecipitated from cell lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>, and the presence of FipA in the immunoprecipitates was tested using anti-FipA antibody. FtsZ immunoprecipitates pulled down endogenous FipA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). In order to understand the role of FHA domain in the interaction of FipA with FtsZ, FipA-KO was complemented with wild type <italic toggle="yes">fipA<sub>MTB</sub></italic> or <italic toggle="yes">fipA<sub>MTB</sub></italic> harboring mutations in conserved amino acid residues of the FHA domain encompassing amino acid residues P82 to V132. FHA domain mutants S101A, H104A and N123A of FipA were impaired in their ability to interact with FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). On the other hand, the FipA (D118A) mutant retained the ability to interact with FtsZ. These results suggest that the FHA domain of FipA plays a role in its interaction with FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The FHA domain of FipA is required for its interaction with FtsZ.</title><p>A. Cell lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> were immunoprecipitated (IP) with anti-FtsZ antibody and immunoblotted (IB) with anti-FipA antibody or antibody against an irrelevant protein (PPK1) [as a negative control]. The blot was reprobed with anti-FtsZ antibody to show equal loading. B. Lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 or FipA-KO complemented with the wild type (WT) or different mutants of FipA<sub>MTB</sub>, were immunoprecipitated with anti-FipA antibody followed by immunoblotting with anti-FtsZ antibody and reprobing with anti-FipA antibody. Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>FHA domains are known to interact with ser/thr kinases <xref rid="pone.0008590-Durocher1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Therefore, we tested whether FipA of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (FipA<sub>MSMEG</sub>, encoded by MSMEG_0034), is phosphorylated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. FipA was immunoprecipitated from cell lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> followed by Western analysis using anti-phosphothreonine antibody. The results affirmed that FipA<sub>MTB</sub> and FipA<sub>MSMEG</sub> are phosphorylated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> on threonine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Incubation of immunoprecipitates with purified PstP resulted in dephosphorylation of agarose-bound FipA<sub>MTB</sub> and FipA<sub>MSMEG</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). In a reverse experiment, capture of proteins from lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> on phosphothreonine agarose, followed by Western analysis of the bound proteins with anti-FipA antibody, also confirmed that FipA is phosphorylated within cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>FipA is phosphorylated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and localizes to the membrane.</title><p>A, B. Lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>(A) or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (A, B) were immunoprecipitated either with anti-FipA antibody (A) or with phosphothreonine agarose (B), left untreated (−) or treated (+) with S-tagged PstP<sub>MTB</sub> followed by immunoblotting with anti-phosphothreonine (A) or anti-FipA (B) antibody as indicated; and reprobing with anti-FipA antibody for panel A. C. Cell lysates were fractionated and membrane and cytosolic fractions were immunoblotted with anti-FipA antibody followed by reprobing with anti-FtsZ (marker for the cytosol) or with anti-FtsW (membrane marker). Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Subcellular Localization of FipA</title><p>In order to understand the function of FipA and in view of the fact that it interacts with FtsZ, we felt it imperative to localize FipA in cells. Its topology predicted using the program HMMTOP <xref rid="pone.0008590-Tusnady1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> suggest that it is a transmembrane protein. Fractionation of lysates into membranes and cytosolic components, followed by Western blotting confirmed that FipA localizes in mycobacterial membranes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Crosscontamination of membrane and cytosol fractions was ruled out by the fact that membranes were positive for the membrane protein FtsW but not for the cytosolic protein FtsZ, whereas the cytosol fraction was positive for FtsZ but not for FtsW.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>FipA Is Phosphorylated by PknA</title><p>In order to test whether FipA is phosphorylated by the neighbouring ser/thr kinase PknA, we expressed FipA in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> with an N-terminal hexahistidine or S-tag. Purified His-tagged FipA migrated as a protein of approximately 20 kDa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). We expressed and purified the kinase domain of PknA encompassing Y13 to A273 (PknA<sub>13–273</sub>) as a GST-tagged protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). Recombinant FipA could be phosphorylated by PknA<sub>13–273</sub> in the presence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> and [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). The kinase-dead K42A mutant of PknA<sub>13–273</sub>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> was unable to phosphorylate FipA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). In order to evaluate the role of FHA domain amino acid residues S101, H104, D118 and N123 on interaction of FipA with PknA and its phosphorylaton, these residues were individuallly mutated to alanine. None of the mutants other than the D118A mutant, could interact with PknA<sub>13–273</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>), nor were these mutants (with the exception of D118A) phosphorylated by PknA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>). These results confirmed the importance of the FHA domain residues S101, H104, and N123 in interaction with PknA and in PknA-mediated phosphorylation of FipA.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>FipA interacts with, and is phosphorylated by PknA <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</title><p>A, B. Coomassie blue-stained gels of uninduced (1), or induced (2) cells of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> expressing FipA (A), GST-PknA<sub>13-273</sub> (B), purified FipA (A, lane 3) and GST-PknA<sub>13–273</sub> (B, lane 3). C. Purified FipA was phosphorylated by GST-PknA<sub>13–273</sub> or its K42A mutant <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> in the presence of [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP followed by autoradiography. D. Recombinant S-tagged FipA or its mutants were incubated with GST-PknA<sub>13–273</sub> bound to glutathione-Sepharose beads. Proteins bound to the beads were detected by immunoblotting with anti-FipA antibody. The blot was reprobed with anti-GST antibody. E. Purified FipA or its mutants were phosphorylated by GST-PknA<sub>13–273</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> in the presence of [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP followed by autoradiography. The first lane represents autophosphorylated GST-PknA<sub>13–273</sub>. Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments. Lower blots of panels C and E are Coomassie blue-stained gels showing the levels of FipA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>The NET Phos program <xref rid="pone.0008590-Blom1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> predicted threonine residues at positions 77 and 142 as putative phosphorylatable residues. Mutation of T77 abrogated PknA<sub>13–273</sub>-dependent phosphorylation of FipA, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>) but not its interaction with PknA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). This identified T77 as a possible site of PknA-dependent phosphorylation. Mutation of T142 had no effect in PknA<sub>13–273</sub>-mediated phosphorylation (data not shown). In order to confirm that FipA is phosphorylated on a single threonine residue by PknA<sub>13–273</sub>, mass analysis of His-FipA and the protein phosphorylated by PknA<sub>13-273</sub>, was undertaken. The increase in the molecular mass of the intact protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s003">Figure S3</xref>), confirmed incorporation of a single phosphate residue by PknA<sub>13–273</sub>.</p><p>In order to investigate the role of phosphorylation of FipA on its interaction with FtsZ, FipA-KO was complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> or <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB(T77A)</sub>. Wild type FipA<sub>MTB</sub> could immunoprecipitate FtsZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>) while the T77A mutant could not, suggesting the requirement of FipA phosphorylation for its interaction with FtsZ. In addition, phosphorylation-defective FipA(T77A) could not restore the growth defect of the FipA-KO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>) or its ability to withstand H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). This suggests that phosphorylation of FipA on T77 is required to support survival under oxidative stress.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>FipA Is Phosphorylated <italic toggle="yes">In Vivo</italic> by PknA in Mycobacteria</title><p>In order to demonstrate PknA-dependent phosphorylation of FipA <italic toggle="yes">in vivo,</italic> we performed gradual depletion of the protein in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> by acetamide-inducible expression of an antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic>. Depletion of PknA was confirmed by immunoblotting of lysates with anti-PknA antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). Gradual depletion of PknA was concomitant with gradual decrease in threonine phosphorylation of FipA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>), suggesting that PknA mediates phosphorylation of FipA <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>A, B. FipA is phosphorylated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> in a PknA-dependent manner.</title><p>A, B. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> was transformed with a construct carrying <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> in antisense orientation under an acetamide-inducible promoter. Transformed cells were induced with 0.2% acetamide for the indicated periods of time in order to downregulate <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> expression. Antisensing was followed by immunoblotting of cell lysates with anti-PknA antibody, followed by reprobing with anti-FtsW antibody (A); or cell lysates at different periods of time were immunoprecipitated with anti-FipA antibody followed by immunoblotting with anti-phosphothreonine antibody and reprobing with anti-FipA antibody (B). Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments. IB: immunoblotting; IP: immunoprecipitation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Interaction of FtsZ with FipA Is Required for Septal Localization of FtsZ under Oxidative Stress</title><p>Considering that FipA interacts with FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), we attempted to understand whether this interaction is necessary for the localization of FtsZ at mid-cell in dividing cells. Immunolocalization of FtsZ in FipA-KO showed that FtsZ was compromised in its ability to localize at mid-cell in FipA-KO cells subjected to oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g006">Fig. 6A, B</xref>), but could localize to mid-cell in the absence of oxidative stress (data not shown). Complementation of FipA-KO with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> restored the localization of FtsZ at mid-cell even under oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g006">Fig. 6C,D</xref>). The frequency of Z ring formation in the absence or presence of oxidative stress, was measured by microscopy. The data presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t001">Table 1</xref> clearly indicate that Z ring formation under oxidative stress requires FipA. No Z ring formation could be observed in FipA-KO under oxidative stress. However, complementation with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> restored Z ring formation in 63 out of 81 FtsZ-positive cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t001">Table 1</xref>). We hypothesize that FipA facilitates localization of FtsZ at mid-cell under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Localization of FtsZ to mid-cell in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> under oxidative stress requires FipA.</title><p>FipA-KO (A,B) or FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (C, D) was subjected to stress by incubation in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as described under “<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>”. Immunolocalization of FtsZ was carried out by incubation with anti-FtsZ antibody followed by staining with Alexa 488-conjugated rabbit IgG (green). Images shown are fluorescence micrographs (A, C) and the merge of phase contrast and fluorescence micrographs (B,D). Bar, 2 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g006.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0008590-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Presence of Z ring in cells.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0008590-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">septum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">others</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT without stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FipA-KO without stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FipA-KO after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> without stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub>, after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>FtsZ positive cells were counted.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>PknA-Mediated Phosphorylation of FtsZ</title><p>The present study shows that FipA is phosphorylated by PknA on T77 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>) and phosphorylation is required for its interaction with FtsZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Thakur and Chakraborti (2006) had earlier demonstrated that FtsZ is phosphorylated by PknA without identifying the site of PknA-dependent FtsZ phosphorylation. In order to further understand the role of PknA-dependent phosphorylations, we attempted to identify the site of phosphorylation of FtsZ. Computational analysis using the Net Phos program <xref rid="pone.0008590-Blom1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, suggested that T343 is a putative site of phosphorylation of FtsZ. Recombinant PknA<sub>13–273</sub> could phosphorylate recombinant wild type His-FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> but not the T343A mutant <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>). In addition, mass analysis of FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> after phosphorylation by PknA<sub>13–273</sub> showed an increase in mass corresponding to phosphorylation on a single residue by (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s004">Figure S4</xref>). The T343A mutant, on the other hand, showed no increase in mass after treatment with PknA<sub>13-273,</sub> supporting our contention that T343 represents the only site of PknA-mediated phosphorylation of FtsZ. In order to confirm PknA-mediated threonine phosphorylation of FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> was partially knocked down by inducing the expression of an antisense RNA to <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> driven by the acetamidase promoter. Knock down of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> inhibited phosphorylation of FtsZ on threonine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>), just as in the case of FipA.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>FtsZ is phosphorylated in a PknA-dependent manner.</title><p>A. Purified FtsZ or its T343A mutant was phosphorylated by GST-PknA<sub>13-273</sub> in the presence of [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP followed by autoradiography. The lower blot is a Coomassie blue-stained gel showing the levels of FtsZ. B. Conditional knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> was induced by growing <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> expressing an antisense construct of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> (under the control of an acetamide-inducible promoter) in the absence (-) or in the presence (+) of acetamide for 12 h. Cells were lysed and lysates were immunoprecipitated with preimmune sera (first lane) or anti-FtsZ antibody, followed by immunoblotting with anti-phosphothreonine and reprobing with anti-FtsZ antibody. Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Formation of a Complex between FtsZ, FipA and FtsQ and the Role of PknA</title><p>Considering that FipA appeared likely to play a role in cell division, we tested whether FipA influences interaction of FtsZ with any divisomal protein which follows it to the site of division. Among the proteins which have been recognized as following FtsZ and preceding FtsW to the site of division is FtsQ of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (or DivIB of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>). The ORFs Rv2151c and MSMEG_4229 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s005">Figure S5</xref>) encode <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> FtsQ respectively <xref rid="pone.0008590-Roy1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Like FtsZ, both FipA and FtsQ localize to mid-cell in dividing <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s006">Figure S6</xref>) as observed by immunofluorescence microscopy. Numerical data show that FipA localizes to the septum to a similar extent in untreated and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0008590-t002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Localization of FipA in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0008590-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth condition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Septum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Untreated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjected to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>In each set, FipA localization was counted among 100 cells.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>*Not determined.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We tested the possibility that FipA is part of a larger divisomal complex including FtsQ and FtsZ. FtsQ could be pulled down in a complex with FtsZ in wild type <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> as well as in FipA-KO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8A</xref>) in the absence of stress. However, under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> stress, FtsQ immunoprecipitated with FtsZ only in the wild type, but not in FipA-KO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8A</xref>), suggesting that FipA is required for FtsZ to interact with FtsQ in oxidatively stressed cells, whereas FipA likely plays a redundant role in the absence of oxidative stress. In support of this contention, FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> rescued the ability of FtsZ to interact with FtsQ under oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8A</xref>). FtsZ-FtsQ interaction was compromised in oxidatively stressed cells of FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB(T77A)</sub> (i.e. phosphorylation-defective FipA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8B</xref>). Under oxidative stress, 67% of the FipA-KO cells showed punctate distribution of FtsQ in membranes with no visible localization at mid-cell, as opposed to 52% of the wild type cells showing septal localization of FtsQ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t003">Table 3</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that (a) FipA supports septal localization of FtsQ even under oxidative stress and (b) phosphorylation of FipA is required for FipA to fulfill this function.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Interactions between FtsZ, FtsQ and FipA <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</title><p>A. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> wild type (WT) or FipA -KO (KO) or FipA -KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (complemented) was left untreated (−) or treated (+) with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, as described under “<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>”, lysed and immunoprecipitated with preimmune sera (first lane) or with anti-FtsZ antibody followed by immunoblotting with anti-FtsQ antibody. B. FipA-KO or FipA-KO complemented with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub>(WT) or the T77A mutant, was grown, subjected to oxidative stress, lysed and immunoprecipitated with anti-FtsZ antibody followed by immunblotting with anti-FtsQ antibody. C. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> strains mc<sup>2</sup>155, F1 or F2, were grown and subjected to the same treatment as in panel B, followed by immunoprecipitation with anti-His antibody (for pull down of FtsZ) and immunoblotting with anti-FtsQ antibody. D. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> before or after conditional knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> (performed as described under <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g007">Fig. 7</xref>), was subjected to oxidative stress, lysed and immunoprecipitated with preimmune sera (first lane) or anti-FtsZ antibody, followed by immunblotting with anti-FtsQ antibody. E. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmati</italic>s-F1 or -F2 cells subjected to oxidative stress, were lysed and immunoprecipitated with anti-His antibody followed by immunoblotting with anti-FipA antibody. Blots (A–E) were reprobed with anti-FtsZ antibody. Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g008.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0008590-t003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Localization of FtsQ in FipA-KO and complemented strains.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0008590-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type and treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">punctate <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">septum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">**</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (−) stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (+)stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (−)stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (+)stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (−) stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (+) stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>*Cells showing punctate distribution of FtsQ in the membrane.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>**Not determined.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>In each set, FtsQ localization was scored in 100 cells.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In order to understand the role of phosphorylation of FtsZ on its interaction with FtsQ, merodiploid strains lacking the chromosomal copy of <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> and carrying an integrated copy of the wild type His-<italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1) or its T343A mutant (<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2), were generated. FtsZ-FtsQ interactions were supported under oxidative stress by <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> strain F1 but not strain F2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8C</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1, FtsQ showed septal localization in 67 and 55% cells in the absence of stress or under oxidative stress, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t004">Table 4</xref>). On the other hand, in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2, septal localization of FtsQ was visible in the absence of stress, but not in oxidatively stressed cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008590-t004">Table 4</xref>). These observations suggest that phosphorylation of FtsZ is required for the interaction between FtsZ and FtsQ as well as for the septal localization of FtsQ. A role of PknA-mediated phosphorylation of FipA and FtsZ in sustaining FtsZ-FtsQ interactions under oxidative stress was also suggested by the observation that immunoprecipitation of FtsZ failed to pull down FtsQ in <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic>-depleted cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8D</xref>) under oxidative stress. Further, immunoprecipitation of FtsZ from lysates of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis-</italic>F1 or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2 strains showed that, like FtsQ, FipA could also be pulled down with wild type FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> but not with FtsZ<sub>MTB(T343A)</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g008">Fig. 8E</xref>) under oxidative stress, suggesting that FtsZ phosphorylation is required for the FtsZ-FipA interaction.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0008590-t004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Localization of FtsQ in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1 and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0008590-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type and treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">punctate <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">septum</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">**</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1 (−) stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1 (+)stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2 (−)stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2 (+) stress</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>*Cells showing punctate distribution of FtsQ in the membrane.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>**Not determined.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label/><p>In each set, FtsQ localization was scored in 100 cells.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Immunoprecipitation of cell lysates with anti-FipA antibody, followed by immunoblotting with either anti-FtsQ or anti-FtsZ antibody showed that FipA could pull down FtsQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>) or FtsZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9B</xref>) under oxidative stress However, FipA-FtsQ or FipA-FtsZ interaction was abrogated when <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> had been knocked down (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9A,B</xref>) supporting the contention that formation of the FtsZ-FtsQ-FipA complex under oxidative stress requires PknA. Taken together, our results suggest a role of PknA-mediated phosphorylation of FipA on T77 and FtsZ on T343 in mediating formation of a complex between FtsZ, FtsQ and FipA as well as their localization at mid-cell, under oxidative stress.</p><fig id="pone-0008590-g009" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008590.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>FipA is a bridging partner for interactions between FtsZ and FtsQ.</title><p>A, B. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> before or after conditional knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic>, was subjected to oxidative stress, lysed and immunoprecipitated with preimmune sera (lane 1) or anti-FipA antibody (lanes 2 and 3), followed by immunblotting with anti-FtsQ (A) or –FtsZ (B) antibody and reprobing with anti-FipA antibody. C. Recombinant S-tagged FtsQ<sub>MTB</sub> immobilized on S-agarose was incubated with buffer only (lane 1) or with recombinant FipA<sub>MTB</sub> followed by washing and further incubation with FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> (lane 2); or incubated with FipA<sub>MTB</sub> and FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> simultaneously (lane 3). Resin-bound proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunblotted with different antibodies as indicated. For lanes 4 and 5, Ni<sup>2+</sup> -NTA bound His-tagged FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> was incubated with (lane 4) or without (lane 5) FipA<sub>MTB</sub> followed by washing and further incubation with FtsQ<sub>MTB</sub>. Bound proteins were identified by immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies. The blot was reprobed with anti-FtsZ antibody. Blots shown are representative of three separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0008590.g009.jpg"/></fig><p>Given the above findings, we tested the hypothesis that FtsZ, FtsQ and FipA are capable of forming a ternary complex <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. S-tagged FtsQ<sub>MTB</sub> was immobilized on S-agarose, followed by simultaneous incubation with phosphorylated His-FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> and phosphorylated His-FipA<sub>MTB</sub>. The pulled down proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and probed by Western blotting with anti -FtsZ and -FipA. Both FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> and FipA<sub>MTB</sub> were pulled down from lysates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>, lane 3). When FipA<sub>MTB</sub> was incubated with immobilized FtsQ<sub>MTB</sub>, beads were washed, and FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> was subsequently added, neither FipA<sub>MTB</sub> nor FtsZ<sub>MTB</sub> could be pulled down with FtsQ<sub>MTB</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>, lane 2). These observations suggest that prior interaction between FtsZ and FipA is necessary for formation of the FtsZ-FipA-FtsQ ternary complex. In support of this, FtsZ immunoprecipitates which contained FipA were able to pull down FtsQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>, lane 4), whereas FtsZ immunoprecipitates alone could not pull down FtsQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>, lane 5). These results suggest that FipA influences the ability of FtsZ to interact with partner divisomal proteins, and that initial interaction between FtsZ and FipA is necessary for ternary FtsZ-FipA-FtsQ complex formation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The gene cluster encompassing the products of the ORFs <italic toggle="yes">Rv0014c-Rv0019c</italic> is conserved throughout the genus <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium</italic>. It encompasses two transmembrane sensor kinases PknA and PknB, a phosphatase PstP, a transpeptidase PBPA and the FHA domain protein encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic> (FipA). There has been speculation that this gene cluster plays a role in cell division <xref rid="pone.0008590-Narayan1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. However, knowledge of the roles of the individual gene products of this cluster in the genus <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium</italic>, is scanty. The <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> cluster is conserved across the genus mycobacterium and includes genes such as <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ftsQ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ftsW</italic> whose products are central to the process of cell division. Here we establish two important findings. In the first instance we demonstrate a synergy of action between two products of the first gene cluster, (PknA and the FHA domain protein FipA), and two products of the <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> cluster (FtsZ and FtsQ) in maintaining cells in a division-competent state under oxidative stress. We uncover a novel role of phosphorylated FipA in assembly of the divisome under oxidative stress. In the second instance, we demonstrate that the network of interactions between FtsZ, FipA and FtsQ, is critically dependent on the serine/threonine kinase PknA. These findings are discussed below.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> resides within host macrophages following inhalation into the alveolar spaces of the lung. The bacterium is exposed to adverse environmental conditions and toxic agents such as reactive oxygen intermediates (ROI). It is logical that the bacterium must be endowed with mechanisms of withstanding the stressful conditions of its intracellular niche to an extent that allows multiplication and survival within macrophages. Control of cell division as well as maintenance of cell shape are critical factors for the survival of mycobacteria within the host. After replication, the multiprotein complex that comprises the divisome, assembles at mid-cell in order to facilitate cell division <xref rid="pone.0008590-Hett1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In mycobacteria, the repertoire of proteins required for cell division of mycobacteria within macrophages, remains incompletely understood. In order to test whether the FHA domain protein FipA plays a role in supporting intramacrophage growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> was knocked down. Knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> was associated with a cell division defect of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> in macrophages after 5 days of infection, providing evidence that FipA is required to sustain growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> within macrophages. The role of FipA was investigated using <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> as the model. Knockout of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> resulted in a cell division defect in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> exposed to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. In <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, cell division block is frequently associated with induction of <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic>-dependent SOS response <xref rid="pone.0008590-DAri1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. In <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, ROI produced by macrophages can damage DNA and induce the SOS response. In the classical pathway, DNA damage induces <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">lexA</italic>-dependent SOS response <xref rid="pone.0008590-Davis1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. However, in this instance we could rule out the possibility of induction of a classical SOS response at the concentrations and times of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> exposure used. Consequently, we investigated other causes of FipA-linked cell division block under oxidative stress, focusing on the interaction of FipA with well-characterized proteins of the divisome.</p><p>Our results indicate that FipA interacts with FtsZ in a phosphorylation-dependent manner. Earlier studies have focused on biochemical characterization of PknA <xref rid="pone.0008590-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, and identified substrates such as MurD <xref rid="pone.0008590-Thakur2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Kang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. <xref rid="pone.0008590-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> reported that in mycobacteria, partial knock down of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">pknB</italic> leads to the formation of narrow and elongated cells, suggesting a role of these protein kinases in cell division. However, the significance of PknA-dependent phosphorylation of divisomal proteins is still not clear. Unlike Thakur and Chakraborti <xref rid="pone.0008590-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> we did not observe phosphorylation-dependent inhibition of the GTPase activity of FtsZ. It is pertinent to point out that Thakur and Chakraborti <xref rid="pone.0008590-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> used GST-FtsZ, whereas we have worked with His-FtsZ. It may be mentioned that Schulz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. <xref rid="pone.0008590-Schultz1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> failed to observe PknA-dependent inhibition of polymerization of <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic> FtsZ. During infection, membrane-bound kinases are thought to transmit environmental signals inside bacteria. In fact, <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pknB</italic> are upregulated by more than 10-fold when THP-1 cells are infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-Singh1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. It therefore appears likely that the serine/threonine kinases of mycobacteria play important roles during infection. Understanding their function could in the long run provide newer directions for development of antituberculosis drugs. With this in view, we pursued investigation on the possible role of PknA in cell division. We now establish that FipA is phosphorylated on T77 in a PknA-dependent manner, and elucidate a functional role for such a phosphorylation event. Coimmunoprecipitation assays confirm that the FHA domain of FipA is necessary for its interaction with PknA. FipA<sub>MTB</sub> could complement FipA-KO with restoration of growth and survival under oxidative stress. The phosphorylation-defective T77A mutant failed to support cell division in FipA-KO under oxidative stress, underscoring the importance of PknA-dependent phosphorylation of FipA in sustaining cell division under oxidative stress.</p><p>In <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, FtsQ interacts with a large number of divisomal proteins <xref rid="pone.0008590-DUlisse1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and is required for divisome assembly <xref rid="pone.0008590-Goehring4" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Recruitment of FtsZ, FtsQ and FtsA to mid-cell is required for the septal localization of FtsW <xref rid="pone.0008590-Mercer1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. In mycobacteria, FtsQ is required for localization of FtsW to the septum in dividing cells (unpublished observations) suggesting that it plays an important role in mycobacterial cell division. We provide evidence that FipA interacts with FtsZ and FtsQ in a PknA-dependent manner. We hypothesize that FipA is required for divisomal protein assembly under oxidative stress, in a manner that is dependent on phosphorylation of FipA mediated by PknA. We show that in the absence of oxidative stress, FtsQ interacts with FtsZ <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> both in the wild type as well as in FipA-KO, although the two proteins do not interact directly with each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008590-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>). This suggests that FipA, as a member of the divisomal complex, plays a redundant role in the absence of stress. Additional, unidentified accessory protein(s) probably fulfill a bridging function (between FtsZ and FtsQ) under normal conditions. This probably suffices to sustain septation of growing cells even in the absence of FipA. However, the accessory protein(s) are probably incapable of functioning under oxidative stress. FipA assumes a critical role in these conditions. In vitro grown <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> exposed to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growing in macrophages, are longer than cells cultured <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> in the absence of exogenous oxidative stress. These cells nevertheless survive in the presence of functional FipA. On the other hand, there is a much more severe division block under these conditions in the absence of FipA. It therefore seems reasonable to contend that FipA supports cell division in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growing in macrophages to an extent that is optimal for its survival in the stressful environment of the phagosome. The FipA proteins are unique to mycobacteria, even though FtsZ and FtsQ are present across numerous genera. It is likely that FipA fulfils a function in the process of cell division and multiplication, specifically required for survival of mycobacteria in the intracellular mileu of the host. Our observations provide knowledge for the first time that in mycobacteria (i) there is synergy between the gene cluster Rv0014c-Rv0019c and the <italic toggle="yes">dcw</italic> cluster; (ii) PknA-dependent phosphorylation events fine tune cell division and play a critical role under oxidative stress and (iii) the product of the ORF <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic>, FipA, plays an important role in supporting cell division under oxidative stress. While our work was in progress, Gupta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. <xref rid="pone.0008590-Gupta1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> reported that FipA (Rv0019c) interacts with polyketide-associated protein, PapA5 of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis in vitro</italic> and that it is phosphorylated by PknB on T36. However, the physiological importance of these findings is unclear in the absence of any in vivo experiments. It remains to be investigated whether PknA-mediated phosphorylation of FipA on T77 and PknB-mediated phosphorylation on T36 are interdependent, whether PknB-dependent phosphorylation is constitutive or inducible, and whether it too plays a role in cell division. It is possible that site-specific phosphorylations of FipA by two different kinases regulate interaction with different substrates. Another FHA domain containing protein, GarA <xref rid="pone.0008590-England1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> has been found to be phosphorylated by two kinases, PknG and PknB which differentially regulate its interaction with other proteins. Detailed investigations to resolve these unanswered question are in progress. In summary, our observations offer new insight into how targeting FtsZ-FipA interaction could block cell division to an extent that would compromise mycobacterial multiplication in macrophages.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Molecular Biological Procedures</title><p>Standard procedures for cloning and analysis of DNA, PCR, electroporation and transformation were used. Enzymes used to manipulate DNA were from Roche Applied Science, Mannheim, Germany. All constructs made by PCR were sequenced to verify their integrity. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were routinely grown in Luria broth (LB). Details of strains and plasmids are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s007">Table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Construction of Suicidal Delivery Vector for Inactivation of fipA in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>
</title><p>The two step homologous recombination strategy described by Parish and Stoker <xref rid="pone.0008590-Parish1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> was used to disrupt <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_</italic>0034, the counterpart of <italic toggle="yes">Rv0019c</italic> at its native locus in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>. Briefly, a suicide plasmid was constructed in three steps. First, an 860 bp DNA fragment containing the 5′ end of <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_0034</italic> alongwith upstream sequence was PCR amplified using the genomic DNA of wild type <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155 as template and the primer pair FipA 1F sense and FipA 1F antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>). The amplicon was cloned between the asymmetric <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III and <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI sites of p2NIL to give pJB110. In the next step, a 900 bp fragment bearing the 3′ end of <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_0034</italic> and its downstream region was amplified using the primer pair FipA 2F sense and FipA 2F antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>) and cloned between the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Pac</italic>I sites of pJB110 to give pJB111 carrying a truncated <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> gene. The hygromycin cassette was excised from pUC-HY–INT (Mahenthiralingam <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998) and introduced into pJB111 to give pJB112. Finally, a 6.1 kb <italic toggle="yes">Pac</italic>I cassette carrying the <italic toggle="yes">lacZ</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">aph</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sacB</italic> genes, was isolated from pGOAL17 and inserted into pJB112 to generate the suicide plasmid pJB113.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Isolation of the FipA –Knockout Mutant</title><p>Denatured pJB113 was electroporated into electrocompetent cells of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155. Cells were plated on Lemco agar supplemented with hygromycin B, kanamycin and 50 µg/ml x-gal. Blue colonies were streaked onto Lemco agar without any selection to enhance the recombination process. Cells were then plated onto Lemco agar supplemented with 2% sucrose and 50 µg/ml x-gal. The white colonies were restreaked onto replica plates containing hygromycin, x-gal and sucrose, either without or with kanamycin. White, kan<sup>S</sup>, hyg<sup>R</sup>, suc<sup>R</sup> colonies generated by double crossover represented the <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> –inactivated strain (FipA–KO). Expression of FipA was checked using antibody raised against FipA.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Complementation of FipA<sub>MTB</sub> in FipA-KO Using an Integrating Vector</title><p>An integrating vector carrying <italic toggle="yes">His-FipA</italic>(or its mutants) of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter was constructed as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Complementation with <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> was achieved by electroporation of the integrating vector into FipA–KO. The presence of His-FipA was confirmed by Western blotting using anti-His antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Cloning and Expression of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv Genes</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">FipA</italic> was amplified from genomic DNA of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv using the sense primer “a” and antisense primers “d” (for pET28a+) and “e” (for pET29a+) depicted in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>. The amplicons were cloned between asymmetric <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III sites in pET28a or the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>RI sites in pET29a+ to generate pJB120 and pJB121 respectively. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C41 (DE3) harbouring the respective constructs was grown to an Abs<sub>600</sub> of 0.6 at 37<sup>o</sup>C, IPTG was added at a concentration of 0.25 mM, and growth was continued for 2–3 h. His- or S-tagged proteins were purified from cell lysates by chromatography on Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA- or S-agarose respectively. Mutants of FipA<sub>MTB</sub> were generated by overlap extension PCR. Initial rounds of PCR were performed using primers “a”and “b”; or primers “c” and “d” (or “e”) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>). Using the products of the initial round as template, the second round of PCR was performed using primers “a” and “d” (or “e”). Products were cloned in pET28a+ or pET29a+. The T343A mutant of FtsZ was generated using pJB101 (Datta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002) as template and primers “a” and “d” (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>).</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">ftsQ</italic> was amplified using the sense and antisense primers shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>, and cloned either in pET28a+ or in pET29a+ between the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III sites. Expression was carried out in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C41(DE3) using 0.1 mM IPTG for 4 h at 37°C.</p><p>The kinase domain of <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic>
<sub>13-273</sub>) was amplified using the sense and antisense primers shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>, and cloned between the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>RI sites of pGEX-2T to generate the plasmid pJB122. Expression was carried out in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21 by induction with 0.1 mM IPTG at 37°C for 4 h, and the expressed protein was purified by chromatography on glutathione Sepharose. The K42A mutant was generated by overlap extension PCR using primers “b” and “c” depicted in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>. His-PknB<sub>1–276</sub> was purified as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The <italic toggle="yes">pstP</italic> (Rv0018c) gene was amplified using the sense and antisense primer pair shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>, and cloned between the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III sites of pET29a<sup>+</sup>. N-terminal S-tagged PstP was obtained by induction for 3 h at 37°C with 50 µM IPTG and purified by chromatography on S-agarose</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Construction of ftsZ Replacement Vectors in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>
</title><p>A construct for replacement of the chromosomal <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> was generated using the method of described above <xref rid="pone.0008590-Parish1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. A suicide plasmid with a 488 bp internal deletion in the <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> gene was constructed in two steps. In the first step, a 1244 bp DNA fragment encompassing the 5′ end of <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> and its upstream region was PCR amplified using the primer pair FtsZ 1F sense and FtsZ 1F antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>) and cloned in pBluescript SK between the asymmetric <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>RI sites to give rise to pJB114. In the next step 1153 bp of DNA bearing the 3′ end of <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> and its downstream flanking region was amplified using the primer pair FtsZ 2F sense and FtsZ 2F antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>) and cloned between the <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>RI and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic> III sites of pJB114 to generate pJB115. The truncated <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> gene was excised from pJB115 by digesting with <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III and cloned into p2NIL between the same sites to generate pJB116. Finally, the 6.1 kb PacI fragment was isolated from pGOAL19 and inserted into pJB116 to generate the suicide plasmid pJB117.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Isolation of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> Strains Carrying Wild Type or Mutated ftsZ<sub>MTB</sub>
</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> was electroporated with denatured pJB117. Single cross over (SCO)s were selected on agar plates containing kanamycin and x-gal. Kanamycin-resistant blue SCOs were isolated. In the next step, His-tagged <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (or its mutant) was cloned under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter in pUC19 using <italic toggle="yes">Kpn</italic>I and <italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic>III sites as described above. The 3.757kb Hyg-integrase cassette was excised from pUC-HY-INT <xref rid="pone.0008590-Mahenthiralingam1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and inserted into the above construct to generate an integrating vector. Before inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> at its native location, <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> in the integrating vector was electroporated into the SCOs. The resultant merodiploid strains carrying His-tagged <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F1) or <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic>
<sub>MTB(T343A)</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>-F2) were then screened for double cross over (DCO) as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Chauhan1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. White kan<sup>S</sup> Hyg<sup>S</sup> and sucrose-resistant DCOs were analyzed by PCR.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In Vitro</italic> Kinase Assay</title><p>In vitro kinase assays were performed with the purified kinase domain of PknA<sub>13–273</sub> (1 µg) in 25 mM Tris/HCl, pH 7.5, 5 mM β-glycerophosphate, 2 mM DTT, 2 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mM sodium orthovanadate as described by Dasgupta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2006). Dephosphorylation assays were carried out in 50 mM HEPES buffer pH 7.5 containing 0.1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT and 5 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub> as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In some experiments, proteins separated by SDS-PAGE were electrotransferred and Western blotting was performed using monoclonal anti-phospho-threonine or anti-phosphoserine (Sigma Chemical Co.) or anti-phospho-tyrosine (Cell Signaling Technology) antibody.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Conditional Inactivation of pknA in Mycobacteria</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic> gene was amplified using the primer pair pknA sense and pknA antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s007">Table S1</xref>) followed by cloning of the PCR product in reverse orientation in the vector pSD29 <xref rid="pone.0008590-Daugelat1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref> between the <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>RV sites to generate pJB118. In order to conditionally inactivate <italic toggle="yes">pknA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> was electroporated with pJB118. Transformants were grown up to mid log phase and induced with 0.2% acetamide for different periods of time. Western blotting was performed to confirm the antisensing of PknA.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Knock Down of FipA in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>
</title><p>For knock down of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>
<sub>MTB</sub>, an antisense construct (pJB119) of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> was generated by PCR amplification of the <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic> gene using the primer pair FipA<sub>MTB</sub> sense and FipA<sub>MTB</sub> antisense (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0008590.s008">Table S2</xref>) followed by cloning of the PCR product in reverse orientation under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter using the strategy described by Sureka <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0008590-Sureka1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Western blotting using anti-FipA antibody was performed to confirm the antisensing of <italic toggle="yes">fipA</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Induction of Oxidative Stress and Treatment with Mitomycin C</title><p>Cells were subjected to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-mediated oxidative stress as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Sureka1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Briefly, cells were grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.3 to 0.4, diluted into fresh medium to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2 and treated with 50 µM hydrogen peroxide for 1 h, followed by addition of hydrogen peroxide to 5 mM and incubation for the desired period of time. Mitomycin C treatment was carried out similarly by exposing cells (suspended at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2) to mitomycin C (0.2 µg/ml) for 4 h.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Preparation of Cell Lysate, Antibodies and Immunoprecipitations</title><p>Cell lysates were prepared by disrupting cells in a Mini Bead Beater (Biospec Products) as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Sureka1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Immunoprecipitations were carried out by overnight incubation of lysates with antibodies at a dilution of 1∶1,000 at 4°C, followed by precipitation with Protein A/G agarose for 3 h. Antibodies against the kinase domain of PknA, PknB, PBPA, PstP, FtsQ, FipA and FtsZ were raised by Imgenex, Bhubaneswar.</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Fluorescence Microscopy</title><p>Immunostaining was performed as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0008590-Datta2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Briefly, cells were fixed by incubation for 15 minutes at room temperature followed by 45 minutes on ice in 2.5% (v/v) paraformaldehyde, 0.04% (v/v) glutaraldehyde, 30 mM sodium phosphate (pH 7.5). After washing in PBS, the cells were permeabilized by exposing to 2% toluene for 2 min, and immediately transferred to slides. The slides were washed with PBS, air-dried, dipped in methanol (−20°C) for 5 min and then in acetone (−20°C) for 30 s and allowed to dry. After rehydration with PBS, the slides were blocked for 2 h at room temperature with 2% (w/v) BSA-PBS and incubated for 1 h with appropriate dilutions of primary antibody in BSA-PBS. The slides were washed extensively with PBS and then incubated with a 1∶1,000 dilution of Alexa 488-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA) in BSA-PBS. After extensive washing with PBS, the slides were mounted using 50% glycerol. In controls for assessing specificity of the primary antibodies, the incubation with the preimmune sera was included. Images were viewed in a Zeiss Axioimager A1 microscope.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>A. Schematic representation of the genomic region of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> encompassing Rv0014c-Rv0019c and the corresponding region in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>. B. Alignment of the amino acid sequences of FipA of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (encoded by Rv0019c) and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (encoded by MSMEG_0034). The FHA domain is over-scored.</p><p>(0.21 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>A. Expression of PknB, PknA, PBPA, PstP, FipA and FtsZ in wild type (WT) or FipA-KO (KO) or FipA-KO complemented with fipA of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (com.). B,C. Transcriptional analysis of lexA and recA in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>. Cells were treated with hydrogen peroxide or mitomycin C. RNA was isolated and subjected to q-RT-PCR for the lexA (B) and recA (C) genes. Fold increase represents the change with respect to untreated cells. Values shown are means with S.D. of three separate determinations.</p><p>(0.11 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Mass analysis of FipA or FipA phosphorylated by PknA.</p><p>(1.82 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>Mass analysis of FtsZ (unphosphorylated), or phosphorylated by PknA or FtsZ(T343A).</p><p>(0.47 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s004.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the genomic region encompassing the dcw cluster of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (Mtb) and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> (Msmeg).</p><p>(1.27 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s005.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p>Immunolocalization of FipA (A) and FtsQ (B) in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>. Immunolocalization of was carried out by incubation with anti-FipA or anti-FtsQ antibody followed by staining with Alexa 488-conjugated rabbit IgG and visualization by fluorescence microscopy.</p><p>(0.03 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>List of strains and plasmids used in this study.</p><p>(0.04 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s007.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0008590.s008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Primers used in this study.</p><p>(0.06 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0008590.s008.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Prof. Jaya Tyagi for genomic DNA of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv, and Dr. Richard Stokes for pUC-HY-INT.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by a grant from the Council of Industrial Research, Government of India. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0008590-Adams1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Bacterial cell division: assembly, maintenance and disassembly of the Z ring.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrmicro2198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Errington1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Cytokinesis in bacteria.</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12626683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MMBR.67.1.52-65.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC150516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Rothfield1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothfield</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taghbalout</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Spatial control of bacterial division-site placement.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrmicro1290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Goehring1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Diverse paths to midcell: assembly of the bacterial cell division machinery.</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>R514</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16005287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cub.2005.06.038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Goehring2"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gueiros-Filho</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Premature targeting of a cell division protein to midcell allows dissection of divisome assembly in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1253805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC540231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Goehring3"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Premature targeting of cell division proteins to midcell reveals hierarchies of protein interactions involved in divisome assembly.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16824093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05206.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Vicente1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Structure, function and controls in microbial division.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1996.tb02482.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-deBoer1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothfield</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>The essential bacterial cell-division protein FtsZ is a GTPase.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>359</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1528268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/359254a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-RayChaudhuri1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>RayChaudhuri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> cell-division gene <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> encodes a novel GTP-binding protein.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>359</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1528267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/359251a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Bramhill1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramhill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>GTP-dependent polymerization of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> FtsZ protein to form tubules.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>5813</fpage><lpage>5817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8016071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.91.13.5813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC44087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-DiLallo1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiLallo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagioli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barionovi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheraldini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paolozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Use of two-hybrid assay to study the assembly of a complex multicomponent protein machinery: bacterial septosome differentiation.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>149</volume><fpage>3353</fpage><lpage>3359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/mic.0.26580-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Katis1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katis</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wake</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Septal localization of the membrane-bound division proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> DivIB and DivIC is codependent only at high temperatures and requires FtsZ.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>3607</fpage><lpage>3611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10852898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.182.12.3607-3611.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC101979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Datta1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhakta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Interaction between FtsZ and FtsW of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>24983</fpage><lpage>24987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12101218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M203847200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Datta2"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Interaction between FtsW and penicillin-binding protein (PBP)3 directs PBP3 to mid-cell, controls cell septation and mediates the formation of a trimeric complex involving FtsZ, FtsW and PBP3 in mycobacteria.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>1655</fpage><lpage>1673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17427288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05491.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-AvGay1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Av-Gay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The eukaryotic-like Ser/Thr protein kinases of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis.</italic>
</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10785641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0966-842x(00)01734-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Wehenkel1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehenkel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellinzonia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grañaa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villarino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Mycobacterial Ser/Thr protein kinases and phosphatases: Physiological roles and therapeutic potential.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1784</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17869195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbapap.2007.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Greenstein1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenstein</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacGurin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> Ser/Thr protein kinase D phosphorylates an anti-anti-sigma factor homolog.</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17411339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1847690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Villarino1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villarino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehenkel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>England</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Proteomic identification of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> protein kinase substrates: PknB recruits GarA, a FHA domain-containing protein, through activation loop-mediated interactions.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>350</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmb.2005.05.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Dasgupta1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The serine/thronine kinase PknB of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> phosphorylates PBPA, a penicillin-binding protein required for cell division.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>152</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/mic.0.28630-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Kang1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dascher</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> serine/threonine kinases PknA and PknB: substrate identification and regulation of cell shape.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1692</fpage><lpage>1704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15985609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1311105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1176007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Durocher1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durocher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henckel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fersht</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>The FHA domain is a modular phosphopeptide recognition motif.</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1097-2765(00)80340-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Hofmann1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>The FHA domain: a putative nuclear signalling domain found in protein kinases and transcription factors.</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7482699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0968-0004(00)89072-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Grundner1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grundner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> serine/threonine kinases PknB, PknD, PknE, and PknF phosphorylate multiple FHA domains.</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1918</fpage><lpage>1921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1110/ps.051413405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2253351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Strong1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graeber</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beeby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Visualization and interpretation of protein networks in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> based on hierarchical clustering of genome-wide functional linkage maps.</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>7099</fpage><lpage>7109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkg924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC291866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Walker1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>The SOS response of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neidhardt</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtiss</surname><given-names>R</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingraham</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>ECC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli and Salmonella: Cellular and Molecular Biology</italic>, 2nd edn</source><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>1400</fpage><lpage>1416</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Witkin1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witkin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year><article-title>Ultraviolet mutagenesis and inducible DNA repair in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Bacteriol Rev</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">795416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/br.40.4.869-907.1976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC413988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-OSullivan1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> DNA repair in response to subinhibitory concentrations of ciprofloxacin.</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jac/dkn387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2583065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Tusnady1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tusnady</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The HMMTOP transmembrane topology prediction server.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.9.849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Blom1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gammeltoft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Sequence and structure-based prediction of eukaryotic protein phosphorylation sites.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>294</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jmbi.1999.3310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Roy1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananda</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederweis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajitkumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification and semi-quantitative analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv <italic toggle="yes">ftsZ</italic> gene-specific promoter activity-containing regions.</article-title><source>Research in Microbiology</source><volume>155</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.resmic.2004.06.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Narayan1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachdeva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Serine threonine protein kinases of mycobacterial genus: phylogeny to function.</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00221.2006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Hett1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hett</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Bacterial growth and cell division: a Mycobacterial perspective.</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MMBR.00028-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-DAri1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Ari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Novel mechanism of cell division inhibition associated with the SOS response in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>156</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6352679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.156.1.243-250.1983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC215076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Davis1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dullaghan</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Definition of the mycobacterial SOS box and use to identify LexA regulated genes in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>184</volume><fpage>3287</fpage><lpage>3295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.184.12.3287-3295.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC135081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Thakur1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborti</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>GTPase activity of mycobacterial FtsZ is impaired due to its transphosphorylation by the eukaryotic-type Ser/Thr kinase, PknA.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>40107</fpage><lpage>40113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17068335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M607216200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Thakur2"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Ability of PknA, a mycobacterial eukaryotic-type serine/threonine kinase, to transphosphorylate MurD, a ligase involved in the process of peptidoglycan biosynthesis.</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>415</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18557704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BJ20080234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Schultz1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niebisch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwaiger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viets</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Genetic and biochemical analysis of the serine/threonine protein kinases PknA, PknB, PknG and PknL of <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic>: evidence for non-essentiality and for phosphorylation of OdhI and FtsZ by multiple kinases.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19788543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06897.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2784874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Singh1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Protein kinase I of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: Cellular localization and expression during infection of macrophage-like cells.</article-title><source>Tuberculosis</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16256441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tube.2005.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-DUlisse1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Ulisse</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagioli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghelardini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paolozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Three functional subdomains of the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> FtsQ protein are involved in its interaction with the other division proteins.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>153</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/mic.0.2006/000265-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Goehring4"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrovska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Mutants, suppressors, and wrinkled colonies: mutant alleles of the cell division gene <italic toggle="yes">ftsQ</italic> point to functional domains in FtsQ and a role for domain 1C of FtsQ in divisome assembly.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>189</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.00991-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1797389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Mercer1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>KLN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> cell division protein FtsW is required to recruit its cognate transpeptidase, FtsI (PBP3), to the division site.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>184</volume><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.184.4.904-912.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC134820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Gupta1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tandon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>FHA domain containing protein Rv0019c and polyketide-associated protein PapA5, from substrates of serine/threonine kinase PknB to interacting proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>284</volume><fpage>34723</fpage><lpage>34734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19826007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M109.058834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2787335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-England1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>England</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehenkel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>André-Leroux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The FHA-containing protein GarA acts as a phosphorylation-dependent molecular switch in mycobacterial signaling.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>583</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2008.12.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Parish1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Use of a flexible cassette method to generate a double unmarked <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis tlyA plcABC</italic> mutant by gene replacement.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/00221287-146-8-1969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Mahenthiralingam1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahenthiralingam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marklund</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Site-directed mutagenesis of the 19-kilodalton lipoprotein antigen reveals no essential role for the protein in the growth and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium intracellulare</italic>.</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>3626</fpage><lpage>3634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9673242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.66.8.3626-3634.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC108395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Chauhan1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madiraju</surname><given-names>VVS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lofton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> cells growing in macrophages are filamentous and deficient in FtsZ rings.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>1856</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16484196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.188.5.1856-1865.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1426569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Daugelat1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daugelat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bumann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The RD1 proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: expression in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> and biochemical characterization.</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14554249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1286-4579(03)00205-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008590-Sureka1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sureka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Polyphosphate kinase is involved in stress-induced <italic toggle="yes">mprAB-sigE-rel</italic> signaling in mycobacteria.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05814.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>