
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">582</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0372763</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Diabetes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2661595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2661595.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2661595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2661595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db08-1287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">081287</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Complications</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intranasal Insulin Ameliorates Experimental Diabetic Neuropathy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names initials="G">George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names initials="J">Jose</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names initials="T">Thuhien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayer</surname><given-names initials="A">Amit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fine</surname><given-names initials="J">Jared</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names initials="D">Douglas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names initials="LR">Leah R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names initials="WH">William H.</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names initials="C">Cory</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Clinical Neurosciences, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta, Canada; </aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Hotchkiss Brain Institute, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta, Canada; </aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Alzheimer's Research Center, Regions Hospital, St. Paul, Minnesota; and </aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Pharmaceutics, University of Minnesota, St. Paul, Minnesota.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Cory Toth, <email>corytoth@shaw.ca</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">177593</issue-id><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>945</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2009 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creative-commons"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="zdb934.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zdb00409000934.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Diabetes" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4274693"><article-title>Intranasal Insulin Ameliorates Experimental Diabetic Neuropathy. Diabetes 2009;58:<related-article related-article-type="retracted-article" vol="58" page="934" xlink:href="19136650" ext-link-type="pubmed">934–945</related-article>. DOI: 10.2337/db08-1287</article-title><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><fpage seq="2">1817</fpage><lpage>1817</lpage><source>Diabetes</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4274693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24757204</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>We hypothesized that intranasal insulin (I-I) delivery targets the nervous system while avoiding potential adverse systemic effects when compared with subcutaneous insulin (S-I) for experimental streptozotocin-induced diabetic peripheral neuropathy (DPN).</p></sec><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>I-I or S-I at 0.87 IU daily or placebo were delivered in separate cohorts of diabetic and nondiabetic CD1 mice during 8 months of diabetes. Radiolabeled insulin detection was used to compare delivery and biodistribution for I-I and S-I. Biweekly behavioral testing and monthly electrophysiological and quantitative studies assessed progression of DPN. At and before end point, morphometric analysis of DRG, peripheral nerve, distal epidermal innervation, and specific molecular markers were evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Radiolabeled I-I resulted in more rapid and concentrated delivery to the spinal cord and DRG with less systemic insulin exposure. When compared with S-I or intranasal placebo, I-I reduced overall mouse mortality and sensory loss while improving neuropathic pain and electrophysiological/morphological abnormalities in diabetic mice. I-I restored mRNA and protein levels of phosphoinositide 3-kinase/Akt, cyclic AMP response element–binding protein, and glycogen synthase kinase 3β to near normal levels within diabetic DRGs.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>I-I slows the progression of experimental DPN in streptozotocin mice, avoids adverse effects associated with S-I treatment, and prolongs lifespan when compared with S-I. I-I may be a promising approach for the treatment of DPN.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The most common form of peripheral nervous system (PNS) disease complicating diabetes mellitus is diabetic symmetric sensorimotor polyneuropathy (DPN) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Diabetic PNS is subject to behavioral, electrophysiological, and morphological changes within peripheral nerve axons, the dorsal root ganglion (DRG), and epidermal nerve fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Although considered an “end-stage” complication, DPN may occur early and may involve children with diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p>Clinical intervention trials in both type 1 and type 2 diabetes have demonstrated that chronic hyperglycemia has a strong association with the prevalence of complications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Beyond chronic hyperglycemia, other commonly hypothesized mechanisms relevant for pathogenesis of DPN include excessive sorbitol-aldose reductase pathway flux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), protein kinase C isoform(s) overactivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), increased oxidative and nitrative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), microangiopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), and advanced glycation end products and their receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). An important mechanism of DPN may also relate to impaired availability, action, or uptake of growth factors necessary to support peripheral neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). For diabetic neuropathy, modifications in neurotrophin levels or evidence of a supportive role have been identified for many neurotrophin family members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). An important neurotrophic factor critical in supporting peripheral neurons, and diminished in diabetes mellitus, is insulin. Both insulin and IGF-1 are important for neuronal survival and phenotypic expression in DRG neurons, neuritic outgrowth through specific insulin receptor or IGF-1 receptor-mediated signaling pathways within the adult sensory neuron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). Insulin binds to the insulin receptor α subunit, promoting tyrosine autophosphorylation of the β subunit and subsequent phosphorylation of cellular substrates, including the insulin receptor substrate (IRS) proteins and Shc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Phosphorylation of IRS-1 or IRS-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) creates an active signaling complex involving phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K), Akt, and the downstream effectors cyclic AMP response element–binding protein (CREB) and glycogen synthase kinase 3β (GSK-3β), among other molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><p>In an experimental type 1 diabetes model of DPN, we hypothesized that a novel form of direct neuronal long-term insulin replacement therapy could slow DPN progression. Previous experiments have demonstrated that direct intrathecal insulin is capable of reversing features or preventing progression of DPN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). We designed experiments using behavioral and electrophysiological testing to assist in delineating insulin's trophic and antihyperglycemic effects in DPN using intranasal insulin (I-I) delivery to target insulin to the nervous system without significant alteration of blood levels of insulin or glucose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Intranasal delivery was first developed to bypass the blood-brain barrier and directly target growth factors and other therapeutic agents to the central nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) with travel along both olfactory and trigeminal neural conduits within extracellular pathways exclusive of axonal transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Proteins as large as 27 kDa, including IGF-1, have been successfully delivered to the brain using this method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) in rodents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) and humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Our primary goal was to determine efficacy of I-I intervention, but we also used these studies to determine complications of interventions used as secondary end points.</p><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>We studied a total of 484 male CD1 wild-type mice with initial weight of 20 to 30 g housed in plastic sawdust covered cages with a normal light-dark cycle and free access to mouse chow and water. In all cases, mice were raised and studied in strict pathogen-free environments. All protocols were reviewed and approved by the institutional animal care and use committee at Regions Hospital (21 mice, experiment 1) and the University of Calgary Animal Care Committee using the Canadian Council of Animal Care guidelines (463 mice, experiment 2). Mice were anesthetized with pentobarbital (60 mg/kg) before all procedures. At the age of 1 month, 304 mice were injected with streptozotocin (STZ) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) intraperitoneally once daily for each of 3 consecutive days with doses of 60 mg/kg, 50 mg/kg, and then 40 mg/kg with the remaining 180 mice injected with carrier (sodium citrate) for 3 consecutive days. Studies using harvested tissues occurred after 1 month (36 diabetic mice, 30 nondiabetic mice), 3 months (48 diabetic mice, 30 nondiabetic mice), 5 months (60 diabetic mice, 30 nondiabetic mice), and 8 months (160 diabetic mice, 90 nondiabetic mice).</p><p>Whole blood glucose measurements were performed monthly with puncture of the tail vein and a blood glucometer (OneTouch Ultra Meter; LifeScan Canada, Burnaby, BC, Canada). Hyperglycemia was verified 1 week after STZ injections with a fasting whole blood glucose level of 16 mmol/l or greater (normal 5–8 mmol/l), our definition for experimental diabetes. All animals were weighed monthly. Mice were followed and harvested at 1, 3, 5, or 8 months of diabetes (&gt;9 months of life). Mice that did not develop diabetes were excluded from further assessment.</p><p>Animals were inspected twice daily and examined for signs of depressed level of consciousness, ataxia, or general malaise. When such signs were identified, whole blood glucose testing was performed with a measurement of less than 3.5 mmol/l defined to represent hypoglycemia. No intervention was performed at any time with regard to additional insulin, glucose, or fluid delivery. In situations in which the mouse was obviously ill, euthanasia was performed. In circumstances in which severe hyperglycemia was found (&gt;33 mmol/l) in an ill mouse, euthanasia was performed.</p><p>We studied cohorts with a maximum of eight mice in each group initially as a result of resource limitations. After the initial cohorts containing eight mice each were studied, a second cohort was used to obtain additional mouse data for mouse cohorts with higher levels of mortality. For any animal that experienced mortality after the 20-week point of the sensorimotor studies, the data were carried through using the last obtainable data point.</p><p>In this work, delivery of subcutaneous saline is indicated as “S-S,” subcutaneous insulin as “S-I,” intranasal saline as “I-S,” and intranasal insulin as “I-I.”</p><sec><title>Experiment 1: pharmacokinetic studies of intranasal or subcutaneous delivery.</title><p><sup>125</sup>I-labeled I-I administration was performed to determine distribution of intranasally delivered insulin in 21 nondiabetic mice. Before experimentation, animals were acclimated for handling during awake intranasal delivery for 2 weeks. <sup>125</sup>I-labeled I-I was provided to 12 CD1 mice (male, 6–8 weeks; Charles River) and <sup>125</sup>I-labeled S-I was provided to nine mice under pentobarbital anesthesia (60 mg/kg). Insulin (Humulin R; Eli Lilly, Toronto, Canada) with an initial concentration of 100 units/ml or 4033.98 mg/ml was dissolved in PBS and custom-labeled with <sup>125</sup>I (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ). Radiolabeled insulin solution contained 344.3 uCi/μg at synthesis. <sup>125</sup>I-labeled I-I delivery was performed in a fume hood behind a lead-impregnated shield with anesthetized mice placed supine. A mixture of <sup>125</sup>I insulin (15.8 μCi) and unlabeled insulin (3.3 μg) were administered as I-I or S-I. <sup>125</sup>I I-I was delivered as eight 3-μl drops with an Eppendorf pipette over alternating nares every 2 min for a total volume of 24 μl. For subcutaneous delivery, <sup>125</sup>I S-I was delivered with a single subcutaneous injection of 24 μl in a fume hood behind a lead-impregnated shield.</p><p>At each of 1, 2, and 6 h after <sup>125</sup>I I-I or S-I delivery, cardiocentesis was performed to extract blood followed by euthanasia using transcardial perfusion using 120 ml of 4% paraformaldehyde under anesthesia. To quantify <sup>125</sup>I distribution, portions of the nervous systems were harvested along with blood, urine, lymphatic, and visceral organ structures. Olfactory epithelium and trigeminal nerve were examined as a result of their role in intranasal delivery into the nervous system and cerebrospinal fluid. Gamma signal was quantified in each tissue using a Packard Cobra II auto-gamma counter (PerkinElmer Life and Analytical Sciences, Waltham, MA). Concentrations of <sup>125</sup>I insulin were calculated based on the gamma counting data, tissue weight, specific activity of the insulin administered, and measured standards.</p></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: daily intranasal and subcutaneous insulin delivery studies.</title><p>Daily I-I (Humulin R; Eli Lilly) and intranasal saline (I-S) was administered to either diabetic or nondiabetic male CD1 mice after a 1-week training period immediately after STZ injection using only intranasal saline for accustoming mice before diabetes verification. Although each mouse was held in a supine position while in neck extension, a total of 24 μl containing either a total of 0.87 IU of insulin or 0.9% saline only was provided as four drops of 6 μl each through Eppendorf pipette over alternating nares every 1 min. Daily S-I (0.87 IU) (Humulin R) and S-S were also administered daily to either diabetic or nondiabetic male CD1 mice at the same dose. All therapies began immediately after confirmation of presence of diabetes for each cohort. In the first week, daily glucometer testing was performed for all mice followed by once-monthly testing and during times of illness.</p><p>We attempted to use other control groups but found their usefulness to be limited in each case. The delivery of S-I by a sliding scale approach requiring daily whole blood glucose sampling through repeated punctures or the use of a protected venous catheter led to intolerable rates of infection and/or tail amputation, so the morbidity accrued with this procedure was deemed unacceptable and a potential confounder with any behavioral studies. Delivery of reduced subcutaneous doses of insulin failed to modify glycemic levels. Therefore, we selected the S-I dose to be equivalent to I-I dosing (0.87 IU) for the cohorts studied.</p></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2a: electrophysiology during intranasal and subcutaneous insulin delivery studies.</title><p>Electrophysiological assessment of sciatic nerve function was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) under halothane anesthesia. Initial baseline studies were carrier out before STZ or carrier injections; no significant difference between groups was identified. Of all cohorts of mice receiving I-I, S-I, I-S, or S-S, both diabetic and nondiabetic, at least five mice in each group underwent monthly electrophysiological testing beginning before induction of diabetes and after 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 months of diabetes. For orthodromic sensory conduction studies, the sural nerve was used with a fixed distance of 30 mm from platinum subdermal stimulation needle electrodes (Grass Instruments, Astro-Med, West Warwick, RI) to the sciatic notch where recording electrodes were placed to measure the sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitude and sensory nerve conduction velocity (SNCV). Near-nerve temperature was kept constant during testing at 37 ± 0.5°C using a heating lamp.</p></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2b: behavioral testing during intranasal and subcutaneous insulin delivery studies.</title><p>A total of 10 mice in each cohort had behavioral testing performed twice monthly to evaluate mechanical and thermal sensation. A 2-week training period was performed to acclimatize mice to the procedure immediately after STZ injections and during diabetes verification. Mice were placed in a Plexiglas cage on a glass plate (for thermal testing) or on a plastic mesh floor (for tactile testing) and were allowed to acclimate for at least 5 min before recording in all cases. Thermal sensation was tested using the Hargreaves apparatus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). In brief, a radiant heat source was applied individually to the middle of either hind paw for up to 60 s with the latency (seconds) to withdrawal measured. Heating rate ramped from 30 to 58°C over 60 s in consistent fashion on each occasion. Paws were inspected before and after thermal testing to ensure that no evidence of thermal damage was present. There were 5-min intervals provided between a total of three trials performed during the same day. To quantify mechanical sensitivity of the foot, withdrawal in response to a stimulus consisted of sequentially smaller von Frey filaments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Five trials were performed at each filament size with a total of three or more withdrawals to up-and-down movements indicating sensitivity at the smallest positive filament size. Mechanical and thermal testing was performed on identical days with an interval of at least 1 h between the two tests.</p></sec><sec><title>Other procedures and testing.</title><p>Harvesting of tissues and their subsequent morphometric processing and analysis along with quantification of epidermal fibers and all other molecular testing (Western immunoblotting, polymerase chain reactions, and electrophoretic mobility shift assays) have been described in detail in an online appendix (available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/db08-1287/DC1">http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/db08-1287/DC1</ext-link>).</p><p>All statistical comparisons were intended between the following groups: diabetic I-I and S-I; diabetic I-I and I-S; diabetic I-I and control I-I; diabetic S-I and S-S; diabetic S-I and control S-I; control I-I and S-I; control I-I and I-S; and control S-I and S-S. Comparison testing was not performed between other grouped cohorts with Bonferroni corrections applied as appropriate for these group comparisons.</p><p>Data collected in the groups were expressed as mean ± SE in all cases. Data from each individual mouse were used to obtain means in each case. One-way matched/unmatched ANOVA and Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests were performed to compare means between diabetic and control groups. For immunohistochemistry comparisons demonstrated as low/medium/high intensity, the individual values were compared using unmatched ANOVA testing. Also, AUC statistical testing was performed for behavioral testing performed and was calculated using the trapezoidal method. Again, only the groups intended to have statistical comparisons were analyzed as such. Correlational relationships for AUC were tested using multiple linear regression analysis. For the purposes of molecular studies and comparisons, in some cases, only one control (nondiabetic) group was used as a control value with subsequent comparisons to other diabetic groups for the molecular test studied; Bonferroni corrections were made as appropriate depending on the number of relevant comparisons.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Experiment 1: distribution of administered insulin.</title><p>At 1 h after I-I or S-I delivery, insulin concentrations were higher within cervical spinal cord, DRGs, and spinal dura with I-I delivery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Insulin concentrations in blood were substantially higher after S-I delivery (850× greater), but insulin concentrations within kidney, liver, and lung were higher after I-I delivery.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 1.</label><caption><p>Detection of radiolabeled insulin after 1 and 6 h of both I-I and S-I. Initial blood and organ insulin levels were lower than those achieved with S-I (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>; after 1 h). At 6 h after delivery (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), I-I was associated with increased blood levels, and S-I was more readily identified in nervous tissues. Significant differences were determined by matched Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests, with an asterisk indicating a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) between the I-I and S-I delivery techniques for each tissue (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4 mice in each mouse cohort for each time point).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="zdb0040956760001.jpg"/></fig><p>At 6 h after I-I or S-I delivery, insulin concentrations were higher in DRGs and spinal dura after S-I delivery compared with I-I delivery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). After 6 h, blood concentrations of insulin were higher after I-I delivery with this peak detected at 6 h. Insulin concentrations in systemic organs were now higher after S-I delivery. When 2-h data are considered, I-I delivery led to peaks in insulin concentration within DRGs and systemic organs after 1 h and peaks in blood concentrations of insulin after 6 h. S-I delivery, in contrast, led to peaks in insulin concentration at DRG and systemic organs after 6 h, whereas blood concentrations peaked after 1 h. Blood concentrations of insulin after S-I delivery peaked at a value nearly 1,000× the peak value obtained with I-I delivery.</p><p>Mice receiving I-I treatment maintained good health throughout the 1-, 2-, and 6-h monitoring periods before being euthanized, whereas S-I delivery led to more frequent development of hypoglycemia-induced illness, including death, and also to reduced consciousness levels in many mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: diabetes model.</title><p>After STZ injection, mice developed diabetes within 2 weeks in greater than 85% of animals, and in each case, diabetes was maintained over the length of the study. Diabetic mice were smaller than nondiabetic mice within 1 month after STZ injection, and diabetic mice had smaller body weights throughout life (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>); diabetic mice receiving I-I maintained weight better than the cohort receiving I-S. Hyperglycemia was identical in mice receiving I-I or I-S, but S-I mice had more documented hyperglycemia and more episodes of illness or death associated with confirmed hypoglycemia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Mouse glycated hemoglobin was increased in all diabetic mice after more than 9 months of life and was identical between I-I and I-S mice but was reduced in surviving S-I mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The mortality rate in diabetic mice was significantly higher than in nondiabetic mice, although diabetic I-I mice had improved mortality relative to diabetic I-S, diabetic S-S, and diabetic S-I mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Murine weights, fasting glycemia levels, glycated hemoglobin levels, and survival numbers at induction of diabetes and at harvesting at months 1, 3, 5, and 8 of diabetes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-1">*</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time point</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injection of STZ/carrier</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Month 1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Month 3</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Month 5</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Month 8</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 ± 3.2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 ± 3.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.7 ± 4.0 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4 ± 4.3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2 ± 4.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 23)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8 ± 3.9 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 ± 4.1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.6 ± 4.7 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 ± 5.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 15)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0 ± 5.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1 ± 3.7 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 ± 3.9 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1 ± 4.2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7 ± 4.6 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1 ± 5.2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 ± 3.3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 25)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9 ± 3.5 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 ± 4.9 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 23)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.1 ± 5.3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4 ± 4.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2 ± 3.3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 40)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9 ± 4.2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 34) (3 nondiabetic)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4 ± 4.3 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 30)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6 ± 5.7 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 ± 5.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4 ± 3.4 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 40)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4 ± 4.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 31) (2 nondiabetic)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2 ± 3.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2 ± 4.1 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8 ± 4.9 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2 ± 3.4 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 40)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2 ± 4.8 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 33) (3 nondiabetic)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9 ± 4.2 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 30)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2 ± 4.9 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 22)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 ± 5.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 ± 3.5 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 40)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 ± 4.0 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 36) (3 nondiabetic)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9 ± 4.5 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 35)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8 ± 3.6 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 33)</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6 ± 4.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 30)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine glycemia and 8-month glycated Hemoglobin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 ± 2.3</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 2.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 ± 2.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 3.0</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">6.6</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">3.2</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref><italic toggle="yes">(12.4%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">4.8%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 ± 2.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 ± 2.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 ± 2.9</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 ± 3.0</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">4.0</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">3.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref></italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-5">‖</xref><italic toggle="yes">(9.2%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">4.1%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 ± 2.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 2.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 2.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 ± 3.1</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">6.3</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">2.7 (12.1%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">4.7%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 2.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 2.9</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 ± 3.0</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 3.0</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">5.7</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">3.2 (12.6%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">4.9%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 ± 2.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 ± 4.9</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3 ± 6.1</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2 ± 6.2</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">32.4</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.0 (31.6%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.2%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6 ± 2.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 ± 5.2</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9 ± 5.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 ± 5.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">24.8</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.1 (24.1%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.6%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 ± 2.9</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2 ± 4.6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 ± 5.3</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 ± 5.2</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">32.3</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">5.8 (32.0%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.0%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 ± 2.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5 ± 4.5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6 ± 5.0</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6 ± 5.2</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">32.0</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">5.6 (30.2%</italic> ± <italic toggle="yes">6.4%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murine survival numbers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/25 (960%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/25 (96%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">23/25 (92%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/25 (80%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/25 (68%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/25 (60%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">12/25 (48%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-2">†</xref></italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-5">‖</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">24/25 (96%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/25 (96%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/25 (92%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/25 (88%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">21/25 (84%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/37 (3 nondiabetic, 92%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/37 (81%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/37 (54%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">16/37 (43%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/38 (2 nondiabetic, 82%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/38 (63%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/38 (42%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">12/38 (32%)</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/36 (3 nondiabetic, 92%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/36 (83%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/36 (61%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">18/36 (50%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref></italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (100%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36/39 (3 nondiabetic, 92%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/39 (90%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/39 (85%)</td><td align="char" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">30/39 (77%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-3">‡</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1-4">§</xref></italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means ± SEM and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%).</p></fn><fn id="TF1-1"><p>*Glycated hemoglobin values are presented in italics in the 8-month column for glycemia levels. For murine survival, Kaplan-Meier statistics were performed between cohort groups.</p></fn><fn id="TF1-2"><p>†Significance at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 with comparison of nondiabetic S-S and S-I mice cohort groups.</p></fn><fn id="TF1-3"><p>‡Significance between diabetic cohort groups receiving I-S and I-I.</p></fn><fn id="TF1-4"><p>§Significance with comparison of diabetic I-I mice to S-S and I-S diabetic cohort groups.</p></fn><fn id="TF1-5"><p>‖Significance with comparison of nondiabetic S-I mice to all other nondiabetic mice using Bonferroni post hoc comparisons (α = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125) (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.96 and 144.8 for indicated groups and time points, df = 7,4, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8–10). S-S = subcutaneous saline; S-I = subcutaneous insulin; I-I = intranasal insulin; I-S = intranasal saline.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on sensorimotor behavioral data.</title><p>Before induction of diabetes, there were no baseline differences in sensory behavior testing between any of the mouse cohorts identified. All diabetic mice developed tactile allodynia after 5 to 7 weeks of diabetes when compared with nondiabetic mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Diabetic I-I mice developed less allodynia in the first 3 months of diabetes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) as compared with the other diabetic cohorts. In the later stages of diabetes, I-I mice had less tactile sensory loss than other diabetic mouse cohorts, although diabetic S-I mice had greater maintenance of sensation for tactile stimuli than diabetic mice receiving S-S or I-S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). During serial thermal testing, each cohort of diabetic mice also developed thermal hypersensitivity when compared with nondiabetic mice after several weeks, earlier than identified in other species or mouse strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). However, diabetic I-I mice demonstrated less hypersensitivity in the early stages of diabetes and maintained thermal sensation better in the later stages of diabetes. Diabetic S-I mice had less thermal sensory loss in the later stages of diabetes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) when compared with diabetic mice receiving S-S and S-I. Within the first 20 weeks, AUC measurements were statistically different for diabetic I-I mice as compared with other diabetic mouse cohorts for both tactile and thermal testing, and all diabetic cohorts had thermal hypersensitivity and tactile allodynia when compared with nondiabetic mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 2.</label><caption><p>Tactile (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and thermal (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) sensory testing data for sciatic nerve function in mice with or without diabetes. Significant differences were determined by multiple ANOVA tests, with an asterisk indicating a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 using Bonferroni corrections) between the diabetic I-I mouse group and other diabetic mouse cohorts and with φ indicating a significant difference (nonmatched ANOVA tests; <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 1.08 and 11.76 for indicated groups and time points; df = 3,5; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 using Bonferroni corrections) between the diabetic S-I mouse group and diabetic S-S and diabetic I-S groups for the respective time points. AUC measurements also revealed greater values for nondiabetic cohorts as compared with relevant diabetic cohorts in each case (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125). AUC values were also greater for diabetic I-I mice for the first 20 weeks studied as compared with other diabetic cohorts (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6–8 mice in each mouse cohort for each time point). C, control; D, diabetic; I-I, intranasal insulin; S-I, subcutaneous insulin; S-S, subcutaneous saline.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="zdb0040956760002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on electrophysiology.</title><p>Before induction of diabetes, there were no baseline electrophysiological differences between any of the mouse cohorts identified. Sensory amplitudes and sensory conduction velocities demonstrated age-related declines over time in both diabetic and nondiabetic cohorts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, with more rapid declines in diabetes. Overall reductions in SNAP amplitudes and in SNCV occurred in diabetic mice relative to nondiabetic mice beginning after 2 to 3 months, similar to previous results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Protection against declining SNAPs and SNCV occurred beginning at 3 to 4 months in diabetic I-I mice as compared with all other cohort groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) and slightly later in diabetic S-I mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Overall, in comparison to S-S, I-S, and S-I diabetic mice, diabetic I-I mice displayed significant protection against electrophysiological deterioration in sensory function.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 3.</label><caption><p>Sensory nerve conduction study data for sciatic nerves in mice with or without diabetes. Diabetic I-I mice had more successful amelioration than diabetic S-I mice of decline of sensory nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitudes (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and sensory nerve conduction velocities (SNCV) (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) when compared with other diabetic cohorts. Significant differences were determined by multiple ANOVA tests, with an asterisk indicating significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 using Bonferroni corrections) between the diabetic I-I mouse group and other diabetic mouse cohorts and with φ indicating significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 using Bonferroni corrections) between the diabetic S-I mouse group and diabetic S-S and diabetic I-S groups for the respective time points (nonmatched ANOVA tests; <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.98 and 6.44 for indicated groups and time points; df = 3,5; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6–8 mice in each mouse cohort for each time point). <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, control; <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, diabetic; S-I, subcutaneous insulin; I-I, intranasal insulin; S-S, subcutaneous saline.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="zdb0040956760003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on peripheral nerve.</title><p>In diabetic mice, sciatic nerves had axonal atrophy without axonal loss identified (supplemental Table 1), and sural nerves from diabetic mice developed a loss of fiber density and axonal area (atrophy) relative to nondiabetic controls (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> and supplemental Fig. 1). Diabetic I-I mice were protected from declines in sural axon density and from axonal atrophy in both the sural and sciatic nerves after 8 months of diabetes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) when compared with diabetic S-I, S-S, and I-S mice (supplemental Tables 1 and 2 and supplemental Fig. 1). Diabetic sural and sciatic nerve myelin thickness was also reduced after 8 months of diabetes (supplemental Tables 1 and 2) with some protection offered by I-I delivery.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Morphological properties of sural nerves in nondiabetic and diabetic nerves from mice receiving intranasal or subcutaneous insulin or saline after 1 and 8 months of diabetes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical property</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 month of diabetes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 months of diabetes</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal fiber density (per mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,024 ± 136</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,522 ± 124</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,122 ± 142</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,113 ± 132</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,098 ± 138</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,222 ± 128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,055 ± 151</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,151 ± 147</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,104 ± 157</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,377 ± 168<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,085 ± 164</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,982 ± 175<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,063 ± 161</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,522 ± 115<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,002 ± 168</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,916 ± 172<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal area (μm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 ± 0.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7 ± 0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9 ± 0.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4 ± 0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9 ± 0.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6 ± 0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4 ± 0.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3 ± 0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8 ± 0.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 ± 0.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-2">†</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 ± 0.7</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2 ± 0.8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1 ± 0.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 ± 0.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 ± 0.8</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6 ± 0.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal diameter (μm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34 ± 0.20</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92 ± 0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 ± 0.21</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.77 ± 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28 ± 0.20</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 ± 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19 ± 0.19</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83 ± 0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18 ± 0.16</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34 ± 0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-2">†</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08 ± 0.15</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80 ± 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22 ± 0.12</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 ± 0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11 ± 0.13</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78 ± 0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelination thickness (μm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 ± 0.05</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 ± 0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 ± 0.05</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 ± 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 ± 0.04</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 ± 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 ± 0.05</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 ± 0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 ± 0.05</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 ± 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-3">‡</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 ± 0.04</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 ± 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 ± 0.04</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 ± 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="–" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 ± 0.05</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 ± 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2-1">*</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means ± SEM.</p></fn><fn id="TF2-1"><p>*Significance between diabetic mice and their nondiabetic intervention counterpart (D I-I versus C I-I, D I-S versus C I-S, D S-I versus C S-I, and D S-S versus C S-S) (α = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.016) (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.85 and 0.02 for indicated groups and time points, df = 4,3, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4–6).</p></fn><fn id="TF2-2"><p>†Significance with comparison of D I-I mice to both D S-I and D I-S mice.</p></fn><fn id="TF2-3"><p>‡Significance with comparison of D I-I mice to D I-S mice using multiple ANOVA testing with Bonferroni post hoc <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test comparisons (α = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.016) (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.98 and 3.55 for indicated groups and time points, df = 5,4, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4–6). D = diabetic; I-I = intranasal insulin; C = control; I-S = intranasal saline; S-I = subcutaneous insulin; S-S = subcutaneous saline.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Morphological properties of DRG neurons in nondiabetic and diabetic mice receiving intranasal or subcutaneous insulin or saline after 8 months of diabetes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical property</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 months of diabetes</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuronal density (per mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,567 ± 44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,516 ± 37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,549 ± 40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,517 ± 41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,488 ± 42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-3">‡</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,416 ± 47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,444 ± 42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,412 ± 45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total neuronal numbers (per L5 DRG)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,675 ± 68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,596 ± 57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,609 ± 70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,587 ± 61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,252 ± 62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-2">†</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,965 ± 52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,047 ± 48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,916 ± 55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuronal area (μm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">625 ± 18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 ± 17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624 ± 20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Nondiabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">614 ± 19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">579 ± 16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-3">‡</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic I-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">550 ± 17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-I mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">569 ± 16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">    Diabetic S-S mice</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">543 ± 17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3-1">*</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means ± SEM.</p></fn><fn id="TF3-1"><p>*Significance between diabetic mice and their nondiabetic intervention counterpart (D I-I versus C I-I, D I-S versus C I-S, D S-I versus C S-I, and D S-S versus C S-S) (α = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.016) (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.88 and 8.76 for indicated groups and time points, DF = 4,3, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4–6).</p></fn><fn id="TF3-2"><p>†Significance with comparison of D I-I mice to both D S-I and D I-S mice.</p></fn><fn id="TF3-3"><p>‡Significance with comparison of D I-I mice to D I-S mice using multiple ANOVA testing with Bonferroni post hoc <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test comparisons (α = 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.016) (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.98 and 3.55 for indicated groups and time points, df = 5,4, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4–6). D = diabetic; I-I = intranasal insulin; C = control; I-S = intranasal saline; S-I = subcutaneous insulin; S-S = subcutaneous saline.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on dorsal root ganglia.</title><p>DRG neurons developed mild neuronal atrophy and loss of density with exposure to long-term diabetes (supplemental Fig. 2 and Table 3), except in the case of diabetic I-I mice, in which no significant loss in neuronal density was identified, indicating neuronal protection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Similarly, diabetic I-I mice again had preservation of DRG neuronal size and density when compared with diabetic I-S and diabetic S-S mice (supplemental Fig. 2 and Table 3). There was evidence of partial protection among diabetic S-I mice (supplemental Fig. 2 and Table 3). DRG neurons from diabetic I-I mice had elevated levels of PI3K, Akt, and pAkt mRNA and protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 4.</label><caption><p>Quantitative RT-PCR identified marked downregulation for PI3K (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and Akt (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) mRNA in DRG and sciatic nerve from diabetic mice with protection in diabetic I-I mice in DRG but not in sciatic nerve. Downregulation of PI3K, Akt, and pAkt mRNA in diabetic DRG neurons was complemented by downregulation of CREB, pCREB, GSK3β, and pGSK3β protein within diabetic DRGs (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). Quantification of three Western blots for each mouse cohort identified downregulation of each of PI3K, Akt, pAkt, CREB, pCREB, GSK3β, and pGSK3β protein for all diabetic DRG (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) with partial protection in diabetic I-I mice. An asterisk indicates a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 after Bonferroni corrections) between groups indicated by horizontal bars (nonmatched ANOVA tests; <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 1.22 and 6.74 for indicated groups and time points; df = 2,3; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5–6). All diabetes values were significantly less than nondiabetes values (significance not visually demonstrated). <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, control; <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, diabetic; S-I, subcutaneous insulin; I-I, intranasal insulin; S-S, subcutaneous saline.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="zdb0040956760004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on epidermal innervation.</title><p>The hind footpad epidermal nerve fiber density of all mouse cohorts with diabetes was reduced compared with nondiabetic mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Overall, diabetic I-I mice were protected from epidermal fiber loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>), whereas diabetic S-I mice had better maintained epidermal nerve fiber density than diabetic S-S or diabetic I-S mice by the 8-month end point. The separate methods of analyses for epidermal nerve fiber densities yielded similar results.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 5.</label><caption><p>Epidermal footpads from mice with and without diabetes were assessed. The basement membrane and vasculature were identified with immunohistochemistry for collagen type IV (<italic toggle="yes">red</italic>). Epidermal axons were identified with PGP 9.5 (<italic toggle="yes">green</italic>) for a control I-S mouse (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>), control I-I mouse (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), diabetic I-S mouse (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>), and diabetic I-I mouse (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). Note the presence of epidermal end bulbs (arrows) in axons of diabetic mice. Diabetes was associated with the loss of epidermal nerve fibers (per epidermal area [<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, hindfoot; <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>, forefoot] and length [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>, hindfoot; <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>, forefoot]), with partial preservation in diabetic I-I mice and less preservation in diabetic S-I mice (□, C S-S; ▧, D S-S; <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="image" xlink:href="permzspch076.jpg"/>, D S-I; ■, D I-S; ▨, D I-I). All measures of epidermal fiber density are listed as means ± SEM. Asterisk indicates significance with comparison of diabetic I-I and diabetic I-S mice; φ indicates significance with comparison of diabetic I-I and diabetic S-I mice (nonmatched ANOVA tests, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>-values range between 0.89 and 5.21 for indicated groups and time points, df = 5,3, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5–6). Bar = 100 μm. <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, control; <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, diabetic; I-S, intranasal saline; I-I, intranasal insulin; S-I, subcutaneous insulin. (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="zdb0040956760005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experiment 2: impact of intranasal insulin on signaling pathways.</title><p>Quantification of mRNA and protein for Akt and PI3K demonstrated general downregulation in diabetic tissues with at least partial reversal of both PI3K and Akt mRNA and protein levels occurring in diabetic I-I mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) in DRG, but not in sciatic nerve. Diabetic I-I mice also had partial protection from downregulation of pGSK3β, GSK3β, and pCREB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Finally, CREB protein binding to DNA was identified to be depressed with diabetes (supplemental Fig. 3) with partial resolution in diabetic I-I mice.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>I-I protected diabetic mice from behavioral, structural, and molecular changes associated with DPN. We propose that insulin's neuroprotective effects on the PNS are the result of restoration of the PI3K/Akt pathway components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Additionally, I-I led to less mortality than S-I delivery and provided greater protection against the effects of long-term diabetes on the PNS.</p><sec><title>Systemic and peripheral nervous system impact of subcutaneous and intranasal insulin.</title><p>Replacement of insulin in a type I model of diabetes through either I-I or S-I delivery led to improvements in behavioral, electrophysiological, morphological, and molecular status (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and supplemental Figs. 1–3) related to diabetes. Paradoxically, S-I delivery in diabetic mice led to greater mortality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), relating in part to episodes of hypoglycemia, a complication avoided by I-I. Although S-I led to improved glycated hemoglobin levels at final end point, this effect was not seen in diabetic I-I mice. These results suggest that the beneficial effects of I-I in diabetes are not primarily related to corrections in hyperglycemia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Role of insulin as a neuroprotective trophic factor.</title><p>Insulin, a highly conserved peptide, has now emerged as a key neurotrophic factor in the nervous system, a role that is lost in type 1 diabetes. The major site of insulin's activity, the insulin receptor, is found in high concentrations among DRG neurons and myelinated sensory root fibers and in lesser concentrations on myelinated anterior root fibers and in the ventral horn of the spinal cord (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Intrathecal insulin prevents degeneration and promotes regeneration in injured peripheral nerve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Meanwhile, systemic or intrathecal insulin delivery prevents diabetes-mediated electrophysiological changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), whereas intrathecal insulin restores distal skin epidermal innervation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). In vitro, insulin exerts a direct neuritic outgrowth effect through insulin receptors or perhaps through crossactivation of IGF-1 receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Insulin's greatest impact appears to be at the level of the DRG, where insulin may prevent a “dying-back” that begins in the most distal epidermal fibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Insulin's downstream signaling pathways.</title><p>Insulin stimulation upregulates protein-tyrosine phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) through downstream activation of IRS-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Insulin also modulates the inner mitochondrial membrane potential through activation of the PI3K pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), stimulating phosphorylation of Akt and Akt substrates such as CREB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). PI3K promotes translocation of voltage-dependent calcium channel currents to the neurolemma in an Akt-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Activated Akt is important for sensory neurite extension and branching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>), and the PI3K–Akt pathway has a positive regulatory effect on myelin-associated glycoprotein (MAG) expression in Schwann cells, Schwann cell differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>), and promotion of myelination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) through Schwann cell biosynthesis of fatty acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Similar to insulin, IGF-I also activates the PI3K/Akt pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>), leading to phosphorylation of Akt effectors, including CREB and GSK-3β (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). IGF-I also leads to accumulation of pAkt within DRG neuronal nuclei and increases CREB-mediated transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). In our studies, prevention of downregulation of PI3K/Akt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) in murine DRG was associated with amelioration of behavioral, electrophysiological, and morphological changes pertaining to diabetes.</p><p>CREB is also a neuroprotective molecule; CREB phosphorylation inhibits apoptosis in embryonic neurons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>), whereas the loss of CREB results in impaired axonal growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). Meanwhile, GSK-3β, downstream of PI3K/Akt, is a neuron-specific promoter of apoptosis in DRG neurons when it is active (nonphosphorylated state) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Phosphorylation of GSK-3β by Akt renders it inactive, leading to antiapoptotic properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). GSK-3β also regulates the transcriptional activities of CREB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>) and may regulate gene expression and activity of transcriptional factor binding to the MAG promoter region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). GSK-3β also promotes Schwann cell differentiation, suggesting that the PI3K/Akt/GSK-3β pathway is crucial for initiation and possibly maintenance of myelination through promotion of MAG expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Thus, insulin may be important in maintaining conduction velocities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by direct effects on Schwann cells. In our studies, I-I delivery was associated with elevation of pCREB and pGSK-3β levels and reversal of diabetes-associated suppression of CREB-DNA binding within diabetic mouse DRGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> and supplemental Fig. 3).</p></sec><sec><title>Usefulness of intranasal delivery in diabetic neuropathy.</title><p>Intranasal administration allows insulin to bypass the blood-brain barrier and enter the brain and spinal cord parenchyma, as well as CSF, within 1 h. Its entry into the nervous system and CSF likely occurs through extracellular bulk flow transport along both olfactory and trigeminal neural pathways and may use perivascular channels of blood vessels entering the CNS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). This method of insulin delivery permitted us to study the impact of insulin without affecting glycemia levels such as occurs with systemic insulin delivery, easing difficulty in dissecting the relative contributions of hyperglycemia and insulin's trophic properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Prior studies using intranasal delivery of insulin-like molecules such as IGF-1 have demonstrated safety and efficacy in experimental stroke (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). I-I delivery in humans has led to improvements in memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) within minimal impact on plasma glucose levels, which remain in the euglycemic range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Although the use of I-I for the management of systemic diabetes has been limited, in our mouse cohorts, I-I was also associated with better maintenance of body weight and improved mortality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Limitations of our results using I-I delivery in diabetic mice must be acknowledged. Our results must be considered under the limitations of working with a murine model, and the inability to achieve a long-term model of murine type 1 diabetes with optimal glycemic management as a suitable control group. The mouse cohorts were subjected to intensive testing throughout their lifetime, which may have led to stress impacting on behavioral testing results. Diabetic CD1 mice developed sensory behavioral changes earlier than has been observed in other rodent models of diabetes, which may limit portability of these findings to other models. It is also possible that hypoglycemia may have impacted on sensorimotor testing; the impact of hypoglycemia on the diabetic I-S and control I-S cohort groups was anticipated but unavoidable. Distribution of insulin within the diabetic nervous system may differ from results obtained in nondiabetic mice examined in our radiolabeling studies. In addition, although I-I–obtained concentrations were higher in nervous system tissues, tissue concentrations at later time points were not different between I-I and S-I delivery, suggesting that differences in systemic exposure and possibly different metabolic rates for insulin may also play a role in our results. Based on our studies, it is difficult to develop a more appropriate control group of diabetic mice with long-term glycemic control based on the STZ-induced diabetic model. However, our results also provide evidence for potentially robust benefits of insulin independent of its actions on hyperglycemia. These results support its role as an important neurotrophic factor in the management of diabetic neuropathy. Our results support the development of human I-I clinical trials for the prevention and slowing of the development of DPN.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Online-Only Appendix</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_58_4_934__index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="supp_db08-1287_db08-12871.suppl.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked “advertisement” in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by an operating grant from the Alberta Heritage Foundation for Medical Research (AHFMR) and the Canadian Diabetes Association (CDA). C.T. is a Clinical Investigator of the Alberta Heritage Foundation for Medical Research, and D.W.Z. is a Scientist of the Alberta Heritage Foundation for Medical Research (AHFMR).</p><p>W.F. is the inventor of a patent for intranasal insulin (Neurologic agents for nasal administration the brain. World Intellectual Property Organization. PCT priority date 5.12.89, WO 91/07947; 1991), a patent and technique that has no goal of commercialization and therefore no measurable financial conflict of interest. Although W.F. is an inventor on this patent about intranasal insulin, this patent is wholly owned by Chiron/Novartis and, to the best of our knowledge, the company has no intent to commercialize intranasal insulin. None of the other co-authors have any relationship with Chiron/Novartis. No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Diabetic neuropathies and pain</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source><volume>15</volume>:
<fpage>917</fpage>–
<lpage>931</lpage>,
<year>1986</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3536205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0300-595x(86)80080-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Diabetes mellitus and the peripheral nervous system: manifestations and mechanisms</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Muscle Nerve</italic></source><volume>36</volume>:
<fpage>144</fpage>–
<lpage>166</lpage>,
<year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17469109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mus.20785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Epidermal nerve innervation in impaired glucose tolerance and diabetes-associated neuropathy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source><volume>57</volume>:
<fpage>1701</fpage>–
<lpage>1704</lpage>,
<year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11706115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/wnl.57.9.1701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brussee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Diabetes mellitus and the sensory neuron</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</italic></source><volume>63</volume>:
<fpage>561</fpage>–
<lpage>573</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15217085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnen/63.6.561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mah</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darwish</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephure</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Comparison of conventional and non-invasive techniques for the early identification of diabetic neuropathy in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Diabetes</italic></source><volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>305</fpage>–
<lpage>310</lpage>,
<year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17212597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1399-5448.2006.00208.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The Diabetes Control and Complications Trial Research Group: The effect of intensive treatment of diabetes on the development and progression of long-term complications in insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source><volume>329</volume>:
<fpage>977</fpage>–
<lpage>986</lpage>,
<year>1993</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8366922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJM199309303291401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>UK Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) Group</collab>:
<article-title>Intensive blood-glucose control with sulphonylureas or insulin compared with conventional treatment and risk of complications in patients with type 2 diabetes (UKPDS 33)</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source><volume>352</volume>:
<fpage>837</fpage>–
<lpage>853</lpage>,
<year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcutt</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freshwater</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizisin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Prevention of sensory disorders in diabetic Sprague-Dawley rats by aldose reductase inhibition or treatment with ciliary neurotrophic factor</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetologia</italic></source><volume>47</volume>:
<fpage>718</fpage>–
<lpage>724</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15298349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-004-1354-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yajima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagihashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Correction of protein kinase C activity and macrophage migration in peripheral nerve by pioglitazone, peroxisome proliferator activated-gamma-ligand, in insulin-deficient diabetic rats</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source><volume>104</volume>:
<fpage>491</fpage>–
<lpage>499</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17995925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2007.05050.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obrosova</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabley</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Role of nitrosative stress and peroxynitrite in the pathogenesis of diabetic complications. Emerging new therapeutical strategies</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Med Chem</italic></source><volume>12</volume>:
<fpage>267</fpage>–
<lpage>275</lpage>,
<year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/0929867053363207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2225483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrella</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturges</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernau</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LeCouteur</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizisin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Endoneurial microvascular pathology in feline diabetic neuropathy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Microvasc Res</italic></source><volume>75</volume>:
<fpage>403</fpage>–
<lpage>410</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18207200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mvr.2007.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2413429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bierhaus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haslbeck</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humpert</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liliensiek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehmer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morcos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrassy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiekofer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neundörfer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dierl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tritschler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwaninger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haering</surname><given-names>Hu</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schleicher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawroth</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Loss of pain perception in diabetes is dependent on a receptor of the immunoglobulin superfamily</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Invest</italic></source><volume>114</volume>:
<fpage>1741</fpage>–
<lpage>1751</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15599399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI18058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC535062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brussee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>RAGE and experimental diabetic neuropathy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source><volume>57</volume>:
<fpage>1002</fpage>–
<lpage>1017</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/db07-0339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcutt</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolivalt</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernyhough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Growth factors as therapeutics for diabetic neuropathy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Drug Targets</italic></source><volume>9</volume>:
<fpage>47</fpage>–
<lpage>59</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18220712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/138945008783431727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sima</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Diabetic neuropathy differs in type 1 and type 2 diabetes</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source><volume>1084</volume>:
<fpage>235</fpage>–
<lpage>249</lpage>,
<year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17151305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1196/annals.1372.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brussee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Rescue and regeneration of injured peripheral nerve axons by intrathecal insulin</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscience</italic></source><volume>139</volume>:
<fpage>429</fpage>–
<lpage>449</lpage>,
<year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.11.065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brussee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Remote neurotrophic support of epidermal nerve fibres in experimental diabetes</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetologia</italic></source><volume>49</volume>:
<fpage>1081</fpage>–
<lpage>1088</lpage>,
<year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16528572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-006-0169-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yenush</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The IRS-signaling system: a network of docking proteins that mediate insulin and cytokine action</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</italic></source><volume>228</volume>:
<fpage>179</fpage>–
<lpage>208</lpage>,
<year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9401207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-3-642-80481-6_8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leinninger</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Backus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhler</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase and Akt effectors mediate insulin-like growth factor-I neuroprotection in dorsal root ganglia neurons</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">FASEB J</italic></source><volume>18</volume>:
<fpage>1544</fpage>–
<lpage>1546</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1096/fj.04-1581fje</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reger</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Intranasal insulin administration: a method for dissociating central and peripheral effects of insulin</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Drugs Today (Barc)</italic></source><volume>42</volume>:
<fpage>729</fpage>–
<lpage>739</lpage>,
<year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17171192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1358/dot.2006.42.11.1007675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Delivery of insulin-like growth factor-I to the rat brain and spinal cord along olfactory and trigeminal pathways following intranasal administration</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neuroscience</italic></source><volume>127</volume>:
<fpage>481</fpage>–
<lpage>496</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15262337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2004.05.029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The window of opportunity for treatment of focal cerebral ischemic damage with noninvasive intranasal insulin-like growth factor-I in rats</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</italic></source><volume>13</volume>:
<fpage>16</fpage>–
<lpage>23</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17903945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2004.01.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reger</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cholerton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fishel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plymate</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitner</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeGroodt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Intranasal insulin improves cognition and modulates beta-amyloid in early AD</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source><volume>70</volume>:
<fpage>440</fpage>–
<lpage>448</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/01.WNL.0000265401.62434.36</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>A new and sensitive method for measuring thermal nociception in cutaneous hyperalgesia 630</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Pain</italic></source><volume>32</volume>:
<fpage>77</fpage>–
<lpage>88</lpage>,
<year>1988</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3340425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0304-3959(88)90026-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaplan</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pogrel</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaksh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Quantitative assessment of tactile allodynia in the rat paw</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci Methods</italic></source><volume>53</volume>:
<fpage>55</fpage>–
<lpage>63</lpage>,
<year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7990513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0165-0270(94)90144-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sima</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Expression and localization of insulin receptor in rat dorsal root ganglion and spinal cord</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Peripher Nerv Syst</italic></source><volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>44</fpage>–
<lpage>53</lpage>,
<year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11939351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1529-8027.2002.02005.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotecha</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Insulin as an in vivo growth factor</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Neurol</italic></source><volume>188</volume>:
<fpage>43</fpage>–
<lpage>51</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15191801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.expneurol.2004.03.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernyhough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willars</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Insulin and insulin-like growth factor I enhance regeneration in cultured adult rat sensory neurones</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Brain Res</italic></source><volume>607</volume>:
<fpage>117</fpage>–
<lpage>124</lpage>,
<year>1993</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8481790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0006-8993(93)91496-f</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verge</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Does diabetes target ganglion neurones? Progressive sensory neurone involvement in long-term experimental diabetes</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source><volume>124</volume>:
<fpage>2319</fpage>–
<lpage>2334</lpage>,
<year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/brain/124.11.2319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motoshima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Integration of multiple downstream signals determines the net effect of insulin on MAP kinase vs. PI 3′-kinase activation: potential role of insulin-stimulated H(2)O(2) 7</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Signal</italic></source><volume>16</volume>:
<fpage>323</fpage>–
<lpage>331</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14687662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cellsig.2003.08.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verkhratsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernyhough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Insulin enhances mitochondrial inner membrane potential and increases ATP levels through phosphoinositide 3-kinase in adult sensory neurons</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Neurosci</italic></source><volume>28</volume>:
<fpage>42</fpage>–
<lpage>54</lpage>,
<year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15607940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mcn.2004.08.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcutt</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verkhratsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernyhough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Insulin prevents depolarization of the mitochondrial inner membrane in sensory neurons of type 1 diabetic rats in the presence of sustained hyperglycemia</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source><volume>52</volume>:
<fpage>2129</fpage>–
<lpage>2136</lpage>,
<year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.52.8.2129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernyhough</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verkhratsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Mechanism of mitochondrial dysfunction in diabetic sensory neuropathy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Peripher Nerv Syst</italic></source><volume>8</volume>:
<fpage>227</fpage>–
<lpage>235</lpage>,
<year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14641647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1085-9489.2003.03028.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruss</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lienhard</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cartee</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Increased phosphorylation of Akt substrate of 160 kDa (AS160) in rat skeletal muscle in response to insulin or contractile activity</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source><volume>54</volume>:
<fpage>41</fpage>–
<lpage>50</lpage>,
<year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15616009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.54.1.41</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Requirement for phosphatidylinositol-3 kinase in the prevention of apoptosis by nerve growth factor</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Science</italic></source><volume>267</volume>:
<fpage>2003</fpage>–
<lpage>2006</lpage>,
<year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7701324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.7701324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nürnberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heblich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolphin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>PI3K promotes voltage-dependent calcium channel trafficking to the plasma membrane</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Neurosci</italic></source><volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>939</fpage>–
<lpage>946</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15311280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nn1300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimtula</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mearow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The synergistic effects of NGF and IGF-1 on neurite growth in adult sensory neurons: convergence on the PI 3-kinase signaling pathway</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source><volume>86</volume>:
<fpage>1116</fpage>–
<lpage>1128</lpage>,
<year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12911620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2003.01925.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Opposing extracellular signal-regulated kinase and Akt pathways control Schwann cell myelination</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source><volume>24</volume>:
<fpage>6724</fpage>–
<lpage>6732</lpage>,
<year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15282275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5520-03.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6729716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Axonal regulation of Schwann cell proliferation and survival and the initial events of myelination requires PI 3-kinase activity</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source><volume>20</volume>:
<fpage>4635</fpage>–
<lpage>4645</lpage>,
<year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10844033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-12-04635.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6772460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macica</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>IGF-1 stimulates de novo fatty acid biosynthesis by Schwann cells during myelination</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Glia</italic></source><volume>55</volume>:
<fpage>632</fpage>–
<lpage>641</lpage>,
<year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/glia.20496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quirion</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Insulin-like growth factor-1-induced phosphorylation of transcription factor FKHRL1 is mediated by phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt kinase and role of this pathway in insulin-like growth factor-1-induced survival of cultured hippocampal neurons</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Pharmacol</italic></source><volume>62</volume>:
<fpage>225</fpage>–
<lpage>233</lpage>,
<year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12130673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/mol.62.2.225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muravlev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>During</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dragunow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>CREB phosphorylation promotes nerve cell survival</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source><volume>73</volume>:
<fpage>1836</fpage>–
<lpage>1842</lpage>,
<year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10537041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonze</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginty</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Apoptosis, axonal growth defects, and degeneration of peripheral neurons in mice lacking CREB</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Neuron</italic></source><volume>34</volume>:
<fpage>371</fpage>–
<lpage>385</lpage>,
<year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0896-6273(02)00686-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hetman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavanaugh</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Role of glycogen synthase kinase-3beta in neuronal apoptosis induced by trophic withdrawal</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurosci</italic></source><volume>20</volume>:
<fpage>2567</fpage>–
<lpage>2574</lpage>,
<year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10729337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-07-02567.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6772233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pap</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Role of glycogen synthase kinase-3 in the phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinase/Akt cell survival pathway</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source><volume>273</volume>:
<fpage>19929</fpage>–
<lpage>19932</lpage>,
<year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9685326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.273.32.19929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frame</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The renaissance of GSK3</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</italic></source><volume>2</volume>:
<fpage>769</fpage>–
<lpage>776</lpage>,
<year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35096075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jope</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>CREB DNA binding activity is inhibited by glycogen synthase kinase-3 beta and facilitated by lithium</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source><volume>78</volume>:
<fpage>1219</fpage>–
<lpage>1232</lpage>,
<year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11579131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00495.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1947002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Glucose neurotoxicity</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Neurosci</italic></source><volume>9</volume>:
<fpage>36</fpage>–
<lpage>45</lpage>,
<year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrn2294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zochodne</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Experimental diabetic neuropathy with spontaneous recovery: is there irreparable damage?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Diabetes</italic></source><volume>54</volume>:
<fpage>830</fpage>–
<lpage>837</lpage>,
<year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.54.3.830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>