
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2957445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2957445.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2957445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2957445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20976071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PONE-RA-18207R2</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Ecology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Ecology/Conservation and Restoration Ecology</subject><subject>Ecology/Environmental Microbiology</subject><subject>Ecology/Evolutionary Ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Evolutionary Ecology</subject><subject>Microbiology/Environmental Microbiology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Bacterial Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Natural Cross Chlamydial Infection between Livestock and Free-Living Bird Species</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Cross Chlamydial Infection</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemus</surname><given-names initials="JA">Jesús A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fargallo</surname><given-names initials="JA">Juan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names initials="P">Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parejo</surname><given-names initials="D">Deseada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banda</surname><given-names initials="E">Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Ecología Evolutiva, Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales (CSIC), Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>School of Biological Sciences, Aberdeen Centre for Environmental Sustainability (ACES), University of Aberdeen, Aberdeen, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Departmento de Ecología Funcional y Evolutiva, Estación Experimental de Zonas Áridas (CSIC), Almería, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Oficina de Especies Migratorias, Ministerio de Medio Ambiente y Medio Rural y Marino, Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Häcker</surname><given-names initials="G">Georg</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Technical University Munich, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jlemus@ebd.csic.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JAL JAF PV DP EB. Performed the experiments: JAL JAF PV DP EB. Analyzed the data: JAL JAF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JAL JAF. Wrote the paper: JAL JAF PV DP EB.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">190416</issue-id><elocation-id>e13512</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Lemus et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0013512.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC3466096"><article-title>Retraction: Natural Cross Chlamydial Infection between Livestock and Free-Living Bird Species</article-title><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><date><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><elocation-id>10.1371/annotation/9b33ec1f-9579-41c0-bede-3a38ee6af21c</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3466096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23056164</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The study of cross-species pathogen transmission is essential to understanding the epizootiology and epidemiology of infectious diseases. Avian chlamydiosis is a zoonotic disease whose effects have been mainly investigated in humans, poultry and pet birds. It has been suggested that wild bird species play an important role as reservoirs for this disease. During a comparative health status survey in common (<italic toggle="yes">Falco tinnunculus</italic>) and lesser (<italic toggle="yes">Falco naumanni</italic>) kestrel populations in Spain, acute gammapathies were detected. We investigated whether gammapathies were associated with <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> infections. We recorded the prevalence of different <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species in nestlings of both kestrel species in three different study areas. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I (or <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic>), an ovine pathogen causing late-term abortions, was isolated from all the nestlings of both kestrel species in one of the three studied areas, a location with extensive ovine livestock enzootic of this atypical bacteria and where gammapathies were recorded. Serovar and genetic cluster analysis of the kestrel isolates from this area showed serovars A and C and the genetic cluster 1 and were different than those isolated from the other two areas. The serovar I in this area was also isolated from sheep abortions, sheep faeces, sheep stable dust, nest dust of both kestrel species, carrion beetles (<italic toggle="yes">Silphidae</italic>) and Orthoptera. This fact was not observed in other areas. In addition, we found kestrels to be infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic>, the first time these have been detected in birds. Our study evidences a pathogen transmission from ruminants to birds, highlighting the importance of this potential and unexplored mechanism of infection in an ecological context. On the other hand, it is reported a pathogen transmission from livestock to wildlife, revealing new and scarcely investigated anthropogenic threats for wild and endangered species.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cross-species infection is a major cause of emerging infectious diseases <xref rid="pone.0013512-Parrish1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>-<xref rid="pone.0013512-Davidson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The economic influence of the animal industry has promoted many investigations regarding the potential of wildlife as a reservoir of cattle and poultry diseases <xref rid="pone.0013512-Frolich1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. On the contrary, little is known about the role of domestic species as infectious agents causing diseases in wildlife <xref rid="pone.0013512-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-HernandezDivers1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p><p>Avian chlamydiosis is a well-known human disease caused by the bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0013512-Everett1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Zweifel1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> and contracted from poultry and wild birds, although pet bird (mainly parrots) are still considered the primary cause <xref rid="pone.0013512-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. In the wild, isolates have been reported from more than 460 avian species <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> as well as from some mammals, such as hares and muskrats <xref rid="pone.0013512-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Spalatin1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. In birds it is often systemic and infections can be unapparent, severe, acute or chronic with intermittent shedding <xref rid="pone.0013512-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (also identified as <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I) is an abortogenic pathogen in ruminants rarely found in birds <xref rid="pone.0013512-Chahota1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Factors leading to different degrees of symptomatology of this disease may be both internal, such as immune capacity, and external, such as stress <xref rid="pone.0013512-Cray1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Zwart1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Indeed, adults more often have non-symptomatic infections while young birds frequently have acute disease, probably because adults are able to develop a better immunity response than young birds <xref rid="pone.0013512-Cray1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Schettler1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Additionally, stress will commonly trigger the onset of severe symptoms, resulting in rapid deterioration and death <xref rid="pone.0013512-Andersen2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-OIE1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.</p><p>Death outbreaks due to chlamydiosis can be found in wild bird species and are presumed to be due to infection with a strain uncommon to the host or due to secondary infections <xref rid="pone.0013512-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Chlamydiosis has been reported to be transferred by translocation of birds of prey, to spread during falconry bird flight or to spread across countries by migratory species <xref rid="pone.0013512-Forbes1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schettler2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. It has also been noted that colonially nesting birds are more likely to spread disease during reproduction than solitary breeders <xref rid="pone.0013512-Burkhart1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Grimes1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>Chlamydiosis transmission from mammals to birds has been scarcely investigated, even with the knowledge that parenterally inoculated, polyarthritis-producing chlamydiae of ovine origin affected the leg joints of turkeys, and abortion-producing chlamydiae of ovine origin was infectious for pigeons and fatal for sparrows. Also, several species of small wild birds when inoculated perorally with <italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> of turkey origin, seroconverted (36%) and shed the organism (79%) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In this same review, authors also indicated that their aim was to determine whether strains of <italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> from domesticated ruminants would infect, multiply in, or be shed by these wild birds, indicating whether or not these species of birds are natural hosts or biologic vectors of these strains. However, considering the heterogeneity of the chlamydial species, certain birds may harbour strains that are associated with naturally occurring infections in some animals. The results are also additional evidence of the more restricted host range of mammalian <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia</italic> species when compared with avian isolates.</p><p>In this article we present the results of an episode of clinical chlamydiosis in common kestrels (<italic toggle="yes">Falco tinnunculus</italic>) and lesser kestrels (<italic toggle="yes">F. naumanni</italic>). During a study about kestrel health status <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vergara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, most of the birds in a given area showed a marked gammapathy in the protein electrophoresis pattern. We explored the origin of this abnormality. Gammapathies are well-documented as specific clinical laboratory tools for the study of several infections, including <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0013512-Cray1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Tatum1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. We show the results of serology, PCR studies and the serovar and genetic clusters of the isolated <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> samples, and we explore the possibility of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> cross-species transmission. Additionally, other chlamydial species such as <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> were tested in spite of the fact that they have not shown to be of major interest in veterinary medicine or as cross-species transmission pathogens. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic> is a rodent pathogen, especially of laboratory mice and hamsters, causing respiratory disease. No records have been published about its incidence in wild rodents or birds. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic>, on the other hand, is a swine pathogen that causes important economic losses in intensive swine production due to digestive disease, and is extremely resistant to most antibiotics. There is no report about its incidence in extensive swine or in birds.</p><p>There is some controversy in Chlamydiaceae taxonomy <xref rid="pone.0013512-Everett1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Everett2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schiller1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, and especially in the <italic toggle="yes">psittaci</italic> serovars involved in livestock diseases <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schiller1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. We followed the taxonomy proposed by Schiller et al (2004) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schiller1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>Protein electrophoresis showed that both kestrel species from LL showed higher levels of γ-globulins than kestrels from CA and LM, being this difference statistically significant (GLMM, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
<sub>2,65</sub> = 47.73, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Lesser kestrels showed higher values than common kestrels (GLMM, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
<sub>1,65</sub> = 15.47,<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). This was due to the between-species difference found in LL while no between-species differences were found in CA and LM. This resulted in a significant species x area interaction (GLMM, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
<sub>2,65</sub> = 23.89, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g003">Figure 3</xref> the protein electrophoresis profiles in LL kestrels are represented showing a standard profile and the detected gammapathies.</p><fig id="pone-0013512-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Between-area differences in kestrel gammaglobulin levels.</title><p>Differences in gammaglobulin levels (percentage of total proteins) between the three study areas for both Eurasian and Lesser kestrels. Interaction between species and study area is statistically significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0013512-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Gammaglobulin levels in infected and uninfected kestrels.</title><p>Differences in gammaglobulin levels (percentage of total proteins) between kestrels uninfected and infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I). The interaction between infection and species is statistically significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.g002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0013512-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Protein electrophoretic pattern.</title><p>A) Protein electrophoretic profile showing a typical gammapathy found in kestrel individuals infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I). B) Normal kestrel protein electrophoretic profile.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> serovar I) was the most prevalent of the three species found in kestrel populations (12.6%), followed by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> (5.7%) with the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic> the lowest (3.8%). All individuals infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> were also infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic>, while none of the individuals infected by <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> were found to be infected by any other <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species. In order to explore gammapathies associated with a given <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species we excluded from the analyses individuals infected with the other two species, thus comparing infected vs. uninfected individuals. Gammapathies in kestrels were found to be associated with <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> serovar I) infection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t001">Table 1</xref>), showing significantly higher levels of immunoglobulins in blood in infected compared to uninfected individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). The model also showed significant differences between kestrel species and significant infection x species interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0013512-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Similar results were found for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> infection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t001">Table 1</xref>). However, note that all of these individuals were also infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic>, for which reason we could not separate the effect of both Chlamydiaceae species. Gammapathies in kestrels were not found to be associated with <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0013512-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Effects of kestrel species and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> infection on immunoglobulin levels.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0013512-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">d.f.</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection * species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection * species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.877</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection * species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Results of general linear mixed models (GLMM) in which immunoglobulin levels are included as a response variable and infection (infected vs. uninfected) and kestrel species are fixed factors. Between-factor interaction is also shown.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Serology analyses showed that all nestlings from LL had <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C.p</italic>.) antibodies, while only a small proportion of kestrels from LM and none from CA had these antibodies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t002">Table 2</xref>). Between-area differences were significant for both common (GENMOD, χ<sup>2</sup> = 51.18, <italic toggle="yes">d.f.</italic> = 2, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) and lesser (GENMOD, χ<sup>2</sup> = 44.46, <italic toggle="yes">d.f.</italic> = 2, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) kestrels. No other antibodies were found during the serology evaluation. Due to the results obtained from the samples, we prepared a serovar and cluster double blind study in order to establish the <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> origin.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0013512-t002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0013512-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Falco tinnunculus</italic>
</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Falco naumanni</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">LM</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">LL</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">CA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n = 6</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">LM (n = 28</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">LL</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 13)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> antibody serology</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25% (2)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (17)c</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1% (2)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (13)b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> PCR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3% (5)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5% (3)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (17)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (2)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25% (7)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (13)b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real time <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> PCR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3% (5)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5% (3)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% (17)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (2)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25% (7)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%(13)b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7% (11)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 % (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.5% (8)b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> MLST</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7% (11)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 % (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.5% (8)b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia muridarum</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3% (1)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7% (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 % (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3% (6)b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (0)ac</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 % (0)a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0% (3)bc</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species and strains isolated from both kestrel species in different areas. Prevalence is expressed as percentage of infected individuals. Numbers in brackets represent infected individuals. Different letters indicate between-area significant differences as resulted from between-group contrasts in GENMOD procedure.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>First, we performed a classical <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> PCR <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> and real time PCRs. Both PCRs showed the same result, <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> being identified in all individuals from LL, while only a small proportion of kestrels showed <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> in the other two areas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t002">Table 2</xref>). The difference was significant for both kestrel species (GENMOD, both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001)</p><p>We found that a proportion of kestrels from LL, but no kestrels from the other two areas had antibodies for <italic toggle="yes">C. abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> serovar I) and <italic toggle="yes">C. suis</italic>. The between-area differences were significant for <italic toggle="yes">C. abortus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. suis</italic> in both kestrel species (GENMOD, all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.017), while no between-area differences were found in <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> in any of the kestrel species (GENMOD, both <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.43). MLST analysis showed the same results observed with PCRs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>Serovar characterization indicated that both kestrel species from LL showed positive tests for serovars A and C of <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic>, while kestrels from CA and LM were positive for serovars F and G (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0013512-t003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci filiation.</italic>
</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0013512-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Falco tinnunculus</italic>
</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Falco naumanni</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campo Azálvaro (CA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Monegros (LM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Llanos (LL)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campo Azálvaro (CA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Monegros (LM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Llanos (LL)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Serovar</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Clusters</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> filiation based in serovars and genetic clusters (ordered following avian phylogenetic origin) of the different kestrel isolates from the three sampled locations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Genetic cluster analyses for <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> indicated that kestrel samples from LL were located mainly in cluster I with few samples belonging to cluster III. Lesser kestrels from CA and LM populations mainly “showed clusters” of type II and few of type I and III. Finally, common kestrels from CA and LM populations only showed clusters of type II and III (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>In LL, <italic toggle="yes">C. abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> serovar I) was found in all the possible sources explored: sheep abortions, sheep faeces, sheep stable dust, nest dust of both kestrel species, carrion beetles (<italic toggle="yes">Silphidae</italic>) and Orthoptera (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t004">Table 4</xref>). In LM, it was found in lower proportions in sheep stable dust. <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> was also found in low proportion in samples of stable dust, lesser kestrel nest dust and Orthoptera. In CA, kestrels breed in nest boxes and old buildings, for which reason only Orthoptera invertebrates were checked. We did not find <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> in these prey species from this locality.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0013512-t004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013512.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Presence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> in kestrel environment.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0013512-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0013512.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Los Llanos (LL)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Campo Azálvaro (CA)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Los Monegros (LM)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C psittaci</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C abortus (C psittaci serovar I)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C psittaci</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C abortus (C psittaci serovar I)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C psittaci</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C abortus (C psittaci serovar I)</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sheep abortions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sheep faeces (Facilities)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sheep stable dust (Facilities)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian kestrel nest dust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lesser kestrel nest dust</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carrion beetles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grasshoppers/locust/crickets</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Presence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> serovar I) in different potential sources of infection for kestrel species.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>a No sheep presence in the area.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>b Nests in nest-boxes.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>c Nest material was not collected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Exploring the health status of common and lesser kestrel populations from three different locations we detected gammapathies in individuals of both species in one of the locations (LL). This gammapathy was found to be associated with infections of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> serovar I). In this same area a <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> outbreak was observed in sheep, sheep facilities and also in insects, suggesting a cross <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> infection between livestock and wild insect and bird species.</p><p>Chlamydiosis diagnosis is difficult, because there are many false negatives due to the absence of immunological reaction. In our case, common and lesser kestrel nestlings from LL showed a response to infection in protein electrophoresis and serology that was not observed in kestrels from the other two areas. Within the LL area, lesser kestrels showed stronger gammapathies (higher percentage of immunoglobulins) than common kestrels. Between-species differences can be promoted by differences in diet, as lesser kestrels are more insectivorous, thus more prone to ingesting carrion beetles and Orthoptera carrying <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> serovar I. Furthermore, lesser kestrels tend to use sheep stables as breeding sites in a higher proportion than common kestrels, hence being more exposed to inhaling <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> fomites, such as dust.</p><p>In this study we have tried all diagnostic procedures with the exception of culture. Detection by PCR only isolates genetic material, not pathogens, but allows the detection of Chlamydiaceae exposure. When combining Chlamydiaceae with the determination of pathogen antibodies we can clearly detect those individuals that are clinically infected.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> is ubiquitous and causes many different diseases and prognoses in birds, and is more aggressive in nestlings <xref rid="pone.0013512-Gerlach1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. In a previous paper we showed that those kestrels from LL were in poorer condition when compared to CA and LM individuals <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vergara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>Serovar characterization and genetic clusters indicate zone differentiation in the serovars affecting kestrels. While LL typical serovars are A and C of <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic>, kestrels from CA and LM were positive for serovars F and G (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t003">Table 3</xref>), the serovars typical of raptors <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Few wildlife studies have described <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> clusters. Our study also indicates this zone differentiation in <italic toggle="yes">C.p.</italic> clusters. Isolates from LL were located mainly in cluster I with few samples belonging to cluster III. Lesser kestrel isolates from CA and LM populations were mainly clustered in type II and few of the type I and III. Finally, common kestrels from CA and LM populations only showed clusters of type II and III. Together, these results indicate the origin of all isolates and permit the linkage of isolates to their original host. With the exception of the ruminant-hosted <italic toggle="yes">C.p</italic>. serovar I, the remaining <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> isolated from kestrels were avian-hosted <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic>. Serovar A (found in LL) is naturally hosted by psittacines, columbids and several corvids <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, while serovar C is naturally hosted by storks <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Raptors are not natural hosts for either serovar. On the contrary, kestrels from CA and LM were infected with typical F or G serovars that are only susceptible to disease in case of immunological disruption, since these serovars are considered to be moderately pathogenic in their natural hosts <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.</p><p>Enzootic abortion (the denomination of <italic toggle="yes">C.p</italic>. serovar I in sheep) is endemic in Spanish locations, including the Extremadura region where the <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> outbreak was found <xref rid="pone.0013512-Martin1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Abortions and mothers remain uncontrolled in the field with no assistance. We have identified potential infectious agents that can act through the two known <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> transmission routes: ingestion and inhalation. Invertebrates can be infected by direct consumption of sheep abortions, carcasses and faeces. Apart from these routes, vertebrates, as in the case of kestrels, can also be infected through the ingestion of infected insects. The presence of <italic toggle="yes">C. p.</italic> in dust from sheep facilities (also in kestrel nests) suggests that both vertebrates and invertebrates can contract the disease through inhalation in the surroundings of sheep stables. Measures including 1) vaccination <xref rid="pone.0013512-Anonymous1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> of all the sheep at risk or in enzootic areas and 2) increasing the frequency of health controls should be mandatory to minimize the risk of transmission to wildlife. To our knowledge this is the first study in which <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> is detected in livestock remains and in the environment. This isolation reflects the infective potential of this pathogen and the environmental dependence of prophylactic measures in order to avoid cross-species transmission. It is important to be aware of the potential of zoonotic transmission of <italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> from poultry to men <xref rid="pone.0013512-Verminnen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Verminnen2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, and also the zoonotic potential to pregnant women <xref rid="pone.0013512-Thomson1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.</p><p>Similarly, <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> have never been recorded in birds. They typically appear in swine and rodents, respectively <xref rid="pone.0013512-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. In principle, this suggests two more cases of cross-species pathogen transmission found in this study, which would be expected to provoke a conspicuous immune reaction. However, we have only actually detected the genetic material of these two species, because no antibody reactions have occurred in the serology panel. This was observed in the case of <italic toggle="yes">C. suis</italic>. However, due to the fact that individuals infected by <italic toggle="yes">C. suis</italic> were infected by <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> as well, we could not disentangle its true effect on immunoglobulin levels. In the case of <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> we did not detect gammapathies in infected individuals. The paucity of knowledge about <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> pathology in wildlife makes it difficult to explain this lack of immunological reaction. One possibility is that we are only measuring one component of the immune system, and that other immunological branches, such as a cell-mediated immune response, could be acting without our detection. A second possibility is that <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> could be a common pathogen in kestrels, as they usually prey on rodents. In this sense, our study highlights the interest of investigating this aspect in future studies.</p><p>The lesser kestrel is considered as a “Vulnerable” species throughout its range (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link>, 25). Farmlands and grasslands are the most common habitats for this species <xref rid="pone.0013512-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Extremadura possesses up to 25% of the lesser kestrel Spanish population and its numbers have shown a positive trend over the last several years <xref rid="pone.0013512-Atienza1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. The common kestrel, on the other hand, is the most common diurnal raptor species in Spain, however with negative population trends in Europe <xref rid="pone.0013512-Tucker1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The changes in land-use practices (agricultural intensification and pesticide use) and direct persecution have traditionally been the causes proposed to explain population declines in both kestrel species <xref rid="pone.0013512-Atienza1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Rodrguez1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. However, other problems more subtle to identify, such as infectious disease episodes, call into question the conservation efforts, especially those devoted to the lesser kestrel. Epizooties can operate in wild species causing population declines at a local scale <xref rid="pone.0013512-Franson1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Pennycott1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Wildlife populations are immunologically prepared for many of the pathogens in the environment, but changes in the serovars usually imply mortality episodes <xref rid="pone.0013512-Davidson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Frolich1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-HernandezDivers1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Our study emphasizes the necessity of wildlife veterinary controls as useful tools for conservation plans and detection of risks in wild species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Samples examined</title><p>We tested for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> in a total of 91 common (n = 44) and lesser (n = 47) kestrel nests present in three study areas located in Los Llanos (Cáceres province, 39° 28′ N, 6° 22′ W), Campo Azálvaro (Segovia province, 40° 40′ N, 4° 20′ W) and Los Monegros (Zaragoza province, 41° 20′ N, 0° 11′ W). The three locations are subjected to high extensive livestock pressure, with extensive ovine livestock in Los Llanos (LL) and Los Monegros (LM) and extensive bovine livestock in Campo Azálvaro (CA); see Vergara et al. (2008) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vergara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> for more study area characteristics. Ovine livestock receive no veterinary interference except legal controls in LL, and receive some veterinary assistance and prophylactic treatments in LM. Sample size for each kestrel species and area is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0013512-t002">Table 2</xref>. One chick per nest in each kestrel species was randomly selected for blood samples.</p><p>All the nestlings were sampled at about three weeks old. One ml of blood was taken from the brachial vein, centrifuged and the pellet was separated from plasma and both were frozen until analyses.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Protein electrophoresis</title><p>As a part of the health status design, protein electrophoresis was performed in all checked specimens. Plasma protein electrophoresis fractions were run on commercial agarose gels (Hydragel Protein (E), Sebia Hispania S.A., Barcelona, Spain) using a semi-automated Hydrasys System (Sebia Hispania S.A., Barcelona, Spain) with manufacturer's reagents to determine the concentration of albumin and globulins (α, β and γ-globulins) in percent, that were used in the analyses. Total plasma proteins were determined by the Biuret method <xref rid="pone.0013512-Lumeij1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Total plasma protein concentrations (g/dl), which were also used in the analyses, were calculated by the multiplication of each protein fraction with the total protein value.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serology</title><p>A serology panel that included <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serology was performed using plasma samples. A whole blood-plate agglutination test was used to detect the <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> antigen presence Difco (TM) <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> O Group B Antigen (1-4-5-13) (Becton Dickinson and Company, Maryland, USA). The test was conducted by using the manufacturer's standard instructions <xref rid="pone.0013512-Sack1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> antibodies were determined by using Rida-Screen antibody ELISA (R-Biopharm, Darmstadt, Germany)</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> PCR, real time PCR and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I) PCR</title><p>Blood PCRs were performed following Hewinson et al, 1997, for conventional PCR for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic>, Sachse et al, 2009, for real time PCR <italic toggle="yes">for Chlamydophila psittaci</italic>, and Laroucau et al, 2001 were used to <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> conventional PCR <xref rid="pone.0013512-Hewinson1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0013512-Laroucau1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. We have considered <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> serovar I as <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic>, following Kaleta &amp; Taday (2003) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Kaleta1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> and Schiller et al. (2004) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schiller1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. This technique has been demonstrated to be successful when showing pathogen exposure in common and lesser kestrels <xref rid="pone.0013512-Alcaide1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>.</p><p>Due to the presence of extensive livestock in the area, and the occurrence of enzootic chlamydial abortion, we also performed a chlamydial serovar characterization to establish the serovar involved in the epizootic episode. In addition, we also obtained the genetic cluster of the same isolates according to Chahota et al, 2006 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Chahota1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. We explored the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia</italic> species, <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis and Chlamydia muridarum.</italic> For <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia suis</italic> we used the specification of Laroucau et al, 2001, and Robertson et al, 2009 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Laroucau1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Robertson1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> whilst for <italic toggle="yes">C. muridarum</italic> we used the specifications of Pantchev et al and Robertson et al, 2009 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Robertson1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Pantchev1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Serovar characterization</title><p>For serovar characterization the isolates were either grown directly in Buffalo green monkey (BGM) cells or in 6-day-old specific pathogen-free embryonated chicken eggs as is indicated in Vanrompay et al, 1993 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The six serovar- specific MAbs were designated VS-1 (serovar A specific; psittacine group), CP3 (serovar B specific; pigeon I group), GR-9 (serovar C specific; duck group), NJ-1 (serovar D specific; turkey group), MP (serovar E specific; pigeon II group), NJ-1D3 (serovar F) and serovar G <xref rid="pone.0013512-Sudler1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. The microimmunofluorescence test was also performed following Vanrompay et al. (1993) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> genetic diversity</title><p>Genetic diversity and epizootiology of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> was based on the VD2 region of the <italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic> gene. DNA was extracted, a nested PCR was performed followed by cloning of the PCR product and sequencing <xref rid="pone.0013512-Chahota1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The sequence analyses were performed following Chahota et al. (2006) <xref rid="pone.0013512-Chahota1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p>We also tested for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> type I in sheep abortions, sheep faeces, sheep stable dust, kestrel nest dust, necrophilous beetles and orthoptera (grasshoppers, locusts, crickets) in the study areas. Beetles and orthoptera are common prey species of common and lesser kestrels in Spain <xref rid="pone.0013512-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0013512-Aparicio1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Arthropods were collected close to nests (50 m away from carcasses in the case of beetles and 200 m away from nests in the case of orthoptera), and were euthanized by congelation.</p><p>Sheep abortion samples were processed following Schiller et al, 2004 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Schiller1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, whilst sheep faeces and dust preparation was performed following Tanaka et al, 2005 <xref rid="pone.0013512-Tanaka1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, and arthropods were prepared by homogenization <xref rid="pone.0013512-Taft1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> MLST analysis</title><p>Because of the difficulty to discriminate between <italic toggle="yes">C. psittaci</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. abortus</italic> and not possible on the basis of the major outer membrane protein A, we additionally carried out a. MLST analyses as described by Pannekoek et al.(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmlst.org/chlamydiales">http://www.pubmlst.org/chlamydiales</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Statistical procedures</title><p>Nestlings share genes and environments within the nest for which reason these cannot be considered independent samples. We attempted to analyse between-location and between-species differences in nestling infection (infected vs. uninfected) by using Generalized Mixed Models, in which the nest was included as a random factor and species as a fixed factor. This procedure avoids pseudoreplication considering the nestling as the sampling unit. Due to the fact that some chlamydial isolates where absent in some locations our data were unbalanced and most of the models did not converge. For this reason we randomly selected one nestling from each nest and analysed frequencies of infection in different locations and species by using GENMOD procedure with logit link function and binomial distribution in SAS statistical software (SAS 9.0, 2002, Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Differences in protein electrophoresis between kestrel species and populations were analysed using General Linear Mixed Models with GLMM procedure in. The percentage of γ-globulins was arcsine transformed. Nest was included in the model as a random factor and location and species as fixed factors.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Our study followed ethical guidelines proposed for the Spanish Royal Decree 1205/2005 about the protection of animals used in experiments and scientific research and was approved by the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (CGL2007-61395/BOS).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>L. de Neve, J.I. Aguirre, A. Gajón, P. Laiolo, J.C. Núñez and M. Kauffman helped in the field. Regional Governments from Extremadura, Castilla y León and Aragón provided the necessary licenses for sampling kestrels. Sarah Young revised the English.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>The Spanish Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación (Project CGL2007-61395/BOS) financed the study. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0013512-Parrish1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morens</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Cross species transmission and the emergence of new epidemic diseases.</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MMBR.00004-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2546865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Daszak1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daszak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Wildlife ecology - Emerging infectious diseases of wildlife - Threats to biodiversity and human health.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>287</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10642539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.287.5452.443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Davidson1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Creation of diversity in the animal virus world by inter-species and intra-species recombinations: lessons learned from poultry viruses.</article-title><source>Virus Genes</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17922180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11262-007-0165-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Frolich1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frolich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiede</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozikowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakob</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A review of mutual transmission of important infectious diseases between livestock and wildlife in Europe.</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>9489</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2002.tb04343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Weiss1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Cross-species infections.</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12934941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-3-642-55541-1_3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-HernandezDivers1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Divers</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villegas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Divers</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Backyard chicken flocks pose a disease risk for neotropic birds in Costa Rica.</article-title><source>Avian Dis</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19166045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1637/8298-032808-Reg.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Everett1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>The ribosomal intergenic spacer and domain I of the 23S rRNA gene are phylogenetic markers for <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia</italic> spp.</article-title><source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9103637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/00207713-47-2-461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Everett2"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Emended description of the order Chlamydiales, proposal of <italic toggle="yes">Parachlamydiaceae</italic> fam. nov. and <italic toggle="yes">Simkaniaceae</italic> fam. nov., each containing one monotypic genus, revised taxonomy of the family <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic>, including a new genus and five new species, and standards for the identification of organisms.</article-title><source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10319462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/00207713-49-2-415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Kaleta1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaleta</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taday</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Avian host range of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> spp. based on isolation, antigen detection and serology.</article-title><source>Avian Pathol</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14522700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03079450310001593613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Zweifel1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zweifel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pospischil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bore</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> in wild birds—potential risk for domestic poultry, pet birds, and public health?</article-title><source>Eur J of Wildl Res</source><comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10344-009-0275-2">10.1007/s10344-009-0275-2</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Smith1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stobierski</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tengelsen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Compendium of measures to control <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> (formerly <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia psittaci</italic>) infection among humans (psittacosis) and pet birds.</article-title><source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source><volume>226</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15742693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.2005.226.532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Andersen1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Avian Chlamydiosis.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Infectious Diseases of Wild Birds</source><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Spalatin1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spalatin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1966</year><article-title>Agents of psittacosis-lymphogranuloma venereum group isolated from muskrats and snowshoe hares in Saskatchewan.</article-title><source>Can J Comp Med Vet Sci</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4226345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1494580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Chahota1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chahota</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsuhashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Genetic diversity and epizootiology of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> prevalent among the captive and feral avian species based on VD2 region of ompA gene.</article-title><source>Microbiol Immunol</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16985288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1348-0421.2006.tb03839.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Cray1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatum</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Applications of protein electrophoresis in avian diagnostics.</article-title><source>J Avian Med Surg</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Zwart1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Bacterial Diseases.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samour</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Avian Medicine</source><publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>264</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Schettler1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schettler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langgemach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Streich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frolich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Seroepizootiology of selected infectious disease agents in free-living birds of prey in Germany.</article-title><source>J Wildl Dis</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11272489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7589/0090-3558-37.1.145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Andersen2"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanrompay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Avian chlamydiosis.</article-title><source>OIE Rev Sci Tech</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10935270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-OIE1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>OIE (Office International des Epizooties)</collab><year>2000</year><article-title>Avian chlamydiosis.</article-title><comment>Manual of standards for diagnostic test and vaccines 1312000. Office International des epizooties, Paris, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oie.int/eng/normes/mmanual/A">http://www.oie.int/eng/normes/mmanual/A</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Forbes1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Caryospora neofalconis</italic>: An emerging threat to captive bred raptors in the United Kingdom.</article-title><source>J Avian Med Surg</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Schettler2"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schettler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Streich</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Newcastle disease virus and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia psittaci</italic> in free-living raptors from eastern Germany.</article-title><source>J Wildl Dis</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12685068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7589/0090-3558-39.1.57</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Burkhart1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>Chlamydiosis (ornithosis-psittacosis).</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karstad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trainer</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name></person-group><source>Infectious and parasitic diseases of wild birds</source><publisher-loc>Ames</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Iowa State University Press</publisher-name><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>140</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Brand1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Chlamydial infections in free-living birds.</article-title><source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source><volume>195</volume><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2689407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Grimes1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Avian chlamydiosis.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beran</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Handbook of zoonoses</source><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>402</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Vergara1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fargallo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parejo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemus</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Low frequency of anti-acetylcholinesterase pesticide poisoning in lesser and Eurasian kestrels of Spanish grassland and farmland populations.</article-title><source>Biol Conserv</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Tatum1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatum</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mealey</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossart</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Protein electrophoresis as a diagnostic and prognostic tool in raptor medicine.</article-title><source>J Zoo Wildl Med</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11428396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1638/1042-7260(2000)031[0497:PEAADA]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Vanrompay1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanrompay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducatelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haesebrouk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Serotyping of European Isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia psittaci</italic> from Poultry and Other Birds.</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8417017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jcm.31.1.134-137.1993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC262635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Schiller1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schifferli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gysling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pospischil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Growth characteristics of porcine chlamydial strains in different cell culture systems and comparison with ovine and avian chlamydial strains.</article-title><source>Vet J</source><volume>168</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15158211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1090-0233(03)00039-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Gerlach1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Chlamydia.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Avian medicine</source><publisher-loc>Florida</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wingers</publisher-name><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>996</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Martin1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Diseases of sheep.</article-title><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Scientific Publications</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Anonymous1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anonymous</surname></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Aborto enzoótico de las ovejas (clamidiosis ovina).</article-title><source>Manual de la OIE para Animales Terrestres.</source><publisher-name>OIE</publisher-name><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>689</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Verminnen1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verminnen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanrompay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> infections in turkeys: overview of economic and zoonotic importance and vaccine development.</article-title><source>Drugs Today (Barc)</source><volume>45</volume><issue>Suppl B</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20011707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Droogenbroeck1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Droogenbroeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beeckman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verminnen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nauwynck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Simultaneous zoonotic transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> genotypes D, F and E/B to a veterinary scientist.</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18963600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2008.09.047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Verminnen2"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verminnen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duquenne</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Keukeleire</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannekoek</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Evaluation of a <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> infection diagnostic platform for zoonotic risk assessment.</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18003799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JCM.01153-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2224303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Thomson1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila abortus</italic> genome sequence reveals an array of variable proteins that contribute to interspecies variation.</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15837807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.3684805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1088291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Cramp1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>KEL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>The Birds of the Western Palearctic.</article-title><volume>Vol. 2</volume><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press </publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Atienza1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tella</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Cernícalo Primilla, <italic toggle="yes">Falco naumanni.</italic>
</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madroño</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atienza</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Libro Rojo de las Aves de España</source><publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Dirección General para la Biodiversidad-SEO/BirdLife</publisher-name><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Tucker1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Birds in Europe: Their conservation status.</article-title><source>Cambrigde: BirdLife Conservation Series N°</source><volume>3</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Bustamante1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Predictive models for lesser kestrel <italic toggle="yes">Falco naumanni</italic> distribution, abundance and extinction in southern Spain.</article-title><source>Biol Conserv</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Rodrguez1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>How do crop types influence breeding success in lesser kestrels through prey quality and availability? A modeling approach.</article-title><source>J Appl Ecol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>597</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Franson1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Probable epizootic chlamydiosis in wild California (<italic toggle="yes">Larus californicus</italic>) and ring-billed (<italic toggle="yes">Larus delawarensis</italic>) gulls in North Dakota.</article-title><source>J Wild Dis</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7589/0090-3558-31.3.424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8592370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Herrman1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Josensen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psittaci</italic> in Fulmars, the Faroe Islands.</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3201/eid1202.050404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3373105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Pennycott1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennycott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagleish</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila psttaci</italic> in wild birds from the UK.</article-title><source>Vet Rec</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/vr.164.5.157-b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Lumeij1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumeij</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Total protein determination in pigeon plasma and serum: comparison of refractometric methods with the Biuret method.</article-title><source>J Avian Med Surg</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Sack1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Serologic test for the diagnosis of enterobacterial infections.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Manual of Clinical Laboratory Inmunology, 3rd ed</source><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Hewinson1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewinson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia psittaci</italic> DNA in avian clinical samples by polymerase chain reaction.</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9057259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0378-1135(96)01268-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Sachse1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vretou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pospischil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Recent developments in the laboratory diagnosis of chlamydial infections.</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18986778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2008.09.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Laroucau1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroucau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souriau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodolakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Improved sensivity of PCR for Chlamydia using pmp genes.</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11423206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0378-1135(01)00381-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Alcaide1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcaide</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemus</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tella</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>MHC diversity and differential exposure to pathogens in kestrels (Aves: Falconidae).</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04507.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Robertson1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belfiore</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydiaceae</italic> species using PCR and high resolution melt curve analysis of the 16S rRNA gen.</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol Epub</source><volume>May 20</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2009.04388.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19583801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Pantchev1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantchev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sting</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauerfeind</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyczka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Detection of all <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydophila</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia</italic> spp of veterinary interest using species-specific real-time PCR assays.</article-title><source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis</source><comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cimid.2009.08.002">10.1016/j.cimid.2009.08.002</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cimid.2009.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19733907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Sudler1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoelzle</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoop</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Molecular characterization of chlamydial isolates from birds.</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15036532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2003.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Aparicio1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Differences in the diets of resident and non-resident Kestrels in Spain.</article-title><source>Ornis Fenn</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Tanaka1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watarai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishiquro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Bacteriological survey of faeces of feral pigeons in Japan.</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16210811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1292/jvms.67.951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0013512-Taft1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taft</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Distribution of borreliae among ticks collected from eastern states.</article-title><source>Vect Borne Zoon Dis</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/vbz.2005.5.383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16417434</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>