
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gastroenterology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0374630</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gastroenterology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0016-5085</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1528-0012</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2677121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2677121.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2677121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2677121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS95190</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19208366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2009.01.069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS95190</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA95190</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Up-regulation of anterior cingulate cortex NR2B receptors contributes to visceral pain responses in rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names initials="J">Jing</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoyin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhijun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="S">Shengliang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Owyang</surname><given-names initials="C">Chung</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="A1">Gastroenterology Research Unit, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Ying Li, MD, Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology, University of Michigan, Medical Sciences Research Building I, Room 6510, 1150 West Medical Center Drive, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, E-mail: <email>yli@umich.edu</email>, Phone: 734-647-5980, Fax: 734-763-2535</corresp><fn id="FN3" fn-type="current-aff"><p>Z.C. and S.C. are currently with the Department of Gastroenterology, Renji Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiaotong University, China.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>136</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">178546</issue-id><fpage>1732</fpage><lpage>1740.e3</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>17</day><month>02</month><year>2009</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>05</day><month>05</month><year>2009</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-05 21:25:13.220"><day>05</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms95190.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" vol="166" page="548" journal-id="Gastroenterology" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="38206267"><article-title>Retraction notice to "Up-Regulation of Anterior Cingulate Cortex NR2B Receptors Contributes to Visceral Pain Responses in Rats" Gastroenterology 2009;136:1732-1740.e3.</article-title><date><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><source>Gastroenterology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38206267</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Background &amp; Aims</title><p id="P2">Electrophysiological and behavioral studies have demonstrated that increased <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor activation of anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) neurons has a critical role in modulating visceral pain responses in viscerally hypersensitive (VH) rats. This study aimed to identify the NMDA receptor subtypes in perigenual ACC (pACC) neurons involved in the facilitation of visceral nociception.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P3">We performed in vivo electrophysiological recordings of pACC neurons and examined the visceromotor response (VMR) to colorectal distention (CRD) in normal and VH rats induced by colonic anaphylaxis. The NR2A subtype receptor antagonist NVP-AAM077 and the NR2B receptor antagonist Ro25-6981 were microinjected into the pACC. To downregulate NR2B receptor gene expression, an NR2B-specific small interfering RNA (siRNA) and a plasmid (pEGFP-N1) that expressed the green fluorescent protein were administered into ACC neurons by electroporation.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P4">Reverse microdialysis of NVP-AAM077 had no effect on basal and CRD-induced ACC neuronal firing in VH and control groups. In VH rats, Ro25-6981 (500 μM) inhibited ACC neuronal firing, evoked by 30 and 50 mmHg CRD, by 98%, and 52%, respectively. NVP-AAM077 did not affect the VMR in either group. Ro25-6981 significantly suppressed the VMR in VH but not normal rats. Immunoblot analysis showed increased NR2B receptor expression in the pACC of VH rats. NR2B siRNA-treated VH rats showed a significant reduction in the VMR, compared to controls.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P5">The NR2B subunit of the NMDA receptor has a critical role in the modulation of ACC sensitization and visceral pain responses in VH rats.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S5"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P6">Human brain imaging studies have revealed new roles of cortical neuronal networks in chronic visceral pain.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref> Experiments in animals demonstrate that the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) receives nociceptive inputs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref> and suggest that ACC neuronal activity is related to stimulus–reward learning.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref> Electrophysiological studies in our laboratories have demonstrated that ACC sensitization occurs in viscerally hypersensitive (VH) rats.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref> Allodynia and hyperalgesia in these rats appear to be mediated by enhanced glutamate <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor activities in the ACC.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> Hypersensitivity to colonic distention can be observed up to 7 weeks after the initiation of colonic anaphylaxis and is independent of mucosal inflammation. This suggests mediation by a mechanism for learning and triggering of pain memories in the ACC neuronal circuitry. Nociceptive transmission in the ACC is mediated by glutamate α-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-isoxazole propionic acid (AMPA) receptors in normal circumstances. In VH rats, the synaptic transmission in ACC neurons is enhanced. This enhancement is mediated mainly by NMDA receptor activation,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref> indicating neuronal plasticity in the ACC circuitry in the VH state.</p><p id="P7">NMDA receptors contain heteromeric combinations of the NR1 subunit plus one or more of the subunits NR2A–2D. Whereas NR1 is distributed widely in the brain, NR2 subunits exhibit regional specificities. In humans and rodents, subunits NR2A and NR2B predominate in forebrain structures.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref> In the ACC, the NMDA receptor containing NR2A or NR2B subunits contributes to most NMDA receptor currents.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref> Mice that genetically overexpress the NR2B receptor subtype in the forebrain show enhanced responsiveness to painful stimuli<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref> and superior learning ability and memory of different behavioral tasks.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref> Considering the distinct roles that NMDA receptors may serve, identification of the receptor subtype in the ACC that mediates visceral hypersensitivity will promote our understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying nociceptive processes in the VH state.</p><p id="P8">We hypothesize that ACC sensitization and visceral hyperalgesia in our VH rat model may be mediated by changes in the expression and the function of NMDA receptor subtypes in ACC neurons. To test this hypothesis, we used VH rats to characterize the electrophysiological properties of neurons of the perigenual ACC (pACC; i.e., areas 24b, 24a, and 32)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref> that are activated by colorectal distention (CRD). Single neuronal recording of pACC neurons was combined with reverse microdialysis of NR2A and NR2B subtype-selective NMDA receptor antagonists NVP-AAM077 and Ro25-6981 to identify which receptor subtypes mediate visceral hypersensitivity. The selectivity of these two antagonists has been established in vitro.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> Visceromotor response (VMR) studies were conducted in parallel to examine the antinociceptive effects of subtype-selective NMDA receptor antagonists. Finally, to down-regulate the gene expression of the NR2B subtype of the NMDA receptor, NR2B-specific small interfering RNA (siRNA) was administered into the pACC neurons of VH rats by electroporation. Our results suggest that activation of ACC NR2B-containing NMDA receptors may be involved in ACC sensitization and hyperalgesia in the VH state.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S6"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p id="P9">Experimental procedures were approved by the University Committee on Use and Care of Animals at the University of Michigan. Experiments were performed on adult male Sprague-Dawley rats (275–300 g). The animals were housed 4 per plastic cage and maintained on a 12:12 h light:dark cycle (lights on at 7 AM) and given access to food and water ad libitum. For surgical preparations, rats were anesthetized with a mixture of xylazine and ketamine.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></p><sec id="S7"><title>Viscerally hypersensitive (VH) rat model</title><p id="P10">The rats were sensitized to chicken egg albumin (EA) with an intraperitoneal injection of normal saline (1 mL) containing EA (10 mg) as the antigen and aluminum hydroxide (10 mg) as the adjuvant. Beginning on day 3, the antigen solution was perfused into the colon and CRD was performed 30 min after EA instillation. VMR studies were conducted 5–7 days after the induction of colonic anaphylaxis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Electrophysiological recording of pACC neuronal activity in response to CRD in control and VH rats</title><p id="P11">Three cytoarchitectural regions of the cingulate cortex have been identified in rats: the ACC with perigenual and subgenual parts, midcingulate cortex, and retrosplenial cortex.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref> A similar classification has been applied to the rabbit.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref> In the present study, neurons were recorded in the perigenual ACC (pACC) using glass microelectrodes (tip diameters, 0.08 μm and impedance of 20–40 MΩ) at the following coordinates: 2.0–3.8 mm anterior to bregma, 0.5–1.0 mm lateral to midline, 2.5 mm ventral to the brain surface. These areas correspond to perigenual 24b and portions of perigenual 24a and area 32. The recording electrode was advanced until the spontaneous activity of a single unit could be accurately discriminated from the background neuronal noise. The recording had uniform spike amplitude and could be maximized and separated from neighboring neurons. Noise levels were typically 40–50 μV. We analyzed only well-isolated neurons that showed a signal-to-noise ratio of at least 4:1.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref> A neuron was deemed responsive to CRD if its spike firing rate increased or decreased at least 10% from its predistention baseline activity. Neuronal discharge rates were measured 30 s before, 30 s during, and 120 s after CRD, with 5-min intervals between each measurement, and evaluated on a time histogram (5 s bin width). On completion of the experiment, recorded neurons were labeled by injecting neurobiotin using the technique of juxtacellular iontophoresis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> Brain sections were incubated with peroxidase-conjugated avidin–biotin complex (ABC, 1:100; Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA). Thionine was used as a counterstain.</p><p id="P12">Data on spontaneous firings in various experimental groups were evaluated using the Dunnett T3 multiple comparisons method after 1-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Statistical comparisons of the CRD-pressure responses in various groups were made using the 1-way repeated measures ANOVA, followed by multiple comparisons adjusted by the Bonferroni test. Results were expressed as means ± SEM. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Studies of antagonists of NMDA receptor subtypes</title><p id="P13">The NR2A-selective antagonist [(<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>)-[(<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>)-1-(4-bromo-phenyl)-ethylamino]-(2,3-dioxo-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoxalin-5-yl)-methyl]-phosphonic acid<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref> (NVP-AAM077, Novartis, Basel, Switzerland) or the NR2B-selective antagonist Ro25-6981<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref> (Tocris Bioscience, Ellisville, MO) were infused into the pACC using reverse microdialysis. One dose of antagonist was applied to each CRD-excited neuron.</p><p id="P14">Reverse microdialysis was performed as described previously.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref> Briefly, microdialysis probes with 3–4 mm of exposed membrane were implanted into the pACC at the following coordinates: 2.0–3.8 mm anterior to bregma, 0.5–1.0 mm lateral to midline; and lowered about 4.0 mm at a 30-degree angle. Glass microelectrodes filled with neurobiotin were lowered into the pACC about 1 mm lateral or rostral to the probe and angled at 10 degrees toward the probe.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> Investigators have reported serial measurements of drug concentrations in tissue after microdialysis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref> In our study, drugs were dissolved in artificial cerebrospinal fluid (ACSF) at a concentration 100 times that predicted to be necessary according to data from in vitro studies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref> ACSF containing NVP-AAM077 or Ro25-6981 (50, 100, and 500 μmol/L) was perfused. The doses were chosen in accordance with the results of previous brain slice recordings in which NVP-AAM077 or Ro25-6981 at a concentration of 0.4–3.0 μmol/L blocked cingulate NMDA excitatory postsynaptic currents<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref> and cingulate long-term potentiation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref> Electrophysiological recordings were performed as described above.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Visceromotor response to CRD</title><p id="P15">Details of this protocol have been described previously.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref> Briefly, 32-gauge stainless steel wires were implanted in the external oblique pelvic muscles 4–6 days before the beginning of the experimental procedures. Graded-pressure CRD (20, 40, and 60 mm Hg) was produced by rapidly injecting saline into a colonic balloon over 1 s and maintaining the distention for 20 s. The results of electromyography were quantified by calculating the area under the curve (AUC). Statistical comparisons of the VMR in various groups were made using 1-way repeated measures ANOVA, followed by multiple comparisons adjusted by the Bonferroni test using baseline values as a covariate and two main factors (i.e., distention level as the repeated factor and group as the independent factor).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Chronic ACC cannulation</title><p id="P16">pACC cannulation was performed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> using the following coordinates: AP +4.0 to +2.0 mm from bregma, DV −2.5 mm, L +0.7 mm. The VMR experiments were performed 6 days postoperatively. The location of the point of termination of the cannula track was determined by histological studies. Serial coronal sections (50 μm) were cut with a cryostat along the path of the cannula, mounted on gelatin-coated slides, and stained with thionine.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Glutamate antagonist studies</title><p id="P17">After establishing a stable VMR induced by graded-pressure CRD, the NR2B antagonist Ro25-6981<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> or the NR2A antagonist NVP-AAM077<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref> were microinjected into the pACC. A total volume of 60 nL per hemisphere were administered. A similar volume of vehicle (saline) was administered into the pACC as a control. The 1 mmol/L and 10 mmol/L doses of Ro25-6981 and NVP-AAM077 were chosen in accordance with doses used in previous behavioral studies, which showed that microinjection of similar doses of NR2A and NR2B receptor antagonists into the perirhinal cortex or the ACC impaired long-term recognition memory and reduced mechanical allodynia, respectively.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref> Each rat served as its own control. Vehicle and a single drug were tested on each day. Two doses (1 mmol/L and 10 mmol/L) of Ro25-6981 or NVP-AAM077 were infused randomly into the pACC at 2-h intervals, by which time the VMR had returned to its preinjection level, as demonstrated in the pilot study.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Microelectroporation of siRNA</title><p id="P18">To inhibit NR2B expression specifically in the pACC, siRNA against NR2B with a reporter plasmid encoding EGFP was delivered bilaterally by microelectroporation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref> Green fluorescent protein (GFP) expression was used as a novel genetic reporter system. For the detailed procedures of electroporation, tissue acquisition, and Western blot analysis, please refer to the <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Document</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S14"><title>Results</title><sec id="S15"><title>Effects of NMDA receptor antagonists on pACC neuronal activation evoked by CRD in normal and VH rats</title><p id="P19">A total of 25 control rats and 69 neurons were examined for their responses to CRD (50 mm Hg). Spontaneous activity was sufficiently stable to permit recording for 45–70 min. Among the 69 neurons, 18 neurons (26%) exhibited an excitatory response characterized by increased spike firing from baseline (7.0 ± 0.5 to 16.0 ± 1.0 impulses/10 s). These 18 neurons were referred to as CRD-excited neurons. Seven of 69 neurons were inhibited by 50 mm Hg CRD; their spontaneous activity was reduced to 0.35 ± 0.05 impulses/10 s. All 18 CRD-excited neurons were examined for the effects of the two glutamate antagonists on pACC neuronal responses to CRD. One dose of antagonist was applied to each CRD-excited pACC neuron. Microdialysis of vehicle (ACSF, 2 μL/min) had no effect on pACC neuronal firing. Application of NR2A receptor antagonist NVP-AAM077 or NR2B receptor antagonist Ro25-6981 at concentrations of 100 μmol/L and 500 μmol/L did not change spontaneous firing. Intra-pACC administration of either receptor antagonist also had no effect on 50 mm Hg CRD-evoked pACC neuronal responses (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p><p id="P20">In a separate study, 94 neurons from 31 VH rats were evaluated. Of these 94 neurons, 36 neurons (38%) were excited by 50 mm Hg CRD. This represents an increase in the numbers of CRD-excited pACC neurons in VH rats as compared with normal rats (38% vs 26%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). pACC spike firing in response to 50 mm Hg CRD increased from a basal level of 18.5 ± 2.0 to 42 ± 4.5 impulses/10 s (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>) suggesting an increase in pACC neuronal excitability in VH rats. Microdialysis of NR2A receptor antagonist NVP-AAM077 at concentrations of 100 μmol/L and 500 μmol/L did not change pACC neuronal spontaneous firing and had no effect on 30 mm Hg and 50 mm Hg CRD-evoked pACC neuronal responses (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). In contrast, microdialysis of the NR2B receptor antagonist Ro25-6981 at concentrations of 100 μmol/L and 500 μmol/L significantly decreased basal pACC neuronal firing from 21.0 ± 4.5 to 15.5 ± 3.0 and 10.5 ± 1.5 impulses 10/s, respectively (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Further, Ro25-6981 at concentrations of 100 μmol/L and 500 μmol/L produced 84% and 98% inhibition of 30 mm Hg CRD-induced neuronal firing, and 14% and 52% inhibition of 50 mm Hg CRD-induced neuronal firing (6 neurons in the normal group and 9 neurons in the EA group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Administration of Ro25-6981 at 2.0 mmol/L did not cause further inhibition of basal and CRD-induced pACC neuronal firing (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Examples of original tracings are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and 2<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>. Histological localization of the CRD-responsive neurons showed that the recording electrodes were successfully placed in all of the CRD-exited neurons of normal and EA rats. Several examples of neurobiotin-labeled neurons are presented in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, 2<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, and 2<italic toggle="yes">E</italic></xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Effects of NMDA receptor antagonists on the VMR to CRD in normal and VH rats</title><p id="P21">Both control and EA rats showed pressure-dependent increases in the VMR to CRD. These responses were significantly enhanced in EA rats. Graded CRD pressures of 20, 40, and 60 mm Hg caused an increase in the number of muscle contractions to 1 ± 0.02, 20 ± 4, and 31 ± 3 contractions/5 s, respectively, in normal rats, and to 24 ± 4, 41 ± 3, and 50 ± 5 contractions/5 s in EA rats. The mean amplitude of the electromyogram (area under the curve [AUC], μV/s) is shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. These results are consistent with enhanced visceral pain responses (i.e., hyperalgesia) in EA rats.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></p><p id="P22">The specific NR2A subunit antagonist NVP-AAM077 and the specific NR2B subunit antagonist Ro25-6981 were microinjected into the pACC. A total of 12 normal rats and 13 EA rats were studied. Histological studies confirmed the accuracy of the microinjection sites in all but 2 normal rats and 1 EA rat. Hence, VMR data from 10 normal rats and 12 EA rats were analyzed. Several examples of the pACC injection sites are shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. Microinjection of either NVP-AAM077 (1 and 10 mmol/L) or Ro25-6981 (1 and 10 mmol/L)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref> into the pACC (areas 24b, 24a, and 32) did not change the VMR to graded-pressure CRD in normal rats (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). These results suggest that the pACC neuronal network is not involved in the mediation of visceral pain responses in normal rats, confirming our previous investigations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref> In EA rats, NVP-AAM077 had no effect on the VMR (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>), whereas Ro25-6981 dose-dependently decreased the VMR to CRD (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>). In response to graded CRD pressures of 20, 40, and 60 mm Hg, Ro25-6981 (1 mmol/L) reduced the number of muscle contractions from 25 ± 3, 43 ± 2, and 57 ± 6 contractions/5 s to 15 ± 2, 32 ± 4, and 46 ± 3 contractions/5 s, respectively, representing 40%, 26%, and 20% inhibition. Ro25-6981 at a dose of 10 mmol/L produced 52%, 30%, and 22% inhibition (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic></xref> &lt; 0.05). Application of 100 mmol/L Ro25-6981 did not produce additional inhibition. Bilateral microinjections of vehicle control (saline) did not significantly affect the VMR. These observations suggest that NMDA NR2B receptor activities in the pACC are responsible for allodynia and hyperalgesia in VH rats.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Expression of NR2B and NR2A receptors in normal and EA rats</title><p id="P23">The up-regulation of NR2B receptor protein was verified by Western blot analysis. Compared to control rats, the level of NR2B expression in the pACC was significantly increased in VH rats at 10 days after the induction of visceral hypersensitivity. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows an example of a Western immunoblot using polyclonal antibodies against the NR1, NR2A, and NR2B subunits of the NMDA receptors. Quantitative densitometry of the immunoblot bands for NR2B in EA rats was significantly increased to 169 ± 10% of the control (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, n = 5 for each group, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The increase in NR2B expression was time dependent. The increased expression was maintained at 4 weeks after colonic anaphylaxis, but at 6 weeks the NR2B protein level was similar to that in saline-injected rats (data not shown). On the other hand, no significant increases in NR1 and NR2A protein expression were observed at 10 days (n = 4) after the induction of visceral hypersensitivity (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). These findings suggest that changes in NMDA receptors are selective for NR2B subunits in the pACC. The up-regulation of NMDA NR2B receptor expression is consistent with the hypothesis that the enhanced NR2B subunit of NMDA receptor activation mediates ACC neuronal sensitization and visceral hyperalgesia in VH rats. In this study, we did not specifically determine whether up-regulation of NR2B receptors occurred in some or all layers of the pACC of VH rats.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Effects of NR2B siRNA on the CRD-evoked VMRs in normal and VH rats</title><p id="P24">Western blots were performed to confirm the effectiveness, specificity, and time course of RNA interference (RNAi)-induced gene silencing by electroporation of NR2B siRNA (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Immunohistochemistry showed GFP expression and a lack of NR2B expression in the pACC after NR2B siRNA administration (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, 7<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Examples of electroporation sites in 3 rats are shown in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, 7<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, and 7<italic toggle="yes">E</italic></xref>. Guided by the data from the Western blot analysis and the recovery time of the animals, VMRs to graded-pressure CRD were measured 4 days after electroporation. Results were obtained from 6 normal rats and 6 VH rats. In VH rats, electroporation of NR2B-specific siRNA into the pACC significantly decreased the VMR to 20, 40, and 60 mm Hg CRD from 24 ± 3, 43 ± 5, and 58 ± 4 contractions/5 s in the control siRNA group to 10 ± 1, 25 ± 4, and 40 ± 3 contractions/5 s in NR2B siRNA-injected rats. The mean amplitudes expressed as AUC are shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>. Administration of NR2B siRNA produced a 58%, 42%, and 31% inhibition of VMR to 20, 40, and 60 mm Hg CRD, respectively. However, pACC electroporation of NR2B siRNA in normal rats had no significant effect on the VMR to all CRD pressures. Considered together, this suggests that activation of NR2B in the pACC plays a critical role in the mediation of visceral hyperalgesia in VH rats.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S19"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P25">In this study, we demonstrated the up-regulation of ACC NR2B-containing NMDA receptors in VH rats. The increase in NR2B receptor expression in the pACC contributes to enhanced responses of pACC neurons to CRD. Blocking NR2A receptors with NVP-AAM077 did not affect the background activity or the CRD-induced response in either normal or VH rats. Further, reverse microdialysis of the NR2B antagonist Ro25-6981 had no effect on basal or stimulated pACC neuronal firing in normal rats. In VH rats, however, Ro25-6981 significantly inhibited the enhanced background activity and abolished the pACC response to CRD. Thus, in VH rats, synaptic transmission in the pACC neurons was enhanced, and this enhancement was mediated mainly by activation of NR2B subtypes of NMDA receptors.</p><p id="P26">NMDA receptors undergo plastic changes in physiological or pathological conditions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref> The changes in NMDA receptor subunit composition may also have consequences for activity-dependent plasticity. Previous research has shown that transgenic overexpression of NMDA NR2B receptors in the forebrain increases behavioral responses to persistent inflammatory pain.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref> In the current study, we demonstrated that in the VH rat model, colonic anaphylaxis leads to up-regulation of NR2B receptors in the pACC region. Western blot analysis showed that the level of NR2B expression in the pACC was significantly increased at 10 and 20 days after induction of visceral hypersensitivity. The increase in NR2B expression was time dependent and unit specific. The increase in NR2B protein level was maintained up to 4 wk and returned to basal level at 6 wk after the induction of visceral hypersensitivity. We did not see any significant increases in NR1 and NR2A at 10 and 20 days after induction of visceral hypersensitivity. Furthermore, there were no significant increases in NR2B expression in the hippocampus of the same animals (data not shown).</p><p id="P27">How does the increase in NR2B receptors in the pACC influence neuronal activity? NR1 is reportedly synthesized in considerable excess (estimated to be 10-fold) compared with NR2, as one pool of NR1 was not assembled with NR2 and showed rapid degradation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref> In our study, we observed the selective up-regulation of NR2B but not NR1 in VH rats. It is conceivable that the up-regulated NR2B can form functional NMDA receptors with the excessive amount of NR1. Moreover, NR2B overexpression may affect NMDA receptor internalization and stability in the synapses of pACC neurons.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></p><p id="P28">Our behavioral studies using the NR2B receptor antagonist Ro25-6981 showed that local inhibition of NR2B in the pACC (areas 24b, 24a, and 32)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref> produced a significant reduction in allodynia and hyperalgesia in VH rats. The concentrations of drugs used in this study were higher than the IC50 value for inhibition of NR2B-containing receptors. This is a general technical problem in microinjection studies because the local concentration and diffusion of drugs are difficult to quantify.</p><p id="P29">Our pharmacological observations were further confirmed with studies to silence the gene expression of NR2B. In experimental vertebrate models, RNAi has been successfully applied to target gene expression in organ systems such as liver, spleen, kidney, lung, and pancreas via systemic delivery.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref> In this study, to down-regulate the gene expression of NR2B in VH rats, we administered NR2B-specific siRNA and plasmid pEGFP-N1 carrying the GFP gene into the pACC by electroporation. The success in knocking down the target genes was validated by Western blot analysis. NR2B siRNA-treated rats showed a mean 72% reduction in the VMR to graded-pressure CRD in the VH rats compared to control.</p><p id="P30">Our observations suggest a role for the NR2B subunit of the NMDA receptor in neuropathological visceral pain processes and support the notion that the NR2B receptor is an important molecular target for therapeutic agents in the treatment of visceral pain. Ro25-6981 is an ifenprodil derivative and both ifenprodil and Ro25-6981 show selective interaction with the NR2B subunit.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref> Compared to ifenprodil, Ro25-6981 possesses greatly improved selectivity and affinity towards the NR2B subunit of the NMDA receptor and shows relatively low affinity to δ1-adrenergic as well as serotonergic binding sites.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref> Moreover, Ro25-6981 is more than 5000-fold more selective for the heteromeric NR1/NR2B receptors than the NR1/NR2A receptors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref> Analysis of the distribution of [<sup>3</sup>H]Ro25-6981 binding in the central nervous system shows a restricted localization pattern similar to that of the NR2B subunit.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref> Although these receptors are functional on spinal dorsal horn neurons, there are indications that supraspinal structures may be involved in ifenprodil-induced anti-nociception.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref> Our studies further support the therapeutic potential of NR2B receptor antagonists such as Ro25-6981 in treating disorders involving visceral hypersensitivity.</p><p id="P31">We conclude that up-regulation and activation of ACC NR2B-containing NMDA receptors play a critical role in ACC sensitization and mediate hyperalgesia in the viscerally hypersensitive state.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S20"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>01</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS95190-supplement-01.doc" id="N0x1ca9080N0x2a6ef30" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="S21" sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures</title><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Spike firing rates of CRD-excited pACC neurons during infusion of NR2A or NR2B specific antagonists in normal and VH rats</title><p>Results were collected from 6 and 9 CRD-excited pACC neurons per group in normal and VH rats, respectively. 50 mm Hg CRD but not 30 mm Hg CRD evoked an excitatory response. pACC neurons of EA rats had high spontaneous activities. There were marked increases in response to 30 mm Hg CRD- and 50 mm Hg CRD-evoked pACC neuronal responses in EA rats. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>)</bold> Application of NR2A antagonist NVP-AAM077 at a dose of 500 μmol/L had no effect on either basal (CRD 0 mm Hg) or CRD-evoked pACC neuronal activity in both normal and EA rats. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>)</bold> Administration of NR2B antagonist Ro25-6981 at doses of 100 μmol/L and 500 μmol/L had no effect on either basal or CRD-evoked pACC neuronal activity in normal rats. In contrast, Ro25-6981 dose-dependently (100 μmol/L, 500 μmol/L, and 2 mmol/L) decreased basal pACC neuronal firing and suppressed or abolished CRD-evoked pACC spike firing in EA rats. These observations suggest that NR2B subtypes of NMDA glutamate receptors are responsible for the mediation of pACC neuronal activities evoked by noxious visceral stimulation in VH rats. Data are presented as means ± SEM. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with 0 mm Hg CRD in (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and compared with EA-vehicle in (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f1.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Recording of CRD-excited pACC neurons during infusion of NR2A or NR2B antagonists in VH rats</title><p>Colorectal distention (50 mm Hg) markedly increased pACC neuronal firing during microdialysis of vehicle (artificial cerebrospinal fluid) in VH rats. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>)</bold> Microdialysis of NR2A antagonist NVP-AAM077 (500 μmol/L) did not change basal or CRD-evoked pACC neuronal firing. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>)</bold> Application of NR2B receptor antagonist Ro25-6981 (500 μmol/L) significantly decreased basal pACC neuronal activities and suppressed CRD-induced pACC neuronal responses. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>,)</bold> Microphotograph of neurons in the pACC labeled by neurobiotin. Thionine-stained coronal sections show the laminar distribution of neurons located in layer II/III. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></bold>′<bold>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>′, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>′)</bold> Higher magnification of neurobiotin-labeled pACC neurons. Scale bars: C, D, E, 250 μm; C′, D′ E′, 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f2.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effects of bilateral injection of selective NMDA NR2B or NR2A receptor antagonists into the pACC on the VMR induced by graded-pressure CRD in normal and VH rats</title><p>Results were obtained from 10 normal rats and 12 EA rats. Mean amplitude of the abdominal muscle contraction is expressed as the area under the curve (AUC) after baseline subtraction. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>)</bold> Summary of data is expressed as AUC after vehicle or NR2B antagonist Ro25-6981 were microinjected bilaterally into the pACC. Infusion of Ro25-6981 at a higher dose of 10 mmol/L had no effect on the VMR to CRD in normal rats; however, it produced marked decreases in the VMR to 20, 40, and 60 mm Hg CRD in EA rats. Injection of a lower dose of Ro25-6981 (1 mmol/L) into the <underline>pACC</underline> also produced significant decreases in the number of muscle contractions in EA rats. The response was dose dependent. Data are presented as means ± SEM. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with EA-vehicle. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>)</bold> Administration of NR2A receptor antagonist NVP-AAM077 (10 mmol/L) did not change the numbers of spontaneous muscle contractions in either normal or EA rats. Data are presented as means ± SEM. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with normal vehicle-treated rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f3.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Microphotographs of thionine-stained coronal sections show injection sites in the pACC of 1 normal rat (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and 2 VH rats (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>)</title><p>Scale bars: 250 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f4.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Expression of NR2A and NR2B subtypes of NMDA receptors in the pACC of normal and VH rats</title><p><bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>)</bold> Representative immunoblots from the pACC show the expression of NMDA receptor subunits NR1, NR2A, NR2B, and actin, with an indication of size (kilodaltons, kDa). One control lane is shown along with a lane from EA rats. Western blot showed that the expression level of NR2B, but not NR1 or NR2A, was significantly increased in the pACC of EA rats 10 days after the induction of visceral hypersensitivity <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>)</bold> Relative intensity of NMDA receptors protein from immunoblots was measured by densitometric analysis. Quantification of protein expression in the pACC of EA rats expressed as the percentage of controls. Each column represents the means ± SEM (n = 3–5 rats for each group). *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, significantly different from control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f5.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Western blot analysis of pACC protein homogenates from animals receiving bilateral microinfusion of control siRNA or NR2B-siRNA</title><p><bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>)</bold> Representative lanes from each group are shown. pACC proteins were separated using sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS–PAGE) and transferred to a membrane. The membrane was probed sequentially with antibodies to NR2B. Treatment with NR2B-siRNA resulted in a significant reduction in NR2B protein level, while there was no change in protein level of the nontargeted NR2B. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>)</bold> Quantification of protein expression in the pACC with NR2B siRNA microinfusion expressed as the percentage of controls. Each column represent means ± SEM (n = 3/condition). **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, significantly different from control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f6.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>GFP and NR2B immunoreactivity in pACC neurons 3 days after electroporation</title><p><bold>(<italic toggle="yes">Aa</italic>)</bold> Coronal section showing GFP-expressing neurons 3 days after electroporation. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic>)</bold> Higher magnification illustrates GFP expression of the inset in <bold><italic toggle="yes">Aa</italic></bold>. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">Ac</italic>)</bold> With TUNEL costaining, few cells underwent apoptosis in the targeted pACC. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bb</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bc</italic>)</bold> Microinfusion of a mixture of control siRNA and pEGFP-N1 vector. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">Bd</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Be</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bf</italic>)</bold> Microinfusion of a mixture of pEGFP-N1 vector and NR2B-specific siRNA. <bold><italic toggle="yes">Ba</italic></bold> and <bold><italic toggle="yes">Bd</italic></bold> show expression of GFP staining in pACC neurons in both control and siRNA-treated groups. <bold><italic toggle="yes">Bb</italic></bold> shows immunoreactivity for NB2B receptor in control rats. <bold><italic toggle="yes">Be</italic></bold> shows lack of NR2B expression in pACC neurons after treatment with NR2B-siRNA. <bold><italic toggle="yes">Bc</italic></bold> pACC neurons expressing both GFP and NR2B (arrows) appear yellow in the merged image. <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>)</bold> Microphotographs of thionine-stained coronal sections show electroporation sites in 3 rats. Scale bars: <bold><italic toggle="yes">Aa</italic></bold>, 100 μm; <bold><italic toggle="yes">Ab</italic></bold> and <bold><italic toggle="yes">Ac</italic></bold>, 10 μm; <bold><italic toggle="yes">Ba–f</italic></bold>, 20 μm; <bold><italic toggle="yes">C</italic></bold>, <bold><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></bold>, <bold><italic toggle="yes">E</italic></bold>, 250 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f7.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Effects of bilateral injection of NR2B-specific siRNA into the pACC on the VMR induced by graded-pressure CRD in normal and VH rats</title><p><bold>(<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>)</bold> Original electromyograms show that microinjection of NR2B-specific siRNA (1 μg/μL) into the pACC of a normal rat (upper panel) did not change the number of muscle contractions in response to CRD. In the VH rat (lower panel), infusion of NR2B-specific siRNA (1 μg/μL) into the pACC produced significant decreases in response to all CRD pressures (20, 40, 60 mm Hg). <bold>(<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>)</bold> Summary of data is expressed as the AUC of the VMR in response to CRD. Results were obtained from 15 normal rats and 16 EA rats. NR2B siRNA-injection had no effect on the VMR in normal rats. In the pACC of NR2B siRNA-injected EA rats, significant inhibition of VMR compared with control siRNA-injected EA rats was observed. Data are presented as means ± SEM *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with control siRNA-injected EA rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms95190f8.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec><ack id="S22"><p>Grant Support</p><p>Supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke Grant RO1 NS051466-01 (YL) and NIH Grant P30-DK-34933 (CO).</p></ack><glossary id="GL"><title>Abbreviations</title><glossary content-type="gloss-group"><def-list><def-item><term id="G1">ACC</term><def><p>anterior cingulate cortex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">AUC</term><def><p>area under the curve</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">CRD</term><def><p>colorectal distention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">EA</term><def><p>egg albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">GFP</term><def><p>green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">NMDA</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methyl-D-aspartate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">NVP-AAM077</term><def><p>[(<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>)-[(<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>)-1-(4-bromo-phenyl)-ethylamino]-(2,3-dioxo-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoxalin-5-yl)-methyl]-phosphonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">pACC</term><def><p>perigenual ACC</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">RNAi</term><def><p>RNA interference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">siRNA</term><def><p>small interfering RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">VH</term><def><p>viscerally hypersensitive</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12">VMR</term><def><p>visceromotor response</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></glossary><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naliboff</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroimaging of the brain–gut axis: from basic understanding to treatment of functional GI disorders</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2006</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1925</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2006.10.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cingulate cortex and disease models</article-title><source>The rat nervous system</source><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press</publisher-name><year>2003</year><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>727</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and properties of visceral nociceptive neurons in rabbit cingulate cortex</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>2008</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18022321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pain.2007.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2649778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikes</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nociceptive neurons in area 24 of rabbit cingulate cortex</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1720</fpage><lpage>1732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1479441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/jn.1992.68.5.1720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The affective component of pain in rodents: direct evidence for a contribution of the anterior cingulate cortex</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>8077</fpage><lpage>8082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11416168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.141218998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC35470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owyang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced response of the anterior cingulate cortex to colonic distension in viscerally hypersensitive rats</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>570</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16239277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1113/jphysiol.2005.096073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1464293</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="36942712"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anterior cingulate cortex modulates visceral pain as measured by visceromotor responses in viscerally hypersensitive rats</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.11.057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role for NMDA receptors in visceral nociceptive transmission in the anterior cingulate cortex of viscerally hypersensitive rats</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>G918</fpage><lpage>G927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpgi.00452.2007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnashev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developmental and regional expression in the rat brain and functional properties of four NMDA receptors</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1994</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7512349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0896-6273(94)90210-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Roles of NMDA NR2B subtype receptor in prefrontal long-term potentiation and contextual fear memory</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2005</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.08.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerchner</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic enhancement of inflammatory pain by forebrain NR2B overexpression</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/83993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic enhancement of learning and memory in mice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10485705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/43432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabarean</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A specific role for NR2A-containing NMDA receptors in the maintenance of parvalbumin and GAD67 immunoreactivity in cultured interneurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4722-05.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6675509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trube</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ro-25-6981, a highly potent and selective blocker of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methyl-D-aspartate receptors containing the NR2B subunit. Characterisation in vitro</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1997</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><lpage>1292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9400004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auberson</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allgeier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>5-Phosphonomethylquinoxalinediones as competitive NMDA receptor antagonists with a preference for the human 1A/2A, rather than 1A/2B receptor composition</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem Lett</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0960-894x(02)00074-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct examination of local regulation of membrane activity in striatal and prefrontal cortical neurons in vivo using simultaneous intracellular recording and microdialysis</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>2002</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/jpet.301.3.867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative microdialysis</article-title><source>Microdialysis in the neurosciences</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>1991</year><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingledine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The glutamate receptor ion channels</article-title><source>Pharmacol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10049997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological isolation of postsynaptic currents mediated by NR2A- and NR2B-containing NMDA receptors in the anterior cingulate cortex</article-title><source>Molecular Pain</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17470281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1744-8069-3-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1871573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Roles of NMDA NR2B subtype receptor in prefrontal long-term potentiation and contextual fear memory</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2005</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.08.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subdiaphragmatic vagal afferent nerves modulate visceral pain</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>1441</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpgi.00588.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3222235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Upregulation of forebrain NMDA NR2B receptors contributes to behavioral sensitization after inflammation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>11107</fpage><lpage>11116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1678-05.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6725642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gareth</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The different effects on recognition memory of perirhinal kainate and NMDA glutamate receptor antagonism: implications for underlying plasticity mechanisms</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>3561</fpage><lpage>3566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16571764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3154-05.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6673858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Calmodulin regulates synaptic plasticity in the anterior cingulate cortex and behavioral responses: a microelectroporation study in adult rodents</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>8402</fpage><lpage>8409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12968002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.23-23-08402.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6740679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roldan</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changing subunit composition of heteromeric NMDA receptors during development of rat cortex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/368144a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenthold</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Turnover analysis of glutamate receptors identifies a rapidly degraded pool of the <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunit, NR1, in cultured cerebellar granule cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9867823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.274.1.151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular determinants of NMDA receptor internalization</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>794</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11477425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/90498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA interference targeting Fas protects mice from fulminant hepatitis</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12579197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zender</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liedtke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Caspase 8 small interfering RNA prevents acute liver failure in mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>7797</fpage><lpage>7802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1330920100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC164667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trube</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ro 25-6981, a highly potent and selective blocker of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-methyl-D-aspartate receptors containing the NR2B subunit. Characterization in vitro</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1997</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><lpage>1292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9400004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klingelschmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro binding properties in rat brain of [<sup>3</sup>H]Ro 25-6981, a potent and selective antagonist of NMDA receptors containing NR2B subunits</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1998</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>2147</fpage><lpage>2155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9572302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1471-4159.1998.70052147.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chizh</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reissmüller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlütz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Supraspinal vs spinal sites of the antinociceptive action of the subtype selective NMDA antagonist ifenprodil</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0028-3908(00)00148-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p>No conflicts of interest exist</p></fn><fn id="FN4"><p content-type="publisher-disclaimer">This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>