
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">483</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jexpmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">2985109R</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2211879</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2211879.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2211879</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2211879</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20031467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20031467</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>KSHV vFLIP Is Essential for the Survival of Infected Lymphoma Cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guasparri</surname><given-names initials="I">Ilaria</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names initials="SA">Shannon A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesarman</surname><given-names initials="E">Ethel</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1c0f620N0x1d3f8c8">Weill Medical College of Cornell University, New York, NY 10021</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address correspondence to Ethel Cesarman, Dept. of Pathology, Weill Medical College of Cornell University, 1300 York Ave., New York, NY 10021. Phone: (212) 746-8838; Fax: (212) 746-4483; email: <email>ecesarm@med.cornell.edu</email>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>199</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">159562</issue-id><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2003</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2008</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-23 15:25:14.093"><day>23</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><license license-type="openaccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="20031467.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="correction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="correction" journal-id="J Exp Med" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC2121217"><volume>203</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2006</year></date><fpage>1383</fpage><lpage>1383</lpage><source>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><named-content content-type="heading">Correction</named-content><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2121217</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="J Exp Med" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7927431"><article-title>Retraction: KSHV vFLIP Is Essential for the Survival of Infected Lymphoma Cells</article-title><volume>218</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>jem.2003146702062021r</elocation-id><source>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.2003146702062021r</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7927431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33599700</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Primary effusion lymphomas (PELs) associated with infection by the Kaposi's sarcoma–associated herpesvirus (KSHV/HHV-8) have constitutive nuclear factor (NF)–κB activity that is essential for their survival, but the source of this activity is unknown. We report that viral FADD-like interleukin-1-β–converting enzyme [FLICE/caspase 8]-inhibitory protein (FLIP) activates NF-κB more potently than cellular FLIP in B cells and that it is largely responsible for NF-κB activation in latently infected PEL cells. Elimination of vFLIP production in PEL cells by RNA interference results in significantly decreased NF-κB activity, down-regulation of essential NF-κB–regulated cellular prosurvival factors, induction of apoptosis, and enhanced sensitivity to external apoptotic stimuli. vFLIP is the first virally encoded gene shown to be essential for the survival of naturally infected tumor cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>HHV-8</kwd><kwd>NF-kB</kwd><kwd>Kaposi's sarcoma</kwd><kwd>AIDS</kwd><kwd>viral oncogenes</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Abbreviations used in this paper:</italic> DD, death domain; DED, death effector domain; DISC, death-inducing signaling complex; Doxy, doxycycline; EMSA, electrophoretic mobility shift assay; FA, Fas-associated; FLIP, FADD-like interleukin-1-β–converting enzyme [FLICE/caspase 8]-inhibitory protein; HTLV-1, human T cell leukemia virus 1; IBL, immunoblastic lymphoma; IKK, IκB kinase; KSHV, Kaposi's sarcoma–associated herpesvirus; LANA, latency-associated nuclear antigen; NF, nuclear factor; PARP, poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase; PEL, primary effusion lymphoma; si, small interfering; vCYC, viral cyclin; vGPCR, viral G protein–coupled receptor.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Activation of nuclear factor (NF)–κB is a mechanism used by lymphomagenic viruses to prolong cellular survival and induce proliferation. EBV and human T cell leukemia virus 1 (HTLV-1) encode viral (v) oncoproteins, mainly LMP1 and Tax, that subvert cellular signaling pathways to constitutively activate NF-κB (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Another lymphomagenic virus, Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV, also called human herpesvirus 8 or HHV-8), infects B cells and is present in B cell lymphoproliferative disorders, specifically primary effusion lymphomas (PELs; reference <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and a subset of cases of multicentric Castleman's disease (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) and associated plasmablastic lymphomas (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Like other virus-associated lymphomas, the transcription factor NF-κB is constitutively activated in PEL cells, and is essential for their survival (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). We postulated that expression of viral genes was a primary source of constitutive activation of NF-κB in PEL cells. Consistent with this has been our previous finding that types of NF-κB complexes, although varying in levels of intensity, are identical among different KSHV-infected PEL cell lines, which suggests a common source of activation.</p><p>Apoptotic cell death is a tightly regulated process that is crucial for the defense against certain infectious diseases and cancer. Interaction between immune effector cells as well as some infected cells can lead to apoptosis by the exogenous or death receptor pathway. Death receptors are a family of transmembrane proteins that belong to the TNF family of receptors (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). They all contain a cytoplasmic sequence called death domain (DD) that couples each receptor to caspases, inducing death signals that trigger apoptosis. Current understanding suggests that binding of extracellular death ligands to their receptors, such as the Fas ligand to Fas, results in conformational changes of preformed receptor clusters (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). This leads to recruitment of the bipartite molecule Fas-associated (FA)DD, composed of an amino terminal death effector domain (DED) and a carboxyl terminal DD. FADD binds to Fas via homophilic DD–DD interactions and recruits the upstream DED-containing procaspase 8 to the receptor by homophilic DED–DED interactions. This forms the death-inducing signaling complex (DISC), which autoactivates itself via proteolytic cleavage of caspase 8 and induces apoptosis by subsequent cleavage of downstream effector caspases.</p><p>Apoptosis is tightly regulated and can be inhibited at the receptor level (receptor endocytosis, soluble ligands, and decoy receptors) during signal transduction and at the effector stage (caspase inhibitors such as CrmA, p35, IAPs, BCL-2, etc.). The transcription factor NF-κB can inhibit apoptosis by controlling the expression of some of these antiapoptotic inhibitory proteins. A different and direct mechanism of apoptosis inhibition is mediated by a group of inhibitors of death receptor–induced apoptosis, called FLIP (FADD-like interleukin-1-β–converting enzyme [FLICE/caspase 8]-inhibitory protein; reference <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), but also having received the names of FLAME-1, I-FLICE, Casper, CASH, MRIT, CLARP, and Usurpin. FLIP proteins contain two DED domains and were shown to inhibit DED–DED interactions between FADD and procaspases 8 and 10. Two forms of cellular FLIP have been identified and characterized, both of which can inhibit caspase 8 activation at the DISC. These are cFLIP<sub>L</sub> (long form) and cFLIP<sub>S</sub> (short form), which correspond to splice variants. cFLIP<sub>S</sub> consists of two DEDs with a short cytoplasmic tail, whereas cFLIP<sub>L</sub> has an additional COOH-terminal caspase domain and resembles procaspase 8 in its overall structural organization, but lacks proteolytic activity (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Only cFLIP<sub>L</sub> has been found in human B cells by us (unpublished data) and others (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) when using antibodies that recognize both protein forms. Several viruses contain proteins with two DED with slight homology to cFLIP. The first described and most studied are MC159L from the Molluscum Contagiousum virus, E8 from the Equine Herpes Virus 2, and ORF71/K13 from KSHV (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Rhesus rhadinovirus and herpesvirus saimiri also contain FLIP homologues, but murine herpesvirus 68 does not. KSHV vFLIP has two DED domains, and structurally most closely resembles cFLIP<sub>S</sub>. When transfected into a murine B cell lymphoma cell line, which was subsequently injected into immunocompetent mice, it facilitated tumor growth, suggesting that in confers cells with resistance to T cell–induced apoptosis (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). KSHV vFLIP has also been shown to be able to activate the IκB kinase (IKK) complex and NF-κB in a variety of ectopic overexpression systems, and to be present in IKK complexes in PEL cells (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In addition, a recent paper by An et al. showed that vFLIP is responsible for IL-6 expression in a PEL cell line, where suppression of vFLIP resulted in a 100% reduction of AP-1 transcriptional activity and 70% reduction of NF-κB activity, providing the first direct evidence indicating that vFLIP is responsible for a significant proportion of the constitutive NF-κB activity observed in PEL cells (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>In addition to KSHV vFLIP, three different viral transmembrane proteins have been shown to induce signaling that leads to NF-κB activation in ectopic expression systems. These are K1 (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), viral G protein–coupled receptor (vGPCR; reference <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and K15 (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). We sought to confirm previous findings suggesting that vFLIP is responsible for initiating and maintaining the signaling cascade responsible for NF-κB in latently infected lymphoma cells, and to exclude a possible contributory role for K1, vGPCR, and K15 during latent infection. Our studies show that of these genes, vFLIP is largely responsible for the constitutive NF-κB activity in PEL cells. In addition, we show that KSHV vFLIP expression is essential for the survival of the infected lymphoma cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Cloning and Expression Vectors.</title><p>To clone KSHV vFLIP, viral Cyclin (vCYC), and cellular FLIPs (long and short forms), cDNA from the human PEL cell line BC3 was amplified using the following specific primers: vFLIP, 5′-GGGATGGCCACTTACGGGGTT-3′ and 5′-GGTGTATGGCGATAGTGTTGG-3′; vCYC, 5′-GGGATGGCAACTGCCAATAAC-3′ and 5′-ATAGCTGTCCAGAATGCGCGG-3′; cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, 5′-GGGATGGCTGCTGAAGTCATCCAT-3′ and 5′-TATGTGTAGGA-GAGGATAAGTTTC-3′; and cFLIP<sub>S</sub>, 5′-GGGATGGCTGC-TGAAGTCATCCAT-3′ and 5′-ACATGGAACAATTTCCA-AGGATTT-3′.</p><p>All the constructs were cloned into the eukaryotic expression vector pcDNA3.1 (Invitrogen). Correct orientation and sequence integrity was confirmed by nucleotide sequencing. vFLIP and cFLIP<sub>L</sub> were also cloned in frame with a COOH-terminal 3X-FLAG in a CMV14 vector backbone (Sigma-Aldrich). Comparable expression of transfected plasmids was confirmed by RT-PCR or immunoblot with an anti-FLAG monoclonal antibody. vFLIP was also cloned into pTRUF2-Tet (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) by blunt end ligation into the single NsiI site, and the resulting plasmid called pTRUF2-tet/vFLIP.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Lines and Culture Conditions.</title><p>Cell lines used were as follows: PEL cell lines were BC1, BC2, BC5 (KSHV<sup>+</sup>/EBV<sup>+</sup>), BC3, and BCBL-1 (KSHV<sup>+</sup>/EBV<sup>−</sup>). All of these were established in our laboratory from lymphomatous effusions as described previously (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), except BCBL-1 (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) that was obtained from the AIDS and Cancer Specimen Bank. Burkitt lymphoma cell lines were Namalwa and BJAB, obtained from the American Type Culture Collection. An EBV-positive immunoblastic lymphoma (IBL) cell line was derived in our laboratory from an HIV-positive patient. A lymphoblastoid cell line (LCL9001) was obtained by infection of peripheral blood lymphocytes with EBV. Cells were grown in RPMI 1640 (GIBCO BRL) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated FBS (Atlanta Biologicals) and 50 mg/ml gentamicin (Sigma-Aldrich). The human embryonal kidney 293T cell line was grown in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS. Cells were cultured at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. NF13 was established by electroporation of Namalwa cells with 10 μg of pTRUF2-tet/vFLIP. The cells were allowed to recover for 48 h in full culture medium, and 1 mg/ml of Geneticin (Invitrogen) was added. After 20 d under antibiotic selection, single cells approximated by limiting dilution were placed on irradiated fibroblast feeder layers (10<sup>4</sup> to 2 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well; 5,000 rad of cobalt γ-irradiation) in 96-well plates. After 2 wk, only wells with a single colony were expanded. 76 clones were screened for tetracycline inducibility-related protein expression by transfection with 10 μg of pTRE-Luc (CLONTECH Laboratories, Inc.), containing a tetracycline response element, and ± 2 μg/ml doxycycline (Doxy). Three clonal populations were selected having low basal transcription and up to 100-fold inducibility with the TRE-luciferase reporter and an NF-κB luc reporter, as well as by RT-PCR and immunoblot analysis for vFLIP. One of these, NF-13, was chosen to evaluate cellular gene expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assays (EMSAs).</title><p>Nuclear proteins were evaluated for binding to a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled oligonucleotide probe corresponding to the Igκ NF-binding sequence (a gift from H.-C. Liou, Weill Medical College of Cornell University) or Oct-1 (Promega) by EMSA. The methodology used was described previously in detail (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Northern Blot Analysis.</title><p>Total RNA was extracted with the RNAZOL solution (GIBCO BRL) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Poly(A)-selected RNA was isolated with the PolyATract mRNA Isolation System (Promega). RNA samples were treated with 2 U of RNase-free DNase I (Boehringer) before Northern blot analysis. 800 ng aliquots of poly(A)-selected RNA were separated electrophoretically in 1.5% denaturing formaldehyde agarose gel and blotted onto nylon filters (Dupont). After fixation, the blots were subjected to hybridization to PCR-generated double-stranded DNA probes that had been <sup>32</sup>P-labeled by the random primer extension method. To evaluate K15 expression, probes for the predominant (P) and minor (M) forms were used. Washing of the filters and autoradiography was performed according to standard methodology.</p></sec><sec><title>Transient Transfection and Luciferase Assays.</title><p>BJAB and Namalwa cells (5 × 10<sup>6</sup>) were transfected by electroporation (Gene Pulser II; Bio-Rad Laboratories) at settings of 270 mV and 975 μF in 0.8-cm cuvettes (Invitrogen). The amount of DNA transfected was equalized by addition of pcDNA3.1 control empty vector. All the transfections were performed in the presence of pRSV-RL vector (Promega), encoding renilla luciferase, to normalize the results for the transfection efficiencies. After 48 h, lysates were prepared using 1× cell culture lysis reagent as specified by the manufacturer (Promega). Luciferase assays were performed with a luminometer (Dynex Tech). The NF-κB firefly luciferase reporter derived from a Igκ promoter was provided by H.-C. Liou. Each experiment was independently performed a minimum of three times, and within each experiment each transfection was performed in triplicate.</p><p>Transient transfection of vCYC was performed using FuGene 6 transfection reagent (Roche). This method is highly efficient for transfection of BC-3 cells, achieving delivery into up to 90% of cells as determined by a control green fluorescent protein–expressing plasmid. BC3 cells were plated in RPMI 1640 without FBS at a density of 7.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml (2 ml in a six-well plate). 3 μl of FuGene 6 reagent were added in a small sterile tube containing serum-free medium to a total of 100 μl. Subsequently, 2 μg of pcDNA3.1/vCYC were added to the prediluted FuGene 6 and mixed gently. After 15 min of incubation, the mixture was added to the cells. This method was also used to transfect 3× FLAG-tagged vFLIP and cFLIP<sub>L</sub> into BC-3 cells.</p><p>Transient transfection experiments were performed in 293T cells when the confluence of the cells was 30–50% using the Calcium Phosphate Transcription System (GIBCO BRL).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Interference.</title><p>RNA duplexes were synthesized with 2-nt (2′deoxy) uridine overhangs by Dharmacon Research. The target region of vFLIP small interfering (si) RNA was 58 amino acids downstream of the start codon. The siRNA target sequence to vFLIP mRNA is 5′-AAGUGGUAUUGUUCCUCCUAA-3′. A control scramble siRNA duplex was obtained from Dharmacon (Scramble II Duplex). We performed the transfection of siRNA duplex using Oligofectamine Reagent (Invitrogen) and assayed for silencing 2 d after transfection. With this method, we achieved delivery into 60–80% of the cells in each of the lymphoma cell lines tested, as determined by transfection with a fluoresceinated control siRNA and flow cytometric analysis (unpublished data). For extended studies, the cells were transfected every 2 d, for a total of four transfections and an 8-d time course. Cells were plated in 12-well plates at a density of 7.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml. For each well, we used 1.68 μg siRNA duplex. We mixed 6 μl of 20 μM siRNA duplex with 100 μl of OPTI-MEM (Invitrogen). In another tube, 6 μl of Oligofectamine Reagent was mixed with 24 μl of Opti-MEM, incubated for 10 min at room temperature. These solutions were combined, mixed, and incubated for another 25 min at room temperature. 76 μl of fresh Opti-MEM were added to the tubes to obtain a final solution volume of 212 μl, which was added to cultured cells. Each RNA interference experiment was performed at least three times, and reporter assays were performed in triplicate within each experiment.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblot Analysis.</title><p>NF13 cells were plated at a density of 7.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml without Doxy (Sigma-Aldrich) or with 2 μg/ml Doxy for 48 h. Namalwa cells were also evaluated with and without 2 μg/ml Doxy as a control for drug effects. BC-3 cells that were untransfected, mock-transfected, or transfected with siRNA were collected 48 h after transfection. Lysates were prepared in standard radioimmunoprecipitation assay buffer supplemented with 1 μg/ml each of aproptinin, leupeptinin, and pepstatin; 0.5 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride; and 1 mM each NAV04 and NaF (Sigma-Aldrich). Lysates were prepared from three independent experiments and subsequently evaluated by Western blotting. The proteins were quantitated by the Bradford method, and 80 μg whole cell extract was loaded onto 7.5–12.5% SDS-polyacrylamide gels. After electrophoresis, semi-dry transfer to a polyvinylindene difluoride membrane (Millipore) was performed. Blots were probed with primary Ab overnight at 4°C. Horseradish peroxidase–conjugated secondary Ab was added after washing and was detected by an enhanced chemiluminescence system (Amersham Biosciences).</p><p>The following primary Abs were used: anti-vFLIP (provided by M. Collins, University College of London, London, UK; reference <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>); anti-cFLIP, anti–cIAP-1, and cIAP-2 (Qbiogene); anti–Bcl-X, anti–Bcl-2, and anti–IL-6 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.); anti-Caspase 3 (Upstate Biotechnology); anti-poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) (BD Biosciences); anti–latency-associated nuclear antigen (LANA; ABI); anti-vCYC (Exalpha); and anti–β-actin and anti-FLAG (Sigma-Aldrich).</p></sec><sec><title>Flow Cytometry Analysis.</title><p>Cells were placed in culture at a density of 7.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml without anti-FAS Ab or with 800 ng/ml anti–human Fas ligand (B-R17; Upstate Biotechnology) for 24 h. Annexin V analysis was performed as described by the manufacturer (CLONTECH Laboratories, Inc.). In brief, 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells were washed once with 1× binding buffer and resuspended in 200 μl of 1× binding buffer. 5 μl FITC–Annexin V was added, and the cells incubated for 15 min in the dark at room temperature and analyzed by flow cytometry using a FACSCalibur™ (Becton Dickinson).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The KSHV-encoded FLIP (vFLIP) Can Activate NF-κB.</title><p>We first sought to determine which of the KSHV-encoded genes that can activate NF-κB in ectopic expression systems is responsible for the constitutive NF-κB activity seen in PEL cells. We performed Northern blot analysis using probes for vGPCR, K1, K15 (not depicted), and vFLIP (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), and compared the amount of transcripts in latently infected PEL cells (BC1, BC2, and BC3) to the level of NF-κB as measured by EMSAs in these three PEL cell lines. This analysis confirmed previous analyses (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) indicating that K1, vGPCR, and K15 are lytic genes that are not significantly expressed by latently infected PEL cells, whereas vFLIP is expressed at significant levels during latency. In addition, we found that the transcript encoding vFLIP is present in PEL cells at levels that correlate with the degree of NF-κB DNA-binding activity (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Because vFLIP is encoded in a bicistronic mRNA together with vCYC, the levels of vCYC also parallel those of NF-κB. However, in our hands, vCYC cannot activate NF-κB (see <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B). The protein levels of vFLIP also paralleled those of NF-κB, as indicated by an immunoblot analysis using a monoclonal antibody to vFLIP (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Although this simple correlation is insufficient to draw firm conclusions, it prompted us to further investigate the role of vFLIP in PEL.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Correlation of NF-κB activity and vFLIP expression in PEL cell lines. (top) EMSA using a NF-κB–specific oligonucleotide probe, demonstrating constitutive activity in three PEL cell lines. Competition with cold NF-κB and random oligonucleotides has confirmed the specificity of this binding (not depicted). The level of NF-κB activity was in the following order: BC1&gt;BC3&gt;BC2. In all three PEL lines, activity was higher than in BJAB, a virus-negative lymphoma cell line. (middle) Northern blot analysis was performed on polyA-selected RNA extracted from the BC-1, -2, and -3 cell lines, as well as from BC3 after induction of lytic replication by treatment with tetradecanoyl phorbol acetate (TPA) for 48 h. BJAB cells were used as negative control. A probe that recognizes vFLIP and vCYC was used, and filters were reprobed with β-actin to ensure even loading. (bottom) Immunoblot analysis with an antibody to vFLIP showed vFLIP protein in BC1, -2, and -3 cells, but not in KSHV-negative BJAB. Equal protein loading was found in all four lanes with an antibody to β-actin.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f1.jpg"/></fig><p>Activation of NF-κB by vFLIP was evaluated in Namalwa cells by transient transfection assay, using a pcDNA3.1/vFLIP construct and an NF-κB firefly luciferase reporter derived from the Igκ promoter. We chose Namalwa because this is a KSHV-negative B cell lymphoma line with relatively low endogenous NF-κB, and therefore, corresponds to the same lineage as PEL, but does not contain endogenous vFLIP. The luciferase activity was measured 48 h after transfection and it was found to be markedly increased in the cells transfected with vFLIP as compared with the control cells transfected with NF-κB firefly luciferase reporter and empty vector (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). This is the first demonstration that vFLIP can indeed activate NF-κB in human B cells. Notably, vFLIP was a more potent activator of NF-κB than saturating doses of TNFα. Cellular FLIP (the short and long isoforms, cFLIP<sub>S</sub> and cFLIP<sub>L</sub>) were also evaluated for comparison. These were cloned into the same vector (pcDNA3.1) and transiently cotransfected in Namalwa cells with the NF-κB luciferase reporter. vFLIP was a more potent activator of NF-κB than both forms of cFLIP (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B). When tested in 293T cells, vFLIP was also a more potent activator of NF-κB than TNFα, and the ability of vFLIP to induce NF-κB was at least 2-fold higher as compared with cFLIP<sub>L</sub> and 10-fold higher than cFLIP<sub>S</sub> (unpublished data). To assess the levels of the different FLIP proteins in the transfected cells using a single antibody, and to determine whether the differences in NF-κB activity may be explained by variability protein levels, we subcloned vFLIP and cFLIP<sub>L</sub> into a vector in frame with a COOH-terminal 3X-FLAG. This also allowed us to examine the ability of these proteins to activate NF-κB when transfected into BC-3 cells and to distinguish them from the endogenous proteins. No significant differences in activity were found between FLAG-tagged and untagged proteins (unpublished data). The vFLIP-FLAG also showed higher activation of NF-κB than cFLIP<sub>L</sub>-FLAG in BC-3 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C) and 293T cells (not depicted). Proteins were extracted from these transfected cells, and immunoblot analysis using an anti-FLAG antibody was performed. We consistently found in BC-3 and 293T cells that the levels of cFLIP<sub>L</sub> were approximately threefold higher than those of vFLIP. This is probably due to higher translation efficiency or stability of the cFLIP<sub>L</sub> protein because these differences were not seen by RT-PCR. These results show that vFLIP has an intrinsically higher signaling capacity than cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, and that the difference between viral and cellular proteins is larger than that apparent in the reporter assays when protein levels are taken into account.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Activation of NF-κB by KSHV-encoded vFLIP. (A) vFLIP induces NF-κB transcriptional activity in human lymphoma cells. Namalwa cells were cotransfected by electroporation with 5 μg NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid, 0.5 μg of control renilla luciferase reporter (pRL-CMV), and vFLIP expression vector (vFLIP/pcDNA3.1) in the indicated amounts, or empty vector (pcDNA3.1). Total DNA content was maintained at 25 μg with empty vector. In all experiments, luciferase activities were measured 48 h after transfection, and firefly luciferase was normalized to renilla luciferase (control reporter) activity. Values shown are averages (± SEM) of one representative experiment out of three in which each transfection was performed in triplicate. As an experimental control, cells were transfected with reporter constructs and treated with 100 ng/ml recombinant human TNF-α for 3 h (at which maximal activation was identified in previous time course experiments) before cell lysis (top). (B) Namalwa cells were cotransfected with 5 μg NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid, 0.5 μg of control reporter (pRL-CMV), and 5 and 10 μg of vFLIP, cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, or cFLIP<sub>S</sub> expression vectors. (C) BC-3 cells were cotransfected with 5 μg NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid, 0.5 μg of control reporter (pRL-CMV), and 5 and 10 μg of 3X-FLAG-tagged vFLIP and cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, or empty vector (P3X-FLAG-CMV14). NF-κB activation was measured using a luciferase reporter assay. No significant difference was found between FLAG-tagged and untagged proteins (not depicted). (D) Immunoblot analysis of extracts from transfected BC-3 cells using an anti-FLAG monoclonal antibody is shown (top), indicating lower protein levels for vFLIP than cFLIP<sub>L</sub> in spite of higher NF-κB–inducing activity. Because the sizes of vFLIP and cFLIP<sub>L</sub> are very different, the bands in this figure were cut from a single gel to show only the specific band.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>KSHV vFLIP Induces the Expression of Cellular Antiapoptotic Genes.</title><p>To better characterize the effect of KSHV vFLIP in neoplastic B cells, this gene was cloned in pTruf2-Tet, an inducible plasmid expression vector developed in our laboratory based on a combination of the tetracycline-inducible system and adeno-associated virus (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) and was stably transfected in Namalwa cells. Selected and subcloned populations were tested for expression and inducibility of vFLIP after treatment with Doxy. Three clonal populations were selected, having low basal transcription and up to 100-fold inducibility. Results from a representative clone, designated NF13, are shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. NF-κB activity was increased greater than two-fold in induced cells as compared with the uninduced control cells. Because NF-κB is a transcription factor that controls a number of cellular genes that are critical mediators of cell survival and proliferation, we evaluated the effect of vFLIP on cellular gene expression. We have identified a set of cellular genes that are antiapoptotic NF-κB targets in PEL cells. These include cFLIP<sub>L</sub> (no cFLIP short was identified in PEL cells), cIAP-1, and cIAP-2. We have also found that BCL-X<sub>L</sub> and BCL-2 are not NF-κB targets in PEL cells (unpublished data). Expression of vFLIP induced by Doxy in NF13 cells resulted in expression of cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, cIAP-1, and cIAP-2, but no changes in BCL-X<sub>L</sub> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). No changes in NF-κB activity or expression of cFLIP<sub>L</sub> were seen when the parental Namalwa cells were treated with Doxy. These data suggest that virus-encoded vFLIP could inhibit apoptosis by inducing expression of a specific set of cellular NF-κB–dependent antiapoptotic genes.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The KSHV-encoded FLIP induces NF-κB and expression of NF-κB–regulated cellular genes in stably transfected lymphoma cells. (A) NF13 cells were transfected with 5 μg NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid and 0.5 μg of control reporter (pRL-CMV), divided, and cultured at 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml in the absence and presence of 2 μg/ml Doxy. As a control, the parental cell line, Namalwa, was similarly treated with 2 μg/ml Doxy. After 48 h, luciferase activity was measured. Values shown are averages (± SEM) of one representative experiment out of three in which each transfection was performed in triplicate. (B) Proteins extracted from untreated and Doxy-induced NF-13 cells were assessed for vFLIP (to confirm induction), cFLIP, cIAP-1, cIAP-2, and BCL-X<sub>L</sub> expression by Western blotting. BC-3 was used as a positive control because it has constitutive NF-κB activity and expresses these proteins. The Namalwa cells were also treated with Doxy to exclude drug-related effects and evaluated for expression of vFLIP and cFLIP. Actin reprobing was performed to assure even protein loading. Doxy induction and analysis of protein expression was confirmed in three independent experiments of which one representative is shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of KSHV vFLIP by RNA Interference.</title><p>We evaluated the role of vFLIP in PEL cells, which are naturally infected with KSHV and presumably a target of transformation by this virus, using RNA interference. We developed and tested a siRNA duplex that specifically targets the KSHV vFLIP sequence, but not cFLIP or any other known genomic sequence. This siRNA was transfected into a PEL cell line (BC-3) and a significant inhibition of vFLIP protein was obtained, as assessed by immunoblot analysis (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A). Although all experiments showed marked silencing by immunoblot analysis, it appears to be complete in some, partial in others, and seen by longer gel exposure. This is probably due to a threshold of detection by the antibody to vFLIP, where a small amount of residual vFLIP protein can no longer be detected. siRNA to vFLIP was able to inhibit basal NF-κB activity by ∼80% in BC-3 cells, indicating that a substantial proportion of the constitutive NF-κB activity is being induced by vFLIP (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). Scramble siRNA used as a negative control did not have a significant effect on NF-κB activity and did not affect the levels of vFLIP protein. This result confirms a previously published work in which siRNA to vFLIP was found to significantly inhibit NF-κB reporter activity in the BCBL-1 PEL cell line (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). We also confirmed that siRNA to vFLIP inhibits transcription for an AP-1 reporter construct, as demonstrated previously (reference <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and unpublished data).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of endogenous vFLIP by siRNA results in depletion of constitutive NF-κB activity in PEL cells. (A) BC-3 cells were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v) and scramble siRNA (s) and compared with mock-transfected cells (–). Protein extracts were prepared 48 h after transfection. Actin reprobing was performed to assure even protein loading. This experiment has been performed at least 10 times, and a representative immunoblot is shown. (B) BC-3 cells were transfected with an NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid and either scramble siRNA as a control or siRNA for vFLIP. Luciferase assays were performed 48 h after transfection. Values shown are averages (± SEM) of one representative experiment out of three in which each transfection was performed in triplicate. (C) Electrophoretic mobility shift assays using a radiolabeled probe containing an NF-κB–binding site. BC-1 and BC-3 cells were transfected with vFLIP siRNA (v) or scramble siRNA (s) and compared with mock-transfected cells (–). Cold competition using 50-fold molar excess of an unlabeled NF-κB oligonucleotide (c) demonstrated the specificity of the protein–DNA-binding complexes. Nuclear extracts were prepared 48 h after transfection. In the lane labeled H<sub>2</sub>O, water was used instead of nuclear extract. Binding to a radiolabeled oligonucleotide containing an octamer (Oct) motif was similarly examined as a control for specificity and for nuclear protein amount (bottom), where cold competition (c) was performed with nuclear extracts from mock-transfected cells and excess unlabeled oligonucleotide containing an octamer motif. This experiment was performed three times with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f4.jpg"/></fig><p>To confirm the effect of vFLIP siRNA on NF-κB activity, we performed EMSAs. We evaluated BC-1 and BC-3 cells transfected with siRNA to vFLIP, using mock-transfected cells and cells transfected with scramble siRNA as controls. Nuclear extracts were made 48 h after transfection and evaluated for binding to a radiolabeled probe containing an NF-κB binding sequence. Silencing of vFLIP resulted in a marked decrease of NF-κB DNA binding activity (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C). In contrast, no significant changes were seen in the level of proteins binding to an oligonucleotide containing an octamer binding motif, indicating that not all transcription factors are affected by vFLIP down-regulation.</p><p>vFLIP is encoded in a bicistronic transcript also encoding for vCYC. In addition, vFLIP is also present in a tricistronic transcript encoding the LANA and also containing downstream vCYC and vFLIP sequences. Therefore, it was important to determine whether protein production of LANA and/or vCYC is affected by the siRNA to vFLIP. Our results indicate that LANA is unaffected by siRNA to vFLIP. The reason for this protection is unclear; LANA remains unchanged even after 8 d of siRNA treatment, so it is unlikely to be due to a longer half life of the protein. In contrast, expression of vCYC is dramatically reduced (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). To overcome the down-regulation of vCYC, and to be able to dissociate the effects resulting from loss of vFLIP from those due to vCYC inhibition, we transfected vCYC as a monocistronic transcript and expressed it independently of vFLIP in BC-3 cells. We were able to achieve continuous expression of vCYC at levels comparable to those of untreated BC-3 cells (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A). The functional effects of treatment with siRNA to vFLIP described in the next paragraphs were also seen in vCYC-transfected BC-3 cells, where vCYC protein levels were maintained in the presence of siRNA to vFLIP, and thus can be attributed to vFLIP down-regulation. In addition, transfection of vCYC did not induce NF-κB, and did not affect the NF-κB activity induced by vFLIP (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B); thus, we did not find vCYC to be a contributing factor to NF-κB activation.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>siRNA to vFLIP inhibits vCYC, but this protein can be reconstituted and its expression does not affect NF-κB activity. (A) BC-3 cells were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v) and scramble siRNA (s) with or without 2 μg of a viral cyclin (vCYC) expression vector at days 0, 2, 4, and 6, and compared to mock-transfected cells (–). Protein extracts were prepared at day 8. This experiment was performed three times, and a representative immunoblot is shown. (B) 293T cells were transfected with 5 μg of NF-κB luciferase reporter plasmid in addition to 5 μg of vFLIP/pcDNA3.1, vCYC/pcDNA3.1, both, or vector alone. Luciferase activities were measured 48 h after transfection and firefly luciferase was normalized to renilla luciferase (control reporter) activity. Values shown are averages (± SEM) of one representative experiment out of three in which each transfection was performed in triplicate.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f5.jpg"/></fig><p>We assumed that a single transfection of siRNA into PEL cells would lead to incomplete and transient delivery, so we modified this approach by transfecting BC-3 cells every 2 d with siRNA, thus achieving sufficient and prolonged inhibition of vFLIP in PEL cells. Proteins were extracted at various time points during the course of this experiment, and the effect of vFLIP reduction on selected cellular proteins was evaluated. siRNA to vFLIP decreased the expression of the three NF-κB–dependent cellular antiapoptotic proteins examined, cFLIP, cIAP-1, and cIAP-2 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), although down-regulation of cIAP-1 was not immediate, perhaps due to a long half life of this protein. Reconstitution of vCYC did not affect this down-regulation of cellular proteins, as shown for cFLIP<sub>L</sub> in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A. siRNA to vFLIP also decreased expression of cellular IL-6, another NF-κB–dependent factor, consistent with recently published findings (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). siRNA to vFLIP did not affect the levels of cellular BCL-2 and BCL-X<sub>L</sub> proteins, which are not dependent on NF-κB in PEL cells (unpublished data), indicative of pathway specificity. These results show that vFLIP is largely responsible for sustaining the expression of cellular NF-κB–dependent antiapoptotic genes in PEL cells.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of endogenous vFLIP by siRNA results in down-regulation of NF-κB–dependent proteins in PEL cells. BC-3 cell lines were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v), scramble siRNA (s), or mock-transfected (–) at days 0, 2, 4, and 6, and protein extracts were prepared at the indicated time points. Western blot analysis was performed on these extracts using antibodies to the indicated proteins. Actin reprobing was performed to confirm even protein loading. Similar results were obtained in three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f6.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Elimination of KSHV vFLIP Leads to Apoptosis of PEL Cells.</title><p>If NF-κB activity is essential for the survival of PEL cells, and vFLIP is responsible for this activity in latently infected cells, elimination of vFLIP should lead to apoptosis. However, it has never been shown that elimination of a single viral gene results in apoptosis of infected lymphoma cells. To test this, we have measured apoptosis by flow cytometry for annexin V after inhibition of vFLIP by RNA interference. Initially, we evaluated BC-3 cells transfected with siRNA for apoptosis up to 48 h after transfection. Because no significant cell death was seen, vFLIP BC-3 cells were transfected every 2 d (days 0, 2, 4, and 6), and annexin V was evaluated at 2-d intervals (days 2, 4, 6, and 8, before the next transfection), for a total of four transfections and an 8-d time course. The number of apoptotic cells increases over time when transfected with siRNA to vFLIP, and by day 8, a significant proportion of cells (∼80%) express surface annexin V. In contrast, cells similarly transfected with nonspecific (scramble) siRNA and mock-transfected cells remain largely viable (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A, 18 and 13% apoptotic cells). Reconstitution of BC-3 cells with vCYC did not protect cells from apoptosis, indicating that apoptosis results from vFLIP and not vCYC suppression. siRNA to vFLIP also resulted in partial cleavage of caspase 3 and PARP, confirming induction of apoptosis (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B). Because the possibility remained that multiple transfections were inducing stress and sensitizing the cell to apoptosis in the context of NF-κB inhibition, we determined whether apoptosis would also occur in cells that had only been transfected once (at day 0), or twice (at days 0 and 4). A similar proportion of cells underwent apoptosis as in cells transfected four times (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A), but in all experiments it took 6–8 d for this process to be obvious.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of endogenous vFLIP by siRNA results in apoptosis of PEL cells. (A) BC-3 cells were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v), scramble siRNA (s), or mock-transfected (–) at days 0, 2, 4, and 6, with or without vCYC, and assessment of apoptosis was performed by annexin V staining at the indicated time points. BC-3 cells were also evaluated for annexin V positivity at day 8 after being transfected once at day 0 (*) and twice at days 0 and 4 (**). Bars represent the average number of Annexin V positive cells (± SEM) of one representative experiment out of three in which each transfection and analysis was performed in triplicate. Inset shows a representative flow cytometric histogram plot at day 8 for annexin V analysis of untreated BC-3 cells (dashed line), cells transfected with scrambled siRNA as a negative control (solid line), and cells treated with siRNA to vFLIP (gray line and filled area). (B) Induction of apoptosis was confirmed by cleavage of caspase 3 and a caspase substrate, PARP, by Western blot analysis. Actin reprobing was performed to confirm even protein loading. Three independent experiments were performed, and a representative Western blot is shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f7.jpg"/></fig><p>To exclude the possibility that the vFLIP siRNA induces apoptosis through toxicity or other nonspecific mechanisms mimicking those seen upon inhibition of NF-κB, we tested additional cell lines. siRNA was transfected every 2 d for 8 d into four additional PEL cell lines, containing KSHV and expressing vFLIP (BC-1, BCBL-1, BC-2, and BC-5), and into four cell lines lacking KSHV, which included two Burkitt lymphoma cell lines with low constitutive NF-κB activity (BJAB and Namalwa), as well as one EBV-positive immunoblastic lymphoma cell line established in our laboratory (IBL) and one lymphoblastoid cell line (LCL9001), both with high constitutive NF-κB activity. The results shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> clearly demonstrate that transfection of siRNA to vFLIP only leads to apoptosis of the PEL cell lines, whereas the cell lines lacking endogenous vFLIP are not significantly affected by this treatment.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Only KSHV-positive PEL cell lines are sensitive to vFLIP siRNA. The indicated cell lines were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v), scramble siRNA (s), or mock-transfected (–) at days 0, 2, 4, and 6, and flow cytometry using antibodies to annexin V was performed at day 8. Bars represent the average number of annexin V positive cells (± SEM) of an experiment in which each transfection and analysis was performed in triplicate. Efficiency of transfection as documented by flow cytometry analysis after transfection with a fluoresceinated siRNA to luciferase, was comparable in all cell lines (not depicted). KSHV-positive PEL cell lines (BC-1, BCBL-1, BC-2, and BC-5) and KSHV-negative B cell lymphoma (BJAB, Namalwa, and IBL) or lymphoblastoid cell lines (LCLs) were evaluated.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f8.jpg"/></fig><p>cFLIP has been shown to inhibit apoptosis by virtue of containing two DEDs, and preventing signaling from death receptors to the upstream caspases (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). vFLIP has also been shown to inhibit Fas-mediated apoptosis and caspase activation when transfected into a cell line that is sensitive to death induction by this pathway (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). We evaluated whether vFLIP contributes to resistance to Fas-mediated apoptosis in PEL cells. We chose the sixth day time point that provides suboptimal apoptosis by vFLIP inhibition alone. We found that BC-3 cells are largely resistant to Fas-mediated apoptosis, but when treated with siRNA to vFLIP, there was a further increase in annexin V positivity when Fas was engaged by agonistic antibodies (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>). This increase was statistically significant (P = 0.001). Therefore, reduction of vFLIP not only leads to spontaneous apoptosis but it sensitizes PEL to extrinsic apoptotic stimuli.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Inhibition of vFLIP in BC-3 cells sensitizes them to FAS-mediated apoptosis. BC-3 cells were transfected with a vFLIP siRNA (v) or scramble siRNA (s) at days 0, 2, and 4, and flow cytometry using antibodies to annexin V was performed at day 6. An agonistic antibody to Fas was added as indicated 24 h before flow cytometry at a concentration of 800 ng/ml. Bars represent the average number of annexin V positive cells (± SEM) of a representative experiment out of three, in which each transfection and analysis was performed in triplicate. A Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test showed that the difference between the untreated and anti-FAS–treated cells in conjunction with vFLIP siRNA was statistically significant (P = 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f9.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Classic approaches to determine which proteins of oncogenic viruses are involved in transformation cannot be used to characterize KSHV. Although this virus is associated with specific lymphoma subtypes (suggesting a role in their pathogenesis), it is clearly not sufficient for their development and additional cofactors are necessary. One of these is probably EBV because a large proportion of PEL cells are coinfected by both viruses, but other cofactors are still unknown. A puzzling observation has been that in spite of the fact that KSHV encodes several genes that are transforming in vitro and/or are homologous to cellular oncogenes, in vitro infection of B cells does not transform them (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). This clearly distinguishes KSHV from EBV and may explain why KSHV-associated lymphomas are much less common than those associated with EBV infection. Nevertheless, once a lymphoma develops, when both KSHV and EBV are present, KSHV expresses a set of latent genes, whereas EBV latent gene expression is fairly restricted (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). In addition, alterations in common oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes are rare, in spite of multiple cytogenetic abnormalities (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). These observations suggest that KSHV may be a sustaining force in PEL, and the results presented here support this notion.</p><p>We propose a model, illustrated in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>, whereby vFLIP may act by two mechanisms: (a) by preventing activation of the DISC complex, and (b) by activating the NF-κB signaling pathway, therefore inducing survival signals. The potential for vFLIP to directly inhibit DISC function is mainly suggested by homology to cFLIP long and short forms, which have been clearly shown to affect cleavage and/or release of caspase 8 (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). However, there are minimal data to support a direct role of vFLIP in the DISC; a single paper indicates that vFLIP has the potential of playing such a role because it can bind and inhibit cleavage of procaspase 8 (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), but this interaction has only been shown in transfected HeLa cells and never documented in PEL cells. The second pathway, whereby vFLIP induces NF-κB and inhibits apoptosis by inducing expression of cellular prosurvival factors is clearly demonstrated by our data. We suggest that vFLIP forms an active signaling complex, which we propose to call a life-inducing signaling complex (LISC). At this time, it is unknown what elements are in this complex in naturally KSHV-infected B cells, and whether activity depends on the presence and/or activation of TNF receptors. PEL cells do not express many of the members of the TNF receptor family, and lack CD40, which is expressed in most other B cell types and tumors. However, they do express low levels or TNF-R2 and variable levels of Fas (CD95; unpublished data) and TRAIL receptors (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Published work based on ectopic overexpression systems and PEL cell lines suggests that vFLIP can associate with the IKK complex, NIK, RIP, and TRAFs, suggesting that these are components of the life-inducing signaling complex (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). PEL cells express abundant TRAF-2 protein, and variable levels of other TRAFs, but no TRAF-1 (unpublished data). Binding of TRAF-2 to the complex containing vFLIP probably leads to activation of a kinase, perhaps RIP, MEKK1, or another as yet undefined kinase that in turn leads to phosphorylation and activation of JNK (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and the IKK complex. In turn, this would lead to IκBα phosphorylation and degradation, followed by release of NF-κB, that in PEL cells is formed mainly by p65(Rel-A)/p50 heterodimers. Transcriptional activation of cellular prosurvival proteins, including cIAP-1, cIAP-2, and vFLIP, as well as cytokines such as IL-6, leads to protection of virally infected cells from spontaneous apoptosis. Of note, cFLIP feeds back into the same pathway by interfering with the function of the DISC. Our data indicating that vFLIP protects PEL cells from FAS-mediated apoptosis can be explained by direct interference of caspase activation by vFLIP, or by an indirect effect mediated by cFLIP and cIAP up-regulation.</p><fig id="fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Model of vFLIP effect of cellular survival. We propose that vFLIP may inhibit apoptosis via a direct mechanism, by disrupting activation of the DISC complex, and an indirect pathway by forming part of a signaling complex that induces IKK phosphorylation (via an unknown kinase or kinases), IκB degradation, and NF-κB activation. In turn, activation of NF-κB up-regulates expression of genes that inhibit apoptosis, which include cFLIP, cIAP1, and cIAP2. We do not know if TNF receptors (active or inactive) are part of the vFLIP-containing complex and whether this complex is located in membrane lipid rafts in proximity to TNF receptors.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="20031467f10.jpg"/></fig><p>In these studies, apoptosis was not immediate upon down-regulation of vFLIP, and significant apoptosis was only seen after 6 d of treatment with siRNA to vFLIP, whether these were transfected once, twice, or four times. A possible explanation is that some of the antiapoptotic proteins that are controlled by NF-κB have relatively long half lives, and their decrease is gradual upon vFLIP silencing, as seen in the case of cIAP-1. It is likely that a threshold exists in which a combination of antiapoptotic factors are no longer sufficient to protect the cells from apoptotic stimuli. For example, BCL-2 and BCL-X<sub>L</sub> are present throughout the time course of our experiment, and they may play a protective role until down-regulation of other factors reaches a critically low level. In addition, we have examined expression of a set of antiapoptotic proteins that we identified in previous analysis as being NF-κB–dependent (unpublished data), but it is likely that additional factors play a role in this process. It is also possible that silencing of vFLIP does not truly induce spontaneous apoptosis, but rather sensitizes cells to extrinsic apoptotic stimuli, including stress and low levels of basal death receptor signaling. Therefore, it is very likely that down-regulation of vFLIP will also sensitize cells to cyototoxic compounds and greatly enhance their therapeutic effect.</p><p>Our data support the theory that vFLIP, out of all KSHV-encoded genes, is the gene most functionally analogous to that of EBV-encoded oncoproteins LMP-1 and HTLV-I–encoded Tax. Although obvious functional differences exist between these three proteins, they share expression during latency and the ability to activate NF-κB. Activation of NF-κB has emerged as a method by which EBV, HTLV-1, and KSHV protect the host cell from apoptosis to ensure establishment of viral latency and stable infection, with the unfortunate result of becoming a common pathway in viral lymphomagenesis.</p><p>Suppression of vFLIP induces apoptosis of PEL cells, demonstrating that this single gene encoded by KSHV is essential for the survival of infected lymphoma cells. This is the first demonstration that elimination of a single viral protein leads to the death of infected lymphoma cells. Our findings identify vFLIP as a disease-specific therapeutic target for the treatment of PEL and perhaps other KSHV-associated diseases.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant CA68939 and a Leukemia and Lymphoma Society Translational Research grant (to E. Cesarman).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Suzuki, T., H. Hirai, J. Fujisawa, T. Fujita, and M. Yoshida. <year>1993</year>. A transactivator Tax of human T-cell leukemia virus type I binds to NF-kB p50 and serum response factor (SRF) and associates with enhancer DNAs of the NF-kB sit and CarG box. <source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>2391</fpage>–2397.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8361755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yin, M.J., L.B. Christerson, Y. Yamamoto, Y.T. Kwak, S. Xu, F. Mercurio, M. Barbosa, M.H. Cobb, and R.B. Gaynor. <year>1998</year>. HTLV-I Tax protein binds to MEKK1 to stimulate IkappaB kinase activity and NF-kappaB activation. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>875</fpage>–884.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81447-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Laherty, C., H. Hu, A. Opipari, F. Wang, and V. Dixit. <year>1992</year>. The Epstein-Barr virus LMP-1 gene product induces A20 zinc finger protein expression by activating nuclear factor κB. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>:<fpage>24157</fpage>–24160.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1332946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kilger, E., A. Kieser, M. Baumann, and W. Hammerschmidt. <year>1998</year>. Epstein-Barr virus-mediated B-cell proliferation is dependent upon latent membrane protein 1, which simulates an activated CD40 receptor. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1700</fpage>–1709.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/17.6.1700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1170517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cesarman, E., Y. Chang, P.S. Moore, J.W. Said, and D.M. Knowles. <year>1995</year>. Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus-like DNA sequences in AIDS-related body cavity-based lymphomas. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>332</volume>:<fpage>1186</fpage>–1191.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7700311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJM199505043321802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gessain, A., A. Sudaka, J. Brière, N. Fouchard, M.-A. Nicola, B. Rio, M. Arborio, X. Troussard, J. Ausouin, J. Diebold, and G. de Thé. <year>1995</year> Kaposi sarcoma-associated herpes-like virus (Human Herpesvirus Type 8) DNA sequences in multicentric Castleman's disease: Is there any relevant association in non-human immunodeficiency virus-infected patients? (Letter to the Editor). <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>414</fpage>–416.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8547672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dupin, N., T.L. Diss, P. Kellam, M. Tulliez, M.Q. Du, D. Sicard, R.A. Weiss, P.G. Isaacson, and C. Boshoff. <year>2000</year>. HHV-8 is associated with a plasmablastic variant of Castleman disease that is linked to HHV-8-positive plasmablastic lymphoma. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1406</fpage>–1412.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Keller, S.A., E.J. Schattner, and E. Cesarman. <year>2000</year>. Inhibition of NF-κB induces apoptosis of KSHV-infected primary effusion lymphoma cells. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>2537</fpage>–2542.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11001908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Strasser, A., L. O'Connor, and V.M. Dixit. <year>2000</year>. Apoptosis signaling. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>–245.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.biochem.69.1.217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Siegel, R.M., J.K. Frederiksen, D.A. Zacharias, F.K. Chan, M. Johnson, D. Lynch, R.Y. Tsien, and M.J. Lenardo. <year>2000</year>. Fas preassociation required for apoptosis signaling and dominant inhibition by pathogenic mutations. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>288</volume>:<fpage>2354</fpage>–2357.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10875918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.288.5475.2354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Thome, M., P. Schneider, K. Hofmann, H. Fickenscher, E. Meinl, F. Neipel, C. Mattmann, K. Burns, J.L. Bodmer, M. Schroter, et al. <year>1997</year>. Viral FLICE-inhibitory proteins (FLIPs) prevent apoptosis induced by death receptors. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>386</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>–521.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9087414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/386517a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">French, L.E., and J. Tschopp. <year>2002</year>. Defective death receptor signaling as a cause of tumor immune escape. <source>Semin. Cancer Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–55.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11926412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/scbi.2001.0405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hennino, A., M. Berard, P.H. Krammer, and T. Defrance. <year>2001</year>. FLICE-inhibitory protein is a key regulator of germinal center B cell apoptosis. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>–458.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.193.4.447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2195905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chaudhary, P.M., A. Jasmin, M.T. Eby, and L. Hood. <year>1999</year> Modulation of the NF-kappa B pathway by virally encoded death effector domains-containing proteins. <source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5738</fpage>–5746.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1202976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10523854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Djerbi, M., V. Screpanti, A.I. Catrina, B. Bogen, P. Biberfeld, and A. Grandien. <year>1999</year>. The inhibitor of death receptor signaling, FLICE-inhibitory protein defines a new class of tumor progression factors. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>1025</fpage>–1032.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10510092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.190.7.1025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2195646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liu, L., M.T. Eby, N. Rathore, S.K. Sinha, A. Kumar, and P.M. Chaudhary. <year>2002</year>. The human herpes virus 8-encoded viral FLICE inhibitory protein physically associates with and persistently activates the IkappaB kinase complex. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>13745</fpage>–13751.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11830587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M110480200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Field, N., W. Low, M. Daniels, S. Howell, L. Daviet, C. Boshoff, and M. Collins. <year>2003</year>. KSHV vFLIP binds to IKK-gamma to activate IKK. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>3721</fpage>–3728.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12890756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.00691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">An, J., Y. Sun, R. Sun, and M.B. Rettig. <year>2003</year>. Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus encoded vFLIP induces cellular IL-6 expression: the role of the NF-kappaB and JNK/AP1 pathways. <source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>3371</fpage>–3385.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12776188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1206407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Samaniego, F., S. Pati, J.E. Karp, O. Prakash, and D. Bose. <year>2000</year> Human Herpesvirus 8 K1-associated nuclear factor-kappa B-dependent promoter activity: role in Kaposi's sarcoma inflammation? <source>J. Natl. Cancer Inst. Monogr.</source>
<volume>2000</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–23.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jncimonographs.a024252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pati, S., M. Cavrois, H.G. Guo, J.S. Foulke, Jr., J. Kim, R.A. Feldman, and M. Reitz. <year>2001</year>. Activation of NF-kappaB by the human herpesvirus 8 chemokine receptor ORF74: evidence for a paracrine model of Kaposi's sarcoma pathogenesis. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>8660</fpage>–8673.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11507211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JVI.75.18.8660-8673.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC115111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jenner, R.G., and C. Boshoff. <year>2002</year>. The molecular pathology of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta.</source>
<volume>1602</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–22.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11960692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0304-419x(01)00040-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cannon, M., N.J. Philpott, and E. Cesarman. <year>2003</year>. The Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus G protein-coupled receptor has broad signaling effects in primary effusion lymphoma cells. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>–67.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12477810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JVI.77.1.57-67.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC140579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cesarman, E., P.S. Moore, P. Rao, G. Inghirami, D.M. Knowles, and Y. Chang. <year>1995</year>. In vitro establishment and characterization of two acquired immunodeficiency syndrome-related lymphoma cell lines (BC-1 and BC-2) containing Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus-like (KSHV) DNA sequences. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>2708</fpage>–2714.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7670109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arvanitakis, L., E.A. Mesri, R. Nador, J.W. Said, A.S. Asch, D.M. Knowles, and E. Cesarman. <year>1996</year>. Establishment and characterization of a primary effusion (body cavity-based) lymphoma cell line (BC-3) harboring Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV/HHV-8) in the absence of Epstein-Barr virus. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>2648</fpage>–2654.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8839859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Renne, R., W. Zhong, B. Herndier, M. McGrath, N. Abbey, D. Kedes, and D. Ganem. <year>1996</year>. Lytic growth of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (human herpesvirus 8) in culture. <source>Nat. Med.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>342</fpage>–346.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm0396-342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Low, W., M. Harries, H. Ye, M.Q. Du, C. Boshoff, and M. Collins. <year>2001</year>. Internal ribosome entry site regulates translation of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus FLICE inhibitory protein. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>2938</fpage>–2945.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JVI.75.6.2938-2945.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC115920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sarid, R., O. Flore, R.A. Bohenzky, Y. Chang, and P.S. Moore. <year>1998</year>. Transcription mapping of the Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (human herpesvirus 8) genome in a body cavity-based lymphoma cell line (BC-1). <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>–1012.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9444993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jvi.72.2.1005-1012.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC124571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sun, R., S.F. Lin, K. Staskus, L. Gradoville, E. Grogan, A. Haase, and G. Miller. <year>1999</year>. Kinetics of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus gene expression. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>2232</fpage>–2242.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9971806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jvi.73.3.2232-2242.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC104468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Krueger, A., I. Schmitz, S. Baumann, P.H. Krammer, and S. Kirchhoff. <year>2001</year>. Cellular FLICE-inhibitory protein splice variants inhibit different steps of caspase-8 activation at the CD95 death-inducing signaling complex. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>20633</fpage>–20640.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11279218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M101780200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Micheau, O., M. Thome, P. Schneider, N. Holler, J. Tschopp, D.W. Nicholson, C. Briand, and M.G. Grutter. <year>2002</year>. The long form of FLIP is an activator of caspase-8 at the Fas death-inducing signaling complex. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>45162</fpage>–45171.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M206882200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mesri, E.A., E. Cesarman, L. Arvanitakis, S. Rafii, M.A.S. Moore, D.N. Posnett, D.M. Knowles, and A.S. Asch. <year>1996</year>. Human herpesvirus-8/Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus is a new transmissible virus that infects B cells. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>2385</fpage>–2390.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8642350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.183.5.2385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2192551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Horenstein, M.G., R.G. Nador, A. Chadburn, E.M. Hyjek, G. Inghirami, D.M. Knowles, and E. Cesarman. <year>1997</year>. Epstein-Barr virus latent gene expression in primary effusion lymphomas containing Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus human herpesvirus-8. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1186</fpage>–1191.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nador, R.G., E. Cesarman, A. Chadburn, D.B. Dawson, M.Q. Ansari, J. Said, and D.M. Knowles. <year>1996</year>. Primary effusion lymphoma: a distinct clinicopathologic entity associated with the Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus. <source>Blood.</source>
<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>–656.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8695812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Drexler, H.G., C.C. Uphoff, G. Gaidano, and A. Carbone. <year>1998</year>. Lymphoma cell lines: in vitro models for the study of HHV-8+ primary effusion lymphomas (body cavity-based lymphomas). <source>Leukemia.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1507</fpage>–1517.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2401160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Belanger, C., A. Gravel, A. Tomoiu, M.E. Janelle, J. Gosselin, M.J. Tremblay, and L. Flamand. <year>2001</year>. Human herpesvirus 8 viral FLICE-inhibitory protein inhibits Fas-mediated apoptosis through binding and prevention of procaspase-8 maturation. <source>J. Hum. Virol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–73.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11437316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Toomey, N.L., V.V. Deyev, C. Wood, L.H. Boise, D. Scott, L.H. Liu, L. Cabral, E.R. Podack, G.N. Barber, and W.J. Harrington, Jr. <year>2001</year>. Induction of a TRAIL-mediated suicide program by interferon alpha in primary effusion lymphoma. <source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>7029</fpage>–7040.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11704827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1204895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>