
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">349</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plospath</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101238921</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLOS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2873921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2873921.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2873921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2873921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PLPA-RA-1063R4</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Cell Biology/Cell Signaling</subject><subject>Immunology/Immune Response</subject><subject>Immunology/Immunity to Infections</subject><subject>Immunology/Immunomodulation</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Antimicrobials and Drug Resistance</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Neglected Tropical Diseases</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Protozoal Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RETRACTED: <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania donovani</italic> Isolates with Antimony-Resistant but Not -Sensitive Phenotype Inhibit Sodium Antimony Gluconate-Induced Dendritic Cell Activation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Antimony-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">L. donovani</italic> Inhibits DC</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haldar</surname><given-names initials="AK">Arun Kumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names initials="V">Vinod</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names initials="E">Eshu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisht</surname><given-names initials="KK">Kamlesh Kumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="A">Alpana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaumik</surname><given-names initials="S">Suniti</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names initials="R">Rajatava</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names initials="P">Pradip</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names initials="S">Syamal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Division of Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Indian Institute of Chemical Biology, Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Kolkata, India</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Division of Cell Biology and Immunology, Institute of Microbial Technology, Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Chandigarh, India</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Institute of Microbial Technology, Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Chandigarh, India</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names initials="I">Ingrid</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Imperial College London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>psen@imtech.res.in</email></corresp><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: New York University School of Medicine, Skirball Institute of Biomolecular Medicine, Langone Medical Centre, Molecular Pathogenesis, New York, New York, United States of America</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: PS. Performed the experiments: AKH VY ES KKB AS SB RB. Analyzed the data: PS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PS SR. Wrote the paper: PS. Contributed to conceptualization of some aspects of antimony resistance in LD infection: SR.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">186867</issue-id><elocation-id>e1000907</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-10 13:25:13.763"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2010 Haldar et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Haldar et al</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS Pathog" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12822931"><article-title>Retraction: <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania donovani</italic> isolates with antimony-resistant but not -sensitive phenotype inhibit sodium antimony gluconate-induced dendritic cell activation</article-title><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><date><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date><elocation-id>e1013877</elocation-id><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12822931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41564002</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The inability of sodium antimony gluconate (SAG)-unresponsive kala-azar patients to clear <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania donovani</italic> (LD) infection despite SAG therapy is partly due to an ill-defined immune-dysfunction. Since dendritic cells (DCs) typically initiate anti-leishmanial immunity, a role for DCs in aberrant LD clearance was investigated. Accordingly, regulation of SAG-induced activation of murine DCs following infection with LD isolates exhibiting two distinct phenotypes such as antimony-resistant (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) and antimony-sensitive (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) was compared <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Unlike Sb<sup>S</sup>LD, infection of DCs with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD induced more IL-10 production and inhibited SAG-induced secretion of proinflammatory cytokines, up-regulation of co-stimulatory molecules and leishmanicidal effects. Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibited these effects of SAG by blocking activation of PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways. In contrast, Sb<sup>S</sup>LD failed to block activation of SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced PI3K/AKT pathway; which continued to stimulate NF-κB signaling, induce leishmanicidal effects and promote DC activation. Notably, prolonged incubation of DCs with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD also inhibited SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced activation of PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways and leishmanicidal effects, which was restored by increasing the dose of SAG to 40 µg/ml. In contrast, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibited these SAG-induced events regardless of duration of DC exposure to Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or dose of SAG. Interestingly, the inhibitory effects of isogenic Sb<sup>S</sup>LD expressing ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter MRPA on SAG-induced leishmanicidal effects mimicked that of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD to some extent, although antimony resistance in clinical LD isolates is known to be multifactorial. Furthermore, NF-κB was found to transcriptionally regulate expression of murine γglutamylcysteine synthetase heavy-chain (mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>) gene, presumably an important regulator of antimony resistance. Importantly, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD blocked SAG-induced mγGCS expression in DCs by preventing NF-κB binding to the mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter. Our findings demonstrate that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD prevents SAG-induced DC activation by suppressing a PI3K-dependent NF-κB pathway and provide the evidence for differential host-pathogen interaction mediated by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Kala-azar, a life-threatening parasitic disease caused by <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania donovani</italic> (LD), is widening its base in different parts of the world. Currently, there is no effective vaccine against kala-azar. The antimonial drugs like sodium antimony gluconate (SAG) have been the mainstay of therapy for this disease. Recently, due to the emergence of antimony-resistance in parasites, SAG often fails to cure kala-azar patients, which is compounding the disaster further. It is still unknown how infection with LD exhibiting antimony-resistant phenotype, in contrast to antimony-sensitive phenotype, is handled by the kala-azar patients upon SAG treatment. This demands an understanding of the nature of host immune responses against these two distinct categories of parasites. Accordingly, we compared the impact of infection with LD exhibiting antimony-resistant versus antimony-sensitive phenotype on dendritic cells (DCs). DCs upon activation/maturation initiate anti-leishmanial immunity. We showed that parasites with antimony-resistant but not antimony-sensitive phenotype prevented SAG-induced DC activation/maturation by blocking activation of NF-κB. The latter is a key signaling pathway regulating DC activation/maturation. Our studies for the first time provide both a cellular and molecular basis for differential response of host cells to parasite isolates with antimony-resistant and antimony-sensitive phenotype, which may influence the outcome of the disease.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by intramural grant from the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Government of India (S.R. and P.S.). The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Kala-azar, caused by <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania donovani</italic> (LD), is regarded as the most severe form of leishmanial infection, which can be fatal in patients when left untreated. In the absence of an effective vaccine, treatment with pentavalent antimonial compounds such as sodium antimony gluconate (SAG) remains as the first-choice therapy for kala-azar. However, therapeutic utility of SAG is now jeopardized by the emergence of antimony-resistant strains of LD <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Lira1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, which is becoming a major concern of the World Health Organization (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/infections-disease-report/2000" ext-link-type="uri">www.who.int/infections-disease-report/2000</ext-link>).</p><p>Resistance to antimonial drugs, as observed in leishmanial infection, is marked by two independent “checkpoints”. The first is associated with the impaired biological reduction of the pentavalent antimony (Sb<sup>V</sup>) prodrug to a toxic trivalent (Sb<sup>III</sup>) form, although the site (macrophage (Mφ) and/or parasite) and mechanism of reduction (enzymatic or nonezymatic) are undefined. The second checkpoint involves a regulatory mechanism promoting reduced influx and/or enhanced efflux/sequestration of active drug that lowers its intracellular accumulation <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Croft1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Importantly, these two events are largely dependent on the intracellular level of thiol compounds such as glutathione (γglutamylcysteinylglycine, GSH) and parasite-specific trypanothione, which in turn are regulated by both host- and LD-γglutamylcysteine synthetase, a rate-limiting enzyme in glutathione biosynthesis <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Croft1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mukherjee1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Although the increased expression of γglutamylcysteine synthetase (γGCS) gene in antimony-resistant strains of LD is controversial <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Decuypere1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, inhibition of γGCS by buthionine sulfoxamine (BSO) reverses Sb<sup>III</sup> resistance in LD <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Therefore, γGCS expression contributes to antimony resistance in LD by regulating intracellular thiol level.</p><p>In addition to the mechanisms noted above, the unresponsiveness of kala-azar patients to treatment with SAG is also believed to be a consequence of skewed type-2 immune response that suppresses interferon (IFN) γ-mediated protective immunity <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Nonetheless, IFNγ production by T cells is reduced in non-responders compared to SAG-responders <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Narayan1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. The endogenous production of IFNγ and importantly, its principal inducer IL-12, determine the anti-leishmanial efficacy of SAG in a fully immunocompetent host infected with LD <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Murray1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Murray2" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Following LD infection, the early production of IL-12 is exclusively mediated by dendritic cells (DCs) <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Gorak1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. This tempted us to speculate a possible involvement of DCs in regulating “SAG responsiveness” versus “unresponsiveness” in kala-azar patients.</p><p>DCs normally play a key role in initiating and regulating <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania-</italic>specific T cell reactivity <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Suzue1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bennett1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. However, the T cell stimulatory capacity of DCs depends on their state of activation and maturation. In contrast to mature DCs, immature DCs exhibit a reduced capacity to stimulate T cells due to low expression of MHC and co-stimulatory molecules, and the lack of production of proinflammatory cytokines. Gene expression associated with the development, activation, maturation and antigen-presenting cell (APC) function of DCs is largely regulated by the transcription factor NF-κB <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Rescigno1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Weaver1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. For instance, inhibition of NF-κB activation suppresses DC maturation and APC function <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. NF-κB is a hetero- or homo-dimeric complex of structurally related proteins p50, p52, p65 (RelA), cRel and RelB. In resting cells, NF-κB is sequestered in the cytoplasm by the inhibitory proteins IκBα, IκBβ and IκBε <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ghosh1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. However, cellular activation with wide range of stimuli such as LPS, TNFα and IL-1phosphorylates and thereby activates a multisubunit complex IκB kinase (IKK) consisting of IKKα/IKK1, IKKβ/IKK2 and IKKγ/NEMO <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Karin1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Subsequently, activated IKK promotes downstream events, for example, phosphorylation followed by polyubiquitination and 26S proteasome-mediated degradation of IκB proteins <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ghosh1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. NF-κB dimers then translocate to the nucleus, and bind to consensus sequences to induce gene transcription. Notably, the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K)/AKT pathway has been demonstrated in a variety of models to regulate NF-κB activation <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Madrid1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Guha1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>Studies demonstrated that stimulation with SAG induces the PI3K/AKT pathway and enhances production of proinflammatory cytokines and leishmanicidal effector molecules in Mφ <xref rid="ppat.1000907-MookerjeeBasu1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Furthermore, SAG stimulates NF-κB activation in different cell types, such as CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and peripheral blood mononuclear cells <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Barat1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Importantly, blockade of NF-κB activation is shown to impair γGCS expression in murine Mφ-like cell line <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kurozumi1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. However, direct role of NF-κB in transcriptional regulation of murine γGCS promoter is undefined. With this in mind, the current study was initiated to define the role of SAG in murine DC activation and its regulation by LD isolates with SAG-resistant (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) and SAG-sensitive (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) phenotype. We demonstrate that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection suppresses SAG-induced activation/maturation and γGCS expression of DCs by inhibiting NF-κB activation in a PI3K/AKT-dependent manner.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Sb<sup>S</sup>LD- and Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs respond differentially to SAG treatment</title><p>Although Mφs are regarded as a “primary target” for leishmanial infection, recent studies indicate DC infection with various <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania</italic> spp. including LD <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Tejle1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Marovich1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Indeed, LD infection was observed in both immature bone marrow-derived DC (BMDC) (CD11c<sup>+</sup>CD8α<sup>-</sup>) and splenic DC (sDC) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). To determine the leishmanicidal effect of SAG on intracellular Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD in DCs, BMDCs and sDCs were infected with GFP expressing promastigotes of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strain 2001 (GFP-2001) or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strain R5 (GFP-R5) for 3 hours, stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 24 hours, and the frequency of infected DCs measured via flow cytometry. A comparable level of DC infection was observed with both GFP-2001 and GFP-R5 (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). However, the percentage of BMDCs or sDCs infected with GFP-2001 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) was reduced by 5 to 9-fold following SAG treatment (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). In marked contrast, SAG treatment failed to exhibit any significant effect on GFP-R5 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) infection in DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). Furthermore, analyses via Giemsa staining demonstrated that intracellular amastigotes of other Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains exhibit similar resistance to the SAG-induced leishmanicidal effect in DCs. For instance, a significant reduction in both percentage of infected BMDCs and intracellular parasite number were observed in AG83 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)- and to a lesser extent in 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs after SAG treatment (10 and 20 µg/ml) for 24 and 48 hours (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>). Titration of parasites demonstrated that parasite to DC ratio (multiplicity of infection; MOI) of 10∶1 was the optimum ratio for maximum LD infection in DCs (data not shown). Therefore, this MOI was used for all subsequent experiments unless otherwise stated.</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g001" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>SAG treatment exhibits differential effect on Sb<sup>R</sup>LD- and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs.</title><p>(A) BMDCs and <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> derived sDCs were infected with 2001 promastigotes (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> at a MOI of 10∶1 for overnight, washed thoroughly to remove free parasites and localization of intracellular LD parasites was ascertained via Giemsa staining. (B) BMDCs and sDCs were infected <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with GFP-2001 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or GFP-R5 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) promastigotes, as described above, for 3 hours or left uninfected. Free parasites were removed from DCs by thorough washing. The LD-infected DCs were then cultured with or without SAG treatment (20 µg/ml) for another 24 hours whereas uninfected DCs were left untreated. DCs were immunostained with αCD11c-PE and LD infection in DC was analyzed by FACS. Numbers in upper right quadrant indicate the percentage of LD-infected DCs as represented by CD11c<sup>+</sup>GFP<sup>+</sup> cells. In some experiments (C-F), BMDCs were infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (AG83, 2001) or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (39, GE1F8R) strains for 3 hours or left uninfected as described above. DCs were then washed to remove free parasites and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 48 hours and (C) IL-10, (D) IL-12p70 and (E) TNFα secretion in culture supernatants were measured via ELISA or (F) surface expression of co-stimulatory molecules and MHCs measured via FACS. Open histograms represent untreated DCs and shaded histograms represent DCs plus SAG. For this and all other figures the label “Uninf” represents uninfected DCs. Data are the representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.001 versus DC+AG83; <sup>¶</sup>p = 0.001, <sup>#</sup>p = 0.002 and <sup>**</sup>p = 0.003 versus DC+2001; <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.001, <sup>††</sup>p = 0.004 and <sup>§</sup>p = 0.002 versus DC+SAG (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, the regulation of SAG-induced activation and maturation of DCs by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD was investigated. For this purpose, BMDCs and sDCs were infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes for 3 hours, washed and cultured with or without SAG (20 µg/ml) for an additional 48 hours. The activation and maturation of DCs were determined by analyzing MHC and co-stimulatory molecule expression and secretion of cytokines. Infection of BMDCs and sDCs with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains 39 or GE1F8R induced more IL-10 production as compared with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strains AG83 or 2001 (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref>). Interestingly, IL-10 secretion from Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs was not affected by SAG treatment (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref>). In contrast, SAG treatment significantly inhibited IL-10 secretion by Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref>). Furthermore, SAG-stimulated secretion of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-12p70 and TNFα from DCs were inhibited by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D-E</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2B-C</xref>). Finally, SAG treatment up-regulated CD40, CD80, CD86, MHC-I (H2K<sup>d</sup>) and MHC-II (IA<sup>d</sup>) expression in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>). Consistent with work by other groups <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ato1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Donovan1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, co-stimulatory molecule and MHC expression of untreated BMDCs remained unaltered following Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>). Together, these results demonstrate that SAG treatment protects DCs from Sb<sup>S</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection. Moreover, stimulation with SAG fails to activate and mature Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs, while Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs are still capable of activation and maturation upon SAG treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>SAG treatment induces NF-κB activation in DCs</title><p>Since NF-κB is a key regulator of maturation and APC function of DCs, the effect of SAG treatment on NF-κB activation was investigated. BMDCs were treated with SAG for varying times and DNA binding activity of nuclear NF-κB was determined via electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA). Relative to untreated BMDCs, a 23-fold increase in NF-κB DNA binding activity was initially observed by 0.3 hours, which persisted up to 1 hour after SAG treatment (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Notably, OCT-1 DNA binding was unaltered despite SAG treatment indicating that SAG-induced enhancement of nuclear DNA binding was NF-κB-specific (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Furthermore, supershift analysis using antibodies specific for each Rel family member demonstrated that SAG stimulation of BMDCs induced DNA binding of NF-κB complexes consisting of the p50, p65 and RelB subunits (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). In contrast to SAG, BMDC treatment with varying concentrations (25 to 200 µg/ml) of sodium gluconate for 0.3 hours, or 200 µg/ml of sodium gluconate for various times failed to induce DNA binding activity of NF-κB (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C-D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g002" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Stimulation with SAG increases nuclear NF-κB DNA binding activity in BMDCs.</title><p>BMDCs were treated with SAG (20 µg/ml) or specified concentrations of sodium gluconate (SG) for indicated times or left untreated. (A, C-D) DNA binding activity of nuclear NF-κB to H2K-specific oligonucleotide probe was measured via EMSA. The OCT-1 DNA binding was used as an internal control. Densitometric analysis represents the ratio of intensity of NF-κB to OCT-1 binding per unit area and is represented as arbitrary units. (B) Binding of different NF-κB complexes to H2K-DNA probe was determined by supershift EMSA using rabbit IgG (Control Ab) or Abs specific for different NF-κB subunits. For this and all other figures, control (Cont) lane represents uninfected DCs without SAG stimulation. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Consistent with the EMSA data, SAG treatment for 0.3, 0.5 and 1 hour induced degradation of IκB proteins in BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). Importantly, SAG-induced IκB degradation corresponded to enhanced IκBα phosphorylation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>), which could be due to increased activity of upstream IKK complex. To test this hypothesis, BMDCs were stimulated with SAG for 0.3, 0.5 and 1 hour. IKK signalosome was immunoprecipitated from cytoplasmic extracts and kinase activity of the complex determined by measuring phosphorylation of an IκBα-GST substrate <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. BMDCs stimulated with SAG for 0.3, 0.5 and 1 hour exhibited approximately 3.6 to 4.7-fold increase in IKK activity compared to untreated BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). In comparison, the level of IKK1 and IKK2 proteins were similar in all BMDC extracts (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). The SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding, IκBα degradation and IKK activity were also observed in sDCs (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g003" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>SAG-treated BMDCs exhibit increased phosphorylation and degradation of IκB proteins and IKK activity.</title><p>BMDCs were untreated or stimulated either with 20 µg/ml SAG (A-F) or 500 ng/ml LPS (D-F) for specified times. (A) Expression of IκBα, IκBβ, IκBε and β-actin protein in cytoplasmic extracts was detected by Western blot using the same blot. Densitometric analyses represent the ratio of intensity of the corresponding IκB protein to β-actin expression per unit area and are represented as an arbitrary unit. (B) Cytoplasmic phospho-IκBα versus β-actin protein expression was detected via Western blot with the same blot. (C) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity was determined by measuring phosphorylation of an IκBα-GST substrate. IKK1 and IKK2 protein expression in immunoprecipitated samples was analyzed via Western blot. Densitometric analysis indicates the intensity of phosphorylated (P) IκBα-GST substrate in an arbitrary unit. The levels of (D) phospho-p38MAPK versus p38MAPK, (E) phospho-ERK versus ERK and (F) phospho-JNK versus JNK protein expression in whole cell lysates were determined via Western blot. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Of note, SAG treatment failed to activate the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway in BMDCs. In contrast to LPS stimulation, phosphorylation of p38MAPK, ERK1/ERK2 and JNK was not detected in SAG-treated DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D-F</xref>). Collectively, these findings demonstrate that stimulation with SAG induces activation of the IKK complex, phosphorylation and degradation of IκB proteins and downstream nuclear DNA binding of NF-κB in both BMDCs and sDCs, and that the induction of these events in DC is contributed by antimonial moiety of SAG. Furthermore, among different signaling pathways, which are known to regulate DC activation/maturation, NF-κB signaling is selectively induced by SAG treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection inhibits SAG-induced NF-κB activation in DCs</title><p>The effect(s) of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection on SAG-stimulated NF-κB activation in DCs was determined. BMDCs were infected with either promastigotes or amastigotes of 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) or 2001 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for varying times, stimulated with SAG for 0.3 hours and nuclear NF-κB DNA binding activity to H2K-specific probe measured via EMSA. SAG-induced NF-κB activity was completely inhibited in BMDCs upon infection with either 39 promastigotes (39Pm) or amastigotes (39Am) (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) at all times of LD infection analyzed (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A-B</xref>). In contrast, BMDC infection with 2001 promastigotes (2001Pm) or amastigotes (2001Am) (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for up to 6 and 3 hours, respectively, failed to inhibit SAG-stimulated NF-κB DNA binding (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A-B</xref>). SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding activity was also inhibited in 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected sDCs (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4A</xref>). The ability of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD to block SAG-stimulated NF-κB DNA binding in DCs was not LD strain specific. For example, BMDC infection with promastigotes of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strain GE1F8R (GE1F8RPm), unlike Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strain AG83 (AG83Pm), completely prevented SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g004" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>SAG-induced NF-κB signaling is inhibited in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD- and not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs.</title><p>BMDCs were infected <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with promastigotes (Pm) (A, C, E-F) or amastigotes (Am) (B, D, G) of specified strains of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD at a MOI 10∶1 for indicated times or left uninfected. DCs were then stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 0.3 hours. (A-B) Nuclear DNA binding of NF-κB to H2K-specific probe was measured via EMSA. DNA binding of OCT-1 was used as internal control. Densitometric analyses were determined by measuring the ratio of intensity of NF-κB to OCT-1 binding per unit area and represented as arbitrary units. (C-D) Cytoplasmic IκBα, IκBβ, IκBε and β-actin protein were detected via Western blot with same blot. (E) Phospho-IκBα was detected by Western blot. The same blot was reprobed for β-actin. (F-G) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity and expression of IKK1 and IKK2 were determined as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Our finding that SAG-induced NF-κB activity is inhibited selectively in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected BMDCs was further confirmed by temporal analysis of IκB protein degradation and activation of IKK. BMDC infection with either 2001Pm or 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for up to 6 or 3 hours, respectively, had no significant effect on SAG-induced IκB degradation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C-D</xref>). In contrast, IκB degradation stimulated by SAG was persistently inhibited by 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) regardless of the duration of BMDC infection and form of parasite (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C-D</xref>). SAG-induced IκBα degradation was similarly inhibited in sDCs infected with 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) and BMDCs infected with promastigotes of a different Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strain (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4C-D</xref>). Interestingly, inhibition of SAG-induced IκB degradation corresponded with a reduction in IκBα phosphorylation in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD promastigotes (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C, E</xref>). Furthermore, SAG-induced IKK activation as determined by <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> IKK activity or phosphorylation of IKK1 and IKK2 was inhibited in extracts prepared from BMDCs and sDCs infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4F</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4E-F</xref>). BMDC infection with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD amastigotes also blocked SAG-stimulated IKK activity (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4G</xref>). Additionally, pretreatment of BMDCs with parasite antigen(s) (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDsAg) or culture supernatant (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDs) of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibited SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding activity, IκB degradation and IKK activity; whereas culture supernatant of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDs) or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-derived antigen(s) (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDsAg) did not (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g005" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>DC pretreatment with antigens or culture supernatant of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibits SAG-induced NF-κB pathway.</title><p>BMDCs were either pretreated with antigens prepared from indicated strains of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDsAg) or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDsAg) (A-C) or cultured in RPMI 1640 complete medium containing culture supernatants of indicated strains of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDs) or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDs) at a complete medium to supernatant ratios of 1∶1 (D) or 1∶3 (D-F) for 3 hours. BMDCs were then washed and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 0.3 hours. (A, D-E) Nuclear NF-κB binding to H2K-DNA probe or OCT-1 DNA binding was measured via EMSA. (B, F) Cytoplasmic IκBα, IκBβ, IκBε and β-actin expression were detected by Western blot using the same blot. (C) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity was determined as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> and the same blot was reprobed for IKK1 and IKK2 protein. Data are representative of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>As demonstrated in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A-D</xref>; SAG-induced NF-κB activation was inhibited in BMDCs infected at a MOI 10∶1 (promastigote or amastigote to DC) with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes or amastigotes for 24 or 6 hours, respectively, similar to Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected BMDCs. Accordingly, we tested whether the increased intracellular parasite number at these time points of infection rendered 20 µg/ml of SAG insufficient to activate NF-κB. In fact, number of intracellular 2001 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) was significantly increased if BMDCs were infected with promastigotes for 24 hours rather than 6 hours (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5A</xref>). Likewise, BMDCs infected with amastigotes of the above LD strains for 6 hours exhibited increased intracellular parasite number compared to BMDCs infected for 3 hours (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5B</xref>). Notably, SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced NF-κB DNA binding and IκBα degradation were detected despite the presence of intracellular parasites in BMDCs infected with 2001Pm and 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 6 and 3 hours, respectively (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4A-D</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5A-B</xref>). Therefore, these two time points of BMDC infection were selected as a “reference” to analyze the basis of defective SAG-induced NF-κB activation in BMDCs infected with 2001Pm or 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 24 or 6 hours, respectively. Initially, the association of increased intracellular parasite number with impairment of SAG-induced NF-κB activation was verified in both BMDCs infected with 2001Pm or 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 24 or 6 hours, respectively. For this purpose, BMDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 24 hours at varying MOIs and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 0.3 hours. Despite LD infection for fixed duration (24 hours), this approach established varying levels of intracellular parasite number, which was elevated in BMDCs infected at MOI 10∶1 compared to other MOIs (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S6A</xref>). BMDC infection with both 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) at a MOI 10∶1 inhibited SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding activity and IκBα degradation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A-B</xref>). However, SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding activity and IκBα degradation were observed only in 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs but not 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs when BMDC infection was done at MOIs 2.5∶1 and 5∶1 (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A-B</xref>). Notably, at each of these MOIs both 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs and 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs had comparable level of intracellular parasite number (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S6A</xref>). Using identical MOIs for BMDC infection, similar results were obtained when the intracellular parasite number and SAG-induced NF-κB activation were analyzed in BMDCs infected for 6 hours with 39Am (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) and 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figures 6C-D</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6B</xref>). These findings suggest that irrespective of the form of parasite, 2001 (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) differentially regulate SAG-induced NF-κB signaling in DCs with low intracellular parasite number.</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g006" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>SAG-induced NF-κB activation is restored in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD- but not Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs despite prolonged infection.</title><p>BMDCs were infected with promastigotes of 2001 (2001Pm) (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and 39 (39Pm) (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) (A-B, E-F); or amastigotes of 2001 (2001Am) (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and 39 (39Am) (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) (C-D, G-H) for indicated times at MOIs as specified (A-D) or 10∶1 (E-H). BMDCs were then stimulated with specified concentrations of SAG for 0.3 hours. (A, C, E, G) Nuclear NF-κB binding to H2K-DNA probe or OCT-1 DNA binding was measured via EMSA. (B, D, F, H) Cytoplasmic IκBα and β-actin expression were detected by Western blot using the same blot. SAG<sub>20</sub> and SAG<sub>40</sub> represent stimulation of BMDCs with 20 and 40 µg/ml of SAG, respectively. Data are representative of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>It is possible that with increased intracellular parasite number 2001(Sb<sup>S</sup>LD), similar to 39 (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD), developed the capacity to inhibit SAG-induced NF-κB activation and that occurred when BMDCs were infected at a MOI 10∶1 with 2001Pm or 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 24 and 6 hours, respectively. However, this possibility was ruled out when NF-κB activation in response to 20 and 40 µg/ml of SAG treatment was analyzed in BMDCs infected for 6 and 24 hours with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) at a MOI of 10∶1. The effect of SAG (40 µg/ml) stimulation was also verified in BMDCs infected similarly with 2001Am or 39Am for 3 and 6 hours. Stimulation with both 20 and 40 µg/ml of SAG induced NF-κB DNA binding and IκBα degradation in BMDCs infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 6 hours (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6E-F</xref>). In contrast, BMDCs infected for 24 hours with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) exhibited enhanced NF-κB DNA binding and IκBα degradation only when stimulated with 40 µg/ml of SAG (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6E-F</xref>). Similarly, the inhibition of SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding and IκBα degradation due to BMDC infection with 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 6 hours was overcome by increasing the dose of SAG from 20 to 40 µg/ml (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6G-H</xref>). On the contrary, 39Pm/39Am (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) continued to suppress NF-κB DNA binding and IκBα degradation at various durations of infection tested irrespective of dose of SAG used for stimulation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6E-H</xref>). Together, these results demonstrate that SAG-induced NF-κB signaling is impaired by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection of DCs.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibits SAG-induced NF-κB signaling, DC activation and leishmanicidal effects by suppressing the PI3K/AKT pathway in an IL-10-independent manner</title><p>Stimulation with SAG induces PI3K/AKT activation in Mφ <xref rid="ppat.1000907-MookerjeeBasu1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Furthermore, PI3K/AKT regulates the NF-κB pathway in DCs via IKK <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Therefore, the possibility that SAG-induced activation of NF-κB in DCs is PI3K/AKT-dependent was investigated. Initially, the effect of SAG stimulation on AKT activation was assessed by measuring phosphorylation of AKT. Compared to unstimulated BMDCs, SAG treatment induced a 5 to 7-fold increase in AKT phosphorylation in BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). Notably, SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation was not observed in BMDCs pretreated with PI3K inhibitors wortmannin (Wort) or Ly294002 (Ly) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). Next, the effect of PI3K inhibitors on SAG-induced NF-κB signaling was determined. Pretreatment with Wort or Ly effectively blocked SAG-induced IKK activity, IκBα degradation and nuclear NF-κB DNA binding in BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B-D</xref>). Importantly, infection of BMDCs and sDCs with 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) but not 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 3 hours inhibited SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced AKT phosphorylation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7E</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>). SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced AKT phosphorylation was also inhibited due to BMDCs infection for 1 and 3 hours with 39Am (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) but not 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7F</xref>). Similar to 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs, SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced AKT phosphorylation, however, was not observed if BMDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 24 hours (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7G</xref>). Interestingly, AKT phosphorylation was observed in these 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs but not 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs upon stimulation with of 40 µg/ml of SAG (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7G</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g007" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>PI3K/AKT suppression by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibits SAG-induced NF-κB signaling in an IL-10 independent manner.</title><p>BMDCs were infected with promastigotes of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strains 2001(2001Pm) (E, G-J) and AG83 (AG83Pm) (H), and Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains 39 (39Pm) (E, G-J) and GE1F8R (GE1F8Pm) (H); or amastigotes of 2001(2001Am) and 39 (39Am) (F) for indicated times or left uninfected as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. Subsequently, BMDCs were stimulated or not with 20 (A-J) or 40 (G) µg/ml of SAG for specified times. For experiments (A-D), uninfected BMDCs were treated with 200 nM Wort or 50 µM Ly for 1 hour prior to SAG stimulation. In some experiments (I-J), BMDCs infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 or 24 hours were treated with 10 µg/ml of neutralizing αIL-10 mAb or isotype control Ab as described in <xref rid="s4" ref-type="sec">Materials and Methods</xref> section or left untreated, and stimulated with SAG. (A, E-G, I) AKT phosphorylation in cytoplasmic extract was determined via Western blot and the same blot was reprobed for AKT protein. (B) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity was measured as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. IKK1 and IKK2 protein expression were determined via Western blot using the same blot. (C) Cytoplasmic IκBα and β-actin were detected by Western blot with the same blot. (D, J) Nuclear DNA binding activity of NF-κB to H2K-DNA probe or OCT-1 DNA binding was determined via EMSA. (H) Secretion of IL-10 was measured via ELISA. SAG<sub>20</sub> and SAG<sub>40</sub> represent stimulation of BMDCs with 20 and 40 µg/ml of SAG, respectively. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus DC; <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.005, <sup>‡</sup>p = 0.006 and <sup>§</sup>p = 0.007 versus DC+AG83Pm; <sup>#</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus DC+2001Pm of respective times (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g007.jpg"/></fig><p>Since Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection stimulated high IL-10 secretion by DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref>), the possibility that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibited SAG-induced PI3K/AKT (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7E-F</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>) and NF-κB pathways (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>) in an IL-10-dependent manner was investigated by using a neutralizing αIL-10 Ab. Temporal analyses demonstrated that significant IL-10 production by BMDCs was initially detected after an infection for 12 hours with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7H</xref>). Compared to Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected BMDCs, IL-10 production was significantly increased in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD for 24 and 48 hours (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7H</xref>). Strikingly, SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and NF-κB DNA binding activity were not restored in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD for 3 and 24 hours despite αIL-10 Ab treatment (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7I-J</xref>). However, αIL-10 Ab treatment effectively prevented inhibition of LPS-induced NF-κB DNA binding in BMDCs pretreated with IL-10 (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S8</xref>). Therefore, this finding ruled out the involvement of IL-10 in suppression of SAG-induced PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected BMDCs.</p><p>Consistent with previous report <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mukherjee1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, an overexpression of ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter MRPA (PGPA) was observed in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains 39Pm and GE1F8RPm (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S9A</xref>). Whether MRPA plays any role in mediating the inhibitory effects of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD on SAG-induced PI3K/AKT and NF-κB activation in DC was then investigated. Accordingly, SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and NF-κB activation in BMDCs infected for 3 hours with 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD), 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and isogenic 2001Pm expressing MRPA (2001Pm-MRPA) (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S9B</xref>) were compared. The latter was developed by transfecting 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) with a DNA construct expressing MRPA. A complete blockade of SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and NF-κB DNA binding activity was observed in 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A-B</xref>). In contrast, SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and NF-κB DNA binding activity were detected in 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A-B</xref>). However, infection of BMDCs with 2001Pm-MRPA inhibited SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and DNA binding activity of NF-κB in BMDCs, albeit partially (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A-B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g008" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>2001Pm-MRPA but not 2001Pm inhibits SAG-induced AKT phosphorylation and DNA binding activity of NF-κB.</title><p>BMDCs were infected for 3 hours with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD), 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD), 2001Pm expressing MRPA (2001Pm-MRPA) or 2001Pm transfected with empty vector (2001Pm-EV) and stimulated with 20 µg/ml of SAG as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. (A) Expression of phosphorylated (P) AKT and AKT were measured in whole cell lysates via Western blot using the same membrane. Densitometric readings represent the ratio of intensity of phosphorylated (P) AKT protein to AKT expression per unit area and are represented as arbitrary units. (B) Nuclear NF-κB and OCT-1 DNA binding activities were measured via EMSA. Densitometric analysis represents the ratio of intensity of NF-κB to OCT-1 binding per unit area and is represented as arbitrary units. Data are representative of two independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g008.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, a direct role for PI3K in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD regulation of SAG-induced proinflammatory cytokine secretion and leishmanicidal effects in DCs was investigated using Wort or Ly. In contrast to 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs, SAG-stimulated IL-12 and TNFα production were observed in both uninfected and 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9A-B</xref>). However, pretreatment of uninfected and 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs with Wort or Ly significantly inhibited SAG-induced secretion of IL-12 and TNFα (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9A-B</xref>). Furthermore, PI3K inhibitors prevented SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced reduction of percentage of infected BMDCs and intracellular parasite number in BMDCs infected for 3 hours with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9C-D</xref>). Importantly, BMDCs infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) for 24 hours exhibited a significant reduction in both percentage of infected BMDCs and intracellular parasite number only when treated with 40 but not 20 µg/ml of SAG (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S10</xref>). Treatment of these 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs with Wort or Ly blocked the leishmanicidal effects of SAG (40 µg/ml) (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S10</xref>). In contrast to 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs, SAG-induced leishmanicidal effects were not observed in 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs regardless of duration of infection and dose of SAG (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figures 9C-D</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref>). In addition, BMDC infection for 3 hours with 2001Pm-MRPA, unlike 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD), partly but significantly suppressed SAG-induced leishmanicidal effects (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9E-F</xref>). Collectively, these data demonstrate that blockade of PI3K/AKT pathway by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD impairs SAG-induced NF-κB signaling, DC activation and leishmanicidal function and that is IL-10-independent. Furthermore, these inhibitory effects of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD are partly contributed by MRPA.</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g009" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibits SAG-induced proinflammatory cytokine production and leishmanicidal effects by suppressing PI3K/AKT pathway.</title><p>BMDCs were infected for 3 hours with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strain 39Pm (A-F); Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strain 2001Pm (A-F); 2001Pm expressing MRPA (2001Pm-MRPA) (E-F); or 2001Pm transfected with empty vector (2001Pm-EV) (E-F) or left uninfected as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. BMDCs were washed and then stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 48 (A-B) or 24 (C-F) hours. For experiments (A-D); uninfected BMDCs (A-B), and BMDCs infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) (A-D) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) (C-D) were treated with 200 nM Wort or 50 µM Ly for 1 hour prior to SAG treatment. (A-B) Secretion of IL-12 (A) and TNFα (B) were determined by ELISA. (C-F) Giemsa staining was performed to determine the percentage of infected BMDCs (C, E) and number of intracellular amastigotes per 1000 BMDCs (D, F). Data are representative of three independent experiments.<sup> *</sup>p&lt;0.001 and <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus DC+SAG; <sup>**</sup>p&lt;0.001 and <sup>††</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus DC+2001Pm+SAG; <sup>#</sup>p&lt;0.04 versus DC+2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or DC+2001Pm-EV (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g009.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Inhibition of NF-κB activation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD suppresses SAG-stimulated murine γGCS heavy-chain gene expression in DC</title><p>Previous studies have demonstrated an association of antimony resistance of leishmanial parasite with γGCS heavy-chain (γGCS<sub>hc</sub>) gene expression of host <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. The latter encodes the catalytic subunit of γGCS <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Cai1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In fact, a comparative analysis demonstrated that SAG-induced murine γGCS<sub>hc</sub> (mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>) expression was unaffected in 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs but selectively inhibited in 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10A</xref>). The molecular basis for Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-mediated suppression of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression in DC was then explored. Despite SAG stimulation, the inhibition of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression could be due to suppression of NF-κB activation in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected BMDC. To investigate this possibility, the regulatory role of NF-κB in mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter activity was initially ascertained. An approximately 1.0 kb DNA sequence upstream of the transcriptional start site of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene (<italic toggle="yes">Mus musculus</italic> chromosome 9 genomic contig, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NT_039474.7">NT_039474.7</ext-link>; GI:149260095) was selected as the promoter region using Ensembl and UCSC browsers. The mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter was found to contain a putative NF-κB binding site <named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> that differs from the consensus sequence <named-content content-type="gene">GGGRNNYYCC</named-content> at positions 7, 9 and 10 (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10B</xref>). ChIP analysis demonstrated that SAG treatment of BMDCs induced NF-κB binding to −991/−673 region of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter that includes the sequence <named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10B-C</xref>). Furthermore, DNA binding of NF-κB complexes consisting of p50, RelB and p65 subunits specifically to the sequence</p><fig position="float" id="ppat-1000907-g010" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000907.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Suppression of SAG-induced mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD is NF-κB-dependent.</title><p>Both uninfected BMDCs (A, C-E, G) and BMDCs infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 hours (A, G) were stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for specified times as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. (A) The mRNA expression of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> versus mGAPDH was determined via RT-PCR. Densitometric data represent ratio of intensity of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> to mGAPDH mRNA expression per unit area and are presented as an arbitrary unit. (B) Schematic presentation of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter indicating the position of NF-κB binding site and ChIP primers (P1, P2). (C) NF-κB binding to −991/−673 region of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter was examined by ChIP using the primers shown in B and indicated Abs. Amplification of mGAPDH promoter and chromatin immunoprecipitated by rabbit IgG were used as negative controls, and input DNA (2%) as an internal control. (D, G) Nuclear NF-κB DNA binding to mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter-specific probes containing wild-type NF-κB binding site (WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe) (D, G) or mutant NF-κB binding site (Mut-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe) (D) was determined via EMSA. OCT-1 DNA binding activity was used as internal control. (E) DNA binding of different NF-κB complexes to WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe was determined via supershift analysis using rabbit IgG (Control Ab) or Abs specific for indicated NF-κB subunits. (F) NF-κB-mediated regulation of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter activity was determined by reporter assay. NIH3T3 cells were co-transfected with <italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> luciferase vector (pRL-CMV) and firefly luciferase reporter plasmid containing mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter with wild-type (p987-luc) or mutant (Mut p987-luc) NF-κB binding site. In addition, all co-transfections contained pEGFP-C1 empty vector or pEGFP-p65 and/or pEGFP-IκBαΔN. Twenty-four hours later, firefly and <italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> luciferase activities in cell lysates were measured. The data represent the fold induction of firefly/<italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> luciferase activity ratio relative to pEGFP-C1-transfected cells. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.001 versus NIH3T3+p987-luc+pEGFP-C1 and <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.001 versus NIH3T3+p987-luc+pEGFP-p65 (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.g010.jpg"/></fig><p><named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> in SAG-treated BMDCs was confirmed via EMSA using mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probes containing wild-type sequence <sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup> (WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe) or mutant sequence <named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>CTCTAAGAAT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> (Mut-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe) (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10D</xref>) and supershift analysis (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10E</xref>).</p><p>Next, the role of NF-κB binding site <named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> in regulation of promoter activity of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene was tested via luciferase reporter assay using p987-luc and Mut p987-luc, the reporter constructs of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter fragment containing wild-type and mutant NF-κB binding site, respectively. Compared to control vector (pEGFP-C1) transfected cells, expression of NF-κB subunit p65 strongly induced luciferase activity of p987-luc (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10F</xref>). This enhanced luciferase activity of p987-luc was completely blocked upon co-transfection with pEGFP-dominant negative IκBα (pEGFP-IκBαΔN) encoding the NF-κB-specific inhibitor, IκBαΔN (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10F</xref>). The lack of luciferase activity of Mut p987-luc despite p65 expression (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10F</xref>) further indicated that the sequence <named-content content-type="gene"><sup>-904</sup>GGGGAAACTT<sup>-895</sup></named-content> is required for NF-κB-mediated transcriptional activation of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene. Interestingly, SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding to WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe was inhibited in 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10G</xref>). In contrast, SAG-induced NF-κB DNA binding to WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe was readily detected in 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD)-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10G</xref>). These findings suggest that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD suppresses SAG-induced mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression in DC by inhibiting NF-κB DNA binding to the mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Antimonial drugs activate innate effector cells to promote an anti-leishmanial effect <xref rid="ppat.1000907-MookerjeeBasu1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. However, regulation of antimonial drug-mediated immune activation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD is ill-defined. This is of particular interest in view of the lack of efficacy of antimonial compounds reported for SAG-unresponsive kala-azar patients. Recent studies indicated that DCs play a key role in regulating anti-leishmanial immune response <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Gorak1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bennett1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Qi1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Accordingly, the role of SAG in activation of DCs, its regulation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD and the molecular mechanism involved therein were investigated. Here we provide evidence that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD differentially regulate activation of DCs. Furthermore, SAG-induced signaling pathway associated with DC activation is selectively targeted by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection.</p><p>In an agreement with an earlier report <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Tejle1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, both BMDCs and <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> sDCs were infected <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with LD promastigotes (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). The “SAG-resistant” phenotype did not significantly affect the efficiency of LD infection, but did impact the susceptibility of LD to the leishmanicidal effects of SAG. In contrast, SAG treatment significantly impaired DC infectivity of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD including reduction in both intracellular parasite number and percentage of infected DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1B</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The differential response of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD towards SAG treatment was also noted in their ability to regulate activation and maturation of DCs. In contrast to Sb<sup>S</sup>LD, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection inhibited SAG-induced proinflammatory cytokine secretion and up-regulation of co-stimulatory molecule and MHC expression in DCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D-F</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2B-C</xref>). Noteworthy is that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD induced increased IL-10 secretion by DCs compared to Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref>). This finding reinforces the inherent ability of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD to differentially immunoregulate DC activation. Previous studies demonstrated that IL-10, a potent suppressor of anti-leishmanial immunity, minimizes responsiveness to SAG <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Murphy1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Murray3" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Therefore, increased IL-10 production may play a critical role in disease pathogenesis in the host infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD.</p><p>The second important finding arising from this study is that both promastigotes and amastigotes of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD differentially regulate SAG-induced NF-κB activation in DCs. Indeed, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection blocks SAG-induced NF-κB signaling by suppressing IKK activation, and IκB protein phosphorylation and degradation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>). In this regard, it should be noted that SAG stimulation of uninfected DCs induced concomitant degradation of all three IκB proteins (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>), although degradation of IκBε generally occurs with delayed kinetics upon cellular activation <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Dobrovolskaia1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Whiteside1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. This finding, however, is consistent with a number of studies reporting rapid degradation of IκBβ and IκBε depending on the type of cell and the nature of the stimulation <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Dobrovolskaia1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Laskov1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Nevertheless, the suppression of SAG-induced IκB protein degradation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD ultimately impaired nuclear NF-κB DNA binding activity (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>). Surprisingly, BMDC infection at a MOI 10∶1 with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes or amastigotes for 24 or 6 hours, respectively, also inhibited SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced NF-κB activation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced NF-κB activation was restored in these BMDCs but not Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected BMDCs upon lowering the MOIs (&lt;10∶1) for BMDC infection, which established reduced levels of intracellular parasite number compared to MOI 10∶1(<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figures 6A-D</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6</xref>). This finding suggests that intracellular parasite number plays a critical role for differential regulation of SAG-induced NF-κB activation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD. The early inhibition of NF-κB activation in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD amastigote versus promastigote-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>) is in agreement with the fact that DCs internalize amastigotes more efficiently than promastigotes <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Zhao1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Garg1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. However, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD still retain their ability to differentially regulate SAG-induced NF-κB activation in BMDCs with high intracellular parasite number. This conclusion is supported by results demonstrating that despite stimulation with 40 µg/ml of SAG, NF-κB activation was blocked in BMDCs infected for above durations with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD amastigotes or promastigotes at a MOI 10∶1 but readily observed in BMDCs infected similarly with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). Here, the SAG dose was increased from 20 to 40 µg/ml keeping in mind that SAG therapy requires multiple dosing schedules to ensure enough antimony accumulation in tissues of kala-azar patients <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Chulay1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Furthermore, equivalent and/or increased concentrations of SAG have previously been used by other groups <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Singh1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Singh2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Under identical conditions, the recurrence of NF-κB activation in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected BMDCs by increasing the dose of SAG from 20 to 40 µg/ml (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>) further suggested that 20 µg/ml of SAG was insufficient to activate NF-κB in these BMDCs due to high intracellular parasite number.</p><p>Noteworthy is that the inhibitory effect on NF-κB activation was not dependent on live Sb<sup>R</sup>LD. For instance, parasite antigens derived from Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDsAg) and Sb<sup>R</sup>LD culture supernatant (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDs) but not the Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-derived antigens (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDsAg) or culture supernatant of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDs) efficiently inhibited SAG-induced NF-κB activation (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). These findings suggest that the inhibition of NF-κB activation is specific for Sb<sup>R</sup>LD/Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-derived antigen(s)/factor(s) secreted by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD. Strikingly, the inhibition of NF-κB activation correlated with suppression of SAG-induced DC activation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref>, <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). Studies involving gene transfer of a modified IκBα recombinant into immature DC demonstrated that blockade of NF-κB activation alone prevents up-regulation of co-stimulatory molecule expression and production of proinflammatory cytokines <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Poligone1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Weaver1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Based on these reports coupled with our own observations, we conclude that the Sb<sup>R</sup>LD blocks SAG-induced NF-κB signaling to prevent DC activation and maturation.</p><p>Our results further suggest that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD inhibits IKK and NF-κB activation by blocking SAG-induced PI3K/AKT signaling. SAG stimulation of DCs induced PI3K activation as measured by phosphorylation of AKT, a downstream signaling mediator of PI3K (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7A</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>). Blockade of PI3K/AKT activation by Wort or Ly completely suppressed SAG-stimulated IKK activity and NF-κB signaling (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A-D</xref>), indicating a direct involvement of the PI3K/AKT pathway in NF-κB activation by SAG in DCs. Importantly, PI3K/AKT activation is negatively regulated by Src homology phosphotyrosine phosphatase (SHP)-1, which dephosphorylates PI3K <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Cuevas1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Furthermore, SHP-1activity is inhibited by SAG <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Pathak1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Therefore, blockade of SHP-1activity by SAG may indirectly promote PI3K phosphorylation and activation of downstream AKT, IKK and NF-κB in DCs. Similar to uninfected DCs, SAG treatment induced PI3K/AKT activation in DCs infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes for 3 hours and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD amastigotes for 1 and 3 hours (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7E-F</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>). Importantly, PI3K inhibitors impaired SAG (20 µg/ml)-induced NF-κB pathway, DC activation and leishmanicidal effects in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes for 3 hours (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">Figures 9</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s011" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref>). These results suggest the inability of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD to regulate SAG-induced PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways. Consequently, SAG continues to exhibit leishmanicidal effects in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs. The inability of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD to regulate SAG-induced leishmanicidal effects was maintained despite BMDC infection for 24 hours with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes. This was apparent when increased dose of SAG (40 µg/ml) was used for treatment (<xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S10</xref>). In fact, treatment with 40 µg/ml of SAG restored AKT phosphorylation and therefore exhibited leishmanicidal effects in a PI3K-dependent manner in these Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected BMDCs (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7G</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref>). Interestingly, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection mimicked the effects of the PI3K inhibitors in that all SAG-induced events as mentioned above were also blocked by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD regardless of duration of infection, form of parasite and dose of SAG (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figures 7</xref>, <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s011" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref>). One intriguing possibility is that IL-10 produced by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs mediated Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-induced suppression of PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figures 1C</xref>, <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2A</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>). This correlation can be made because IL-10 inhibits AKT activation and NF-κB pathway in DCs <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Furthermore, the inhibitory effects of IL-10 on DCs can be mediated in an autocrine manner <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Corinti1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. However, this is unlikely since SAG-induced NF-κB activation was inhibited even in BMDCs infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD for 1 and 3 hours, when IL-10 production was not detected (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">7H</xref>). Moreover, neutralization of IL-10 produced by BMDCs upon Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection for 24 hours failed to block Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-induced inhibition of PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7H-J</xref>). Therefore, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD infection of BMDCs for up to 24 hours inhibits SAG-induced PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways in an IL-10-independent manner and eventually impairs DC activation.</p><p>Another key finding is that the suppression of NF-κB activation by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD inhibits not only DC activation but also SAG-induced mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression in DC (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>). Importantly, regulation of host γGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression and therefore host GSH level by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD plays a key role for antimony resistance in LD infection <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Although regulation of γGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression by NF-κB was shown in a murine Mφ-like cell line by blocking NF-κB activation <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kurozumi1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, our observation establishes a direct role for NF-κB in mediating the promoter activity of the mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10C-F</xref>). Interestingly, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD blocked SAG-induced mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression in DC by preventing NF-κB binding to the mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene promoter (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figure 10G</xref>). This suggests a key role for NF-κB in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-mediated suppression of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression in DC. Our findings (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g010" ref-type="fig">Figures 10A</xref> and <xref rid="ppat.1000907.s012" ref-type="supplementary-material">S12</xref>) are consistent with the recent work by Carter and colleagues demonstrating that Sb<sup>R</sup>LD transcriptionally down-regulate host γGCS<sub>hc</sub> expression and up-regulate their own γGCS<sub>hc</sub> (LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub>) expression <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Whereas Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-induced inhibition of host γGCS expression reduces host GSH level and impairs reduction of Sb<sup>V</sup> to toxic Sb<sup>III</sup> form; elevated expression of LD γGCS by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD restores GSH level that promotes efflux of SAG and confers protection against oxidative stress <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>The mechanism of antimony resistance in clinical LD isolates is unknown and may differ from laboratory-derived resistant parasites <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The true markers of clinical antimony resistance in LD isolates are still lacking <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Croft1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. A gene, PG1, is reported to confer antimony resistance in clinical isolates of LD <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Singh2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kothari1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In addition, enhanced expression of several other genes including MRPA and proteophosphoglycans (PPG) was demonstrated in antimony-resistant compared to antimony-sensitive field isolates (Salotra P, Singh R, Nakhasi H. 2005. Clinical Microbiology and Infection. Vol 11, Suppl 2: 47) <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mukherjee1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Samant1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. As an initial effort to determine whether any Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-specific factor(s) mediated the suppression of SAG-induced NF-κB signaling and leishmanicidal effects in DCs, the role for MRPA was investigated. Results obtained using 2001Pm and its isogenic strain expressing MRPA (2001Pm-MRPA) showed that the inhibitory effect of 2001Pm-MRPA on SAG-induced PI3K/AKT and NF-κB pathways and leishmanicidal activities mimics that of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD to some extent (<xref rid="ppat-1000907-g008" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref> and <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). However, the real bearing of this observation in naturally occurring antimony-resistant LD isolates is still questionable and needs detailed investigation further. Moreover, the effects of SAG are likely to be inhibited in DCs by other Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-specific factor(s) also. The relative contribution of these parasite-specific factors in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-mediated suppression of DC activation is currently under investigation. Furthermore, an association of antimony resistance with genetic variation among LD strains has been proposed <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Recent studies demonstrated that due to high genetic polymorphism, strain 39 is remarkably distinct not only from antimony-sensitive strain 2001 but also from other antimony-resistant clinical LD isolates exhibiting homology with antimony-sensitive parasites <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. On the other hand, the antimony-sensitive strains 2001 and Dd8 exhibit significant genetic similarity <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. The extreme genetic polymorphism might be a potential cause of antimony resistance in strain 39 <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. These reports together with our findings emphasize the notion that antimony resistance of clinical LD isolates is “multifactorial” <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>SAG unresponsiveness in kala-azar patients also entails a number of host-regulated events including dominance of a type-2 T cell response and altered host gene expression <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Thakur1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Narayan1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Our findings demonstrate that SAG treatment induces PI3K-dependent NF-κB activation in DCs, which is blocked by Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection. Dysregulation of SAG-induced NF-κB activation favors persistent survival of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD in DCs despite SAG treatment by: 1) inhibiting NF-κB-dependent mγGCS expression, a key mediator of Sb<sup>V</sup> reduction to Sb<sup>III</sup>, and 2) preventing DC activation and maturation required for the initiation of the anti-leishmanial immune response. Notably, a heterogeneous response to SAG treatment may be observed in humans. This possibility is raised by a report demonstrating that SAG treatment of monocyte-derived DCs restores their capacity to respond to LPS in ∼60% of type 1diabetes patients <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mollah1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Importantly, some variability in SAG responsiveness is also reported in kala-azar patients <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Thakur2" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. It is speculated that the genetic differences among individuals may influence the response following SAG therapy in the patients infected with same <italic toggle="yes">Leishmania</italic> species and living in the same endemic area <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Ameen1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Further studies are needed to define how genetic variation, if any, influences the outcome of SAG treatment in kala-azar patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Animals</title><p>BALB/c mice and golden hamsters (<italic toggle="yes">Mesocricetus auratus</italic>) were maintained and bred under pathogen-free conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Use of both mice and hamsters was approved by the Institutional Animal Ethics Committees of Institute of Microbial Technology and Indian Institute of Chemical Biology, India. All animal experimentations were performed according to the National Regulatory Guidelines issued by CPSEA (Committee for the Purpose of Supervision of Experiments on Animals), Ministry of Environment and Forest, Govt. of India.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Parasite cultures and preparation of soluble antigen from LD</title><p>Sb<sup>R</sup>LD [GE1F8R (MHOM/IN/89/GE1), 39, R5] and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD [AG83 (MHOM/IN/83/AG83), 2001] strains are gifts from Dr. Neeloo Singh (Central Drug Research Institute, India) and Dr. Shyam Sundar (Banaras Hindu University, India) and were maintained in golden hamsters as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Singh2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mukhopadhyay1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Singh3" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Amastigotes were obtained from spleens of infected hamsters as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Hart1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. Subsequently, amastigotes were transformed into promastigotes and maintained as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Chakraborty1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. GFP-2001 and GFP-R5 are gifts from Dr. Neeloo Singh and were maintained in M199 complete medium (10% FBS, penicillin/streptomycin) with 720 µg/ml geneticin disulfate (G418) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Dube1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Soluble antigens were prepared from Sb<sup>S</sup>LD and Sb<sup>R</sup>LD promastigotes (10<sup>9</sup>/ml) as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Chakraborty1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Transfection of 2001Pm</title><p>2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) at mid log or stationary phase were washed twice with electroporation buffer (21 mM HEPES, pH 7.05; 137 mM NaCl; 5 mM KCl; 0.7 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>; 6 mM glucose). The promastigotes were resuspended in ice-cold electroporation buffer to a final concentration of 10<sup>7</sup>/ml. An aliquot (400 µl) of parasite suspension was mixed with 35–40 µg of chilled pGEM 7ZF α-neo-α <italic toggle="yes">L. tarentolae</italic> MRPA or pGEM 7ZF α-neo-α DNA (kind gifts from Dr. Marc Ouellette, Laval University, Canada), transferred to a 2-mm gap cuvette and electroporated using BIO-RAD Gene-Pulser X cell instrument at 450 V and 500 µF (3.5 to 4 milli-seconds pulse time). After electroporation, parasites were immediately placed on ice for 10 minutes and cultured at 22°C for 24 hours in Schneider's insect medium with 1500 µg/ml paromomycin and 10 µM Biopterin. Subsequently, 40 µg/ml of G418 was added to the parasite culture. After 24 hours, 1 ml of this promastigote culture was transferred to a new flask containing 5 ml of fresh medium with 10 µM biopterin and 120 µg/ml G418. The culture was maintained for one month under drug pressure (once per week) to obtain the stable transfectants. The mRNA expression of MRPA in these stable transfectants was verified via RT-PCR.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>DC preparation</title><p>BMDCs and sDCs were prepared from male or female BALB/c mice between 8–12 weeks of age as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Flow cytometric analyses indicated &gt;85% and ∼90% purity of BMDCs and sDCs, respectively, based on CD11c expression.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>DC infection with promastigotes or amastigotes of LD</title><p>DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were infected <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> at specified MOIs either with amastigotes of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD; or promastigotes of stationary phase Sb<sup>R</sup>LD, Sb<sup>S</sup>LD or respective GFP-LD for indicated times in a 6-well plate in RPMI 1640 complete medium (10% FBS, penicillin/streptomycin, L-glutamine, sodium pyruvate, non-essential amino acids, 2-mercaptoethanol). Subsequently, DCs were washed, resuspended in RPMI 1640 complete medium and stimulated with SAG (10, 20 and 40 µg/ml) of clinical grade or sodium gluconate (25, 50, 100 and 200 µg/ml) for specified times. The doses of SAG mentioned here and for all experiments represent the concentration of Sb<sup>V</sup>. DC infection with GFP-Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or GFP-Sb<sup>S</sup>LD was determined via flow cytometry. SAG containing 20 µg/ml of Sb<sup>V</sup>, and 35 µg/ml of sodium gluconate had equivalent molar concentration. Sodium gluconate was purchased from Acros Organics, New Jersey, USA. SAG was obtained as kind gift from Albert David Ltd., Kolkata, India. For other experiments, DCs (2.5×10<sup>5</sup>/ml) were adhered on 22×22 mm cover slips, infected with promastigotes/amastigotes of Sb<sup>S</sup>LD or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and treated with SAG for indicated times. The number of intracellular parasites in DCs was determined via Giemsa staining. In some experiments, DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD promastigotes for 3 hours or left uninfected. Alternatively, infection of DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) with LD promastigotes was done for specified times. DCs were then treated or not with Wort (200 nM) or Ly (50 µM) (Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA) 1 hour prior to SAG stimulation as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In some cases, DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were infected with Sb<sup>S</sup>LD or Sb<sup>R</sup>LD promastigotes for 3 and 24 hours or left uninfected. Neutralizing αIL-10 monoclonal Ab (10 µg/ml)/isotype control rat IgG2<sub>b</sub> Ab (10 µg/ml) (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA) were added at 2<sup>nd</sup> hour of BMDC infection. After infection, DCs were washed and stimulated with SAG for 0.3 hours.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>DC pretreatment with soluble antigens/culture supernatant of LD or IL-10</title><p>DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were pretreated for 3 hours with 50 µg/ml soluble antigens derived from Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDsAg) or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDsAg) and stimulated with SAG for 0.3 hours in a 6-well plate. Alternatively, Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD promastigotes (10<sup>6</sup>/ml) were grown in M199 complete medium till the parasite concentration reached ≥10<sup>7</sup>/ml. The respective culture supernatants of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD (Sb<sup>R</sup>LDs) and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD (Sb<sup>S</sup>LDs) were then collected. Subsequently, DCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were cultured for 3 hours in RPMI 1640 complete medium containing Sb<sup>R</sup>LDs or Sb<sup>S</sup>LDs at specified complete medium to supernatant ratios and stimulated with SAG for 0.3 hours as above. In some experiments, BMDCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were pretreated with murine IL-10 (50 ng/ml) (PeproTech, Rocky Hill, NJ) for 24 hours as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, in the presence or absence of 10 µg/ml of αIL-10Ab/isotype control Ab and stimulated with LPS (500 ng/ml) for 0.5 hours.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>EMSA and Western blot</title><p>Nuclear and cytoplasmic extracts were prepared from DC as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Beg1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. EMSA was performed as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Murphy2" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref> using <sup>32</sup>P-labeled DNA probes containing NF-κB binding sites derived from MHC-I H2K promoter:</p><p><named-content content-type="gene">5′-CAGGGCTGGGGATTCCCCATCTCCACAGTTTCACTTC-3′</named-content>
<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In some experiments, DNA probes specific for murine γGCS heavy-chain (mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>) promoter containing wild-type or mutant NF-κB binding sites as represented by WT-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe, <named-content content-type="gene">′-CGGTTCTGAAGGT<underline>GGGGAAACTT</underline>CTGAAGAAACTT-3′</named-content>5and Mut-mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> probe, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CGGTTCTGAAGGT<italic toggle="yes"><underline>CTCT</underline></italic><underline>AA<italic toggle="yes">GAA</italic>T</underline>CTGAAGAAACTT-3′</named-content> (NF-κB binding site is underlined and mutated bases are in italics) respectively, were used. A double stranded OCT-1 DNA probe, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TGTCGAATGCAAATCACTAGAA-3′</named-content> was used as control. Supershift EMSAs were carried out as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> using following Abs: αp50, αRelB (Active Motif, CA); αp65 (Abcam plc. Cambridge, UK); αp52, αcRel, rabbit IgG (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA). Bands were visualized using a phosphoimager (Bio-Rad Molecular Imager FX, Hercules, CA).</p><p>Western blotting was carried out as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Blots were probed with Abs specific for: IκBα, IκBβ, IκBε, IKK1, IKK2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology); pIκBα, pIKK1 (Ser180)/pIKK2 (Ser181), pAKT (Ser473), AKT, pSAPK/JNK (Thr183/Tyr185), SAPK/JNK, phospho-p38MAPK (Thr180/Tyr182), p38MAPK, pERK1/pERK2 (Thr202/Tyr204), ERK1/ERK2 (Cell Signaling Technology); β-actin (Sigma). Binding of secondary HRP-labeled goat-αrabbit (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) or goat-αmouse Abs (Sigma) was analyzed using SuperSignal<sup>R</sup> West Pico or West Dura Chemiluminescent Substrate (Pierce, Rockland, IL).</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>IKK assay</title><p>IKK signalosome was immunoprecipitated from 700 µg of a whole DC lysate using Protein A/G agarose beads (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) and rabbit polyclonal αIKK1 Ab. <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> kinase reaction was performed and kinase activity of immunoprecipitated IKK complex determined as described <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Sen1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p>The following monoclonal antibodies used for flow cytometry were purchased from eBioscience (San Diego, CA): PE-αmouse CD11c, FITC-αmouse CD11b, FITC-αmouse CD40, FITC-αmouse CD86, FITC-αmouse CD80, FITC-αmouse H2K<sup>d</sup> and FITC-αmouse IA<sup>d</sup>. The fluorescence of stained cells was analyzed on a FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences) using Cell Quest Pro software.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Measurement of IL-12, TNFα and IL-10 secretions from DCs</title><p>DCs (1×10<sup>6</sup>/ml) were infected with promastigotes of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD for 3 hours or left uninfected, washed and stimulated with SAG for additional 48 hours in a 24-well plate. Alternatively, DCs (1×10<sup>6</sup>/ml) were infected with promastigotes of Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD for varying times or left uninfected. The culture supernatants were analyzed for IL-12, TNFα and IL-10 productions in triplicate using ELISA kits (BD Biosciences) following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Analysis of murine γGCS heavy-chain (mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>) and LD γGCS heavy-chain (LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub>) expression in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD- and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected BMDCs</title><p>BMDCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were infected with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD or Sb<sup>S</sup>LD for 3 hours or left uninfected, stimulated with SAG for 3 hours and RNA prepared using RNeasy minikit reagent (QIAGEN). The mRNA expression of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>, LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub>, murine glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (mGAPDH) and LD-tubulin genes were determined via reverse transcription-PCR using platinum quantitative RT-PCR Thermoscript One Step system kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and primers: LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub>
<named-content content-type="gene">5′-TATCAAGTCTCGCTACGACT-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CGGAGTCCTTCAGAAGTT-3′</named-content>; LD-tubulin <named-content content-type="gene">5′-ACATCACGAACTCGGTGTTT-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TTCGTCTTGATCGTCGCAAT-3′</named-content>; mγGCS<sub>hc</sub>
<named-content content-type="gene">5′-AGAACAATCGCTTTAGGATCA-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-AGAAGATGATCGATGCCTTC-3′</named-content>; mGAPDH <named-content content-type="gene">5′-AGATTGTTGCCATCAACGAC</named-content> 3′, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-ATGACAAGCTTCCCATTCTC-3′</named-content>
<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Detection of MRPA expression in LD</title><p>RNA was isolated from LD promastigotes and mRNA expression of MRPA was detected by analyzing the amplification of 179 bp cDNA fragment of MRPA via reverse transcription-PCR using primers: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GCGCAGCCGTTTGTGCTTGTGG-3′</named-content>, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TTGCCGTACGTCGCGATGGTGC-3′</named-content>
<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Mukherjee1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. mRNA expression of LD-tubulin was used as loading control.</p></sec><sec id="s4n"><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP)</title><p>BMDCs (5×10<sup>6</sup>/well) were stimulated with SAG for 0.3 hours or left untreated. ChIP was performed using ChIP-IT kit (Active Motif) following the manufacturer's instructions. After immunoprecipitation using rabbit IgG or NF-κB Abs such as αp50, αRelB and αp65, followed by DNA extraction; PCR was performed to amplify −991/−673 region of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter using primers: P1, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CCAGTTCCCAGAGCCTTCCG-3′</named-content> and P2, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TTGTACGACTCCACATGGCATG-3′</named-content>. For a negative control, mGAPDH promoter was amplified by using primers: 5′-CACCCTGGCATTTTCTTCCA-3 and <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GACCCAGAGACCTGAATGCTG-3′</named-content>
<xref rid="ppat.1000907-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4o"><title>Reporter assay</title><p>An approximately 1.0 kb (−987/+25) long 5′-flanking sequence of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> gene was amplified by PCR using murine genomic DNA (Promega, Madison, WI) and cloned into pGL3-Basic vector. Using this resulting construct, p987-luc, and a QuickChangeII PCR-based site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene, Cedar Creek, TX); the construct (Mut p987-luc) containing a mutant NF-κB binding site, similar to that described in EMSA studies, in −987/+25 region of mγGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter was generated. Both constructs were confirmed by sequencing. NIH3T3 cells were transiently transfected with a DNA mixture containing p987-luc or Mut p987-luc (0.266 µg), pRL-CMV (0.200 µg), pEGFP-p65 (0.266 µg) and/or pEGFP-IκBαΔN (IκBα with amino acids 1–36 deleted) (0.266 µg) using lipofectamine LTX (Invitrogen). The latter two expression vectors are gifts from Dr. Johannes Schmid (Medical University of Vienna, Austria) and Dr. Susan Kandarian (Boston University, USA) respectively <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Schmid1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1000907-Judge1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. The DNA amount in each transfection was kept constant. Cells were grown for 24 hours after transfection. The luciferase activity of the cell lysates was determined using Dual Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega) and GLOMAX luminometer (Promega) following the manufacturer's instructions. The level of luciferase activity was normalized to the level of <italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> luciferase activity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s001" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>BMDC infection with AG83Pm but not 39Pm is inhibited by SAG treatment. BMDCs were infected <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> at MOI 10:1 with AG83Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 hours and stimulated with SAG (10 and 20 µg/ml) for 24 and 48 hours as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Untreated (24h) and untreated (48h) represent LD-infected DC controls cultured without SAG treatment for 24 and 48 hours, respectively. The percentage of infected BMDCs (A) and number of intracellular amastigotes per 1000 BMDCs (B) were determined by Giemsa staining. Open and solid bars represent AG83Pm and 39Pm-infected BMDCs, respectively. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.001, <sup>**</sup>p = 0.003, <sup>†</sup>p = 0.002 and <sup>††</sup>p = 0.0012 versus DC+AG83Pm of respective times (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(1.94 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s002" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Sb<sup>S</sup>LD and Sb<sup>R</sup>LD differentially regulate cytokine secretion by sDCs. <italic toggle="yes">Ex vivo</italic> derived sDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 hours or left uninfected. sDCs were then washed to remove free parasites and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 48 hours as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Production of (A) IL-10, (B) IL-12p70 and (C) TNFα in the culture supernatants were measured via ELISA. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p = 0.004 and <sup>**</sup>p = 0.008 versus DC+2001; <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.001 versus DC+SAG (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(1.63 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s002.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s003" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>SAG treatment induces NF-κB pathway in sDCs. sDCs were stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for the specified times or left untreated. (A) EMSA was used to measure DNA binding activity of nuclear NF-κB to H2K-DNA probe. OCT-1 DNA binding was used as internal control. (B) Western blot was used to detect cytoplasmic IκBα and β-actin protein using the same blot. (C) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity was determined as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Expression of IKK1 and IKK2 were determined via Western blot using same membrane. Data are representative of three independent experiments.</p><p>(0.94 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s004" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>BMDCs and sDCs infection with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains GE1F8R and 39, respectively, inhibits SAG-induced NF-κB signaling. sDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) (A, C, E) and BMDCs with AG83Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or GE1F8RPm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) (B, D, F) for 3 hours as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. DCs were then washed and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 0.3 hours. (A-B) Nuclear NF-κB or OCT-1 DNA binding activity was determined via EMSA. (C-D) Cytoplasmic IκBα and β-actin protein were detected by Western blot using the same blot. (E) IKK phosphorylation was detected via Western blot and the same blot was reprobed for IKK1 and IKK2 protein. (F) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity, and IKK1 and IKK2 protein expression were determined as described in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Data are representative of three independent experiments.</p><p>(3.51 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s004.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s005" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>Temporal analysis of DC infection with Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD. BMDCs were infected at a MOI 10:1 with promastigotes (Pm) (A, C) or amastigotes (Am) (B, D) of indicated Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strains for specified times. BMDCs were subsequently washed to remove free parasites. The number of intracellular amastigotes per 1000 BMDCs (A-B) and percentage of infected BMDCs (C-D) were determined by Giemsa staining. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.01 versus BMDCs infected with 2001Pm for 6 hours, <sup>#</sup>p&lt;0.01 versus BMDCs infected with 39Pm for 6 hours, <sup>†</sup>p =  0.014 versus BMDCs infected with 2001Am for 3 hours and <sup>††</sup>p = 0.011 versus BMDCs infected with 39Am for 3 hours (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(3.38 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s005.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s006" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p>DC infection varies with MOIs at specified time points of infection. BMDCs were infected at varying MOIs either with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 24 hours (A, C); or 2001Am (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Am (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 6 hours (B, D). BMDCs were then washed. The number of intracellular amastigotes per 1000 BMDCs (A-B) and percentage of infected BMDCs (C-D) were determined by Giemsa staining. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus BMDCs infected with 2001Pm at MOIs 2.5:1 or 5:1 (promastigote:BMDC); <sup>#</sup>p&lt;0.01 and <sup>##</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus BMDCs infected with 39Pm at MOIs 2.5:1 or 5:1 (promastigote:BMDC); <sup>¶</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus BMDCs infected with 2001Am at MOIs 2.5:1 or 5:1 (amastigote:BMDC); <sup>**</sup>p&lt;0.005 and <sup>†</sup>p&lt;0.01 versus BMDCs infected with 39Am at MOIs 2.5:1 or 5:1 (amastigote:BMDC) (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(3.34 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s006.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s007" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p>Sb<sup>R</sup>LD but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD infection inhibits SAG-stimulated phosphorylation of AKT in sDCs. <italic toggle="yes">Ex vivo</italic> sDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 hours at a MOI 10:1 or left uninfected. The sDCs were washed thoroughly and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 0.3 hours. Expression of phospho-AKT versus AKT in the cytoplasmic extract was determined via Western blot. Data are representative of two independent experiments.</p><p>(0.51 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s007.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s008" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p>Treatment with αIL-10 Ab prevents inhibition of LPS-induced NF-κB DNA binding activity in IL-10-pretreated BMDCs. BMDCs were pretreated with IL-10 (50 ng/ml) for 24 hours in the presence or absence of 10 µg/ml of αIL-10 Ab or isotype control Ab. BMDCs were then washed and stimulated with LPS (500 ng/ml) for 0.5 hours. Nuclear NF-κB binding to H2K-DNA probe or OCT-1 DNA binding was measured via EMSA. Data are representative of two independent experiments.</p><p>(0.62 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s008.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s009" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S9</label><caption><p>An increased expression of MRPA is detected in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and 2001Pm-MRPA but not Sb<sup>S</sup>LD. The mRNA expression of MRPA versus LD-tubulin in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD strains 39Pm and GE1F8RPm (A); Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strains AG83Pm (A) and 2001Pm (A-B); 2001Pm expressing MRPA (2001Pm-MRPA) (B); and 2001Pm transfected with empty vector (2001Pm-EV) (B) was determined via RT-PCR. Densitometric data represent ratio of intensity of MRPA to LD-tubulin mRNA expression per unit area and are presented as an arbitrary unit. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(2.76 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s009.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s010" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S10</label><caption><p>SAG (40 µg/ml) treatment restores leishmanicidal effects in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD- unlike Sb<sup>R</sup>LD-infected DCs despite prolonged infection. BMDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) at a MOI of 10:1 for 24 hours. BMDCs were then washed and treated with 200 nM Wort or 50 µM Ly for 1 hour. Subsequently, BMDCs were stimulated with 20 or 40 µg/ml of SAG for 24 hours or left untreated. The percentage of infected BMDCs (A) and number of intracellular amastigotes per 1000 BMDCs (B) were determined by Giemsa staining. SAG<sub>20</sub> and SAG<sub>40</sub> represent stimulation of BMDCs with 20 and 40 µg/ml of SAG, respectively. Data are representative of three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup>p&lt;0.005, <sup>†</sup>p = 0.094 and <sup>#</sup>p =  0.13 versus DC+2001Pm <sup>**</sup>p&lt;0.005 versus DC+2001Pm+SAG<sub>40</sub> (Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test). Findings were considered significant with "p" values ≤ 0.05. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(1.62 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s010.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s011" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S11</label><caption><p>Pretreatment with PI3K inhibitors block SAG-induced NF-κB signaling in Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected DCs. BMDCs were infected for 3 hours with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) and 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) at MOI 10:1, treated with Wort or Ly and stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for indicated times as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>. (A) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> IKK activity was measured as in <xref rid="ppat-1000907-g003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. The same blot was reprobed for IKK1 and IKK2 protein. (B) Expression of cytoplasmic IκBα and β-actin protein was detected by Western blot using the same blot. (C) Nuclear NF-κB or OCT-1 DNA binding activity was determined via EMSA. Data are representative of three independent experiments.</p><p>(4.49 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s011.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="ppat.1000907.s012" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S12</label><caption><p>LD γGCS heavy-chain (LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub>) expression is more in Sb<sup>R</sup>LD- compared to Sb<sup>S</sup>LD-infected BMDCs. BMDCs were infected with 2001Pm (Sb<sup>S</sup>LD) or 39Pm (Sb<sup>R</sup>LD) for 3 hours at MOI 10:1. Infected DCs were then stimulated with SAG (20 µg/ml) for 3 hours or left untreated. The mRNA expression of LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub> versus LD-tubulin was determined via RT-PCR. Densitometric data represent ratio of intensity of LD-γGCS<sub>hc</sub> to LD-tubulin mRNA expression per unit area and are presented as an arbitrary unit. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Error bars indicate mean ± SD.</p><p>(1.63 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1000907.s012.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Neeloo Singh (Central Drug Research Institute, India) and Shyam Sundar (Banaras Hindu University, India) for Sb<sup>R</sup>LD and Sb<sup>S</sup>LD strains; Johannes Schmid (Medical University of Vienna, Austria) for pEGFP-p65 expression vector; Susan Kandarian (Boston University, USA) for pEGFP-IκBαΔN expression vector; and Marc Ouellette (Laval University, Canada) for pGEM 7ZF α-neo-α and pGEM 7ZF α-neo-α <italic toggle="yes">L. tarentolae</italic> MRPA (PGPA) expression vectors. We want to thank Jagmohan Singh (Institute of Microbial Technology, India), who helped in designing the strategies for cloning murine γGCS<sub>hc</sub> promoter and critical reading of the manuscript. Finally, we thank IMTECH and IICB animal house facilities for providing us animals required for experimentation and Dr. Neeraj Khatri for helping us in carrying out the infection of hamsters with LD via intracardiac route.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1000907-Lira1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Makharia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Evidence that the high incidence of treatment failures in Indian kala-azar is due to the emergence of antimony-resistant strains of Leishmania donovani.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10395884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/314896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Croft1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fairlamb</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Drug resistance in leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/CMR.19.1.111-126.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1360270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Ashutosh1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ashutosh</surname></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of antimony resistance in Leishmania.</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17244793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1099/jmm.0.46841-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Carter1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henriquez</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Legare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Resistance of Leishmania donovani to sodium stibogluconate is related to the expression of host and parasite gamma-glutamylcysteine synthetase.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16377672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.50.1.88-95.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1346807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Mukherjee1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Role of ABC transporter MRPA, gamma-glutamylcysteine synthetase and ornithine decarboxylase in natural antimony-resistant isolates of Leishmania donovani.</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17213267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jac/dkl494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Decuypere1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Decuypere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rijal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Doncker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Gene expression analysis of the mechanism of natural Sb(V) resistance in Leishmania donovani isolates from Nepal.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>4616</fpage><lpage>4621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.49.11.4616-4621.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1280167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Carter2"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spickett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The in vivo susceptibility of Leishmania donovani to sodium stibogluconate is drug specific and can be reversed by inhibiting glutathione biosynthesis.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>1529</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12709318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.47.5.1529-1535.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC153333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Thakur1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Skewing of cytokine profiles towards T helper cell type 2 response in visceral leishmaniasis patients unresponsive to sodium antimony gluconate.</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15259468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0035-9203(03)90071-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Narayan1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bimal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Leishmania donovani vs immunity: T-cells sensitized from Leishmania of one donor may modulate their cytokines pattern on re-stimulation with Leishmania from different donor in visceral leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18948098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.exppara.2008.09.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Murray1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Delph-Etienne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Roles of endogenous gamma interferon and macrophage microbicidal mechanisms in host response to chemotherapy in experimental visceral leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10603400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.68.1.288-293.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC97133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Murray2"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Montelibano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sypek</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Interleukin-12 regulates the response to chemotherapy in experimental visceral Leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11023473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/315890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Gorak1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gorak</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engwerda</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Dendritic cells, but not macrophages, produce IL-12 immediately following Leishmania donovani infection.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1521-4141(199802)28:02&lt;687::AID-IMMU687&gt;3.0.CO;2-N</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Suzue1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suzue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koyasu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Critical role of dendritic cells in determining the Th1/Th2 balance upon Leishmania major infection.</article-title><source>Int Immunol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18195051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/intimm/dxm147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Bennett1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Misslitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Colledge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aebischer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Silent infection of bone marrow-derived dendritic cells by Leishmania mexicana amastigotes.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11241293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/1521-4141(200103)31:3&lt;876::aid-immu876&gt;3.0.co;2-i</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Rescigno1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rescigno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ricciardi-Castagnoli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Dendritic cell survival and maturation are regulated by different signaling pathways.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>2175</fpage><lpage>2180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9841930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.188.11.2175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2212396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Poligone1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poligone</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Elevated NF-kappaB activation in nonobese diabetic mouse dendritic cells results in enhanced APC function.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>168</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.168.1.188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Ouaaz1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ouaaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Dendritic cell development and survival require distinct NF-kappaB subunits.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11869686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1074-7613(02)00272-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Weaver1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poligone</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Motal</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Dendritic cells from nonobese diabetic mice exhibit a defect in NF-kappaB regulation due to a hyperactive IkappaB kinase.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>167</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11466366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.167.3.1461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Bhattacharyya1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wallet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Immunoregulation of dendritic cells by IL-10 is mediated through suppression of the PI3K/Akt pathway and of IkappaB kinase activity.</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>1100</fpage><lpage>1109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2003-12-4302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Sen1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wallet</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Apoptotic cells induce Mer tyrosine kinase-dependent blockade of NF-kappaB activation in dendritic cells.</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17008547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2006-04-017368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1785106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Ghosh1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Missing pieces in the NF-kappaB puzzle.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>109</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>S81</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11983155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(02)00703-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Karin1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>How NF-kappaB is activated: the role of the IkappaB kinase (IKK) complex.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>6867</fpage><lpage>6874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10602462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1203219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Madrid1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schottelius</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Akt suppresses apoptosis by stimulating the transactivation potential of the RelA/p65 subunit of NF-kappaB.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>1638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.20.5.1626-1638.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC85346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Guha1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mackman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-Akt pathway limits lipopolysaccharide activation of signaling pathways and expression of inflammatory mediators in human monocytic cells.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>32124</fpage><lpage>32132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M203298200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-MookerjeeBasu1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mookerjee Basu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mookerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaumik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Sodium antimony gluconate induces generation of reactive oxygen species and nitric oxide via phosphoinositide 3-kinase and mitogen-activated protein kinase activation in Leishmania donovani-infected macrophages.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>1788</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.50.5.1788-1797.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1472228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Barat1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>HIV-1 replication is stimulated by sodium stibogluconate, the therapeutic mainstay in the treatment of leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>195</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17191169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/510398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Kurozumi1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kurozumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Increase of intracellular glutathione by low-level NO mediated by transcription factor NF-kappaB in RAW 264.7 cells.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1744</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15878398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2004.11.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Tejle1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tejle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lindroth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmusson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Wild-type Leishmania donovani promastigotes block maturation, increase integrin expression and inhibit detachment of human monocyte-derived dendritic cells–the influence of phosphoglycans.</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2007.01013.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Marovich1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marovich</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nutman</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>IL-12p70 production by Leishmania major-harboring human dendritic cells is a CD40/CD40 ligand-dependent process.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>5858</fpage><lpage>5865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10820265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.164.11.5858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Ato1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stager</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engwerda</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Defective CCR7 expression on dendritic cells contributes to the development of visceral leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12436111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Donovan1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jayakumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Inhibition of groups 1 and 2 CD1 molecules on human dendritic cells by Leishmania species.</article-title><source>Parasite Immunol</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17883454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-3024.2007.00970.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Cai1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Differential regulation of gamma-glutamylcysteine synthetase heavy and light subunit gene expression.</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>326</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9337864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/bj3260167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1218650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Qi1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Leishmania amazonensis-dendritic cell interactions in vitro and the priming of parasite-specific CD4(+) T cells in vivo.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>167</volume><fpage>4534</fpage><lpage>4542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11591781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.167.8.4534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Murphy1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Villegas</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>IL-10 mediates susceptibility to Leishmania donovani infection.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>2848</fpage><lpage>2856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/1521-4141(2001010)31:10&lt;2848::aid-immu2848&gt;3.0.co;2-t</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Murray3"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mauze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Interleukin-10 (IL-10) in experimental visceral leishmaniasis and IL-10 receptor blockade as immunotherapy.</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>6284</fpage><lpage>6293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.70.11.6284-6293.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC130311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Dobrovolskaia1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrovolskaia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Medvedev</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cuesta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Toshchakov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Induction of in vitro reprogramming by Toll-like receptor (TLR)2 and TLR4 agonists in murine macrophages: effects of TLR “homotolerance” versus “heterotolerance” on NF-kappaB signaling pathway components.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.170.1.508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Whiteside1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteside</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Epinat</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>IkappaB epsilon, a novel member of the IkappaB family, controls RelA and cRel NF-kappaB activity.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9135156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/16.6.1413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1169738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Kearns1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Basak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>IkappaB epsilon provides negative feedback to control NF-kappaB oscillations, signaling dynamics, and inflammatory gene expression.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16735576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.200510155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2063883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Laskov1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laskov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Differential effects of tumor necrosis factor-alpha and CD40L on NF-kappaB inhibitory proteins IkappaB alpha, beta and epsilon and on the induction of the Jun amino-terminal kinase pathway in Ramos Burkitt lymphoma cells.</article-title><source>Eur Cytokine Netw</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Zhao1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cantin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopoulou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>DC-SIGN-mediated transfer of HIV-1 is compromised by the ability of Leishmania infantum to exploit DC-SIGN as a ligand.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>191</volume><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/429673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Pepe1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pepe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Altamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Calvello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saccia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Toll-like receptor-positive cells and recognition of pathogens: how human myeloid dendritic cells respond to in vitro infection with Leishmania infantum.</article-title><source>Curr Pharm Des</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>4255</fpage><lpage>4262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17100627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/138161206778743556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Garg1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ouellet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Leishmania infantum Amastigotes Enhance HIV-1 Production in Cocultures of Human Dendritic Cells and CD4 T Cells by Inducing Secretion of IL-6 and TNF-alpha.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e441</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19468304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2680485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Chulay1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chulay</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fleckenstein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of antimony during treatment of visceral leishmaniasis with sodium stibogluconate or meglumine antimoniate.</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2845611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Singh1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Visceral leishmaniasis, or kala azar (KA): high incidence of refractoriness to antimony is contributed by anthroponotic transmission via post-KA dermal leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>194</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16826477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/505079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Singh2"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Novel mechanism of drug resistance in kala azar field isolates.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>188</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12898450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/377133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Cuevas1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cuevas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>SHP-1 regulates Lck-induced phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase phosphorylation and activity.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>274</volume><fpage>27583</fpage><lpage>27589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10488096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.274.39.27583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Pathak1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Sodium stibogluconate is a potent inhibitor of protein tyrosine phosphatases and augments cytokine responses in hemopoietic cell lines.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>167</volume><fpage>3391</fpage><lpage>3397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.167.6.3391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Corinti1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Corinti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Albanesi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>la Sala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Girolomoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Regulatory activity of autocrine IL-10 on dendritic cell functions.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>4312</fpage><lpage>4318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.166.7.4312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Kothari1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Possibility of membrane modification as a mechanism of antimony resistance in Leishmania donovani.</article-title><source>Parasitol Int</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17169604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parint.2006.10.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Samant1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Samant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sahasrabuddhe</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Proteophosphoglycan is differentially expressed in sodium stibogluconate-sensitive and resistant Indian clinical isolates of Leishmania donovani.</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17362540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0031182007002569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Kumar1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boggula</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shasany</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Identification of genetic markers in sodium antimony gluconate (SAG) sensitive and resistant Indian clinical isolates of Leishmania donovani through amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP).</article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19283900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.actatropica.2009.01.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Mollah1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mollah</surname><given-names>ZU</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Abnormal NF-kappaB function characterizes human type 1 diabetes dendritic cells and monocytes.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>3166</fpage><lpage>3175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.180.5.3166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Thakur2"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Comparison of treatment regimens of kala-azar based on culture &amp; sensitivity of amastigotes to sodium antimony gluconate.</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18765878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Ameen1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ameen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis: disease susceptibility and pharmacogenetic implications.</article-title><source>Pharmacogenomics</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19290793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2217/14622416.10.3.451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Mukhopadhyay1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madhubala</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Antileishmanial activity and modification of hepatic xenobiotic metabolizing enzymes in golden hamster by 2(3)-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyanisole following infection with Leishmania donovani.</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8304969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0006-2952(94)90014-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Basu1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaumik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naskar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Kinetoplastid membrane protein-11 DNA vaccination induces complete protection against both pentavalent antimonial-sensitive and -resistant strains of Leishmania donovani that correlates with inducible nitric oxide synthase activity and IL-4 generation: evidence for mixed Th1- and Th2-like responses in visceral leishmaniasis.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>174</volume><fpage>7160</fpage><lpage>7171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15905560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.174.11.7160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Singh3"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Differential gene expression analysis in antimony-unresponsive Indian kala azar (visceral leishmaniasis) clinical isolates by DNA microarray.</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17306059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0031182007002284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Hart1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vickerman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>A quick, simple method for purifying Leishmania mexicana amastigotes in large numbers.</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7243344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s0031182000066889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Chakraborty1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Leishmania donovani affects antigen presentation of macrophage by disrupting lipid rafts.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>3214</fpage><lpage>3224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16116212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.175.5.3214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Dube1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Refractoriness to the treatment of sodium stibogluconate in Indian kala-azar field isolates persist in in vitro and in vivo experimental models.</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15868188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-005-1339-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Beg1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finco</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nantermet</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Tumor necrosis factor and interleukin-1 lead to phosphorylation and loss of IkappaB alpha: a mechanism for NF-kappaB activation.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>3301</fpage><lpage>3310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8497253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.13.6.3301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC359784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Murphy2"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kulesza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Magram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Regulation of interleukin 12 p40 expression through an NF-kappaB half-site.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>5258</fpage><lpage>5267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.15.10.5258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC230773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Lee1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Melchers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Torrey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slota</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Regulation of the germinal center gene program by interferon (IFN) regulatory factor 8/IFN consensus sequence-binding protein.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>203</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16380510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20051450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2118063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Schmid1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Birbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer-Warbinek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pengg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Dynamics of NF-kappaB and IkappaB alpha studied with green fluorescent protein (GFP) fusion proteins. Investigation of GFP-p65 binding to DNA by fluorescence resonance energy transfer.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>17035</fpage><lpage>17042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M000291200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1000907-Judge1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koncarevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jackman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Role for IkappaBalpha, but not c-Rel, in skeletal muscle atrophy.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><volume>292</volume><fpage>C372</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpcell.00293.2006</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>