
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Eye Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8104312</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Current eye research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0271-3683</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2202</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2827929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2827929.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2827929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2827929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS173449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20021254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/02713680903374208</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS173449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA173449</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of arresten on bFGF induced proliferation, migration and matrix metalloproteinase-2 activation in mouse retinal endothelial cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boosani</surname><given-names initials="CS">Chandra S.</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalabothula</surname><given-names initials="N">Narasimharao</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheibani</surname><given-names initials="N">Nader</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names initials="A">Akulapalli</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Cell Signaling and Tumor Angiogenesis Laboratory, Department of Genetics, Boys Town National Research Hospital, Omaha, NE 68131</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Department of Ophthalmology and Vision Science, University of Wisconsin School of Medicine and Public Health, Madison, WI, 53792</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label> Department of Biomedical Sciences, Creighton University School of Medicine, Omaha, NE 68178</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label> Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE, 68198</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1">Address for Correspondence: Akulapalli Sudhakar, MS., M.Phill &amp; Ph.D., Assistant Professor/Staff Scientist II, Creighton University Medical center and University of Nebraska Mecical Center. Director: Cell Signaling and Tumor Angiogenesis Laboratory, Boys Town National Research Hospital, 555 N, 30th Street, Omaha NE 68131, USA., Office: (402) 498-6681, Lab: (402) 498-6322, Fax: (402) 498-6331, <email>akulapallis@boystown.org</email></corresp><fn id="FN2" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">185211</issue-id><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>09</day><month>02</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>02</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>02</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-06 10:48:32.067"><day>06</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms173449.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" page="1" journal-id="Curr Eye Res" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7239752"><article-title>Statement of Retraction: Inhibitory Effects of Arresten on
bFGF-Induced Proliferation, Migration, and Matrix Metalloproteinase-2 Activation
in Mouse Retinal Endothelial Cells</article-title><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><date><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><source>Current eye research</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7239752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32238010</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Purpose</title><p id="P1">The potential role of arresten (α1(IV)NC1) as an endogenous angiogenesis inhibitor in the prevention of bFGF mediated retinal angiogenesis and regulation of matrix metaloprotenase-2 activation has not been explored.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P2">Mouse retinal endothelial cells (MREC) were cultured on type IV collagen and treated with basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) alone or in the presence of arresten at concentrations ranging from 1 to 10 μg/ml. The proliferation of MRECs were evaluated using 3,(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT) colorimetric assay, and bFGF stimulated endothelial cell migration was assessed using Boyden chamber. Expression of matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) was assessed by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis using RNA isolated from MRECs. Secretion and activation of MMP-2 in arresten treated conditioned MREC growth medium was determined by gelatin zymography and Western blotting.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P3">Different doses of bFGF induced MREC proliferation was significantly inhibited upon arresten treatment (P&lt;0.005). The bFGF-induced migration was significantly inhibited by arresten at 1 and 10 μg/ml concentrations (P&lt;0.01). The bFGF stimulated expression of MMP-2 mRNA and secretion of MMP-2 in MREC was not affected and interestingly activation of MMP-2 was suppressed by arresten in a dose and time dependent manner.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P4">Inhibitory effects of arresten on proliferation, migration and MMP-2 activation but not on expression and secretion of MMP-2 in MREC; this early work with arresten supports potential therapeutic action in retinal neovascularization dependent disorders.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Anti-angiogenesis</kwd><kwd>Retinal Neovascularization</kwd><kwd>Diabetic Retinopathy</kwd><kwd>Retinopathy of Prematurity</kwd><kwd>Matrix Methaloproteinase-2</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S5"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P5">The eye contains highly vascular and non-vascular tissues in a close apposition. This specialized anatomy requires tight regulation of the balance between vascular quiescence and vascular growth. Vascular growth normally occurs during ocular embryonic development and is virtually absent in the eyes of normal adults <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>. In most human eye diseases with neovascular component, this delicate balance between pro- and anti-angiogenic factors is disturbed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>. Angiogenesis plays a crucial role in disorders responsible for loss of vision in humans, including diabetic retinopathy (DR), retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) and choroidal neovascularization (CNV) of age-related macular degeneration (AMD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>. Because of its importance in wound healing, tumor growth and other pathological conditions, angiogenesis has been extensively studied in the fields of oncology, cardiology, rheumatology and ophthalmology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>. The main interest in the above fields is the notion that inhibition of angiogenesis may influence the associated pathology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>.</p><p id="P6">Angiogenesis is a tightly regulated process that involves coordinated activities of both endothelial cells and pericytes. Angiogenesis is influenced by several proangiogenic growth factors, including vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β), and inhibitory factors from extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins such as thrombospondins, endostatin and type IV collagen derived angiogenesis inhibitors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>. Available evidence suggests that bFGF is one of the most important growth factors promoting angiogenesis in several angiogenesis related disorders, besides VEGF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>. Therefore; an antiangiogenic agent with the potential to block bFGF activity may inhibit the associate pathological condition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>.</p><p id="P7">Retinal angiogenesis is believed to start with the degradation of retinal blood vessel basement membrane containing various extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins by matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs), followed by sequential changes in vascular endothelial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>. Type IV collagen is abundant in ECM which plays a crucial role in angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>. Proteolytic remodeling of ECM not only degrades barriers that obstruct vascular endothelial cell migration but also exposes cryptic regions within type IV collagen that enhance novel integrin ligand ECM interactions which are required for angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>. Recently, researchers have identified that in eye diseases with neovascular component such as retinal neovascularization, inhibition of the abnormal retinal angiogenesis could be beneficial <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>.</p><p id="P8">A 26 kDa non-collagenous carboxy terminal domain of type IV collagen α1 chain [α1(IV)NC1 or arresten] was characterized with anti-angiogenic properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>. Here we aimed to study the impact of recombinant baculovirus expressed arresten on different steps of angiogenesis in cultured mouse retinal endothelial cells (MREC), including cell proliferation and migration. In this study, we sought to determine whether arresten could inhibit the proliferation and migration of MRECs incubated with bFGF, and its effect on the expression and activation of MMP-2. In <italic toggle="yes">in-vitro</italic> experiments, we identified that arresten inhibits bFGF induced proliferation and migration in MRECs by inhibiting MMP-2 activation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S6"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><p id="P9">Dulbecco’s modified eagles medium (DMEM) was from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA). H&amp;E staining kit and Heparan were form Fisher Scientific, Inc (Pittsburgh, PA). ICAM-2, rat anti-mouse CD31, 1X binding buffer, and ELISA kit were from R&amp;D systems (Minneapolis, MN). Vectashield anti-fade mounting medium was from Vector Laboratories (Burlingame, CA). HRP labeled secondary antibodies; type IV collagen, heparin and penicillin/streptomycin were from Sigma-Aldrich (St, Louis, MD). NEAA, sodium pyruvate solution, L-Glutamine and HEPES were from Cellgro (Manassas, BA). Fetal calf serum (FCS) was from Atlanta Biologicals (Norcross, GA). Gelatin from Porcine was from Pierce (Rockford, IL). ECL Kit was from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA). MTT assay kit purchased from Chemicon (Temecula, CA). Endothelial cell growth supplement and endothelial mitogen were from Biomedical Technologies, Inc (Stoughton, MA).</p><sec id="S7"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="P10">Primary mouse retinal endothelial cells (MRECs) were maintained in 40% Ham’s F-12, 40% DME-Low Glucose, 20% FCS supplemented with heparan (50 mg/l), endothelial mitogen (50 mg/l), L-glutamine (2 mM), penicillin/streptomycin (100 units/ml each), Na Pyruvate (2.5 mM), NEAA (1X), 5 mg/l of murine INF-γ and cultured on gelatin coated plates at 33°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Sf-9 cells were maintained in TNM-FH medium supplemented with 10% FCS and 100 mg/ml antibiotic and antimycotic solution at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> as described previously by us <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>. Experiments were carried out using sub-confluent early passage MRECs.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Preparation of primary MREC</title><p id="P11">MRECs were isolated from 4 week-old C57BL/6J immortal mice as reviewed and approved by the institutional animal care and use committee as reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>. Briefly, PECAM-1 expressing MRECs were enriched using rat anti-mouse PECAM-1 antibody (BD Biosciences) and sheep-anti-rat secondary antibody conjugated to magnetic beads (Invitrogen). More than 95% of cultured cells were identified as endothelial cells by their positive immunostaining with B4-lectin. These MRECs express a temperature sensitive large T-antigen and can be readily passaged. In addition, MRECs were positive for expression of the endothelial-specific marker, VE-Cadherin at cell junctions and contact points, and were able to take up 1,1′-dioctadecyl-3,3,3′,3′ tetramethyl indocarbocyanine perchlorate Acetylated LDL (DiI-Ac-LDL) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Production of recombinant arresten using baculovirus insect cell system</title><p id="P12">Briefly, the sequence encoding arresten was amplified by PCR using a forward primer (5′-TATATAGAATTCTCTGTTGATCACGGCTTCCT-3′) and reverse primer (5′-TTAATTTCTAGATTATGTTCTTCTCATACAGACTTG-3′). The resulting cDNA fragment was digested with EcoRI and Bgl II and ligated into predigested pAcHLT-A transfer vector (PharMingen). The resulting recombinant vector pAcHLT-A/arresten was co-transfected into Sf-9 cells with Bsu361 digested linearized Baculogold<sup>™</sup>(BD Pharmingen) viral DNA to obtain an infectious complete viral genome according to the Baculovirus expression system manual and the expression and purification of arresten was carried out as reported earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Proliferation assay</title><p id="P13">MREC proliferation was evaluated using 3,(4,5- dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT) colorimetric assay. Briefly, MRECs were trypsinized and plated at a density of 4×10<sup>3</sup> cells in 125 μl of MREC medium per well in a type IV collagen (10 μg/ml) coated 96-well plate and allowed to attach overnight. To select optimal concentration of basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), MRECs were washed three times with PBS and then incubated with different concentrations of bFGF (0.1, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 ng/ml) in MREC medium with 1% FCS. The MREC cultured medium with 1% FCS was used as negative control. MRECs were incubated for 48 hr and during the last 4 hr, 10 μl of MTT (5 μg/ml) reagent was added to each well. Formazan crystals formed were dissolved in 100 μl of dimethyl-sulfoxide and optical density was measured at 570 nm on a Bio-Rad microplate reader. The dose-effect of bFGF on MREC proliferation was estimated by the % compared to the control without bFGF. For other experiments, MRECs cultured in 96-well plates were pre-treated with recombinant human arresten at concentrations of 0.1, 1, and 10 μg/ml for 20 min, and four different concentrations of bFGF (0.25, 0.5, 1, and 5 ng/ml) was added to stimulate MRECs proliferation. MRECs cultured in incomplete medium without bFGF was used as negative control, and cells treated with bFGF alone in incomplete medium was used as positive control for each experiment. After 72 hr, MTT assay was performed and the impact of arresten on bFGF stimulated MREC proliferation was measured by the % compared to negative controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Migration assay</title><p id="P14">A cellulose membrane coated with 10 μg/ml of type IV collagen was placed separating the upper and lower wells of a Boyden chamber. In upper wells, MRECs (1×10<sup>4</sup>/well) were seeded in incomplete medium (no serum) with and without recombinant arresten, and medium containing 10 ng/ml of bFGF was placed in the bottom wells. The chamber was then incubated for 6 hr at 37°C in an incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and the MRECs that migrated to the lower surface of the membrane were determined microscopically and photographed. Four randomly chosen fields were counted per condition and the impact of arresten on bFGF-induced MREC migration was estimated by the % compared with the positive control as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Evaluation of MMP-2 expression and activation</title><p id="P15">MRECs were seeded in a 10 cm<sup>2</sup> type IV collagen (10 μg/ml) coated plate at a density of 5×10<sup>6</sup> cells in 5 ml MREC medium and the cells were allowed to attach overnight. Next day, the medium were replaced with fresh MREC medium containing 1% FCS and the cells were cultured for about 24 hr. After washing twice with PBS, the cells were incubated for 72 hr in MREC medium containing 10 ng/ml bFGF with or without arresten at 0.1, 1 and 10 μg/ml concentrations. Conditioned medium was centrifuged to remove cells and concentrated using ammonium sulphate precipitations (0 to 80%). The concentrated protein solution was then dialyzed against PBS and 10 μg was used for zymography and Western blot analysis. Based on the dose effect of arresten on expression and activation of MMP-2, an optimal concentration of arresten (5 μg/ml) was chosen for time course experiments. MRECs were treated with and without 10 ng/ml bFGF or combined with 5 μg/ml of arresten in MREC medium containing no serum. Cells cultured without bFGF/arresten in MREC medium without FCS were used as negative controls. After 24 and 48 hr, conditioned medium and MRECs were collected and protein concentrations in conditioned medium and cell extracts was determined by Bio-Rad protein assay reagent using BSA as standard. Equal amounts (10 μg/ml) of total concentrated proteins from conditioned MREC medium was subjected to gelatin zymography and Western blot analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>RNA preparation and RT-PCR analysis</title><p id="P16">The levels of MMP-2 mRNA expression were analyzed by RT-PCR amplification. Total RNA from MRECs was prepared using a RNA isolation kit and contaminating genomic DNA was eliminated by digestion with 1 unit of DNase I. Single stranded cDNA was synthesized from 1 μg total RNA in a 20 μI reaction using 200 units of superscript II reverse transcriptase, 500 μM dNTPs, and 0.5 μg of oligo(dT). PCR was performed in a 20 μl reaction volume containing 0.5 units of DNA polymerase, 1 μl single-stranded cDNA, 100 μM dNTPs, 125 nM each of MMP-2-specific primers (5′-GGTGGTGTAGTGGTTGGGGT-3′ and 5′-TGATGGGTTGGGTGGTGGGT-3′) in 50 mM Tris- HCl, pH 8.8, 16 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.01% Triton X-100. For analysis of MMP-2 mRNA expression, amplified PCR products using cDNA samples were adjusted to equal glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) inputs using GAPDH specific primers (5′-GGAGGGGGGAGGGAAAAGGG-3′ and 5′-TGGGAGGGGGAGGGTGAAAG-3′) that amplified mouse GAPDH (566 bp). PCR cycle number was determined to remain within the limit of the exponential relationship between PCR cycle number and amount of template chosen from the amplified cDNA samples with the highest concentrations. The amplified products were resolved on an ethidium bromide stained agarose gel (2%), and the acquired image was scanned in Cannon scanner to identify the band intensities that were quantitated using NIH image software.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Gelatin zymography</title><p id="P17">To detect the effect of arresten on the secretion and activation of MMP-2 by bFGF-stimulated MRECs, conditioned medium was mixed 1:1 with gelatin zymography sample buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, and 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>] and equal volumes containing about 10 μg of total protein from each sample was subjected to gelatin zymography on a 10% SDS-PAGE gel containing 0.8 μg/ml gelatin as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>. After electrophoresis, to renature gelatinase, SDS was removed from the gel by treating with 2.5% Triton X-100. Gels were then incubated at 37°C overnight in incubation buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, ZnCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 μM, and 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> and 0.2% Brij] and enzymatic activity was visualized by negative staining with Coomassie blue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>. The coomassie-stained gels were scanned and the densities for the expression and activation of 72 kDa pro or 66 kDa active forms of MMP-2 were evaluated and quantified using NIH image software.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Western immunoblot analysis</title><p id="P18">To confirm the dose-effect of arresten on secretion or activation levels of MMP-2 in MRECs, MREC conditioned medium was used for Western blot analysis. Concentrated MREC medium or cell extracts (10 μg/lane) were mixed 1:1 with SDS sample buffer and analyzed on 10% SDS-PAGE gel. Proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose membrane and blocked in 5% non-fat milk blocking buffer (TBS with 0.2% Tween-20) for 1 hr at room temperature and the membrane was probed with anti-MMP-2 antibody overnight at 4°C. The probed membrane was washed twice with TBS and incubated for 1 hr at room temperature with HRP conjugated secondary antibody. The MMP-2 specific bands were detected with ECL kit followed by autoradiography. Densitometry of the bands was performed after the images were scanned and quantitated using NIH software as described above.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P19">All the experiments were performed four times and values were expressed as mean ± SEM. Statistical analysis based on student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (unilateral and unpaired) was scored to identify significant differences in multiple comparisons. A level of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S17"><title>RESULTS</title><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S18"><title>Impact on mouse retinal endothelial cell proliferation by arresten</title><p id="P20">Type IV collagen derived arresten inhibits tumor angiogenesis in mice by targeting vascular/capillary endothelial cells in the tumor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>. Here we attempted to delineate the bFGF mediated anti-endothelial cell activity of recombinant human arresten using MRECs. We conducted a series of angiogenic experiments to define the proangiogenic activity of bFGF using MRECs. First, we carried experiments for dose response of bFGF on MREC proliferation, which is increased by bFGF treatment in a concentration dependent manner (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Based on this result, bFGF at different concentrations was used to stimulate proliferation in MRECs. We then tested the antiangiogenic activity of arresten by proliferation assay after bFGF stimulation in MRECs. The impact of different doses of arresten on different doses bFGF induced MREC proliferation was evaluated using MTT assay. The results showed that MREC proliferation was increased significantly by bFGF at 0.5 to 5 ng/ml concentrations for about 48 hrs (*p &lt;0.01 and **P &lt; 0.005) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). When different doses of arresten was treated to 0.25–5 ng/ml bFGF stimulated MRECs, an insignificant inhibition in MREC proliferation at 0 to 0.5 ng/ml of bFGF was observed (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). Interestingly, in the same experiment a significant effect of bFGF (1–5 ng/ml) induced MREC proliferation ranging from 1 and 10 μg/ml of arresten at 48 hr (*P&lt;0.01) was observed (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). In addition, different doses of arresten had no effect on MREC proliferation in absence of bFGF thus eliminating any of its cytotoxic activity (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>, 0.0 ng/ml bFGF). Further, different doses of bFGF stimulated MREC proliferation was inhibited by 10 μg/ml of arresten at 48 hr (*P&lt; 0.005) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>arresten inhibits bFGF-induced MREC migration</title><p id="P21">Migration of endothelial cells play an important early role in neovascularization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>. We next evaluated the effects of arresten on MREC migration. Growth factor bFGF, a known chemo-attractant of endothelial cells was used to stimulate MREC migration that was assessed after 48 hr of incubation. Stimulation of MRECs with 10 ng/ml bFGF on type IV collagen coated membrane resulted in a significant increase in MREC migration compared to untreated control (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). Growth factor bFGF induced MREC migration was attenuated when cells were pre-incubated for 10 min with different concentrations of arresten (0.5, 1 and 10 μg/ml) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). Migration of MRECs across type IV collagen coated membrane towards bFGF in a Boyden chamber was significantly inhibited by arresten in a dose dependent manner (*P&lt; 0.01, 10 ng/ml bFGF vs. 10 μg/ml arresten) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="background" id="S20"><title>Regulation of bFGF stimulated MMP-2 expression by arresten in MREC</title><p id="P22">Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) play crucial role in degradation of the vascular basement membrane ECM proteins, promoting endothelial cell invasion, migration and angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>. Based on the above findings on the inhibition of bFGF stimulated proliferation and migration of MREC by arresten, we next determined the effects of arresten on MMP-2 expression and activity. Expression of MMP-2 mRNA was increased in presence of bFGF compared to control. This increase in MMP-2 mRNA was not significantly altered in presence of different doses of arresten (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, middle and lower gels). The MMP-2 mRNA expression in MRECs incubated with bFGF in presence of different doses of arresten was also assessed by densitometry (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, upper graph). In addition, bFGF induced MMP-2 mRNA levels reached maximum after 24 and 48 hr of treatment. This bFGF stimulated up regulation of MMP-2 expression was not diminished by 5 μg/ml of arresten (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, upper graph and middle gel). Growth factor bFGF stimulation of MMP-2 expression was not altered in presence of different doses of arresten (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, upper graph).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Inhibition of bFGF stimulated MMP-2 activation by arresten in MRECs</title><p id="P23">The bFGF stimulated MMP-2 mRNA expression was not altered in presence of arresten in MRECs. However, incubation with arresten inhibited proliferation and migration of MRECs in response to bFGF, which suggests alterations in the activity of MMP-2. Activation of MMPs is crucial for degradation of ECM proteins and invasion of endothelial cells during angiogenesis. To test the bFGF stimulated secretion and activation of MMP-2, we treated MRECs with different doses of arresten for 48 h and the conditioned medium was analyzed for activated MMP-2 levels. Gelatin zymography results conformed the presence of a 72-kDa pro form of MMP-2 alone in control MREC conditioned medium (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> lower gel, lanes 1), whereas in bFGF stimulated conditioned medium the 72-kDa inactive and 66-kDa active MMP-2 were present (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> lower gel, lanes 2). However, conditioned medium from arresten treated MRECs exhibited dose dependent inhibition of a 66-kDa MMP-2 active form (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> lower gel, lanes 3–7). The 10 ng/ml bFGF stimulated MMP-2 activation in presence of different doses of arresten, was assessed by densitometry. These results indicate a significant inhibition of MMP-2 activation without any significant effect on its expression level (*P&lt; 0.01) at 10 ng/ml bFGF vs. 2.5 and 5 μg/ml arresten (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, upper graph).</p><p id="P24">Gelatin zymography of MREC cytosolic extracts was examined to evaluate total levels of MMP-2 protein. These experiments revealed a 72-kDa pro-MMP-2 that was similar to the basal level seen in control MREC extracts after 48 hr (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A</xref>, lane 1 and 2, with and without bFGF). The pro-MMP-2 band intensity was considerably increased in presence of 10 ng/ml bFGF, and this increase was not inhibited by arresten after 24 and 48 hr (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7A</xref>, lane 3 and 4, with bFGF and arresten). Further we also analyzed inhibition of MMP-2 activation in MREC cultured medium by immunoblotting using anti-MMP-2 antibody, which indicated that arresten inhibits bFGF-mediated MMP-2 activation at 24 and 48 hr (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7B</xref>, lanes 3 and 5). As shown in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">figure 7B</xref> the 72-kDa pro-MMP-2 band was less intense in absence of bFGF and arresten, while its intensity became strong in presence of bFGF with and without arresten treatment. These results were further confirmed by zymographic analysis, which suggests that arresten has the ability to inhibit bFGF induced MMP-2 activation in cultured MRECs (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, zymogram). The level of secreted pro-MMP-2 was significantly up-regulated by bFGF stimulation between 24 and 48 hr (*p &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> graph). Whereas under similar experimental conditions, bFGF induced activated MMP-2 was significantly increased (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> graph). As expected suppression of MMP-2 activation was observed in MREC culture medium upon treatment with arresten (5 μg/ml) (**P &lt; 0.005) (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> graph). Compared with the time-course of RT-PCR analysis, it is evident that the expression of MMP-2 protein occurred a little later than its mRNA expression. In addition, a 66-kDa activated MMP-2 band was clearly observed in gelatin zymography at 24 and 48 hr of bFGF-treated MREC cultured condition medium (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, lanes 2, 3 and 5, 6). In the same experiment arresten treated groups inhibited bFGF stimulated activation of MMP-2 (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, lanes 3, 6). These results indicate that bFGF can also stimulate expression and activation of MMP-2, and this expression was not altered by arresten treatment, whereas activation of MMP-2 was suppressed by arresten.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S22"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P25">The homeostasis of angiogenesis is regulated by a balanced production of endogenous stimulators (growth factors) and inhibitors (antiangiogenic factors). The alterations in this balance will result in abnormal angiogenesis. The pro-angiogenic factor bFGF plays a crucial role in mediating intraocular neovascularization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>. Retinal endothelial cells express bFGF receptors and respond to the proangiogenic stimulus of bFGF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>. Therefore, it has been hypothesized that the antiangiogenic agents would play an important role in the treatment of retinal diseases with a neovascular component.</p><p id="P26">In the past decade much effort has been focused on identifying new endogenous angiogenesis inhibitors aiming treatment options for angiogenesis related diseases. This search has led to the discovery of a number of endogenous circulating angiogenesis inhibitors that are generated through specific proteolysis such as type XVIII collagen or endostatin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>. Later in early 2000, researchers also identified several non-collagenous domains from type IV collagen, as inhibitors of endogenous angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>. One such molecule, arresten (α1(IV)NC1) was isolated from human placenta that showed decreased new blood vessel formation in growing mice tumors and in matrigel angiogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>. Moreover, no signs of toxicity or re-growth of tumors was observed as long as tumor bearing mice were treated with arresten <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>. arresten binds to α1β1 integrin and inhibits type IV collagen dependent proliferation and VEGF mediated migration in different endothelial cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>. However, the effects of arresten on retinal neovascularization <italic toggle="yes">in-vivo</italic> as well as its mechanisms of action remain elusive and have not been examined.</p><p id="P27">In this study, MRECs cultured on type IV collagen and incubated with bFGF was used as a model of retinal angiogenesis <italic toggle="yes">in-vitro.</italic> At different concentrations (0.25 to 5 ng/ml) bFGF treatment was used to stimulate MRECs and the impact of arresten at various concentrations ranging from 0.1 to 10 μg/ml, on bFGF induced endothelial cell proliferation was evaluated. Our results demonstrate that MREC proliferation was significantly increased by bFGF. However, the bFGF-induced proliferation was significantly inhibited by arresten in a dose and time dependent manner.</p><p id="P28">Inhibition of endothelial cell migration is one of the most studied and best-characterized functions reported for arresten <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>. In this study, the impact of arresten on bFGF induced MREC migration was determined using a Boyden chamber cell migration assay. Stimulation of MRECs with 10 ng/ml of bFGF resulted in a significant increase in migration activity. This enhanced cell migration activity was inhibited by pre-incubation of MRECs with arresten in a dose dependent manner. Migration of endothelial cells involves assembly and disassembly of focal adhesions in concert with integrin signaling, and arresten seems to interfere effectively with both systems. Soluble arresten inhibits α1β1 integrin dependent endothelial cell migration and survival <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>. Depending on the cell type and the growth factor environment, the inhibition of cellular migration with soluble arresten was correlated with an increase or decrease in focal adhesion kinase and p38 MAP kinase phosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>. Furthermore, arresten induced down regulation of other hypoxia induced factors, indicating that the signals induced by arresten not only modify the survival signals, but also affect pericellular proteolytic activity. The molecular targets and the signaling mechanisms of arresten are subject of future investigation.</p><p id="P29">The <italic toggle="yes">in-vitro</italic> studies performed here indicate that α1(IV)NCI inhibits MMP-2 activation. Thus a function of arresten may be to interfere with MMP-2 signaling, similar to that reported for endostatin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>. MMP-2, a tightly regulated zinc dependent endopeptidase, is capable of degrading ECM proteins with a significant role in a number of vitreoretinal diseases including diabetic retinopathy, retinopathy of prematurity and choroidal neovascularization of age-related macular degeneration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>. MMP-2 has complex regulatory mechanisms during progression of angiogenesis, which include degradation of ECM, endothelial cell migration, capillary morphogenesis and proliferation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>. In physiological or pathological angiogenesis, MMPs are utilized as an effector pathway to direct the cellular processes. In angiogenesis, the proteolytic activity of MMPs might be a part of biphasic regulation: (1) In early proangiogenic steps MMPs activity is critical for the proteolysis of basement membrane and migration of the endothelial cells; (2) In late antiangiogenic steps, MMPs activity is crucial for generation of endogenous angiogenesis inhibitor fragments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>. It is therefore expected that neovascularization is associated with changes in MMPs activity. Localization of MMP-2 and MMP-9 expression to the areas of new blood vessel formation and Bruch’s membrane suggests a possible role for these gelatinases in the growth of neovascular complexes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>. We earlier reported that arresten inhibits endothelial cell migration on type IV collagen matrix <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>. This effect is now identified to be mediated through association of arresten with pro-MMP-2 and inhibition of MMP-2 activation.</p><p id="P30">In the present study, the expression of MMP-2 mRNA was increased in MRECs incubated with bFGF and this increase was not affected by arresten. However, the secretion and activation of MMP-2 by MRECs was significantly increased in presence of bFGF, and the same was inhibited by arresten in a dose-dependent manner, without affecting MMP-2 mRNA levels. Thus, MMP-2 may be one of the key targets for arresten mediated down regulation of MMP-2 activity. Together our results suggests that arresten may have a potential role in arresting the progression of retinal neovascularization by inhibiting degradation of the retinal basement membrane through inhibition of MMP-2 activation. The implications from our study identify use of arresten for prevention of neovascularization in eye disorders and needs further evaluation through pre-clinical studies.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="S23" sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures</title><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Effects of bFGF on MREC proliferation</title><p>Values are mean ± standard deviation of four independent experiments performed in triplicates, and shown as the % of control (the bFGF free group). Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis. *p &lt; 0.01 and **p &lt; 0.005 as compared with control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f1.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Effects of arresten on bFGF stimulated MREC proliferation</title><p>Panel A represents effect of arresten on MREC proliferation induced by various concentrations of bFGF (0–5 ng/ml) and arresten (0–10 μg/ml) for 48 hr. MRECs cultured in incomplete medium (without serum or other factors) were used as control. Values are mean ± standard deviation of four independent experiments performed in triplicate, and shown as the % of control. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis. There is a difference among groups with and without arresten (10 μg/ml) at 1–5 ng/ml concentration of bFGF (*p &lt; 0.01). Panel A represents effect of arresten on MREC proliferation induced by various concentrations of bFGF (0–5 ng/ml) and arresten (10 μg/ml) similar to panel A (*p &lt; 0.005).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f2.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Effect of arresten on bFGF-induced migration of MREC</title><p>Upper panel represents number of MRECs migrated in incomplete medium with bFGF or with bFGF and different doses of arresten, using a light microscope and representative fields (100× magnification) are shown. Photographs of the underside of Boyden chamber membrane are shown. Arrows represent MRECs that migrated to the underside of the Boyden chamber membrane. Lower panel graph represents the number of migrated cells (mean ± standard deviation of) from four independent experiments performed in triplicate, and reported as the % of with and without bFGF/arresten. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis. *p &lt; 0.01 as compared with bFGF alone and bFGF/arresten.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f3.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>RT-PCR analysis of arresten dose effects on MMP-2 mRNA</title><p>Upper panel represents graphical representations of relative expression levels of MMP-2 mRNA in MRECs treated for 48 hr with 10 ng/ml bFGF alone or combined with various indicated concentrations of arresten. Values are mean ± standard deviation of three amplification reactions performed on a single cDNA sample and shown as the % value obtained for samples without bFGF and arresten. Middle panel represents agarose gel with RT-PCR for MMP-2 mRNA. Lower panel agarose gel GAPDH cDNA used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f4.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Effect of arresten on time course of MMP-2 mRNA expression in MRECs</title><p>Upper panel represents relative RT-PCR expression levels of MMP-2 mRNA in MRECs treated with 10 ng/ml bFGF alone or combined with 5 μg/ml arresten for 24 to 48 hr. MRECs cultured with and without bFGF/arresten treatment. Values are mean ± standard deviation of five amplification reactions performed on a single cDNA sample and shown as the % of the values obtained using bFGF without arresten. Middle panel represents agarose gel with RT-PCR for MMP-2 mRNA. Lower panel agarose gel GAPDH cDNA used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f5.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Effect of arresten on MMP-2 secretion and activation in MRECs</title><p>MRECs were treated for 48 hr with and without 10 ng/ml bFGF or combined with different doses of arresten. Upper graph represents relative percentage of basal expression and activation levels of MMP-2 protein in MREC conditioned medium, determined by densitometry of four independent experiments. Values are mean ± standard deviation of three independent experiments and shown as the percentage (%) of with and without bFGF/arresten. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis. *p &lt; 0.01 as compared without and with bFGF/arresten. The lower panel represents gelatin zymography of MMP-2 secretion and activation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f6.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>arresten does not alter expression of MMP-2 secretion but inhibits its activation upon secretion</title><p>MRECs were treated for 24 to 48 hr with 10 ng/ml of bFGF alone or combined with 5 μg/ml of arresten and cell extracts or cultured conditioned medium was examined by zymography and Western blot analysis for MMP-2. Panel A upper lanes, zymography represents relative expression levels of cytosolic MREC extracts and lower panel shows Western blot of actin as loading control. Panel B represents Western immunoblot of 24 and 48 hr conditioned MREC medium with and without bFGF and arresten.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f7.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>Effect of arresten on time course inhibition of MMP-2 activation</title><p>MRECs were treated with 10 ng/ml of bFGF alone or combined with 5 μg/ml of arresten for 24 to 48 hr. The graph represents relative expression levels for MMP-2 in MREC conditioned medium. Values are mean ± standard deviation of two independent experiments and is shown as the % of the bFGF values observed for cells treated with bFGF but without arresten for 24 and 48 hr. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for statistical analysis. *p &lt; 0.01 and p **&lt; 0.005 as compared with and without bFGF/arresten 24 and 48 hr. Lower panel shows a representative gelatin zymography for the inhibition of MMP-2 activation by arresten treatment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms173449f8.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig></sec><ack id="S24"><p>Research related to this work was supported by Flight Attendant Medical Research Institute Young Clinical Scientist Award Grant FAMRI 062558 (AS); Dobleman Head and Neck Cancer Institute Grant 61905 (AS); startup funds of Cell Signaling and Tumor Angiogenesis Laboratory at Boys Town National Research Hospital (AS) and also supported (in part) by National Eye Institute grant EY16995 (NS).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocular angiogenesis</article-title><source>Int Rev Exp Pathol</source><year>1986</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2422135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Amore</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of retinal and choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3974</fpage><lpage>3979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7525506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor. The trigger for neovascularization in the eye</article-title><source>Lab Invest</source><year>1995</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7540232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jampol</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebroon</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldbaum</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral proliferative retinopathies: an update on angiogenesis, etiologies and management</article-title><source>Surv Ophthalmol</source><year>1994</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8066542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0039-6257(94)90146-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Risau</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenesis and endothelial cell function</article-title><source>Arzneimittelforschung</source><year>1994</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7514414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folkman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenesis in cancer, vascular, rheumatoid and other disease</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm0195-27</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keshamouni</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human alpha1 type IV collagen NC1 domain exhibits distinct antiangiogenic activity mediated by alpha1beta1 integrin</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>2801</fpage><lpage>2810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI24813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1199529</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6934208"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6856005"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boosani</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannam</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of COX-2 mediated signaling by alpha3 type IV noncollagenous domain in tumor angiogenesis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2007</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>1177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2007-01-066282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1939900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of vascular endothelial growth factor and its receptor (KDR/flk-1) mRNA in experimental choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10342375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1076/ceyr.18.3.203.5368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FGF receptor 1 expression in experimental choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Jpn J Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8988422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of basic fibroblast growth factor mRNA in developing choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8921239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/02713689609017649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyashiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of transforming growth factor-beta mRNA in experimental choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9043818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1076/ceyr.16.1.9.5121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boosani</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalabothula</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munugalavadla</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FAK and p38-MAP Kinase-Dependent Activation of Apoptosis and Caspase-3 in Retinal Endothelial Cells by {alpha}1(IV)NC1</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2009</year><comment>Epub ahead of print</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.09-3473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2795568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19443723</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6856005"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Reilly</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endostatin: an endogenous inhibitor of angiogenesis and tumor growth</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9008168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81848-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petitclerc</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutaud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prestayko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New functions for non-collagenous domains of human collagen type IV. Novel integrin ligands inhibiting angiogenesis and tumor growth in vivo</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>8051</fpage><lpage>8061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.275.11.8051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the anti-angiogenic properties of arresten, an alpha1beta1 integrin-dependent collagen-derived tumor suppressor</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yexcr.2008.08.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2613512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of triamcinolone acetonide on bFGF-induced migration and tube formation in choroidal microvascular endothelial cells</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><year>2002</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11954780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00417-001-0398-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of endostatin on bFGF-induced proliferation, migration, and matrix metalloproteinase-2 expression/secretion of bovine choroidal endothelial cells</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16020281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/02713680590959358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalluri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basement membranes: structure, assembly and role in tumour angiogenesis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petitclerc</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteolytic exposure of a cryptic site within collagen type IV is required for angiogenesis and tumor growth in vivo</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11535623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.200103111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2196184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>ESR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recombinant non-collagenous domain of alpha2(IV) collagen causes involution of choroidal neovascularization by inducing apoptosis</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16557520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcp.20645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colorado</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamphaus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-angiogenic cues from vascular basement membrane collagen</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2520</fpage><lpage>2526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10811134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boosani</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning, purification, and characterization of a non-collagenous anti-angiogenic protein domain from human alpha1 type IV collagen expressed in Sf9 cells</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pep.2006.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnamoorthy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serine 48 in initiation factor 2 alpha (eIF2 alpha) is required for high-affinity interaction between eIF2 alpha(P) and eIF2B</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>15398</fpage><lpage>15405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10563826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi991211n</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramaiah</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of serine 51 in initiation factor 2 alpha (eIF2 alpha) promotes complex formation between eIF2 alpha(P) and eIF2B and causes inhibition in the guanine nucleotide exchange activity of eIF2B</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>12929</fpage><lpage>12938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11041858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi0008682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorenson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheibani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of murine retinal endothelial cells</article-title><source>Mol Vis</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12740568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeshima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colorado</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct Anti-Tumor Properties of a Type IV Collagen Domain Derived from Basement Membrane</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>21340</fpage><lpage>21348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M001956200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhakar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeisberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalluri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human tumstatin and human endostatin exhibit distinct antiangiogenic activities mediated by alpha v beta 3 and alpha 5 beta 1 integrins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>4766</fpage><lpage>4771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0730882100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC153630</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6856005"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moberg</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated matrix metalloprotease and angiostatin levels in integrin alpha 1 knockout mice cause reduced tumor vascularization</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>2202</fpage><lpage>2207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10681423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.040378497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC15778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheibani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High Glucose Promotes Retinal Endothelial Cell Migration through Activation of Src, PI3K/Akt1/eNOS, and ERKs</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpcell.00322.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2603562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18945941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liotta</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garbisa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foltz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastatic potential correlates with enzymatic degradation of basement membrane collagen</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1980</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6243750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/284067a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stetler-Stevenson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinases and metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>1999</year><volume>43 </volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>S42</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s002800051097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koivunen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arap</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valtanen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor targeting with a selective gelatinase inhibitor</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10429241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/11703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor/vascular permeability factor is temporally and spatially correlated with ocular angiogenesis in a primate model</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1994</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7521577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1890317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrigg</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor in ocular fluid of patients with diabetic retinopathy and other retinal disorders</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>331</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>1487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7526212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJM199412013312203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweigerer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiddes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gospodarowicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capillary endothelial cells express basic fibroblast growth factor, a mitogen that promotes their own growth</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2433585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/325257a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endostatin inhibits endothelial and tumor cellular invasion by blocking the activation and catalytic activity of matrix metalloproteinase</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>5410</fpage><lpage>5413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New functional roles for non-collagenous domains of basement membrane collagens</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>4201</fpage><lpage>4214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.00106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2789001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egeblad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New functions for the matrix metalloproteinases in cancer progression</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagase</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The second dimer interface of MT1-MMP, the transmembrane domain, is essential for ProMMP-2 activation on the cell surface</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>13053</fpage><lpage>13062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M709327200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2442350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sejersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berglin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seregard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kvanta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinases and metalloproteinase inhibitors in choroidal neovascular membranes</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>2194</fpage><lpage>2200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9761302</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Declaration of Interest:</bold> The authors report no conflict of interest. The authors also alone are responsible for the content and writing of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>