
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Hum Reprod</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">763</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">molehr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">9513710</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">molehr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Molecular Human Reproduction</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1360-9947</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2407</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2816170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2816170.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2816170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2816170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molehr/gap093</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gap093</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>microRNA 21: response to hormonal therapies and regulatory function in leiomyoma, transformed leiomyoma and leiomyosarcoma cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoping</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names initials="N">Nasser</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><addr-line>Department of OB/GYN</addr-line>, <institution>University of Florida</institution>, <addr-line>Box 100294, Gainesville, FL 32610</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>1</label>Correspondence address. Tel: <phone>+1-352-273-7566</phone>; Fax: <fax>+1-352-392-6994</fax>; E-mail: <email>cheginin@ufl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">184586</issue-id><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2009</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2009. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of European Society of Human Reproduction and Embryology</copyright-statement><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="gap093.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Mol Hum Reprod" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC3612010"><article-title>NOTICE OF RETRACTION: ‘MicroRNA 21: response to hormonal
therapies and regulatory function in leiomyoma, transformed leiomyoma and
leiomyosarcoma cells’ by Qun Pan, Xiaoping Luo and Nasser Chegini,
Molecular Human Reproduction (MHR) 16: 215–227 (2010).
doi:10.1093/molehr/gap093</article-title><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><date><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><source>Molecular Human Reproduction</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molehr/gas045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3612010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23097499</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Aberrant expression of microRNAs (miRNAs), including miR-21, and alteration of their target genes stability have been associated with cellular transformation and tumorigenesis. We investigated the expression, regulation and function of miR-21 in leiomyomas which develop from myometrial cellular transformation. The results indicated that miR-21 is over-expressed in leiomyomas with specific elevation during the secretory phase of the menstrual cycle and in women who received Depo-Provera and oral contraceptives, but reduced due to GnRHa therapy (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Bioinformatic analysis of microarray gene expression profiles previously obtained from the above cohorts, and myometrial smooth muscle cells (MSMC) and leiomyoma smooth muscle cells (LSMC) treated with GnRHa, transforming growth factor (TGF)-β and TGF-β receptor type II (TGF-βRII) antisense oligomer, indicated that a number of miR-21-predicted target genes were co-expressed and differentially regulated in these cohorts. Gain- and loss-of-function of miR-21 in MSMC, LSMC, transformed LSMC and leiomyosarcoma cell line (SKLM-S1) resulted in differential expression of many genes, including some of the miR-21-predicted/validated target genes, PTEN, PDCD4 and E2F1, and TGF-βRII, in a cell-specific manner. Gain-of miR-21 function in MSMC and LSMC reduced TGF-β-induced expression of fibromodulin and TGF-β-induced factor (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and moderately altered the rate of cell growth and caspase-3/7 activity in these cells. We concluded that miR-21 is aberrantly expressed and hormonally regulated in leiomyomas where, through functional interaction with ovarian steroids and the TGF-β signaling pathway, either directly or indirectly regulates a number of genes whose products are critical in leiomyoma growth and regression as well as their potential cellular transformation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>leiomyoma</kwd><kwd>miRNA</kwd><kwd>ovarian steroids</kwd><kwd>GnRHa</kwd><kwd>TGF-β receptors</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>microRNAs (miRNAs) have emerged as a key regulator of gene expression stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C17">Engels and Hutvagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C51">Zeng, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C19">Fujita and Iba, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C44">Selbach <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Several thousand miRNAs have been identified and/or predicted and the expression of a large number of them has been profiled in various normal cells and tissues and functionally associated with normal cellular activities such as cell growth, differentiation and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C17">Engels and Hutvagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C3">Baek <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C12">Connolly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C19">Fujita and Iba, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C27">Ku and McManus, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C44">Selbach <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Conversely, aberrant expression of some miRNAs has been associated with a number of disorders; more specifically, cancer, where they regulate gene expression involved in cellular transformation and tumorigenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C5">Calin and Croce, 2006a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C6">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C17">Engels and Hutvagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C51">Zeng, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C10">Cho, 2007</xref>). Furthermore, the genes encoding a number of miRNAs are located at chromosomal fragile sites and at regions of cytogenetic abnormalities associated with cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C6">Calin and Croce, 2006b</xref>). Functionally, miRNAs through base-pairing with complementary sites at 3′-untranslated region's (UTR) of specific target genes cause their translational repression, and in some cases, mRNA degradation.</p><p>Expression profiling has also identified a few hundred miRNAs expressed in myometrium and leiomyomas with altered expression of a number of them, including miR-21 in leiomyomas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C49">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C37">Marsh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Altered expression of miR-21 has been reported in many tumors of various origins and functionally predicted to target the expression of several hundred genes whose products are involved in cellular proliferation, apoptosis, migration, transformation and tumorigenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C13">Corsten <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C25">Iorio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C32">Lui <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C38">Meng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C45">Si <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C2">Asangani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C7">Chan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C16">Dillhoff <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C18">Frankel <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C21">Gabriely <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C31">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Among the experimentally validated genes targeted by miR-21 are phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN), programmed cell death 4 (PDCD4), transcription factor E2F1, tissue inhibitor of matrix metalloproteinase (TIMP3), Sprouty2 (SPRY2), tropomyosin 1 and maspin in a number of cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C38">Meng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C21">Gabriely <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C31">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C43">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C53">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The expression of miR-21 has also been reported to be regulated by ovarian steroids in MSMC and LSMC, and in the MCF-7 breast cancer cell line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C50">Wickramasinghe <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).</p><p>In addition, leiomyomas when compared with myometrium are also characterized by differential expression of a large number of genes, with specific gene polymorphisms and non-random chromosomal abnormalities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C30">Ligon and Morton, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C35">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C1">Al Hendy and Salama, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C15">Denschlag <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C48">Villanova <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C39">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). As such, altered expression of miRNAs, including miR-21 in leiomyoma, may have a direct regulatory function on the expression of specific target genes whose products play a key role in cellular transformation and their subsequent growth and/or apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C41">Peng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). To provide further support for regulatory function of miR-21 in leiomyoma, the present study was designed to (i) examine the expression and hormonal regulation of miR-21 in paired myometrium and leiomyomas and (ii) through gain- and loss-of function determine the expression of genes regulated by miR-21 in MSMC and transition into LSMC, transformed LSMC (t-LSMC) and the human leiomyosarcoma cell line SKLM. In addition, through bioinformatic data mining, we assessed the profile of miR-21-predicted target genes in these tissues, as well as in LSMC and MSMC treated with GnRHa, transforming growth factor (TGF)-β1 and TGF-β receptor type II (TGF-βRII) siRNA. We also examined the influence of gain-of function of miR-21 on the expression of genes downstream from TGF-β receptor signaling and cell growth and apoptosis in these cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Tissues</title><p>Portions of matched leiomyoma and myometrium were collected from premenopausal women (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 23) who were scheduled to undergo hysterectomy for indications related to symptomatic leiomyomas. The patients' age ranged from 27 to 49 years (median = 38). Of these patients, 13 were not taking any medications, including hormonal therapy for the previous 3 months prior to surgery; based on last menstrual period and endometrial histology, they were from the mid-proliferative (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7) and early-mid-secretory (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6) phases of the menstrual cycle. The hormonal therapies administered to women for medical management of their symptomatic leiomyomas included: GnRHa (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4), Depo-Provera (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3) and oral contraceptives (OCPs) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3). All the leiomyomas used in this study were 3–5 cm in diameter and were collected at the University of Florida affiliated Shands Hospital with prior approval from the Institutional Review Board. Immediately after collection, the tissues were snapped frozen and kept in liquid nitrogen for further analysis, or used for isolation of smooth muscle cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Isolation and culture of leiomyoma and myometrial smooth muscle cells</title><p>Myometrial smooth muscle cells (MSMC) and leiomyoma smooth muscle cells (LSMC) were isolated from small portions of matched leiomyoma and myometrium from women who did not receive any hormonal therapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C9">Chegini <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). The cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplement with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and until reaching confluence with change of media every 2–3 days. Prior to use, the cells were characterized using antibodies to α-smooth muscle actin, desmin and vimentin. Spontaneously transformed LSMC (t-LSMC) originally established in our laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>) and a human leiomyosarcoma cell line, SKLM-S1 (purchased from ATCC), were also cultured in DMEM supplement with 10% FBS. All the supplies for isolation and culturing of the cells were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St Louis, MO, USA), Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA, USA) and Fisher Scientific (Atlanta, GA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Transfection with miR-21 oligonucleotides</title><p>On the basis of the type of experiments, MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 were seeded at various densities in 96-, 24- and 6-well plates and in 10 cm Petri dishes and cultured until reaching 70% confluence. The cells were washed and incubated in antibiotic-free media for 24 h. Prior to large-scale transfection, the transfection condition was optimized using cells cultured in 24-well plates in Opti-MEM I serum-reduced medium, BLOCK-iT Fluorescent Oligo and Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Following optimization, the cells were transfected with 50 nM of 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-methoxyethyl (2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE) modified pre-miR-21, anti-miR-21 and their respective negative controls (Ambion) for 6 h. The media were removed and the cells were cultured with full growth medium for 24, 48 and 72 h. Total RNA was isolated from these cells and subjected to real-time PCR. On the basis of the result of miR-21 expression in transfected MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1, all the experiments were carried out for 48 h unless otherwise stated.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Bioinformatic analysis</title><p>The computational algorithms TargetScan (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</uri>) and miRDB (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://mirdb.org">http://mirdb.org</uri>) were utilized for selection of miR-21-predicted target genes. The search results were downloaded to a local database and filtered using Microsoft Access. In addition, a few genes experimentally validated as miR-21 targets in other cell types were identified through PubMed search and added to the database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Table SI</ext-link> consists of 265 genes utilized for data mining and bioinformatic analysis throughout this study.</p><p>Through data mining, we searched for the expression of the 265 genes in the microarray database previously collected from (i) paired leiomyoma and myometrium from Caucasians and African Americans and from women who received GnRHa therapy; (ii) LSMC and MSMC treated with GnRHa (0.1 µM) for 2, 6 and 12 h; (iii) LSMC and MSMC treated with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for 2, 6 and 12 h; and (iv) LSMC and MSMC treated with TGF-βRII antisense oligomer (1 µM) for 24 h and then treated with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for an additional 24 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C34">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C35">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C39">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). The normalized and transformed expression values of 194 genes were commonly identified in these cohorts (all 265 were expressed in paired leiomyoma and myometrium from Caucasians and African Americans), which were sorted based on a 1.5-fold change cut-off (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>) and analyzed by cluster and tree-view. The gene list was also subject to functional analysis using the Ingenuity Pathways Software (Ingenuity<sup>®</sup> Systems, Redwood City, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Real-time quantitative RT–PCR</title><p>Using real-time PCR, the relative expression of miR-21 was determined in paired leiomyoma and myometrium from the proliferative and secretory phases of the menstrual cycle, from women who received GnRHa and Depo-Provera or OCPs. Transfection efficiency of anti- and pre-miR-21 in LSMC, MSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM was also determined using real-time PCR. Total RNA was extracted from these tissues and cells using Trizol (Invitrogen), and RNA quantity and quality were determined using an ND-1000 Spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE, USA) and an Agilent Bio-Analyzer, respectively. Reverse transcription (RT) was performed with the Taqman microRNA RT Kit (Applied Biosystems) using a miR-21 stem-loop primer (Ambion). Each reaction was performed on 10 ng or 1 µg of total RNA. Real-time PCR was carried out using Taqman gene expression master mix and Taqman miRNA and/or gene expression assays, respectively (Applied Biosystems). Reactions were incubated for 10 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles of 15 s at 95°C, and for 1 min at 60°C. Analysis of relative miRNA and mRNA expression was performed using the ΔΔ<italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>T</sub> method with U6 and 18s rRNA as endogenous controls, respectively, according to the manufacturer's guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Western blot analysis was carried out following gain- and loss-of function of miR-21 in LSMC, MSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM. Total protein was isolated from these cells using lysis buffer containing protease inhibitor, centrifuged and the supernatants were collected; their total protein content was determined using a conventional method as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C36">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C39">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Equal amounts of sample proteins (20 µg) were subjected to SDS–PAGE, transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride membranes, and following further processing, the blots were probed with antibodies generated against a select number of miR-21 target genes; including E2F1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA), PTEN (Santa Cruz), PDCD4 (Santa Cruz and Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) and TGF-βRII (Santa Cruz Biotechnology and Abcam) at 1:200 and 1:500 (TGF-βRII) dilutions. The membranes were also probed with an antibody generated against β actin (Sigma-Aldrich) at a 1:10 000 dilution serving as a loading control. Blots were washed and exposed to corresponding horseradish peroxidase-conjugated IgG; immunostained proteins were visualized using enhanced chemiluminescence reagents (Amersham-Pharmacia Biotech, Piscataway, NJ, USA), and band densities were determined as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C29">Levens <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C34">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005a</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C36">, 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Influence of miR-21 gain-of function on TGF-βRII downstream gene expression</title><p>MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 were cultured in 6-well plates and in 10 cm Petri dishes until reaching subconfluence. Following gain- and loss-of-miR-21 function as described above, the cells were serum-starved for 24 h and then treated with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for 24 h. Total RNA and protein were isolated from these cells and subjected to real-time PCR and western blot analysis, respectively, to determine the expression of fibromodulin (FMOD) and TGF-β-induced factor (TGIF)—two known targets of TGF-β regulatory function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C34">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005a</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C36">, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C29">Levens <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). Western blotting was carried out using antibodies generated against FMOD and TGIF at 1:1000 dilution (Santa Cruz Biochemical) and processed as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Cell proliferation and caspase-3/7 production assay</title><p>MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 were cultured in 96-well plates at a density of 5000 cells/well for 24 h, and washed and subjected to gain- and loss-of function of miR-21 as described above. After 48 h of incubation, the cells were subjected to Cell Titer 96 Aqueous Non-Radioactive Cell Proliferation Assay (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The rate of absorbance was determined using a multiplate reader and the results were presented as fold change when compared with their respective untreated controls.</p><p>The cells with miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions were also treated with 100 µl of Caspase Glo 3/7 reagent according to the manufacturer's instructions (Promega). MSMC treated with 1 µM Staurosporine (Sigma) for 24 h was used as a positive control according to the Caspase Glo 3/7 Assay Technical Bulletin. The caspase-3/7 activities were determined using a multiplate reader and relative luminescence intensity was presented as fold change when compared with untreated controls.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Gene expression microarray</title><p>Total RNA isolated from LSMC, MSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 with miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions was subjected to large-scale gene expression profiling. Following amplification and second-strand cDNA synthesis, 5 µg of purified cDNA was reverse transcribed using a high-yield RNA transcript labeling kit (Ambion). The product was purified and 20 µg of cRNA (0.5 µg/µl) was fragmented, mixed with 300 µl of hybridization mixture and 200 µl of the mixture was hybridized to Human Ref-8 v3 Expression BeadChip (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA), consisting of 24 526 oligonucleotide probe sets representing 18 630 transcripts. The beads were processed after meeting recommended criteria for use of the expression arrays according to the manufacturer's protocol.</p><p>The expression values were background-subtracted, globally normalized using BeadStudio version 1.5.1.3 (Illumina), and as recommended, the expression values with a differential score of ≥13 were independently removed from each cohort. Transformed gene expression values were subjected to supervised assessments and differentially expressed genes were selected based on <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05 [analysis of variance (ANOVA), Tukey test] and a 1.5-fold change cut-off (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C39">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Data presented in Fig. 5 were derived from the gene expression values selected based on two-way ANOVA, supervised assessments by removing gene expression values ≤50 and sorted based on a 1.5-fold cut-off in MSMC with miR-21 gain-of function divided to control. These values were subjected to cluster and tree-view analysis and functional analysis using Ingenuity Pathways Software (Ingenuity<sup>®</sup> Systems).</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Whenever appropriate, the results were reported as mean ± SEM of at least three experiments performed using different MSMC and LSMC preparations from three different patients. Comparisons between two or among multiple groups were made using paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and ANOVA followed by a Tukey's honest significant difference <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> pairwise multiple comparison, respectively, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>This study consisted of three integrated parts aiming to analyze the expression, regulation and functional significance of miR-21 in myometrium and leiomyoma, their isolated smooth muscle cells, spontaneously transformed LSMC as well as a leiomyosarcoma cell line.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>miR-21 expression is altered in leiomyomas</title><p>Microarray profiling identified the expression of a few hundred miRNAs with altered expression of several of them, including miR-21, in leiomyomas, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 when compared with myometrium and MSMC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C49">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C37">Marsh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). As part of continuation of this work and the first aim of the present study, we further assessed the expression and regulation of miR-21 in paired leiomyoma and myometrium during the menstrual cycle and in women who received hormonal therapies for medical management of their symptomatic leiomyomas. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F1">1</xref>, miR-21 is expressed at elevated levels in leiomyomas when compared with myometrium from both proliferative and secretory phases of the menstrual cycle (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), confirming the above studies. In addition, the relative expression of miR-21 in leiomyomas, but not myometrium, was higher in women who received Depo-Provera and OCPs and lower in women who received GnRHa therapy (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F1">1</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The pattern of miR-21 expression levels determined by real-time PCR in these cohorts correlated with the pattern obtained from microarray profiling, with the exception of a moderate increase in miR-21 expression in leiomyomas from the OCP group (data not shown).</p><fig id="GAP093F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relative expression of miR-21 in paired leiomyoma (LYO) and myometrium (MYO) from the proliferative (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6) and secretory (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6) phases of the menstrual cycle, and in women who received GnRHa therapy (GnRHa; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3), Depo-Provera (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4) and those taking OCPs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p><p>Lines indicate a significant difference between LYO and corresponding MYO in each cohort. Different letters indicate a significant difference among treatments (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and ANOVA)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09301.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>miR-21-predicted target genes are expressed and regulated by GnRHa therapy</title><p>As a continued part of the first aim, we focused on the expression profile of genes predicted/validated as miR-21 targets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>) in myometrium and leiomyoma. Utilizing the list of 265 genes predicted and/or validated as miR-21 targets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>) through data mining of microarray data sets previously obtained in: (i) paired leiomyomas and myometrium from Caucasians and African Americans and women who received GnRHa therapy; (ii), LSMC and MSMC treated with GnRHa (0.1 µM) or with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for 2, 6 and 12 h; and (iii) LSMC and MSMC treated with TGF-βRII siRNA (1 µM) for 24 h and then treated with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for an additional 24 h, we identified the expression of 194 of these genes commonly expressed among the cohorts with cluster and tree-view analyses shown in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Figs S1–3</ext-link>. The number of genes differentially expressed (≥1.5-fold change cut-off) in leiomyomas when compared with myometrium from Caucasians and African Americans (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Fig. S1A</ext-link>), in women who received GnRHa therapy when compared with the untreated group (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Fig. S1B</ext-link>), and in MSMC and LSMC treated with GnRHa (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Fig. S3A</ext-link>) is presented as part of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SI</ext-link>. Noticeable among the differentially expressed genes are PDCD4, PTEN, SPRY1, E2F1, STAT3 and TGF-βRII, suggesting the possible regulation of some of the miR-21 target genes by GnRHa. Pathway analysis identified and mapped 21 functional networks among these genes, with 15 networks containing a majority of the genes, including networks 1, 2 and 3 with network 1 having most of the TGF-β-related genes (network 1 and merged networks 1, 2 and 3 are shown in two figures in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SI</ext-link>). The biological functions of the genes in these networks are shown in a bar graph (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>), which include regulation of cell growth and proliferation, cell death, connective tissue development and function, cell assembly, transcriptional regulation, and cancer.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Experimental validation of miR-21 target genes</title><p>As a second part of the aim of this study, we focused on experimental validation of a few miR-21 target genes in leiomyoma and myometrial cells. To accomplish this, we isolated MSMC and LSMC (primary cultures through third passage), and t-LSMC and SKLM-S1, and transfected the cells with pre- and anti-miR-21 (gain-and loss-of functions, respectively) for 24, 48 and 72 h. Prior to transfection, the basal expression of miR-21 was determined in each cell type and, as indicated, MSMC expressed a lower level of miR-21 when compared with LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F2">2</xref>A). As expected, gain-of-miR-21 function significantly increased, whereas loss-of function decreased the expression of miR-21, when compared with scrambled-oligo-transfected cells after 48 h (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F2">2</xref>B) and 72 h (data not shown) of incubation. Since PTEN, PDCD4 and E2F1 have been experimentally validated as miR-21 targets in several cell types, we next assessed whether gain- or loss-of function of miR-21 altered their expression and the expression of TGF-βRII in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1. These cells expressed PTEN, PDCD4, E2F1 and TGF-βRII mRNAs and proteins at varying levels (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F4">4</xref>) and gain- and loss-of-miR-21 function differentially altered their expression in a cell-specific manner when compared with scrambled-oligo-transfected controls (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F4">4</xref>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, the level of E2F1 production in MSMC and LSMC, and PDCD4 production in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 were very low with weak band intensity (data not shown). The degree of miR-21 functional regulation of PTEN, PDCD4, E2F1 and TGF-βRII expression in these cells is possibly due in part to differences in the baseline expression of the genes, or cell-type-dependent action of miR-21; i.e. more effective inhibition of TGF-βRII in SKLM-S1 and MSMC, when compared with LSMC with least inhibition in t-LSMC.</p><fig id="GAP093F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Relative level of miR-21 endogenous expression in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 (<bold>A</bold>) and following gain- and loss- of function of miR-21 (<bold>B</bold>).</p><p>Cells were cultured and at 70% confluence, were transfected with 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE miR-21 inhibitor (anti-miR-21), pre-miR-21 or their respective scrambled control (Ctrl) oligonucleotides (50 nM) for 48 h. Total RNA was isolated from these cells and the level of miR-21 expression was determined using real-time PCR. The expression value in MSMC (A) and controls for each cohort independently (B) was set at 1. Different letters or number of asterisks indicate a significant difference among cell types and treatments, respectively, when compared with their respective controls (Ctrl) with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09302.jpg"/></fig><fig id="GAP093F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis of PTEN, E2F1 and TGF-βRII production in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 with gain- and loss-of-function of miR-21.</p><p>Total cellular protein was isolated from cells transfected with 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE anti-miR-21 (<bold>A</bold>), pre-miR-21 (P) or their respective scrambled oligomer controls (AC and PC) for 48 h and subjected to immunoblot analysis. Note considerable changes in the level of production of PTEN in MSMC and LSMC; E2F1 in t-LSMC and SKLM-S1; and TGF-βRII in MSMC, LSMC and SKLM-S1 (see densitometric analysis in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F4">4</xref>) when compared with controls.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09303.jpg"/></fig><fig id="GAP093F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The level of (mean ± SEM) expression of E2F1 (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>), PTEN (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>), TGF-βRII (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) and PDCD4 (<bold>G</bold>) mRNA (A, C, E and G) and protein (B, D, and F) determined by real-time PCR and western blot analysis, respectively, in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM with gain- and loss-of-function of miR-21 as described in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F3">3</xref>. Note considerable alterations in the level of gene expression in pre-mir-21 versus anti-mir-21 treated cells when compared with scrambled oligomer-treated (Ctrl) cells. The basal expression of E2F1, PTEN and PDCD4 is shown in (<bold>H</bold>). The expression values in MSMC (H) and in controls for other cohorts were independently set at 1 for each cell type. Different letters or number of asterisks indicate a significant difference among cell types (A–G) or genes analyzed (H), respectively, when compared with their respective controls (Ctrl) with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09304.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>miR-21 overall regulation of gene expression in MSMC and LSMC</title><p>To further assess the overall regulatory function of miR-21 on MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM gene expression, total RNA was isolated from these cells (with gain- and loss-of function of miR-21) and subjected to gene microarray analysis. Based on <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05 (ANOVA) and a 1.5-fold change cut-off, the expression of 117, 807, 705 and 998 genes was altered (directly and/or indirectly) as a result of miR-21 gain-of function in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1, respectively, when compared with scrambled-oligo-transfected controls (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SIIA–D</ext-link>). Of these genes, the expression of 83, 609, 434 and 702 genes was down-regulated and of 34, 198, 271 and 296 genes was up-regulated in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM, respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SIIA–D</ext-link>). Loss-of function of miR-21 also altered the expression of a number of genes, some displaying an inverse pattern of expression when compared with cells with gain-of miR-21 function (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplemental data, Table SII</ext-link>). Cluster/tree-view analysis of 406 differentially regulated genes in MSMC with gain-of miR-21 function versus control is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F5">5</xref> with the enlarged region showing several genes, including TGF-βRII (TGFBR2), whose expression was altered in MSMC, LSMC and SKLM-S1, and to a lesser extent in t-LSMC (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="GAP093F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Cluster and tree-view analyses of 406 up- and down-regulated genes selected based on two-way ANOVA with a ≥1.5-fold change cut-off in MSMC with gain-of miR-21 function/control in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1.</p><p>The cells were transfected with 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE anti-miR-21(Anti), pre-miR-21 (Pre-mir) or their respective scrambled oligomers (Ctrl) for 48 h. Enlarged area shows the heat map and the list of genes, including TGFBR2 (TGF-βRII), whose expression was altered in these cohorts. The lists of up- or down-regulated genes, the Ingenuity pathways analysis and the biological function of the genes in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 are presented in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SIIA–D</ext-link>, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09305.jpg"/></fig><p>Functional pathway analysis mapped several networks among the genes targeted by gain-of function of miR-21 in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 (see figures embedded into <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SIIA–D</ext-link>, respectively; and network summary in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SII</ext-link>). A majority of the focus genes function as transcriptional, translational and signal transduction mediators, and in cell cycle regulation, ECM turnover, cell–cell communication and metabolic activities etc. (see bar graphs embedded into <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary Table SIIA–D</ext-link>). The list of 15 genes, including TGFβRII, whose expression was commonly altered as a result of miR-21 gain-of function in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-s1, is presented in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SIIE</ext-link>. Additionally, of the 265 genes predicted/validated as miR-21 targets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>), the expression of 9, 10, 31 and 10 genes, including TGF-βRII, was altered in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1, respectively, as a result of miR-21 gain-of function (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplemental data, Table SIIF</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Regulation of miR-21-predicted target genes by TGF-β and influence of gain-of function of miR-21</title><p>Since TGF-βRII appeared to be a target of miR-21 regulatory function (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F4">4</xref>), as a third aim of this study, we assessed whether the expression of genes downstream from TGF-β receptor signaling is altered as a result of miR-21 gain-of function. As illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F6">6</xref>A–C, 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE modified pre-miR-21-transfected MSMC and LSMC (P) treated with TGF-β1 (P-TGF) produced significantly lower levels of FMOD and transforming growth interacting factor (TGIF) when compared with cells transfected with negative control oligo (PC) and PC treated with TGF-β1 (PC-TGF) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F6">6</xref>; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). We extended this aim and assessed the expression pattern of the genes predicted/validated as miR-21 targets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Table SI</ext-link>) in microarray profiles previously obtained from LSMC and MSMC treated with TGF-β (2.5 ng/ml) for 2, 6 and 12 h, and cells treated with TGF-βRII antisense siRNA for 24 h followed by TGF-β treatment. The data mining indicated that 35 genes were differentially expressed and altered by at least 1.5-fold in MSMC and LSMC treated with TGF-β (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Fig. S2A</ext-link>) and TGF-βRII siRNA (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data, Fig. S2B</ext-link>).</p><fig id="GAP093F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Gain-of function of miR-21 alters TGF-βRII and TGF-β-regulated genes.</p><p>MSMC and LSMC were transfected with 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-MOE pre-mir-21 (P) or scrambled oligomer controls (PC) for 48 h, and then treated with TGF-β1 (2.5 ng/ml) for 24 h (P-TGF and PC-TGF). Total protein isolated from these cells was subjected to western blot analysis of FMOD and TGIF (<bold>A</bold>) and their band densities (mean ± SEM) are reported in (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C)</bold>, respectively. β-Actin was used as a loading control. The control (bars representing PC) band intensity values are independently set at 1 for each protein. Different letters indicate a significant difference among treatments when compared with their respective controls (Ctrl), with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09306.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions on cell growth and caspase activity</title><p>Aberrant expression of miR-21 has been associated with alteration of cell growth and apoptosis in various cell types. To follow up on the functional significance of miR-21, we determined the influence of miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions on cell growth and apoptosis of MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1. The results indicated that miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions have a moderate effect on the rate of cell proliferation and caspase-3/7 activity, which occurred in a cell-type-specific manner (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F7">7</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig id="GAP093F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Cell growth and apoptosis in response to miR-21 gain- and loss-of functions.</p><p>MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM were cultured and transfected with anti-miR21, pre-miR-21 or their respective scrambled oligomer (Ctrl) for 48 h and the rate of growth (<bold>A</bold>) and caspase-3/7 activity (<bold>B</bold>) were determined. Bar graphs (mean ± SEM) show that gain-of function of miR-21 (pre-mir-21) in LSMC and SKLM moderately increased the rate of cell growth and reduced caspase-3/7 activities, when compared with loss-of-function of miR-21 (anti-mir21) and Ctrl, respectively. The control values are set at 1 independently for each group. Different letters indicate a significant difference among cell types and treatments, respectively, when compared with their respective controls (Ctrl) with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09307.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Accumulated evidence has associated the aberrant expression of many miRNAs, including miR-21, with various pathological disorders, more specifically cancers, and with the regulation of the expression of specific genes involved in various aspects of tumorigenesis, i.e. cellular transformation, proliferation, apoptosis and migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C45">Si <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C2">Asangani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C7">Chan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C12">Connolly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C16">Dillhoff <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C20">Fujita <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C21">Gabriely <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C43">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C46">Talotta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C53">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In the present study, we confirmed that miR-21 is aberrantly expressed in leiomyomas when compared with myometrium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C49">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C37">Marsh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). We further demonstrated a specific increase in expression of miR-21 in leiomyomas, but not in myometrium, during the secretory phase of the menstrual cycle and in women who received Depo-Provera and OCPs, with lower expression in women who received GnRHa therapy. It was previously observed that miR-21 is differentially regulated by ovarian steroids in MSMC and LSMC, and this included an increase in expression of miR-21 following medroxyprogesterone acetate treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C40">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Although the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> condition does not reflect the complex <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> milieu, these results imply that miR-21 is hormonally regulated in leiomyomas, potentially influencing the expression of genes targeted by miR-21.</p><p>Through data mining, a number of miR-21-predicted/validated target genes, including PDCD4, PTEN, SPRY1, SPRY2, E2F1 and TGFβRII were identified as differentially expressed in leiomyomas when compared with myometrium from African Americans and Caucasians, and from patients who received GnRHa therapy. The co-expression and ethnic and hormonal regulation of miR-21 and predicted target genes in leiomyomas imply their potential functional interactions. As such, using isolated MSMC and LSMC as well as t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 with gain- and loss-of function of miR-21 revealed that a number of genes, including some of miR-21-predicted targets are potentially regulated by miR-21. However, there was a considerable difference in the number and types of genes targeted by miR-21 gain-of function among these cells, which could be due to variation in the level of their endogenous miR-21 expression, or the degree of cellular transformation (benign versus cancerous as in LSMC versus t-LSMC and SKLM-S1). Since altered expression of miR-21 has been associated with cellular transformation and tumorigenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C10">Cho, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C12">Connolly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>), and miR-21 differentially regulates specific genes in a cell-type-based manner, miR-21 could influence cellular events necessary for transformation of myometrial cells into leiomyomas and further into leiomyosarcoma. Since TGF-β plays a central role in pathogenesis of leiomyoma and miR-21 appeared to regulate TGF-βRII expression, we extended our investigation and through data mining we identified that a number of miR-21-predicted/validated target genes differentially expressed in MSMC and LSMC treated with TGF-β and TGF-βRII antisense oligomer. Our preliminary results have also indicate that TGF-β regulates the expression of miR-21 in MSMC and LSMC; these results, in combination with the finding of our study, suggest a direct and/or indirect regulatory interaction between TGF-β and miR-21 in leiomyoma cells.</p><p>The biological significance of regulatory interactions between TGF-β and miR-21 and their target genes, PTEN, E2F1, PDCD4 and TGF-βRII, may lie in their functions in various cellular activities critical to the outcome of tumorigenesis and tissue fibrosis, including in leiomyomas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C8">Chegini, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C34">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C36">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). However, miR-21 differentially regulated the expression of PDCD4, PTEN, E2F1 and TGF-βRII in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM, which could be either due to variations in basal endogenous expression of these genes, or a cell-type-dependent action of miR-21. As such, a feedback regulatory mechanism between miR-21 and these genes, specifically TGF-β, may result in balancing their different functions in a cell- and tissue-dependent context (i.e. inflammatory response, cell growth regulation and tissue turnover), leading to either cellular transformation and tumorigenesis, tissue fibrosis or tumor regression (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F8">8</xref>). Although the TGF-β system is well recognized as a key regulator of establishment and progression of tissue fibrosis, up-regulation of miR-21 has also been observed in several fibrotic disorders over-expressing TGF-β, including cardiac hypertrophy, vascular walls balloon injury and neointimal lesion (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C26">Krichevsky and Gabriely, 2009</xref>). However, controversies exist regarding miR-21 functional regulation of cellular events, and gene expression changes leading to tissue fibrosis. Inhibition of miR-21 reduced hypertrophy of cardiomyocytes and neointima formation, but resulted in cardiac cellular hypertrophy; conversely, over-expression of miR-21 in cardiomyocytes altered the expression of sets of genes and resulted in the development of cellular hypertrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C47">Thum <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C26">Krichevsky and Gabriely, 2009</xref>).</p><fig id="GAP093F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram describing the potential regulatory interactions between ovarian steroids, GnRHa, TGF-β and miR-21.</p><p>miR-21 and TGF-β are differentially regulated by ovarian steroids and GnRHa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C9">Chegini <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C39">Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C33">Luo and Chegini, 2008</xref>). TGF-β increases the expression of miR-21 which suppresses the expression of TGF-βRII, resulting in reduced TGF-β receptor-mediated signaling. Regression of TGF-βRII by miR-21 either directly or indirectly alters TGF-β-induced miR-21 through a feedback mechanism, leading to differential expression of PTEN, E2F1 and PDCD4 and other miR-21 target genes. As such, altered expression of miR-21, TGF-β, TGF-βRII, PTEN, E2F1 and PDCD4 could then alter the balance between the rate of cell growth and apoptosis, inflammatory reaction and extracellular matrix accumulation, resulting in leiomyoma growth and regression, or mediate myometrial and leiomyoma cellular transformation. Using Ingenuity pathway analysis provided a functional network among TGF-βRII-, PTEN-, E2F1- and PDCD4-mediated actions, which include interactions with other gene products and signaling pathways (i.e. Smad, AKT, JUK, NFkβ, cbp/p300, VEGF, 14-3-3 and proteasome) that regulate the above cellular processes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gap09308.jpg"/></fig><p>miR-21 has also been shown to regulate cellular dedifferentiation, and in cell lines with low or undetectable expression of miR-21, their differentiation resulted in increased miR-21 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C26">Krichevsky and Gabriely, 2009</xref>). As such, the cell-specific function of miR-21 on PTEN, E2F1, PDCD4 and TGF-βRII expression in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1, representing various stages of progression from normal to benign, transformed and sarcoma, and differentiated versus undifferentiated status, may reflect the diverse actions of miR-21, including crosstalk with other miRNAs and target gene products. PDCD4 acts as a tumor suppressor and decreases benign and malignant tumor progression, whereas E2F1 acts as an oncogene or a tumor suppressor regulating cell cycle progression and apoptosis, depending on cellular context. PTEN antagonizes the action of phosphatidylinositol-triphosphate kinase (PI3K)-signaling pathways and Akt-signaling cascades, which increase cellular survival and proliferation. Previous studies have demonstrated that TGF-β down-regulates the expression of PTEN in various cell lines, whereas it increases PDCD4 expression, mediating apoptosis through caspase activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C52">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Functional interactions between miR-21 and TGF-β in vascular smooth muscle cells, where TGF-β, acting in part through miR-21 regulation and Smad signaling, down-regulated the expression of PDCD4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C14">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). MSMC and LSMC with gain-of function of miR-21 treated with TGF-β also expressed lower levels of FMOD and TGIF, two genes known to be regulated by TGF-β (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C29">Levens <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C34">Luo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005a</xref>), comparable to TGF-βRII antisense-treated cells. Such cell- and gene-target-specific actions of miR-21 may be necessary since the products of many of the genes targeted by miR-21 also regulate the expression of other genes, i.e. TGF-β regulation of PTEN, E2F1 and PDCD4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C24">Hu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C23">Hjelmeland <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C22">Garcia-Alvarez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C4">Bu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C11">Chow <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C14">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C28">Lacerte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C42">Petrocca <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C44">Selbach <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C46">Talotta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Consistent with the level of gene expression in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 with gain- and loss-of miR-21 functions, proteomic analysis has also indicated that a single miRNA repressed the production of many proteins; however, the level of repression was relatively low, and miRNA actions occurred either directly or indirectly through protein synthesis from thousands of genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C3">Baek <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C44">Selbach <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p><p>The consequence of miR-21 functional regulation of TGF-βRII, E2F1, PTEN and PDCD4 in leiomyoma cells could also involve cell survival, while limiting their cellular transformation and tumorigenesis when compared with t-LSMC and SKLM-S1. Aberrant expression of miR-21 has been associated with alteration of cell proliferation, migration, invasion and malignant transformation by targeting the expression of select genes whose products are integral to these processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C38">Meng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C45">Si <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C12">Connolly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C31">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C42">Petrocca <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C53">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Pathway analysis indicated that many of the genes targeted by miR-21 in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 are functionally involved in regulating the above processes, as well as tissue development, connective tissue development/function, cell assembly, cell cycle, cell death and metabolism. However, gain- or loss-of function of miR-21 in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 had a limited effect on the rate of cell proliferation, while moderately affecting caspase activities. In several cancer cell lines, inhibition of miR-21 decreased cell proliferation, migration and invasion, and reduced PDCD4 production, while increasing PTEN and matrix metalloproteinases 2 and 9 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C13">Corsten <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C38">Meng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C2">Asangani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C18">Frankel <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C31">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C53">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>); we expected a similar trend at least in t-LSMC and SKLM-S1 with miR-21 gain-of function. The reason for differences in miR-21 action on the rate of cell proliferation/caspase activities could be due to cell type specificity and/or the extent of alteration of genes functionally regulating cell cycle progression and apoptosis. Additionally, it has been reported that NFIB, a target of miR-21 regulatory function, binds to the miR-21 promoter and negatively regulates its expression—a double-negative feedback regulation considered to sustain miR-21 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="GAP093C20">Fujita <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). As such, miR-21 functional regulation of TGF-βRII, E2F1, PTEN and PDCD4 in leiomyoma cells could serve in mediating cell survival, while limiting cellular transformation and tumorigenesis when compared with t-LSMC and SKLM.</p><p>In summary, we provided further evidence that miR-21 is over-expressed in leiomyomas when compared with myometrium in a menstrual cycle-dependent manner, with altered expression in women who received GnRHa, Depo-Provera and OCPs. More specifically, we identified a number of genes as potential targets of miR-21 via direct and/or indirect actions, including PDCD4, E2F1, PTEN and TGF-βRII in MSMC, LSMC, t-LSMS and SKLM-S1, with potential regulation by GnRHa and TGF-β in these cells. Functionally, miR-21 had a moderate influence on the rate of proliferation and apoptosis of these cells, but down-regulated the expression of TGF-β downstream target genes. On the basis of our previous and present results, we propose a feedback regulatory interaction between miR-21, TGF-β and ovarian steroids, necessary to balance their different functions in a cell- and tissue-dependent context, influencing events such as inflammatory response, cell growth regulation and tissue turnover, leading either to cellular transformation and tumorigenesis, or tissue fibrosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="GAP093F8">8</xref>). Although the goal of this study was to better understand the regulatory function of miR-21 in leiomyomas, future investigation is required to address the direct interaction of miR-21 with TGF-βRII 3′-UTR and with other miR-21 target genes, as well as the biological significance of other aberrantly expressed miRNAs in leiomyoma and transformation into leiomyosarcoma.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gap093/DC1">Supplementary data are available at http://molehr.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by grants <award-id>RO1HD37432</award-id> and <award-id>RO1HD58664</award-id> (N.C.) and <award-id>RO3HD58779</award-id> (X.L.) from the <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>[Supplementary Data]</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gap093_index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gap093_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gap093_gap093_supp_table_1.xls" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="gap093_gap093_supp_table_2.xls" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="GAP093C1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Hendy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catechol-O-methyltransferase polymorphism is associated with increased uterine leiomyoma risk in different ethnic groups</article-title><source>J Soc Gynecol Investig</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsgi.2005.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asangani</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolova</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leupold</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colburn</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allgayer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 (miR-21) post-transcriptionally downregulates tumor suppressor Pdcd4 and stimulates invasion, intravasation and metastasis in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2128</fpage><lpage>2136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17968323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1210856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of microRNAs on protein output</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>455</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2745094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapanadze</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trojanowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opposite effects of dihydrosphingosine 1-phosphate and sphingosine 1-phosphate on transforming growth factor-beta/Smad signaling are mediated through the PTEN/PPM1A-dependent pathway</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>19593</fpage><lpage>19602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18482992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M802417200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2443671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA signatures in human cancers</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006a</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs and chromosomal abnormalities in cancer cells</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2006b</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>6202</fpage><lpage>6210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-21 microRNA expression in human gastric carcinomas and its clinical association</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18507035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brosens</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression and hormonal response</article-title><source>Uterine Leiomyomata:Pathogenesis and Management.</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher-name><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of GnRH analogues, 'add-back' steroid therapy, antiestrogen and antiprogestins on leiomyoma and myometrial smooth muscle cell growth and transforming growth factor-beta expression</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12468639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/molehr/8.12.1071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OncomiRs: the discovery and progress of microRNAs in cancers</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17894887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1476-4598-6-60</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2098778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carethers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGFbeta modulates PTEN expression independently of SMAD signaling for growth proliferation in colon cancer cells</article-title><source>Cancer Biol Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1694</fpage><lpage>1699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18769113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cbt.7.10.6665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2820113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melegari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchaikovskaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tennant</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slagle</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogler</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavolan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuschl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogler</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated expression of the miR-17-92 polycistron and miR-21 in hepadnavirus-associated hepatocellular carcinoma contributes to the malignant phenotype</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18688024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2353/ajpath.2008.080096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2527078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corsten</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasmieh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krichevsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissleder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 knockdown disrupts glioma growth in vivo and displays synergistic cytotoxicity with neural precursor cell delivered S-TRAIL in human gliomas</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>8994</fpage><lpage>9000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17908999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-1045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilyard</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMAD proteins control DROSHA-mediated microRNA maturation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>454</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18548003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2653422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentz</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hefler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietrowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeillinger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tempfer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotype distribution of estrogen receptor-alpha, catechol-O-methyltransferase, and cytochrome P450 17 gene polymorphisms in Caucasian women with uterine leiomyomas</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2006</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2005.07.1308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillhoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloomston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 is Overexpressed in Pancreatic Cancer and a Potential Predictor of Survival</article-title><source>J Gastrointest Surg</source><year>2008</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2171</fpage><lpage>2176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18642050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11605-008-0584-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4055565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutvagner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles and effects of microRNA-mediated post-transcriptional gene regulation</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>6163</fpage><lpage>6169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christoffersen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Programmed cell death 4 (PDCD4) is an important functional target of the microRNA miR-21 in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1026</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M707224200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Putative promoter regions of miRNA genes involved in evolutionarily conserved regulatory systems among vertebrates</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minoguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-21 Gene expression triggered by AP-1 is sustained through a double-negative feedback mechanism</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18384814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmb.2008.03.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wurdinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esau</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burchard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linsley</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krichevsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA 21 promotes glioma invasion by targeting matrix metalloproteinase regulators</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>5369</fpage><lpage>5380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18591254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.00479-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2519720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Alvarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Checa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampieri</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-3 is up-regulated by transforming growth factor-beta1 in vitro and expressed in fibroblastic foci in vivo in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Exp Lung Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16908447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/01902140600817481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjelmeland</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjelmeland</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigner</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontos</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of phosphatase and tensin homologue increases transforming growth factor beta-mediated invasion with enhanced SMAD3 transcriptional activity</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>11276</fpage><lpage>11281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16357132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-3016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cress</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor beta inhibits the phosphorylation of pRB at multiple serine/threonine sites and differentially regulates the formation of pRB family-E2F complexes in human myeloid leukemia cells</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2000</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/bbrc.2000.3556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Leva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donati</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casalini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taccioli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA signatures in human ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>8699</fpage><lpage>8707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17875710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-1936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krichevsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriely</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-21: a small multi-faceted RNA</article-title><source>J Cell Mol Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19175699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2008.00556.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3823035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behind the scenes of a small RNA gene-silencing pathway</article-title><source>Hum Gene Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/hum.2007.1226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacerte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta inhibits telomerase through SMAD3 and E2F transcription factors</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cellsig.2007.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibromodulin is expressed in leiomyoma and myometrium and regulated by gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogue therapy and TGF-beta through Smad and MAPK-mediated signalling</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/molehr/gah187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ligon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leiomyomata: heritability and cytogenetic studies</article-title><source>Hum Reprod Update</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11212080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/humupd/7.1.8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stribinskis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klinge</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colburn</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 promotes cell transformation by targeting the programmed cell death 4 gene</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>4373</fpage><lpage>4379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18372920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2008.72</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11968769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pourmand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of known and novel small RNAs in human cervical cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>6031</fpage><lpage>6043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-0561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expression and potential regulatory function of microRNAs in the pathogenesis of leiomyoma</article-title><source>Semin Reprod Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0028-1096130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2710997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profiling of leiomyoma and myometrial smooth muscle cells in response to transforming growth factor-beta</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2005a</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2004-1377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leiomyoma and myometrial gene expression profiles and their responses to gonadotropin-releasing hormone analog therapy</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2005b</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2004-1384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CCNs, fibulin-1C and S100A4 expression in leiomyoma and myometrium: inverse association with TGF-beta and regulation by TGF-beta in leiomyoma and myometrial smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16571622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/molehr/gal015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulun</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of microRNA species in human uterine leiomyoma versus normal myometrium</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2008</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1771</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17765232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2007.05.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2773156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehbe-Janek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghoshal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 regulates expression of the PTEN tumor suppressor gene in human hepatocellular cancer</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2007</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17681183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.05.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4285346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic and proteomic profiling I: leiomyomas in African Americans and Caucasians</article-title><source>Reprod Biol Endocrinol</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17716379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1477-7827-5-34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2063502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of microRNAs in myometrium and leiomyomas and regulation by ovarian steroids</article-title><source>J Cell Mol Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18182067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2007.00207.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2730932</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4594693"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melamed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiproliferative effects by Let-7 repression of high-mobility group A2 in uterine leiomyoma</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18403645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-07-0370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onelli</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoloso</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de M</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iliopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilozzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>E2F1-regulated microRNAs impair TGFbeta-dependent cell-cycle arrest and apoptosis in gastric cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18328430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2008.02.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lypowy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vashistha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vatner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdellatif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 targets Sprouty2 and promotes cellular outgrowths</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3272</fpage><lpage>3282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1091/mbc.E08-02-0159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2488276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwanhausser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thierfelder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajewsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread changes in protein synthesis induced by microRNAs</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>455</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-21-mediated tumor growth</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2799</fpage><lpage>2803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17072344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1210083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimmino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matarazzo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casalino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Lauro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An autoregulatory loop mediated by miR-21 and PDCD4 controls the AP-1 activity in RAS transformation</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18850008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2008.370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalucci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauersachs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: novel regulators in cardiac development and disease</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18511432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cvr/cvn137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villanova</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girao</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baracat</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogen receptor alpha polymorphism and susceptibility to uterine leiomyoma</article-title><source>Steroids</source><year>2006</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16935316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.steroids.2006.07.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obijuru</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aris</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soteropoulos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A micro-RNA signature associated with race, tumor size, and target gene activity in human uterine leiomyomas</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17243163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/gcc.20415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manavalan</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klinge</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol downregulates miR-21 expression and increases miR-21 target gene expression in MCF-7 breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2584</fpage><lpage>2595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19264808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkp117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2677875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles of micro-RNA production and maturation</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>6156</fpage><lpage>6162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamajima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasutake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ideguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuhashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of programmed cell death 4 in transforming growth factor-beta1-induced apoptosis in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>6101</fpage><lpage>6112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16682950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GAP093C53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 targets tumor suppressor genes in invasion and metastasis</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cr.2008.24</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>