
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncogene</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8711562</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncogene</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0950-9232</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-5594</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2636853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC2636853.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">2636853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">2636853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS79633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2008.419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS79633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA79633</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Requirement for chromatin-remodeling complex in novel tumor suppressor HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression and growth control</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="B">B</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names initials="KJ">KJ</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names initials="D">D</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names initials="DV">DV</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="S">S</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Cancer Research Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label> CNRS UMR 8161, Institut de, Biologie de Lille, Institut Pasteur de Lille, Lille Cedex, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1">Correspondence: Professor S Wang, Cancer Research Center, R-906, Boston University School of Medicine, 715 Albany Street, Boston, MA 02118, USA. E-mail: <email>sw184@bu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">176150</issue-id><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>02</month><year>2009</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>02</month><year>2009</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-10 19:25:49.697"><day>10</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms79633.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="Fed Regist" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5019603"><article-title>Findings of Research Misconduct</article-title><volume>76</volume><issue>151</issue><date><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><fpage>47589</fpage><lpage>47590</lpage><source>Federal Register</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5019603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27737204</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="30" page="4374" journal-id="Oncogene" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC3378254"><article-title>RETRACTION. Requirement for chromatin-remodeling complex in novel tumor suppressor HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression and growth control</article-title><volume>30</volume><issue>42</issue><date><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date><fpage>4374</fpage><lpage>4374</lpage><source>Oncogene</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3378254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22011759</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="NIH Guide Grants Contracts (Bethesda)" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4259725"><article-title>Findings of research misconduct.</article-title><date><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><elocation-id>NOT-OD-11-103</elocation-id><source>NIH Guide for Grants and Contracts</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4259725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21853555</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p id="P1">HIC1 is a newly discovered tumor suppressor and transcriptional repressor that is frequently silenced in human tumors. HIC1 protein expression has been linked to better outcomes in breast cancers. The molecular mechanism underlying HIC1-mediated transcriptional and growth suppression, and the relevant targets of HIC1-mediated transcriptional modulation, is currently unclear. We have identified an HIC1 DNA-binding site in E2F-responsive gene promoters and demonstrate that HIC1 targets E2F-responsive genes for transcriptional regulation and growth suppression. We and others have recently discovered that Brg1, a central component of the SWI/SNF chromatin-remodeling family, is required for the transcriptional regulation of multiple cell cycle control-related genes, including E2F-responsive promoters. We studied HIC1 interactions with, and dependence upon, Brg1 activity, and found that HIC1 can recruit Brg1 to E2F-responsive promoters and that its transcriptional repression of these genes is dependent upon Brg1. These data indicate that HIC1 is a central molecule in a novel mechanism controlling cell growth and that the disruption of this HIC1-mediated pathway may lead to abnormal cell proliferation and, ultimately, cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>HIC1</kwd><kwd>E2F1</kwd><kwd>Brg1</kwd><kwd>SWI/SNF</kwd><kwd>transcription</kwd><kwd>cell cycle</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Brg1 is a central ATP-dependent chromatin-remodeling molecule of the SWI/SNF complex family that was found to be associated with transcriptional regulation of multiple genes critical to cell cycle control and growth regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Dunaief <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Dasgupta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giacinti and Giordano, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Inayoshi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Earlier studies revealed that Brg1 contains conserved SWI/SNF family domains that are essential for cell growth and transcriptional activation. Other evidences have demonstrated that Brg1 is required for the activation of certain genes, and Brg1 was initially considered to be a transcription activator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Dunaief <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1994</xref>).</p><p id="P3">Subsequent investigations, however, led to the discovery of Brg1 involvement in transcriptional repression. Brg1 was found to associate with Rb and its family members, and to participate in the repression of E2F-responsive genes and growth suppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Dunaief <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Betz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). We have recently established that Brg1 is also required for the transcriptional repression mediated by prohibitin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). The potential importance of Brg1 in the development of cancer, including breast cancer, was further supported by the discovery of mutations of Brg1 in many cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Strobeck <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>).</p><p id="P4">The molecular mechanisms of Brg1-mediated transcriptional repression have been recently investigated. We and others have discovered that the Brg1 and Brm ATPase components of SWI/SNF complexes are recruited by repressors of E2F to E2F-responsive promoters and are required for the repression of E2F-mediated transcription and growth control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Banine <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>).</p><p id="P5">To further investigate the precise molecular mechanism involved in the Brg1-mediated transcriptional regulation, we attempted to identify additional proteins that may associate with Brg1 and discovered that a novel tumor suppressor, HIC1, interacts with Brg1. HIC1 is a newly discovered tumor suppressor and transcriptional repressor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Bertrand <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>) that is found to be silenced in certain cancers, due, in many cases, to the methylation of its promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aggerholm <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Britschgi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Recent data indicate that HIC1 collaborates with p53 and plays critical roles in the regulation of cell growth and death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chen and Baylin, 2005</xref>). Disruption of HIC1 predisposes mice to a gender-dependent spectrum of malignant tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). A clinical study demonstrated that the expression of HIC1 is associated with a good outcome in human breast cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Nicoll <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), suggesting the potential importance of HIC1 as a target for diagnosis, prognosis and treatment of breast cancer. The molecular mechanism of HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression is not yet defined. A screen using synthesized oligos identified a potential HIC1 consensus sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2004b</xref>).</p><p id="P6">The genes that are targeted by the HIC1 tumor suppressor have not been fully defined. A recent study indicated that HIC1 binds to the promoter of the class III histone deacetylase Sirt1 at a GGCA motif and regulates its transcription, which in turn modulates p53-dependent DNA -damage responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). We show here that Brg1 is indeed required for HIC1-mediated transcriptional regulation of Sirt1. Upon discovering that HIC1 interacts with Brg1, a known regulator of transcription and growth, we speculated that the HIC1 tumor suppressor may require the SWI/SNF family to target the cell cycle control machinery through E2F. We show here that HIC1 targets E2F-responsive genes for transcriptional regulation and growth suppression, and this repression is dependent upon Brg1. Depletion of HIC1 by small interfering RNA (siRNA) resulted in the release of growth arrest. In light of the recent studies suggesting that G<sub>1</sub>–S phase cell cycle transit does not appear to be regulated by Rb under normal circumstances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Takahashi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>), alternative mechanisms in the normal cell cycle control therefore remain to be discovered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Stevaux <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). Our novel finding of E2F regulation by HIC1 in collaboration with SWI/SNF family members may represent one new level of control at this critical transition point.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>HIC1 interacts with SWI/SNF family members</title><p id="P7">Earlier studies demonstrated the involvement of SWI/SNF complex in the Rb-mediated E2F regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Strobeck <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). We recently discovered that Brg1 also participates in the regulation of transcription by E2F through an Rb-independent mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>). We extended our studies to investigate the molecular basis of Brg1-mediated growth suppression and transcriptional repression by identifying additional Brg1-interacting factors. HIC1 was of particular interest because of its newly discovered roles in transcriptional regulation and its potential links with cancer development. Furthermore, HIC1 expression is associated with good outcomes in breast cancer and we have recently reported that Brg1 is required in tamoxifen-induced growth suppression of breast cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Nicoll <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). We first tested whether HIC1 can physically interact with Brg1. HIC1-associated protein complexes were immunoprecipitated from human primary fibroblast cell extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>) with an anti-HIC1 antibody or control (anti-Myb) antibody, followed by immunoblot(IB) analysis using an anti-Brg1 antibody. As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>, Brg1 was detected in the HIC1 immunoprecipitates, indicating the ability of these molecules to associate. A reciprocal immunoprecipitation (IP)/IB was also performed that confirmed the association (data not shown). To further verify this novel interaction, IP/IB was also performed in MCF7 cells (which do not express HIC1) transfected with a Flag-tagged HIC1, the expression of which was confirmed by IB analysis using an anti-Flag antibody (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>). The extracts of the Flag-HIC1-transfected MCF7 cells were then IP using anti-tubulin (control) or anti-Flag antibody followed by IB analysis using anti-Brg1 or control (anti-Myb) antibody. Brg1 was detected in the Flag-HIC1 immunoprecipitates, confirming the association of these molecules (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1c</xref>). The reciprocal IP/IB was also performed, which confirmed the interactions (data not shown).</p><p id="P8">To further confirm the association between HIC1 and Brg1 and determine whether it is direct, we performed an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> glutathione <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-transferase (GST) pull-down assay, following protocols we have reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">2002a</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1d</xref>, a direct association between HIC1 and GST-Brg1 was detected. There was no association between HIC1 and the control GST or GST-DP1 (an E2F1-binding partner) protein, demonstrating the specificity of the association. The GST pull-down assay was repeated in the reciprocal fashion, which confirmed the association (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1d</xref>).</p><p id="P9">We and others have recently established that Brg1 is a novel regulator of E2F activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Dunaief <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). We therefore determined whether HIC1, as a transcriptional regulator and binding partner of Brg1, can also modulate E2F-mediated transcription. Reporter assays in HSF8 cells were performed to address this question. Transfection of HIC1 (expression confirmed by IB analysis, data not shown) repressed the positive control, a luciferase reporter the activity of which is controlled by HIC1-binding sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004a</xref>; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>); ectopic expression of HIC1 also effectively repressed an E2F-responsive luciferase reporter, to a similar extent as did the established repressors of E2F-mediated transcription (Rb and prohibitin; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>). HIC1 did not affect the control cFos gene activity, as shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>, confirming the specificity of its actions.</p><p id="P10">The molecular mechanism of HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression is not yet elucidated. A recent investigation identified a potential HIC1 consensus DNA-binding sequence (GGCA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2004b</xref>). The functional importance of this consensus sequence is further suggested by recent reports that demonstrated that the SIRT1 gene is targeted by HIC1 at this consensus site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). To test whether the repression of E2F-responsive transcription by HIC1 involves a direct association with the gene promoter, we first surveyed the human E2F1 promoter sequence. A sequence matching the consensus HIC1-binding site (GGCA) was identified on the E2F1 promoter (position 1644; GenBank accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U47675">U47675</ext-link>). We therefore tested whether HIC1 can indeed bind to the E2F1 promoter, using a chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Unsynchronized, actively growing HSF8 cells were treated to cross-link DNA and protein, followed by IP with anti-HIC1 antibody or control antibody. The cross-linking was then reversed and the DNA recovered from the immunoprecipitates was analysed by PCR, using a pair of primers that span the E2F/HIC1 consensus site. As shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref>, an amplified product was detected in the HIC1 immunoprecipitates of HSF8 cells for the E2F1 promoter, but not for the cFos promoter (a non-E2F-responsive promoter, used here as a control), indicating that HIC1 can indeed associate specifically with an E2F-responsive promoter. A ChIP assay on the same E2F promoter using an irrelevant control antibody (anti-tubulin) failed to generate any product, confirming the specificity of the ChIP assay (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Brg1 is required for HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression</title><p id="P11">We next examined whether Brg1 might participate in HIC1-mediated transcriptional regulation. The first studies were carried out in SW13 cells, which lack Brg1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>). Expression of HIC1 in the Brg1-negative SW13 cells failed to repress the activity of either the endogenous Sirt1 (an HIC1-responsive gene) or E2F1 (an E2F-responsive gene) gene (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>). Co-expression of Brg1 together with HIC1, however, induced strong repression of both genes (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>), which correlated with the recruitment of HIC1 and Brg1 to the promoters of these genes (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3b</xref>, ChIP, HIC1, Brg1). Expression of HIC1 and Brg1 after transfection in these studies was verified by IB (not shown). Transfection of Brg1 alone, without HIC1, produced only modest repression, suggesting that Brg 1 is required for HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p id="P12">To test whether the HIC1 and Brg1 co-occupy these HIC1-responsive promoters, we performed a sequential double-ChIP assay that is a slight modification of the established ChIP protocol we have reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>), on the same endogenous gene promoters, using an anti-HIC1 antibody for the first round of IP and an anti-Brg1 antibody for the second round of IP, followed by amplification and quantitation. The reciprocal double-ChIP assay was also performed. These assays of promoter occupancy indicated co-occupancy by HIC1 and Brg1 on these HIC1-responsive promoters (data not shown).</p><p id="P13">To further verify the necessity of Brg1 in HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression, the activity of the endogenous Sirt1 and E2F1 gene promoters was evaluated after repression of Brg1, using siRNA knock-down and the dominant-negative Brg1 strategy we have established earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>, the activity of both the endogenous Sirt1 and E2F1 genes was effectively repressed when HIC1 was overexpressed. This repression, however, was reversed by the co-transfection of a dominant-negative Brg1 or a Brg1 siRNA, which depleted Brg1 in the cells (knockdown confirmed by IB shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>, and further verified by quantitative reverse transcriptase PCR (RT–PCR) analysis, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4c</xref>), confirming the necessity of Brg1 in the HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression of endogenous HIC1-responsive promoters. HIC1 expression failed to affect a non-E2F-responsive promoter (cFos) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>). The experiment was repeated using three different siRNAs specific for the Brg1 gene, all of which generated comparable results (data from one siRNA is shown in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p id="P14">As shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, HIC1 and Brg1 both associate with the endogenous Sirt1 and E2F1 gene promoters in SW13 cells. We and others have established earlier that Brg1 and its SWI/SNF co-regulatory components are recruited to targeted promoters by certain transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>). We therefore tested whether the requirement for Brg1 in HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression correlates with its recruitment by HIC1 at responsive promoters, and our results show that promoter occupancy of HIC1 and Brg1 was induced significantly when HIC1 was ectopically expressed by transfection and the transcriptional activity of these responsive genes was coincidently repressed, suggesting that HIC1 may recruit Brg1 for transcriptional repression (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5a</xref>). Ectopic expression of HIC1 did not affect SP1 association with the cFos promoter (control), confirming the specificity (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5b</xref>).</p><p id="P15">To further elucidate the role of a Brg1-containing complex in HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression, we investigated the necessity of HIC1 in the recruitment of Brg1 to responsive promoters. As shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6a and b</xref>, transfection of a vector-based siRNA depleted HIC1 from HSF8 cells. This HIC1 depletion induced an increase in transcripts from the endogenous E2F1 gene (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6c</xref>). This release of transcriptional repression in a responsive gene when HIC1 was depleted correlated with decreases in Brg1 occupancy at the promoter of the E2F1 gene (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6c</xref>). The experiments were repeated on another HIC1-responsive gene, the Sirt1, which produced similar results (data not shown). Depletion of HIC1 using a second independent siRNA against HIC1 (depletion of HIC1 again confirmed by both IB and quantitative RT–PCR) produced similar results (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>HIC1 is required for growth arrest</title><p id="P16">A recent report linked expression of the HIC1 protein with a good clinical outcome in breast cancer, suggesting a role for HIC1 in growth control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Nicoll <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). The regulation of E2F transcriptional activity by HIC1 demonstrated above, along with a report showing the regulation of p53 by HIC1, further suggested a potential role for HIC1 in cell cycle control. We therefore tested the activity of HIC1 in growth regulation. Human primary fibroblast cells (HSF8) were stably transfected with either vector-based control siRNA or a specific HIC1 siRNA that depleted cellular HIC1 (confirmed by IB analysis and quantitative RT–PCR, data not shown). These transfected HSF8 cells were exposed to serum starvation, achieved by withdrawing serum for 72 h. The cell cycle profiles of these cells were then analysed by propidium iodide staining and flow cytometry. Serum starvation induced a G<sub>0</sub>/G<sub>1</sub> arrest in the control cells (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>, compare panels 1, 2 and 3) as expected, but this growth arrest did not occur in those HSF8 cells in which HIC1 had been depleted, indicating the necessity of HIC1 in serum deprivation-induced growth arrest at the restriction point (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>, panel 4).</p><p id="P17">To further verify the necessity of HIC1 in the induction of growth suppression, a colony-formation assay was performed. Serum starvation dramatically repressed the number of colonies generated by the control cells (transfected with an empty vector or a control siRNA), demonstrating the expected growth-inhibitory effect (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, as shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, this suppression of growth by serum starvation was released when the level of HIC1 protein was suppressed by transfection of HIC1 siRNA (suppression of HIC1 levels in these cells was confirmed by IB analysis and by quantitative RT–PCR, data not shown).</p><p id="P18">As demonstrated above, HIC1 associates with the E2F1 promoter. As HIC1 is required for the growth suppression induced by serum deprivation (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>), we hypothesized that the recruitment of HIC1 to responsive promoters may be regulated in a cell cycle-specific manner. To test this possibility, we prepared a G<sub>0</sub> cell population and a late G<sub>1</sub> population of HSF8 cells by serum starvation and release, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). E2F1 and HIC1 gene expression was assayed by quantitation of transcript levels. HIC1 association with the E2F1 promoter was also analysed by ChIP assay. As shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8a</xref>, a strong signal for HIC1 occupancy was detected in the G<sub>0</sub> stage, a time when E2F1 promoter activity is repressed, but not in late G<sub>1</sub> phase cells, when the E2F1 promoter is transcriptionally active (confirmed by transcript levels in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8b</xref>), indicating the cell cycle-specific recruitment of HIC1. Conversely, recruitment of E2F1 to the promoter was detected in the late G<sub>1</sub>, but not the G<sub>0</sub>, cell population, as expected (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8a</xref>). Quantitative RT–PCR revealed that the level of expression of HIC1 is also cell cycle regulated and correlated temporally with its pattern of association with E2F-responsive promoters (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8b</xref>). As HIC1 requires Brg1 for the repression of E2F1 gene expression, and the two molecules co-occupy HIC1-responsive promoters simultaneously, we tested for co-occupancy during different stages of the cell cycle by sequential (double) ChIP assay. As described above, the first IP was performed using an anti-HIC1 antibody, followed by a second round of IP on the HIC1 immunoprecipitates, using an anti-Brg1 antibody, followed by amplification and quantitation. As shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8a</xref>, a signal was detected in G<sub>0</sub> cells by the double-ChIP assay, but not in the late G<sub>1</sub> population, indicating HIC1/Brg1 co-occupancy on the E2F1 promoter at the G<sub>0</sub> stage of the cell cycle. We further confirmed this result by the reciprocal IPs, using an anti-Brg1 antibody IP first, followed by an anti-HIC1 IP and amplification (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8a</xref>). Interestingly, recruitment of Brg1 to the promoter was also detected in the late G<sub>1</sub> cell population, although no HIC1/Brg1 double occupancy was observed at that stage of the cell cycle, suggesting that Brg1, in the absence of HIC1, also participates in the transcriptional activation of the E2F1 gene. Double-ChIP assay for E2F1 and HIC1 was also performed and revealed that these two molecules never co-occupied the E2F1 promoter. A control experiment, demonstrating the expected co-occupancy by E2F1 and DP1 in late G<sub>1</sub> phase, validated the double-ChIP assay (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S6"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P19">The newly discovered tumor suppressor HIC1 serves as a transcriptional repressor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>) and growth repressor, but the molecular mechanisms involved in HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression or growth control have not yet been fully defined. Recent reports indicate that HIC1 regulates p53 through the repression of Sirt1 transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chen and Baylin, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>), suggesting the possibility that HIC1 might suppress cell proliferation through control of p53 activity. It has been well established that E2F collaborates with p53 in growth control, and a recent investigation revealed that Sirt1 modulates the E2F pathway by targeting the Rb tumor suppressor family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Wong and Weber, 2007</xref>). Ever since the seminal discovery of the functional interaction between the Rb tumor suppressor and the E2F transcriptional factors, the role of E2F has become a central focus of study regarding cell cycle regulation and cancer development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Nevins, 2001</xref>). Despite the tremendous advances made in this field, however, the precise mechanisms involved in the regulation of E2F transcriptional activity are not yet fully elucidated. Earlier studies indicated the important roles of Rb and its family members in E2F regulation. Yet, more recent technological advances allowing promoter-specific examination of regulatory complexes, such as ChIP assays, have produced findings that cast doubt on the traditional model in which Rb plays the central role in E2F regulation. For example, Rb is not found to associate with E2F-responsive promoters during normal cell cycle progression, and has therefore been theorized to serve as an E2F repressor only in specialized stress situations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Takahashi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). These new developments inevitably raise the question as to what molecule(s) serves as the regulator of E2F-responsive genes during normal cell cycle progression, if not Rb. The findings elucidated in this study indicate that the novel tumor suppressor HIC1 could serve as the alternative repressor of E2F-responsive genes.</p><p id="P20">As discussed above, HIC1 is a transcriptional regulator that might cooperate with p53 for growth suppression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Britschgi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). The data presented in this report reveal that HIC1 can also regulate E2F-responsive genes directly and repress cell growth. Significantly, depletion of HIC1 resulted in the abrogation of normal G<sub>1</sub>/S arrest, demonstrating the strict necessity and fundamental role of HIC1 in growth suppression in response to growth factor deprivation.</p><p id="P21">The molecular mechanism underlying HIC1-mediated transcriptional regulation is not yet clear. Recent biochemical studies identified HIC1-binding consensus sites (GGCA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2004b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Britschgi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). These potential HIC1-binding sites were later discovered in the Sirt1 promoter, which was recently established to be HIC1 responsive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Britschgi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Our results now establish that the E2F1 gene, which encodes an HIC1 consensus binding site in its promoter, is also targeted by HIC1. This discovery suggests a novel critical regulatory mechanism in E2F regulation. We have initiated studies (beyond the scope of this report) to further define this repressive mechanism.</p><p id="P22">The requirement for Brg1 in HIC1-mediated transcriptional regulation and growth suppression demonstrates the critical role of chromatin-remodeling molecules in this machinery. ChIP assay results (shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) indicate that HIC1 may recruit Brg1 only after binding to the responsive promoters; this result suggests a novel regulatory mechanism that achieves transcriptional regulation by temporally regulated association between HIC1 and its co-repressors on targeted promoters. Brg1 is the central core catalytic molecule in SWI/SNF complexes, which contain up to 10 other different proteins, varying according to their activity and specific promoter occupancy. The precise mechanisms involved in the SWI/SNF-mediated transcriptional regulation have been under intensive investigation since the discovery of their involvement in E2F regulation. Brg1 and its related molecules were initially discovered for their contribution to transcriptional activation. We and others, however, have established that this group of chromatin-remodeling molecules is also involved in transcriptional repression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Interestingly, we have recently reported that Brg1 and its related molecules can perform as either suppressors or activators of transcription on the same promoter, depending upon the composition of the complexes they form, suggesting their possible role as a mode-changing mechanism to switch promoters between activated and repressed states. For example, Brg1 was found to be recruited and required for the activation of ER-mediated transcription in response to estrogen. Paradoxically, Brg1 was also recruited and required for the repression of the ER-mediated transcription in response to estrogen antagonists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). We found here that Brg1 occupies the E2F1 promoter during both G<sub>0</sub> and G<sub>1</sub> stages of cell cycle, times when the promoter is either repressed or active, respectively (shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). This finding further indicates the potential involvement of Brg1 in diverse and opposite aspects of the transcriptional regulation of E2F1. The molecular mechanisms underlying these dichotomous actions of Brg1 are currently under investigation.</p><p id="P23">The importance of the E2F pathway in cancer development has been well established. However, the mechanisms linking cancer development and E2F-controlled cell cycle progression have not been fully elucidated. The discoveries presented in this report link the novel tumor suppressor HIC1 with the regulation of the E2F node. HIC1 was initially identified based on its inactivation in multiple cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Melki <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Nicoll <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Waha <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aggerholm <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Recent studies demonstrated a clear correlation between HIC1 expression and good outcomes of human breast cancers. Our data indicate that HIC1 is a critical molecule required for appropriate cellular growth suppression in response to physiological antiproliferative signals such as growth factor availability, and may mediate this cell cycle control through its regulation of the E2F node.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S7"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S8"><title>Transfections</title><p id="P24">HSF-8, MCF7 and SW13 cells were transfected by calcium phosphate precipitation following standard protocols. A total of 2 μg of the plasmids were used for a 10 cm dish, unless noted otherwise. Plasmids pCDNA3-Raf-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1999b</xref>), E2Luc, pSVRb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1999b</xref>) and pCDNA3FlagHIC1 (wild-type HIC1) have been described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Guerardel <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Deltour <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Bertrand <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Lefebvre <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Pinte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Chopin and Leprince, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Stankovic-Valentin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Vector-based pRNAT-U6.1/Neo-HIC1-siRNA and control vector were purchased from GenScript Corporation (Piscataway, NJ, USA) and transfected into cells according to the supplier’s protocols. Brg1 siRNA has been described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Sequences used for HIC1 siRNA were (1) ACG TGATCATCGTGGTGCAGA and (2) CAACCUGUACGU GUGCAUU.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting</title><p id="P25">Immunoprecipitation and IB procedures have been described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Flag antibody (CAT no. F-3165) was purchased from Sigma (StLouis, MO, USA). Prohibitin antibody (CAT no. 11-14-10) was purchased from Lab Vision Products, Thermo Fisher Scientific (Fremont, CA, USA). The following antibodies were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA), Brg1 (CAT no. sc-17796), HIC1 (CAT no. sc-28703) and tubulin (CAT no. sc-8035).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>GST pull-down assay</title><p id="P26">GST pull-down assay was described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). GST-HIC1 was produced by cloning the synthesized full-length human HIC1 into the pGEX-4T vector (GE Healthcare Life Sciences Inc.; CAT no. 27-4580-01) at <italic toggle="yes">Bam</italic>HI and <italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic>I sites (confirmed by sequence analysis). Full-length human Brg1, pE2F1 and DP1 vectors were described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1999a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Quantitative PCR and RT–PCR</title><p id="P27">Experiments were performed by following protocols we have recently reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Dai <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">2008</xref>). Briefly, quantitative PCR was performed using Applied Biosystems Power SYBR Green PCR master mix (for ChIP assay) and Power SYBR Green RT–PCR reagents kit (for RT–PCR). DNA quantities were measured by 7500 Fast Real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) by the 2ΔΔ<italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>t</sub> cycle threshold method. Results were normalized to account for variation in inputs and irrelevant controls to determine the relative quantities. All the experiments were repeated four times. Quantitative PCR conditions were as follows: 95 °C, 10 min; 59 °C, 1 min; 60 °C, 1 min, for 40 cycles. The following RT–PCR primers were purchased from Santa Cruz: HIC-1(h)-PR (CAT no. sc-37712-PR); Brg-1(h)-PR (CAT no. sc-29827-PR); SIRT1(h)-PR (CAT no. sc-40986-PR); and E2F-1(h)-PR (CAT no. sc-29297).</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>ChIP assays</title><p id="P28">The detailed protocol for the ChIP assay of the endogenous E2F1 gene promoter was described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Dai <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">2008</xref>). Primers for the cFos and β-actin genes (control) were described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Dai <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Double-ChIP assay was performed by same procedure, except that a second round of IP was performed on the immunoprecipitated products of the first IP, before quantitative PCR amplification.</p><p id="P29">PCR primers for ChIP assay on E2F1 promoter: 5′-GCAG CCAATTGTGGCGGC-3′; 5′-GACGCTCACGGCCCG-3′.</p><p id="P30">PCR primers for ChIP assay on Sirt1 promoter: 5′-TTGGT TGCCTAAAGTCACGCAGGT-3′; 5′-TGCCTGGAGCAC AGCGTTTCTATC-3′</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Colony-formation assay</title><p id="P31">The protocol for the colony-formation assay was described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Fusaro <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Briefly, HSF8 cells were cultured in 0% serum (serum starvation) or 10% fetal bovine serum, in RPMI. The cells were transfected with the vectors indicated in the text and transfectants were selected by culture in G418 (100 ng/ml) for 14 days. The cells were then fixed and stained, and the colonies with 20 or more cells were scored.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec id="S14" sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Table</title><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>HIC1 interacts with Brg1. (<bold>a</bold>) Extracts of HSF8 cells were analysed by immunoprecipitation (IP), PAGE and immunoblotting (IB) using the indicated antibodies. CE represents cell extract before IP. (<bold>b</bold>) Extracts from MCF7 cells (control) or MCF7 cells transfected with Flag-tagged HIC1 (Flag-HIC1) were analysed by PAGE and IB, using the indicated antibodies. (<bold>c</bold>) Cell extracts of MCF7 cells transfected with Flag-HIC1 shown in panel b were immunoprecipitated by the indicated antibodies, followed by PAGE and IB using the antibodies shown. (<bold>d</bold>) The <sup>35</sup>S-labeled proteins indicated were incubated with GST or the indicated fusion proteins, followed by pull-down analysis using standard protocols. RL represents the <sup>35</sup>S-labeled proteins without binding. GST, glutathione <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-transferase; PAGE, polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f1.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>HIC1 represses E2F-mediated transcription of endogenous genes. (<bold>a</bold>) HSF8 cells were transfected with empty vector (control) or the indicated expression vector plasmids. The cells were collected 72 h after transfection and the transcriptional activity of endogenous Sirt1, E2F1 and cFos (negative control) genes was analysed by quantitative RT–PCR, using standard protocols of the supplier. The experiments were repeated four times, yielding comparable results, and error bars shown represent the s.e.m. from all four assays. β-Actin expression was examined in each experiment as an internal control and used for normalization. The relative expression in the control non-transfected cells was assigned a value of 10. (<bold>b</bold>) The occupancy of HIC1 at the E2F1 and cFos promoters in unsynchronized actively growing HSF8 cells was analysed by ChIP assay with quantitative PCR, using an anti-HIC antibody (or anti-tubulin antibody as a specificity control). Relative quantitation of input DNA (not immunoprecipitated) is shown as ‘total.’ All the experiments were repeated four times and the averages are shown, with error bars representing s.e.m. ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation; RT–PCR, reverse transcriptase PCR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f2.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Brg1 is required for HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression. (<bold>a</bold>) Brg1-negative SW13 cells were transfected with an empty vector (control) or the indicated expression vector plasmids. The cells were collected 72 h after transfection and the expression of the Sirt1, E2F1 and cFos (negative control) genes was analysed by quantitative RT–PCR. The relative expression of these genes was calculated and normalized to the expression of β-actin. Error bars represent the s.e.m. from four independent assays. (<bold>b</bold>) Promoter association of Brg1 and HIC1 was examined by quantitative ChIP and double-ChIP assays, using the indicated antibodies. Relative association, as reflected by the quantitative PCR values, was calculated and normalized to the input DNA results. Error bars represent s.e.m. from four independent assays. ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation; RT–PCR, reverse transcriptase PCR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f3.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Knockdown of Brg1 abrogates HIC1-mediated transcriptional repression. (<bold>a</bold>) HSF8 cells were transfected with the empty control vector, HIC1, a dominant-negative Brg1 vector or a vector-based Brg1 siRNA, followed by quantitation of transcripts to measure the activity of the endogenous HIC1-responsive promoters, and the non-responsive control promoter (cFos), as indicated. (<bold>b</bold>) The cells were analysed by immunoblot using the indicated antibodies, which confirmed the depletion of Brg1 by the transfected siRNA. (<bold>c</bold>) Quantitative RT–PCR was performed for the genes indicated, which further confirmed the depletion of Brg1 by the siRNA. As a control, the tubulin gene was not affected by the Brg1 siRNA, verifying the specificity. A second Brg1-specific siRNA, purchased from Santa Cruz, produced similar results (data not shown). RT–PCR, reverse transcriptase PCR; siRNA, small interfering RNA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f4.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>HIC induces the recruitment of Brg1 to responsive genes. (<bold>a</bold>) HSF8 cells were transfected with empty vector (control), an HIC1 expression vector and/or a vector-based Brg1 siRNA. The cells were collected 72 h after transfection and analysed by quantitative ChIP assay of the Sirt1, E2F1 or cFos (control) gene, using the indicated antibodies. (<bold>b</bold>) As a positive control, SP1 association with the cFos promoter in the same cells explained above was analysed using quantitative ChIP assay. ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation; siRNA, small interfering RNA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f5.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>HIC1 is required for the recruitment of Brg1 to responsive genes. (<bold>a</bold>) HSF8 cells were transfected with empty vector (control), vector-based HIC1 siRNA or control siRNA. The cells were collected 72 h after transfection followed by immunoblot analysis using the indicated antibodies (tubulin as control), which confirmed the depletion of HIC1 by siRNA. (<bold>b</bold>) The cells were analysed by quantitative RT–PCR for the indicated genes (tubulin as control), which further verified the depletion of HIC1 by siRNA. (<bold>c</bold>) Quantitative ChIP assay using the indicated antibodies and quantitative RT–PCR were performed for the E2F1 gene. ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation; RT–PCR, reverse transcriptase PCR; siRNA, small interfering RNA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f6.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>HIC1 is required for serum deprivation-induced growth arrest. HSF8 cells were stably transfected with an empty vector, or control siRNA, or HIC1 siRNA. The cells were serum starved for 72 h and their cell cycle profiles were analysed by propidium iodide staining and flow cytometry. The experiments were independently repeated four times, yielding similar results. Profiles from one representative experiment are shown, with the percentages of cells in each phase of the cell cycle derived from the four independent experiments indicated. siRNA, small interfering RNA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f7.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Cell cycle dependency of HIC1 versus E2F promoter occupancy. (<bold>a</bold>) HSF8 cells were serum starved for 72 h (G<sub>0</sub>), and one portion was then treated with serum for 12 h (late G<sub>1</sub>). The E2F1 and HIC1 genes in these HSF8 cells were analysed for transcription factor occupancy by quantitative ChIP or double-ChIP assays, using the indicated antibodies. (<bold>b</bold>) The E2F1 and HIC1 genes in these HSF8 cells were analysed for activity by quantitation of transcripts. The experiments were repeated four times, which yielded comparable results, and the error bars shown represent the s.e.m. from all four assays. ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" xlink:href="nihms79633f8.jpg" orientation="portrait"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>HIC1 is required for growth suppression by serum starvation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vector transfected</th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Number of colonies
<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment 1</th><th align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment 2</th><th align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experiment 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Empty vector, 0.1% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Empty vector, 10% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">409</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control siRNA, 0.1% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control siRNA, 10% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">435</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIC1 siRNA, 0.1% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">456</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIC1 siRNA, 10% FBS</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p>Abbreviation: FBS, fetal bovine serum.</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><p>Approximately 10 000 HSF8 cells were transfected with 2 μg of the indicated vectors. Seventy-two hours after transfection, serum (FBS) in the medium was decreased to 0.1% for serum starvation or the culture was continued with normal serum concentrations (10% FBS), as indicated. The cells were selected in 100 μg of G418 per ml for 14 days. Colonies with 20 or more cells were counted.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><ack id="S15"><p>We thank Dr Srikumar P Chellappan for his continuous support. This study was partially supported by grants from Susan G Komen Breast Cancer Foundation Research Award (BCTR0403163) (SW) and the National Cancer Institute ((CA102940) (SW) and (CA101992) (DVF)) and by the Karin Grunebaum Cancer Research Foundation (DVF). SW is the recipient of DOD/CDMRP 2008 Breast Cancer Concept Award, Carter Family Foundation for Melanoma Research grant award, a BUSM Department of Medicine Pilot Project Grant Award and an Aid for Cancer Research grant award.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggerholm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guldberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hokland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Promoter hypermethylation of p15, hic1, cdh1, and er is frequent in myelodysplastic syndrome and predicts poor prognosis in early-stage patients</article-title><source>Eur J Haematol</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16343268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-0609.2005.00559.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banine</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunawardena</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaniv</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Swi/snf chromatin-remodeling factors induce changes in DNA methylation to promote transcriptional activation</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>3542</fpage><lpage>3547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15867346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-3554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stankovic-Valentin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour-Balerdi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification and developmental expression of the zebrafish orthologue of the tumor suppressor gene hic1</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1678</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15093138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbaexp.2004.01.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strobeck</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reisman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Re-expression of hsnf5/ini1/baf47 in pediatric tumor cells leads to g1 arrest associated with induction of p16ink4a and activation of rb</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>5193</fpage><lpage>5203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12149641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1205706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Britschgi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grob</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschan</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hugli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Identification of the p53 family-responsive element in the promoter region of the tumor suppressor gene hypermethylated in cancer 1</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>2030</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16301995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahnow</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Overholtzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladanyi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Epigenetic and genetic loss of hic1 function accentuates the role of p53 in tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2004.08.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Inactivation of tumor suppressor genes: choice between genetic and epigenetic routes</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15611624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.4.1.1361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Tumor suppressor hic1 directly regulates sirt1 to modulate p53-dependent DNA-damage responses</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2005.08.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrell</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu Yen</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esteller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Heterozygous disruption of hic1 predisposes mice to a gender-dependent spectrum of malignant tumors</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12539045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng1077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Chromosome arm 17p13.3: Could hic1 be the one?</article-title><source>Med Sci (Paris)</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16386221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1051/medsci/200622154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Sirtuin 1 is required for antagonist-induced transcriptional repression of androgen-responsive genes by the androgen receptor</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17505061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/me.2006-0467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3839341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Prohibitin and the swi/snf atpase subunit brg1 are required for effective androgen antagonist-mediated transcriptional repression of androgen receptor-regulated genes</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>1725</fpage><lpage>1733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgn117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2722849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fusaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Disruption of the rb–raf-1 interaction inhibits tumor growth and angiogenesis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>9527</fpage><lpage>9541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.24.21.9527-9541.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC522224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasylyk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The human candidate tumor suppressor gene hic1 recruits ctbp through a degenerate gldlskk motif</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>4890</fpage><lpage>4901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.22.13.4890-4901.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC133903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunaief</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khavari</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>The retinoblastoma protein and brg1 form a complex and cooperate to induce cell cycle arrest</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90405-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fusaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Differential regulation of rb family proteins and prohibitin during camptothecin-induced apoptosis</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>4539</fpage><lpage>4548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12085232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1205551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacinti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Rb and cell cycle progression</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>5220</fpage><lpage>5227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16936740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Evolutionary divergence in the broad complex, tramtrack and bric a brac/poxviruses and zinc finger domain from the candidate tumor suppressor gene hypermethylated in cancer</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>451</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10371200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0014-5793(99)00583-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inayoshi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mammalian chromatin remodeling complex swi/snf is essential for enhanced expression of the albumin gene during liver development</article-title><source>J Biochem (Tokyo)</source><volume>139</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jb/mvj015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Soudant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slomianny</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The tumor suppressor hic1 (hypermethylated in cancer 1) is o-glcnac glycosylated</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>271</volume><fpage>3843</fpage><lpage>3854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15373830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1432-1033.2004.04316.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melki</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Cancer-specific region of hypermethylation identified within the hic1 putative tumour suppressor gene in acute myeloid leukaemia</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10360376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2401401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevins</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The rb/e2f pathway and cancer</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11257102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/10.7.699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crichton</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kernohan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hupp</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Expression of the hypermethylated in cancer gene (hic-1) is associated with good outcome in human breast cancer</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>1878</fpage><lpage>1882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11747329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1054/bjoc.2001.2163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2363999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour-Balerdi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004a</year><article-title>Identification of a second g-c-rich promoter conserved in the human, murine and rat tumor suppressor genes hic1</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>4023</fpage><lpage>4031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15007385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1207504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stankovic-Valentin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rood</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerardel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004b</year><article-title>The tumor suppressor gene hic1 (hypermethylated in cancer 1) is a sequence-specific transcriptional repressor: definition of its consensus binding sequence and analysis of its DNA binding and repressive properties</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>38313</fpage><lpage>38324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M401610200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stankovic-Valentin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltour-Balerdi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leprince</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>A l225a substitution in the human tumour suppressor hic1 abolishes its interaction with the corepressor ctbp</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>2879</fpage><lpage>2890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16762039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2006.05301.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevaux</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frolov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor-Harding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Distinct mechanisms of e2f regulation by drosophila rbf1 and rbf2</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>4927</fpage><lpage>4937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12234932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/cdf501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC126297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strobeck</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeCristofaro</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banine</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The brg-1 subunit of the swi/snf complex regulates cd44 expression</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>9273</fpage><lpage>9278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11108719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M009747200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dynlacht</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Analysis of promoter binding by the e2f and prb families <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>: distinct e2f proteins mediate activation and repression</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC316494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schramm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Analysis of hic-1 methylation and transcription in human ependymomas</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15122586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.20165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fusaro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002a</year><article-title>Prohibitin co-localizes with rb in the nucleus and recruits n-cor and hdac1 for transcriptional repression</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>8388</fpage><lpage>8396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1205944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Raf-1 physically interacts with rb and regulates its function: a link between mitogenic signaling and cell cycle regulation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>7487</fpage><lpage>7498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9819434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.18.12.7487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC109329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adlam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999a</year><article-title>Prohibitin, a potential tumor suppressor, interacts with rb and regulates e2f function</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>3501</fpage><lpage>3510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10376528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1202684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999b</year><article-title>Regulation of rb and e2f by signal transduction cascades: divergent effects of jnk1 and p38 kinases</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1559</fpage><lpage>1570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10075927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/18.6.1559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1171244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Deacetylation of the retinoblastoma tumour suppressor protein by sirt1</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>407</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17620057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BJ20070151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2275065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002b</year><article-title>Prohibitin requires brg-1 and brm for the repression of e2f and cell growth</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>3019</fpage><lpage>3028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/cdf302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC126057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Brg1/brm and prohibitin are required for growth suppression by estrogen antagonists</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>2293</fpage><lpage>2303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC419909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faller</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Reprogramming of the swi/snf complex for co-activation or co-repression in prohibitin-mediated estrogen receptor regulation</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>7153</fpage><lpage>7157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17486062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1210509</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>