
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">216</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcmedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101190723</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1741-7015</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3851815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3851815.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3851815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3851815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-11-222</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1741-7015-11-222</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>DNA barcoding detects contamination and substitution in North American herbal products</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names initials="SG">Steven G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>snewmast@uoguelph.ca</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grguric</surname><given-names initials="M">Meghan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>mgrguric@uoguelph.ca</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmughanandhan</surname><given-names initials="D">Dhivya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>dhivyas87@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramalingam</surname><given-names initials="S">Sathishkumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>rsathish@buc.edu.in</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragupathy</surname><given-names initials="S">Subramanyam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ragu@uoguelph.ca</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Centre for Biodiversity Genomics, Biodiversity Institute of Ontario (BIO), University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario N1G 2W1, Canada</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Bachelor of Arts and Science Program, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario N1G 2W1, Canada</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Plant Genetic Engineering Laboratory, Department of Biotechnology, Bharathiar University, Coimbatore 641 046, Tamil Nadu, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">218942</issue-id><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-06 17:25:14.040"><day>06</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Newmaster et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Newmaster et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0),</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/11/222"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="22" journal-id="BMC Med" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11229018"><article-title>Retraction Note: DNA barcoding detects contamination and substitution in North American herbal products</article-title><volume>22</volume><date><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><elocation-id>279</elocation-id><source>BMC Medicine</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-024-03504-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11229018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38965520</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Herbal products available to consumers in the marketplace may be contaminated or substituted with alternative plant species and fillers that are not listed on the labels. According to the World Health Organization, the adulteration of herbal products is a threat to consumer safety. Our research aimed to investigate herbal product integrity and authenticity with the goal of protecting consumers from health risks associated with product substitution and contamination.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We used DNA barcoding to conduct a blind test of the authenticity for (i) 44 herbal products representing 12 companies and 30 different species of herbs, and (ii) 50 leaf samples collected from 42 herbal species. Our laboratory also assembled the first standard reference material (SRM) herbal barcode library from 100 herbal species of known provenance that were used to identify the unknown herbal products and leaf samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We recovered DNA barcodes from most herbal products (91%) and all leaf samples (100%), with 95% species resolution using a tiered approach (<italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>). Most (59%) of the products tested contained DNA barcodes from plant species not listed on the labels. Although we were able to authenticate almost half (48%) of the products, one-third of these also contained contaminants and or fillers not listed on the label. Product substitution occurred in 30/44 of the products tested and only 2/12 companies had products without any substitution, contamination or fillers. Some of the contaminants we found pose serious health risks to consumers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Most of the herbal products tested were of poor quality, including considerable product substitution, contamination and use of fillers. These activities dilute the effectiveness of otherwise useful remedies, lowering the perceived value of all related products because of a lack of consumer confidence in them. We suggest that the herbal industry should embrace DNA barcoding for authenticating herbal products through testing of raw materials used in manufacturing products. The use of an SRM DNA herbal barcode library for testing bulk materials could provide a method for 'best practices? in the manufacturing of herbal products. This would provide consumers with safe, high quality herbal products.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Globalization of trade is expanding natural product commodity markets that sustain life and promote good health, yet the challenging financial climate is squeezing profit margins and exacerbating the propensity for contamination, fraudulent market substitution and the use of unlabeled fillers. This comes at a time when consumers are becoming increasingly concerned about the authenticity of the products they purchase. North America is a major provider of goods such as herbal products, a commodity that has come under scrutiny recently in the media due to product substitution
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p><p>The International Trade in herbal products is a major force in the global economy and the demand is increasing in both developing and developed nations. There are currently more than 1,000 companies producing medicinal plant products with annual revenues in excess of US$60 billion. Notably, medicinal herbs now constitute the most rapidly growing segment of the North American alternative medicine market
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], with over 29,000 herbal substances
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] generating billions of dollars in trade. These statistics are indicative of the rapid growth (&gt;15%/year) in the marketplace for natural plant products and the broadening consumer base interested in herbal products from India, Canada, USA and Europe. Yet, as highlighted in recent media reports, product adulteration and ingredient substitution is not uncommon as species of a lower market value are substituted for those of a higher value. This practice constitutes not only product fraud, but according to the World Health Organization (WHO), the adulteration of herbal products is a threat to consumer safety (see Discussion). Eroding consumer confidence is driving the demand for research and market testing on herbal product authentication.</p><p>There are currently no best practices in place for identifying the species of the various ingredients used in herbal products. This is because the diagnostic morphological features of the plants on which the current Linnaean taxonomic system is based cannot typically be assessed from powdered or otherwise processed biomaterials. As a result, the marketplace is prone to contamination and possible product substitution, which dilute the effectiveness of otherwise useful remedies, lowering the perceived value of all related products because of a lack of consumer confidence in them. Herbal product substitution has been documented for many individual medicinal plant species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], teas
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and 'nutraceuticals?
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Although there is limited research available, the frequency of product mislabeling in herbal products has been estimated at 14% to 33% from previous studies
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. There are legitimate health concerns for consumers which results in a lack of confidence in safe, high quality herbal products.</p><p>A broadly accessible commercial tool to detect product substitution and develop best practices for authentication of many commercial products is beginning to emerge. DNA barcoding has been used to test a number of natural products
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Barcoding uses state-of-the-art biotechnology to help identify plant material based on short, standardized gene sequences, in a rapid, accurate and cost-effective manner. For example, Srirama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] has demonstrated the efficiency of DNA barcoding in identifying adulterants in the raw drug trade of <italic toggle="yes">Phyllanthus</italic> (Euphorbiaceae). <italic toggle="yes">Phyllanthus</italic> is one of the most important groups of species traded as a raw herbal drug treatment for liver disorders
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. This study showed that plant DNA barcoding can effectively discriminate <italic toggle="yes">Phyllanthus</italic> species, and hence can be used to resolve species admixtures in the raw drug trade samples; there are several phenotypically similar species that could easily be misidentified and mixed within herbal products. Over the last 3 years, studies of Chinese plant medicine
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] have documented the potential scope and magnitude of market substitution using this biotechnology. However, there are only a few studies
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] available, and they provide a limited assessment of the authenticity of commercial herbal products within the marketplace. Currently there is a gap in our understanding to the extent of herbal product substitution, contamination and use of fillers. Also, there are no studies that have used a standard reference material (SRM) herbal barcode library and barcode regions that facilitate species resolution.</p><p>This study utilized blind sampling of commercially available herbal products, which were tested for authentication of plant ingredients using an SRM herbal DNA barcode library. Our research questions focused on the following three areas. (1) Authentication: is the herbal species on the label found in the product? (2) Substitution: is the main herbal ingredient substituted by other species? (3) Fillers: are there any unlabeled fillers used?</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study design</title><p>We tested the authenticity of 44 (41 capsules; 2 powders; 1 tablet) herbal products representing 12 companies. The samples were submitted in a blind test for authentication (product no. label only) using DNA barcoding at the Centre for Biodiversity Genomics (CBG) within the Biodiversity Institute of Ontario (BIO), University of Guelph.</p><p>The project also included a second blind test in which we barcoded 50 leaf samples (blind labels) collected from living samples of known provenance from horticultural greenhouses. These leaf samples represented 42 species including all those listed on the herbal product labels and some closely related species. This provided an independent test of the ability of barcoding to differentiate all the species on the herbal product labels used in this study. All of the samples are in the Barcode of Life Database (BOLD) (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1) and GenBank (Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Table S2). All vouchers are scanned and recorded in the BOLD and deposited in the BIO Herbarium at the University of Guelph.</p></sec><sec><title>Herbal product sampling</title><p>In North America, herbal products are available in a variety of mainstream outlets such as supermarkets, health food stores, pharmacies and can be ordered online from herbal supply companies. In our study, samples were collected in the greater Toronto area (GTA) in Canada, with several samples mailed from distributors in the USA. All products are available to consumers in both Canada and the USA. The herbal product samples represented 30 herbal species that were each represented by 2 or 3 different companies.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA barcoding (DNA extraction and sequencing)</title><p>We barcoded triplicate samples of plant product (powder) from the 44 herbal products and 50 herbal leaf samples using a tiered approach (<italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Multiple DNA extracts (five to ten) were taken from each of these triplicate samples of which these DNA extracts were barcoded to make sure we did not miss any species? DNA. Since these were only single ingredient herbal products we did not expect to detect more than one plant species barcode unless it was a contaminant. However, our intensive DNA extract sampling allowed us to sample for other plant polymerase chain reaction (PCR) products, which were then sequenced separately. This included building barcode sample by species curves to see how many times we needed to sample to get an accurate estimate of species in a sample. As a result some of the products yielded two difference sequences, each from DNA extracts taken from the same sample product.</p><p>Total genomic DNA was isolated from 100 mg of the dry material using the Nucleospin Plant II Mini DNA Extraction kit. The PCR amplification was performed in a 20 ?L reaction mixture that contained 2.5 ?L of genomic DNA, 2.5 ?L of 10 ? <italic toggle="yes">Pfu</italic> buffer with MgSO<sub>4</sub> (Fermentas?), 2.5 ?L of 2 mM dNTPs (Fermentas), 0.5 ?L each of forward and reverse primers (10 pM) and 0.2 ?L of 2.5 U <italic toggle="yes">Pfu</italic> DNA Polymerase (Fermentas) and 2 ?L 0.5% dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO). The primers and the reaction conditions are previously published for <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">ITS</italic>2
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Touchdown PCR was carried out. The PCR products obtained from these reactions were subjected to Big Dye (version 3.1) sequencing reactions that had a total volume of 10 ?L and included 10 pMol of each primer. The sequencing amplification protocol consisted of 1 cycle of 1 minute at 96?C, followed by 30 cycles of 10 s at 96?C, 5 s at 55?C, and 4 minutes at 60?C. The amplicons were bidirectionally sequenced using ABI 377 sequencer (Applied Biosystems). The chromatographic traces were aligned and codon read in the Codoncode Aligner ver. 3.0 (CodonCode, Dedham, MA, USA) and contigs were generated. Sequences were deposited in BOLD and GenBank.</p></sec><sec><title>SRM herbal barcode library</title><p>An SRM herbal barcode library was prepared and used to identify the unknown herbal products and leaf samples. This library was assembled from 100 herbal species of known provenance that were identified by taxonomic experts. These samples were prepared into herbarium vouchers and are archived at the BIO Herbarium and in the BOLD. Although our library contained 100 herbal species in this study it is part of a larger project in which we are currently expanding the SRM herbal barcode library to include the main species used within herbal product industry in North America.</p></sec><sec><title>Product identification and analysis</title><p>Identification of unknown barcodes from products and leaves was conducted by comparing Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) data against our SRM herbal barcode library with a minimum BLAST cut off of 97% identity for a top match
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. These results were verified by neighbor-joining tree analysis in which we compared the branches of unknown specimens to sequences of reference species. A species is considered as taxonomically resolved if its members showed at least one diagnostic difference from any other taxon in the study and formed a monophyletic clade.</p><p>The definitions of terms used when assessing the identity of DNA barcodes recovered from herbal products are as outlined below.</p><sec><title>Authentic</title><p>A product is authentic if it contains a DNA barcode for a species that is the main ingredient on the label of a tested herbal product.</p></sec><sec><title>Contamination</title><p>A product is contaminated if a DNA barcode is found for a species other than what is labeled on the tested product, in addition to the authentic barcode; this could include known herbal product filler species (see below).</p></sec><sec><title>Substitution</title><p>Product substitution occurs when a DNA barcode is found for a species other than what is labeled on the tested product, AND there is NOT a barcode recovered for the main ingredient listed. Note that this strict definition does not consider whether it is an accidental misidentification of a bulk product or a fraudulent market substitution for a cheaper product.</p></sec><sec><title>Filler</title><p>A product contains fillers if a DNA barcode is found for known herbal product filler species including rice (<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic>), soybean (<italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic>) and wheat (<italic toggle="yes">Triticum</italic> spp.). Fillers may be found in place of (substitution) or in addition to the barcode of the main product ingredient (contamination).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>DNA barcode success</title><p>Recovery of DNA barcodes from various herbal products was successful. High quality DNA barcodes were obtainable for both <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> regions for 100% of the 100 vouchered herbal species (Ontario Agricultural College Herbarium), which served as a high quality SRM herbal barcode library. This library provided a database that could be used to identify unknown haplotypes (barcodes) recovered from herbal products. The SRM classification tree (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) shows that all herbal species have 100% species resolution, with each species presenting at least one diagnostic difference from any other taxon and formed a monophyletic clade (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Herbal product DNA barcode success rate was 91% (40/44 products) for the combined regions, resulting in the recovery of 34 <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> and 40 <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> sequences. Species resolution for barcodes recovered from herbal products was 66% (<italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic>) and 93% (<italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>). Low resolution in <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> was expected, because it is known to have insufficient nucleotide sequence variability to distinguish among closely related species. The three unresolved species with <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> was due to three samples that had product substitution with species that were not in our SRM library; these unknown species barcodes did match the nearest family and genus. We also barcoded blindly labeled herbal leaf samples collected from living samples from horticultural greenhouses. This provided an independent test of the ability of barcoding to differentiate all the species on the herbal product labels. Species resolution for barcodes recovered from the herbal leaf samples was 57% (<italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic>) and 100% (<italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>), with perfect matches to the herbal SRM barcode library using BLAST.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Standard reference material (SRM) herbal barcode library consensus tree (MP-ratchet analysis) for combined barcode data from </bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">rbc L</italic></bold><bold>and </bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">ITS2 </italic></bold><bold>from 100 herbal species of known provenance that were identified by taxonomic experts.</bold></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222-1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Authentication: is the herbal species on the label found in the product?</title><p>What is listed on the label of herbal products is not always what is found within the product. DNA barcoding was able to authenticate 48% of the products tested (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). However, most (59%) of the herbal products tested contained species of plants not listed on the labels (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Some (33%) of the authenticated herbal products also contained contaminants and or fillers not listed on the label (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Some of the DNA sequences recovered were only identified to family as our SRM herbal DNA barcode library is not yet complete (see note above). However, an incomplete SRM barcode library still allows a correct identity in a hierarchical way to family and genera depending on the level of best match within the classification tree. Some of the contaminants were of unrelated species from entirely different plant families (Table?
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Although many of the herbal companies (75%) whose product we tested did have some authentic products, only 2 of the 12 companies provided authentic products with no substitution, contaminants or fillers. Conversely, we were unable to authenticate any of the products for 25% of the companies (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Although these numbers shed light on the number of companies with authenticate products we only sampled three or four products per company and therefore differences among companies are likely due to chance.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>DNA barcode results from blind testing of the 44 herbal products representing 30 medicinal species of plants.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222-2.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>DNA barcode results listed for individual samples from blind testing of the 44 herbal products and 50 herbal leaf samples representing 42 medicinal species of plants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Market label or Herb leaf species</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Sample from</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Barcode ID</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>ITS2 ID</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>rbcL ID</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium</italic> (Yarrow)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP64C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP56L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea millefolium</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Achillea sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic> (Cohosh)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP42C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea asiatica</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea asiatica</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea asiatica</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP20C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP45L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP74L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP77L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic> (Amaranth)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP89P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus albus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP79L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus albus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus albus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus retroflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP49L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus retroflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus retroflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaranthus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic> (Celery)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP34C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaryllidaceae + Oryza sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Amaryllidaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP32C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP43C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP13L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP5L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP51L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Apiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic> (Burdock)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP6C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP22C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP21C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ranunculaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ranunculaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP4L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP92L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Arctium lappa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum cassia (Cinnamon)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP86T<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ranunculaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ranunculaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum cassia (Cinnamon)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP60L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum cassia</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum cassia</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Cinnamomum sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic> (Echinacaea)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP35C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea + Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea + Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Asteraceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP27C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea + Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea + Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Asteraceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP88L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP80L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP70L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP85L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Echinacaea purpurea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic> (Ginkgo)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP63C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP28C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS*<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP81C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP33L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP2L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP78L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP16L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ginkgo biloba</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic> (St. John?s wort)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP8C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Fabaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Fabaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP46C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP82C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP39L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP94L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic> (Walnut)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP40C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP58C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP84C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP30L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP19L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP17L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita (Chamomile)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP37C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita (Chamomile)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP91C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita + Medicago sativa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita + Medicago sativa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita (Chamomile)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP36C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita + Glycine max</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP76L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Matricaria recutita</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic> (Mint)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP3C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lamiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP52L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lamiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha spicata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP15L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha spicata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha spicata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lamiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nepeta cataria</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP9L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nepeta cataria</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nepeta cataria</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lamiaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic> (Evening Primrose)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP48C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic> (Oregano)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP10C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare + Lamiaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare + Lamiaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lamiaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP47L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oenothera biennis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP26L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP50L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata</italic> (WoodSorrel)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP1P<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP72L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis Corniculata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis stricta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP57L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis stricta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis stricta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis acetosella</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP18L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis acetosella</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis acetosella</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oxalis sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic> (Psyllium)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP69C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP71L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago ovate</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago major</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP66L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago major</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago major</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago lanceolata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP14L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago lanceolata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago lanceolata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Plantago sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic> (Purslane)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP83C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP65C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea + Glycine max</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea + Glycine max</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Glycine max</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP38L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP93L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic> (Raspberry)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP24C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP12C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP61L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus idaeus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus parviflorus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP29L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus parviflorus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus parviflorus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rubus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic> (black-eyed Susan)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP62C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP31L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rudbeckia hirta</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra (Elderberry)</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP23C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP59L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus nigra</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP54L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus racemosa</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sambucus sp.</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic> (Thistle)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP87C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP67C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP73L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus arvensis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus asper</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP41L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus asper</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus asper</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Sonchus asper</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale</italic> (Comfrey)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP7C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale + Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP90L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Symphytum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Boraginaceae</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP25C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Parthenium hysterophorus</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Asteraceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP11C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale + Panicum sp.</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale + Panicum sp.</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Panicum sp.</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP75C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Triticum spp. + Musa sp.</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Triticum spp. + Musa sp.</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Musaceae</italic><sup>a</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP53L<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Taraxacum officinale</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic> (Nettles)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP55C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP44C<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica + Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HP68L</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Urtica dioica</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Designates product contamination or substitution.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Refers to use of fillers.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">C</italic> capsule, <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> leaf, <italic toggle="yes">NS</italic> no sequence, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> powder, <italic toggle="yes">T</italic> tablet.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>DNA barcode results from blind testing of the 44 herbal products representing 12 companies.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222-3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Substitution: is the main herbal ingredient substituted for some other species?</title><p>Our barcoding analysis of 44 herbal products representing 30 medicinal plants species identified product substitution in 32% of the samples (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>; Table?
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The criteria we used to determine product substitution was the identity of other plant taxa in place of the product?s main labeled ingredient, which was NOT detected within the sample. We detected product substitution within most (83%) of the 12 companies that we tested (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). It should be noted that for 90% of the herbal species in this study, there were product(s) from at least one company that yielded a correct identity (indicating an authentic product). This is confirmation that processing is not an impediment to recovering barcodes. It should also be noted that we sampled each product intensively without replacement; multiple samples per product were extracted and barcoded to make sure we did not miss any species? DNA. Since these were only single ingredient herbal products we did not expect to detect more than one plant species barcode unless it was a contaminant. Our intensive sampling yielded a maximum of two species barcodes per herbal product of which one was either the correct herbal product species or a substitute, and the other was either a filler or contaminant.</p></sec><sec><title>Fillers: are there unlabeled fillers used in herbal products?</title><p>Some of the herbal products contained fillers that were not listed on the labels. Our definition is limited to the detection of DNA barcodes from <italic toggle="yes">O. sativa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">G. max</italic>. These filler species were detected within 21% of the products. We also detected grasses in the samples, which also included wheat (<italic toggle="yes">Triticum</italic> spp.). It is not known whether or not these plants were intentionally used as fillers or if they are contaminants; we are currently investigating the use of fillers in processing by each individual company. In 9% of the samples only rice or wheat barcodes were detected; there were no barcodes detected for the herbal species on the label. The use of fillers was limited to one-third of companies whose products we tested (Figure?
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Contamination and substitution in North American herbal products</title><p>Few studies have attempted to estimate how prevalent herbal product contamination and substitution is in the marketplace. To date there are only a few
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] studies of herbal product substitution, representing &lt;1% of the herbal products and &lt;5% of the herbal companies in North America. These studies document species-level DNA barcode identification success for 42% to 66% of the herbal species tested. Our study demonstrates increased testing and success, including (i) species-level DNA barcode identification success to 95% of the herbal species tested, and (ii) herbal market testing by approximately 20% for both products and companies. Although we provide new estimates of herbal product contamination and substitution, we caution that these values need to be refined by further studies as we have yet to sample &gt;1% market. However, our estimates do corroborate those of other studies. For example, Stoeckle <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] investigated contamination in 131 herbal tea products representing 48 herbal species and found that although they were able to authenticate 58% of the products, 33% of the herbal teas tested were contaminated. Similar estimates from a marketplace survey
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] of 40 dietary supplement products labeled as 'black cohosh? (<italic toggle="yes">Actaea racemosa</italic>) found that 75% of the samples were authentic black cohosh, whereas 25% were substituted with 4 closely related Asian <italic toggle="yes">Actaea</italic> species (<italic toggle="yes">A. asiatica</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. cimicifuga</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. dahurica</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. simplex</italic>). We also found substitution of black cohosh for Asian <italic toggle="yes">Actaea</italic>, as did another study by Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] also documented that 50% of ginseng products labeled 'Korean ginseng (<italic toggle="yes">Panax ginseng</italic>)? were actually American ginseng (<italic toggle="yes">Panax quinquefolius</italic>). Although the DNA barcode success rate was low (48%, see below) in Wallace?s study, they were still able to detect product substitution in 14% of the herbal samples tested, representing 7 species of herbs in 14 products. This study also detected fillers in 21% of the herbal products
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. We found alfalfa (<italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic>) in 16% of the products tested, which was also previously detected in teas
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. It is unlikely that this was a contaminant as it was found in so many of the products in addition to the main ingredient. It may be possible that this species is used by some companies as a cheap filler as it is commonly grown and bailed in agricultural areas, and available in large quantities throughout the year.</p><p>Contamination and substitution in herbal products present considerable health risks for consumers. In our study, we found contamination in several products with plants that have known toxicity, side effects and/or negatively interact with other herbs, supplements, or medications. For example, we found that one product (HP8) labeled as St. John?s wort (<italic toggle="yes">Hypericum perforatum</italic>) was substituted with <italic toggle="yes">Senna alexandrina</italic> (fabaceae); it contained only senna barcodes and no St. John?s wort barcodes. This is a serious health risk as senna is a Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved non-prescription herbal laxative, which is not for prolonged use as it can cause adverse effects such as chronic diarrhea, cathartic colon, liver damage, abdominal pain, epidermal breakdown and blistering
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Senna contains several unique glycosides called sennosides that interact with immune cells in the colon
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. We also found contamination of several herbal products (Table?
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) with <italic toggle="yes">Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> (feverfew)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Feverfew is native to Eurasia and is an invasive weed in Europe, the Mediterranean, North America and Chile. Although feverfew has been used to treat fever, migraine headaches and arthritis, it does have negative side effects such as swelling and numbness of the mouth, oral ulcers, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, and flatulence; some users experienced withdrawal syndromes when discontinuing use, such as rebound headaches and muscle and joint pain
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Feverfew reacts with a variety of medications metabolized by the liver and may also increase the risk of bleeding, especially if taken with blood-thinning medications such as warfarin or aspirin
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Pregnant women should not consume any amount of feverfew
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Feverfew can also cause allergic reactions, including contact dermatitis due to a toxin found in this plant species called parthenin
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Although it is not known how contamination with feverfew occurred in this product, it is possible that it was a common weed in the crop used to make this herbal product.</p><p>We also found contamination of a Ginkgo product with <italic toggle="yes">Juglans nigra</italic> (black walnut). Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] also found contamination of an <italic toggle="yes">Echinacea</italic> product with walnut and advised that such contamination would be particularly dangerous for a consumer with nut allergies. However, we feel it is unlikely that nuts are the source of contamination, but rather leaves that often litter a very large area surrounding a tree in mid to late summer. It is conceivable that there may have been a field of commercial herbs bordered by walnuts (a common occurrence on the landscape), and that the target crop was harvested along with walnut leaves. Walnut leaves, woods, bark and fruits all contain juglone
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], which is toxic; juglone can lead to oxidative stress or electrophilicity
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. The Registry of Toxic Effects of Chemical Substances (RTECS?)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] defines juglone as an equivocal tumorigenic agent (lungs, thorax and respiration, skin and appendages), which has been shown to promote skin tumors
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Ours and other studies
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] of herbal product contamination in the marketplace have not been able to identify all the contaminants to species-level resolution due to the lack of a complete SRM barcode library for herbal plants; a complete SRM library would include herbal species, related species and known toxic plants. It is possible that there were other contaminants that were missed because they could only be identified to family rather than to species.</p><p>Unlabeled plant fillers may also be found in herbal products, and these fillers are in some cases a potential health risk for consumers. DNA barcoding in our study identified several potential fillers, including rice (<italic toggle="yes">O. sativa</italic>), soybean (<italic toggle="yes">G. max</italic>) and various grasses such as wheat (<italic toggle="yes">Triticum</italic> spp.). This is a health concern for people allergic to these plants, as well as for people seeking gluten free products. Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] found rice and soybean fillers in natural plant and animal products and suggested that these fillers may produce a mixed signal during the sequencing process, contributing to a rather high percentage of failed sequencing reactions in capsulated products. We did not share this high percentage of sequence failures and found barcodes from both the herbal species on the label and fillers within the same product, suggesting that there may be fillers substituted for authentic herbal species. It is probable that barcoding detected rice and soybean, which is a common microcrystalline cellulose and gelatin used as additives in preparing the capsules that contain the herbal product
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. It is also common practice in the natural products industry to use fillers such as those listed above, which are mixed with the active ingredients. Nonetheless, the consumer has a right to see all of the plant species used in producing a natural product on the list of ingredients.</p></sec><sec><title>Challenges and biotechnical advances in DNA barcoding of herbal products</title><p>Authentication of herbal products is challenging, but new DNA barcoding methods are providing tools for routine market analysis
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Several major challenges include the lack of an SRM herbal barcode library, and use of only plastid barcode regions, which has resulted in low species resolution. The original definition of a reliable DNA identification of species requires (i) recovery of a barcode sequence from the sample, (ii) representation of relevant species in the reference database, and (iii) sufficient nucleotide sequence variability to distinguish among closely related species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. We are designing new protocols for recovering DNA barcodes from herbal samples, which satisfies the first requirement, but the second requirement of a reference database has yet to be satisfied. This problem has been discussed in previous market studies that have tested the authenticity of herbal products without a herbal SRM barcode library
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. These studies have defined the uncertainties of assigning unknown haplotypes from herbal products using incomplete reference barcode databases in GenBank and BOLD. The use of GenBank is inappropriate given that many of the DNA sequences do not have vouchers to professionally identified specimens archived in a herbarium. Therefore the reference sequence in GenBank may be from an incorrectly identified plant and there is no way to verify the specific origin of that DNA. Similarly, the 'Medicinal Materials DNA Barcode Database?
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] provides barcodes for many species of medicinal plants for which there is no record of vouchers to confirm identity; this is an essential component of any DNA Barcode
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Our study is the first to build a partial herbal SRM barcode library using vouchered samples of known provenance that was used to test the identity of unknown barcodes recovered from herbal products. Although we only have 100 species in the SRM library, we expect to expand this to over 200 species by the end of 2013, and 1,000 species by 2015. However, this will only add up to 55% of the 1,800 medicinal plant species that are commercially available
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. If we want to have reliable identifications using DNA barcodes we must build an SRM herbal barcode library that has all sister species for the 1,800 known medicinal species used in commercial products. This is one of the goals of our Herb-BOL (barcode of life) research program in the next 5 years.</p><p>The use of only plastid barcode regions is problematic for testing herbal products. Previous studies have not satisfied Hebert?s third criteria for a reliable barcode: sufficient nucleotide sequence variability to distinguish among closely related species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Other studies have adopted the core plant barcodes of <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic>a and <italic toggle="yes">matK</italic> genes
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. We do not recommend using <italic toggle="yes">matK</italic> because of associated problems we encountered with PCR amplification while working on nutmeg
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Other published studies have also encountered similar problems
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. We recommend a tiered
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] approach to analysis as one way to overcome the issue of alignment with non-coding regions, while providing the most variability from two-barcode regions for identifying closely related taxa. The tiered approach is based on the use of a common, easily amplified, and aligned region such as <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> that can act as a scaffold on which to place data from a highly variable region such as <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>. The use of <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> as a primary tier barcode is appropriate because of its universality, ease of amplification, ease of alignment, and because there is a significant body of data available for evaluation
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. We prefer to use <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> as the second tier as proposed by Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] for use in identifying medicinal plants because (i) it provides high species resolution, (ii) it is from the nuclear genome, which evolves at a different rate than the plastid genome, and (iii) it is a much shorter sequence allowing higher recovery from processed plant materials found within herbal products. The use of <italic toggle="yes">rbcL + ITS2</italic> in our study resulted in 95% species resolution of barcodes recovered from herbal products, which is much higher than previous studies that used <italic toggle="yes">rbcL + matK</italic> (42% in Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]; 66% in Stoeckle <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]). DNA success rate was high in our study (91%) and in that of Stoeckle <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] where they recovered barcodes from 90% of commercial herbal tea products. DNA barcode success rate was relatively low (48%) in the study by Wallace <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. This may be attributed to different manufacturing protocols, the type of plant material (for example, leaf, stem, roots and so on) used in the herbal preparation, or insufficient laboratory protocols used to extract, amplify and sequence haplotypes from herbal products. Herbal products contain plant secondary metabolites that may prevent barcode success. Herbal extracts contain complicated mixtures of organic chemicals (for example, fatty acids, sterols, alkaloids, flavonoids, glycosides, saponins, tannins and terpenes) that often result in PCR inhibition
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. In addition, degradation at primer binding sites may also contribute to differential amplification success of selected genes in samples with potentially degraded DNA. In the Baker <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] study, four dietary supplements could not be identified using the laboratory?s PCR amplification protocol, presumably because the DNA was degraded, possibly when heat was applied during the manufacturing process. Amplification failure in some samples, especially in <italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> gene, can be explained by the fact that primer sets used in this analysis may not be suitable for amplification of all species; we are developing new primer sets for mini-<italic toggle="yes">rbcL</italic> barcodes that will be easier to recover from degraded samples such as herbal products. The ideal protocol for barcoding herbal products will be realized as we build a more complete SRM herbal barcode library and continue to test more commercial products in the marketplace. Our study and others have documented that DNA can be routinely extracted from common forms of herbal dietary supplement extracts and powders, supporting a continued effort to explore DNA-based methods for quality assurance and quality control of herbal dietary supplements
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>Many herbal products contain mixtures, which are particularly difficult to barcode. This difficulty is due to varied PCR success of selected genes in samples with potentially degraded DNA due to varied gene copy number and PCR bias; the chemical and physical properties of each piece of DNA can selectively amplify certain sequences more than others
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Several approaches could be developed for testing herbal mixtures such as real-time multiplex PCR and the use of next-generation sequencing
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. In our study we chose to test only single ingredient herbal products. However, some of these products could contain more species than what was labeled. In order to search for other possible DNA barcodes we extracted multiple barcodes per sample in an attempt to obtain the most accurate estimate of identity within a sample. This included building barcode sample by species curves to see how many times we needed to sample to get an accurate estimate of species in a sample. Although we arrived at a figure of five to ten samples, we are currently using other molecular methods to verify the number of barcodes recovered from all of our herbal products that will overcome PCR bias and provide appropriate methods for testing herbal mixtures. Recent innovative approaches have combined morphological, molecular, and chemical techniques in order to identify the plant and chemical composition of some previous-generation smart drugs
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Such a multidisciplinary approach is proposed as a method for the identification of herbal blends of uncertain composition, which are widely available and represent a serious hazard to public health
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Currently there are no standards for authentication of herbal products. Although there is considerable evidence of the health benefits of herbal medicine
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>], the industry suffers from unethical activities by some of the manufacturers, which includes false advertising, product substitution, contamination and use of fillers. This practice constitutes not only food fraud, but according to the WHO, serious health risks for consumers
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. A study of health claims made by herbal product manufacturers on the internet found that 55% of manufacturers illegally claimed to treat, prevent, diagnose or cure specific diseases
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]. Regulators such as the FDA and Canadian Food Inspection Agency (CFIA) may not have the resources to adequately monitor the dietary supplement manufacturers and their advertising claims, and there are concerns that the current regulatory system is not effective in protecting consumers from the risks associated with certain herbal products
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. Chemical research studies have documented poor quality control and high content variability of active ingredients among products from a variety of manufacturers of herbal supplements
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. This is partly because herbs contain complicated mixtures of organic chemicals, the levels of which may vary substantially depending upon many factors related to the growth, production and processing of each specific herbal product
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. Although many manufacturers provide products with consistent levels of active ingredients through a process known as chemical standardization, this technique has uncertain effects on the safety and efficacy of the final product
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. Many of the dangers of commercial plant medicine have been brought to light by DNA technology based studies that have identified contamination of herbal products with poisonous plants
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. Eroding consumer confidence is driving the demand for a product authentication service that utilizes molecular biotechnology. One approach to vetting herbal product substitution and contamination is product authentication using DNA barcoding. Research studies such as ours and others
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] reinforce the importance of using DNA barcoding in the authentication of socioeconomically important herbal species
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. We suggest that the herbal industry should voluntarily embrace DNA barcoding for authenticating herbal products through testing of raw materials used in manufacturing products, which would support sovereign business interests and protect consumers. This would be a minor cost to industry with a limited amount of bulk product testing, which would certify a high quality, authentic product. If the herb is known to have health benefits and it is in the product, then this would provide a measure of quality assurance in addition to consistent levels of active ingredients. Currently we are building an SRM DNA barcode library for commercial herbal species and standard testing procedures that could be integrated into cost effective 'best practices? in the manufacturing of herbal products. This would provide industry with a competitive advantage as they could advertise that they produce an authentic, high quality product, which has been tested using DNA-based species identification biotechnology, therefore gaining consumer confidence and preference. This approach would support the need to address considerable health risks to consumers who expect to have access to high quality herbal products that promote good health.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors? contributions</title><p>SGN, SR and DS conceived of and designed the study, and carried out wet lab analysis and writing of the manuscript. MG carried out the fieldwork and contributed to the study design and writing of manuscript. SGN, SR and RS contributed to final editing and submission of the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Additional file 1: Table S1</title><p>Standard reference material (SRM) herbal Barcode of Life Database (BOLD) accession numbers.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222-S1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Additional file 2: Table S2</title><p>List of GenBank accession numbers.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="1741-7015-11-222-S2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by the grants to SGN from the International Science and Technology Partnership Canada and Humanities Research Council of Canada, Genome Canada through the Ontario Genomics Institute, and the Canadian Foundation for Innovation. We would like to thank Mr Richard Desylva, Managing Director, 'The Herb Works? and Mr Joel Thuna, General Manager, 'Global Botanical?, Ontario, Canada for offering valuable advice and reviewing a previous version of the manuscript. We thank the Administrators and Vice Chancellor of the Bharathiar University, India for their administrative help and support. Thanks to Kawa Cheng and Kevan Berg for providing assistance with editing and referencing.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeckle</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirpekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>Commercial teas highlight plant DNA barcode identification successes and obstacles</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>42</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22355561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep00042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3216529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>DNA barcode identification of black cohosh herbal dietary supplements</article-title><source>J AOAC Int</source><year>2012</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5740/jaoacint.11-261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22970567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boilard</surname><given-names>SMAL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eagle</surname><given-names>SHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spall</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokralla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>DNA barcodes for everyday life: routine authentication of natural health products</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>2012</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2012.07.048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Complementary herbal and alternative drugs in clinical practice</article-title><source>Perspect Psychiatr C</source><year>2002</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1744-6163.2002.tb00663.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12385080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ang-Lee</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zacny</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><article-title>Assessing subjective and psychomotor effects of the herbal medication valerian in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2004.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15159134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Astin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haskell</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><article-title>A review of the incorporation of complementary and alternative medicine by mainstream physicians</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>2303</fpage><lpage>2310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.158.21.2303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9827781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhawan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofbauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Herbal medicines: current trends in anesthesiology practice - a hospital survey</article-title><source>J Clin Anesth</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0952-8180(00)00195-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Techen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crockett</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffler</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>Authentication of medicinal plants using molecular biology techniques to compliment conventional methods</article-title><source>Curr Med Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867043365206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Authentication of the family Polygonaceae in Chinese pharmacopoeia by DNA barcoding technique</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2009.05.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srirama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sreejayan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravikanth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurumurthy</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shivanna</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjappa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganeshaiah</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaanker</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><article-title>Assessing species admixtures in raw drug trade of <italic toggle="yes">Phyllanthus</italic>, a hepato-protective plant using molecular tools</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.04.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaakola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suokas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H?ggman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Novel approaches based on DNA barcoding and high-resolution melting of amplicons for authenticity analyses of berry species</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.04.069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Mattia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galimberti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galasso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casiraghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of poisonous plants by DNA barcoding approach</article-title><source>Int J Legal Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00414-010-0447-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular authentication of the ethnomedicinal plant <italic toggle="yes">Sabia parviflora</italic> and its adulterants by DNA barcoding technique</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1250468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ved</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goraya</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><source>Demand and Supply of Medicinal Plants in India</source><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Bangalore, India: NMPB, New Delhi &amp; FRLHT</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of medicinal plants in the family Fabaceae using a potential DNA barcode ITS2</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.04.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Validation of the ITS2 region as a novel DNA barcode for identifying medicinal plant species</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e8613</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20062805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2799520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>DNA barcodes for discriminating the medicinal plant <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> (Lamiaceae) and its adulterants</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.34.1198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21804206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>But</surname><given-names>PP-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of herbal medicinal materials using DNA barcodes</article-title><source>J Syst Evol</source><year>2011</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1759-6831.2011.00132.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D-Z</given-names></name><article-title>Use of DNA barcode sensu lato to identify traditional Tibetan medicinal plant <italic toggle="yes">Gentianopsis paludosa</italic> (Gentianaceae)</article-title><source>J Syst Evol</source><year>2011</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1759-6831.2011.00127.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Using ITS2 barcode to identify ephedrae herba [in Chinese]</article-title><source>Zhongguo Zhong Yao Za Zhi</source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22779361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragupathy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>DNA barcoding in the land plants: evaluation of rbcL in a multigene tiered approach</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><year>2006</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b06-047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzmina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>DNA Barcoding methods for land plants</article-title><source>DNA Barcodes</source><year>2012</year><publisher-name>New York, NY: Springer</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-61779-591-6_11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22684959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Mechanism of action of sennosides</article-title><source>Bull Acad Natl Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8717178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krenzelok</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><article-title>Skin breakdown and blisters from senna-containing laxatives in young children</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12708936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1345/aph.1C439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hietala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marvola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parviainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lainonen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Laxative potency and acute toxicity of some anthraquinone derivatives, senna extracts and fractions of senna extracts</article-title><source>Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>1987</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0773.1987.tb01794.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3671329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klepser</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klepser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>Unsafe and potentially safe herbal therapies</article-title><source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source><year>1999</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><comment>quiz 139?141</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10030529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajhp/56.2.125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittler</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><article-title>The efficacy and safety of feverfew (<italic toggle="yes">Tanacetum parthenium L.</italic>): an update of a systematic review</article-title><source>Public Health Nutr</source><year>2000</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11276299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s1368980000000598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><article-title>Herbal medicinals: selected clinical considerations focusing on known or potential drug-herb interactions</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>2200</fpage><lpage>2211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.158.20.2200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9818800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><article-title>Potential interactions between alternative therapies and warfarin</article-title><source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source><year>2000</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1227</lpage><comment>quiz 1228?1230</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10902065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown-Woodman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><article-title>A reproductive screening test of feverfew: is a full reproductive study warranted?</article-title><source>Reprod Toxicol</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.reprotox.2006.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16781113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Killoran</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedvis-Leftick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Two cases of compositae dermatitis exacerbated by moisturizer containing feverfew</article-title><source>Dermatitis</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2310/6620.2007.06063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18021604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daglish</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>The determination and occurrence of a hydrojuglone glucoside in the walnut</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1950</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14800933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/bj0470458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1275243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odowole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sales</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><article-title>Semiquinone anion radicals formed by the reaction of quinones with glutathione or amino acids</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1986</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(86)80627-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3011514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damjanovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G?sp?r</surname><given-names>R</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><article-title>The effect of juglone on the membrane potential and whole-cell K+ currents of human lymphocytes</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1996</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1996.0147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8579599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>YouLun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DongMei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>GuangMing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Advances in the phytochemistry and pharmacology researches of <italic toggle="yes">Juglans</italic> Linn</article-title><source>Med Plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NLM</collab><source>Registry of Toxic Effects of Chemical Substances (RTECS)?</source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Bethesda, MD: National Library of Medicine</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Duuren</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusch</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewengart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mat?</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melchionne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Structure and tumor-promoting activity of analogues of anthralin (1,8-dihydroxy-9-anthrone)</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>1978</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm00199a005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">619147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>M?ller</surname><given-names>W-U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leistner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolic relation between naphthalene derivatives in <italic toggle="yes">Juglans</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1978</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)88683-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aithal</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunil Kumar</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shavi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajankila</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udupa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satyamoorthy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satish Rao</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title>Evaluation of pharmacokinetic, biodistribution, pharmacodynamic, and toxicity profile of free juglone and its sterically stabilized liposomes</article-title><source>J Pharm Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>3517</fpage><lpage>3528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jps.22573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21523783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sockovie</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenhoek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellefeuille</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krantis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budzinski</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livesey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnason</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><article-title>In vitro activity of St. John?s wort against cytochrome P450 isozymes and glycoprotein</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880200490512034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucher</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><article-title>Genome-based approaches to the authentication of medicinal plants</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2008-1074517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18449847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeckle</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zemlak</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of birds through DNA barcodes</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e312</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15455034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC518999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>But</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><article-title>An integrated web medicinal materials DNA database: MMDBD (Medicinal Materials DNA Barcode Database)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2996930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clauson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Top herbal products encountered in drug information requests (part 1)</article-title><source>Drug Ben Trends</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>CBOL Plant Working Group</collab><article-title>A DNA barcode for land plants</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>12794</fpage><lpage>12797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0905845106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2722355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Testing candidate plant barcode regions in the Myristicaceae</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Resour</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.02002.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21585825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgress</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesanakurti</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husband</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>SCH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Assessing the utility of coding and non-coding genomic regions for plant DNA barcoding</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Use of ITS2 region as the universal DNA barcode for plants and animals</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e13102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2948509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>Choosing and using a plant DNA barcode</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e19254</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21637336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3102656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D-Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>X-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z-D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>C-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>G-W</given-names></name><collab>China Plant BOL Group</collab><article-title>Comparative analysis of a large dataset indicates that internal transcribed spacer (ITS) should be incorporated into the core barcode for seed plants</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>19641</fpage><lpage>19646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22100737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1104551108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3241788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr?ger</surname><given-names>?</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rydberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj?rk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular identification of commercialized medicinal plants in Southern Morocco</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e39459</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3384669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salamin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunwell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesanakurthi</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haidar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Land plants and DNA barcodes: short-term and long-term goals</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>360</volume><fpage>1889</fpage><lpage>1895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2005.1720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1609218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotblatt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziment</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><source>Evidence-based Herbal Medicine</source><year>2002</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia, PA: Hanley &amp; Belfus</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimino</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><article-title>Successful isolation and PCR amplification of DNA from National Institute of Standards and Technology herbal dietary supplement standard reference material powders and extracts</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1186225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19844865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2945808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesanakurti</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Percy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>SCH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newmaster</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husband</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><article-title>Are plant species inherently harder to discriminate than animal species using DNA barcoding markers?</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Resourc</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02652.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21564972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokralla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spall</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Next-generation sequencing technologies for environmental DNA research</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1794</fpage><lpage>1805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05538.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22486820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borghesi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrenacci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Federici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Smart drugs: green shuttle or real drug?</article-title><source>Int J Legal Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00414-013-0893-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Herbs as medicines</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>2192</fpage><lpage>2199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.158.20.2192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9818799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calixto</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><article-title>Efficacy, safety, quality control, marketing and regulatory guidelines for herbal medicines (phytotherapeutic agents)</article-title><source>Braz J Med Biol Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0100-879X2000000200004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10657057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zollman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Herbal medicine</article-title><source>West J Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ewjm.175.2.125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1071505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zollman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><source>ABC of Complementary Medicine</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swerdlow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Medicine Changes: late 19th to early 20th century</article-title><source>Nature?s Medicine: Plants that Heal</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Washington, DC: National Geographic Society</publisher-name><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>PAGM</given-names></name><article-title>Herbal remedies</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>2046</fpage><lpage>2056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra020398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><source>Medical Herbalism. The Science and Practice of Herbal Medicine</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Rochester, VT: Inner Traditions/Bear &amp; Co</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Herbal medicine in the United States: review of efficacy, safety, and regulation: grand rounds at University of California, San Francisco Medical Center</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11606-008-0632-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18415652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2517879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikam</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kareparamban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadhav</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Future trends in standardization of herbal drugs</article-title><source>JAPS</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>WHO</collab><article-title>WHO Traditional Medicine Strategy 2002?2005</article-title><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/2002/who_edm_trm_2002.1.pdf">http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/2002/who_edm_trm_2002.1.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Internet marketing of herbal products</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2003</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>1509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.290.11.1505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13129992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeAngelis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanarosa</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><article-title>Drugs alias dietary supplements</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2003</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>1519</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.290.11.1519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13129996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coghlan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moolhuijzen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellgard</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Deep sequencing of plant and animal DNA contained within traditional Chinese medicines reveals legality issues and health safety concerns</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1002657</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22511890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3325194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Commonly used herbal medicines in the United States: a review</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2003.10.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15047038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Quality of herbal medicines: challenges and solutions</article-title><source>Complement Ther Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctim.2011.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolsko</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solondz</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Lack of herbal supplement characterization in published randomized controlled trials</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>1087</fpage><lpage>1093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2005.01.076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16194636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grollman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><article-title>Botanical medicines?the need for new regulations</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>2073</fpage><lpage>2076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb022858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Buyer beware? Does the information provided with herbal products available over the counter enable safe use?</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-9-94</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21827684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3180693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>