
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3707900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3707900.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3707900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3707900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874558</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-07253</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Computer Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Computer Modeling</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computerized Simulations</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Systems Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Risk Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical Economics</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Statistics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical Methods</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Economic Models</subject><subject>Mathematical Economics</subject><subject>Money Supply and Banking</subject><subject>Public Finance</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Curve Fitting of the Corporate Recovery Rates: The Comparison of Beta Distribution Estimation and Kernel Density Estimation</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Kernel Density Estimation of Recovery Rates</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="R">Rongda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Ze</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>School of Finance, Zhejiang University of Finance and Economics, Hangzhou, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Coordinated Innovation Center of Wealth Management and Quantitative Investment of Zhejiang University of Finance and Economics, Hangzhou, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Center for Research of Regulation and Policy of Zhejiang Province, Hangzhou, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Convertino</surname><given-names initials="M">Matteo</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>rongdachen@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RDC. Performed the experiments: RDC ZW. Analyzed the data: RDC ZW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RDC ZW. Wrote the paper: RDC ZW.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">224555</issue-id><elocation-id>e68238</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>07</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-17 04:25:16.503"><day>17</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Chen, Wang</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen, Wang</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0068238.pdf"/><abstract><p>Recovery rate is essential to the estimation of the portfolio’s loss and economic capital. Neglecting the randomness of the distribution of recovery rate may underestimate the risk. The study introduces two kinds of models of distribution, Beta distribution estimation and kernel density distribution estimation, to simulate the distribution of recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds. As is known, models based on Beta distribution are common in daily usage, such as CreditMetrics by J.P. Morgan, Portfolio Manager by KMV and Losscalc by Moody’s. However, it has a fatal defect that it can’t fit the bimodal or multimodal distributions such as recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds as Moody’s new data show. In order to overcome this flaw, the kernel density estimation is introduced and we compare the simulation results by histogram, Beta distribution estimation and kernel density estimation to reach the conclusion that the Gaussian kernel density distribution really better imitates the distribution of the bimodal or multimodal data samples of corporate loans and bonds. Finally, a Chi-square test of the Gaussian kernel density estimation proves that it can fit the curve of recovery rates of loans and bonds. So using the kernel density distribution to precisely delineate the bimodal recovery rates of bonds is optimal in credit risk management.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Gant No. 71171176). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Credit risk is the distribution of financial losses caused by unexpected changes in compliance of financial agreements. The recovery rate is an important measure of how much we can retrieve from bad debts. So it is crucial to figure out what kind of distribution recovery rates of the sample comply with. An important key in building the credit risk model is the recovery rate in default or loss given default (LGD) function, expressed as a ratio (dollar recovery/amount invested) <xref rid="pone.0068238-Arnaud1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>.</p><p>Recently, research on recovery rate has mainly focused on factors that impact recovery rate, correlation between recovery rate and default rate, its distribution, etc. <xref rid="pone.0068238-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Compared with default rate, the influencing factors of recovery rate are more complex. The most representative model is Losscalc Model of Moody’s. The correlation between recovery rate and default rate turns out to be positive. Hu &amp; Perraudin <xref rid="pone.0068238-Hu1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, Rosch &amp; Scheule <xref rid="pone.0068238-Rosch1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> find that it will underestimate the portfolio’s loss if the correlation is neglected.</p><p>Histogram is common and is widely used to depict the distribution, but it can’t be a smooth curve <xref rid="pone.0068238-Qu1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Beta distribution estimation is widely used for simulating the curve of the recovery rates <xref rid="pone.0068238-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Besides, Frye <xref rid="pone.0068238-Frye1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> assumes that the recovery rate follows a normal distribution and Pykhtin <xref rid="pone.0068238-Pykhtin1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> establishes a log-normal distribution and Andersen &amp; Sidennius <xref rid="pone.0068238-Andersen1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> discuss the probit-normal distribution. Dullmann &amp; Trapp <xref rid="pone.0068238-Dullmann1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> utilize a logit-normal distribution and empirically analyse the recovery rates. After comparing the results with two other extended models, Frye <xref rid="pone.0068238-Frye1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and Pykhtin <xref rid="pone.0068238-Pykhtin1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, the log-normal distribution is not found to be as good as the other two distributions.</p><p>How to precisely depict the randomness of recovery rate is essential to the estimation of the loss of portfolio and economic capital. In this paper, we mainly focus on distribution of recovery rate. Beta distribution is widely used in many credit risk models such as CreditMetrics by J.P. Morgan, Portfolio Manager by KMV and Losscalc by Moody’s. However, sometimes it ceases to be effective because of the fact that the recovery rates curve always has two peaks while Beta distribution estimation can only demonstrate one peak. So in this paper we adopt the Gaussian kernel density estimation, a nonparametric estimation, to solve this problem and justify our hypothesis. Kernel density estimation put forward by Emanuel Parzen (1955) and Murray Rosenblatt (1962),also named as the Parzen-Rosenblatt window method, is a non-parametric way to estimate the probability density function of a random variable. Ruppert and Cline proposed revision of the kernel density estimation method based upon data density function and clustering algorithm. We can build the prediction model of value at risk through the kernel density estimation of a random variable. Moreover, weighted processing of the estimated variation coefficient can help build different risk prediction models. In order to avoid producing the setting model error caused by the preset distribution of stock returns, Liu &amp; He <xref rid="pone.0068238-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> used the kernel density estimation to fit stock returns, and then tested the result by Monte Carlo simulation. Their study shows kernel density estimation result is a good approximation of the real stock returns distribution. Zhen &amp; Li <xref rid="pone.0068238-Zhen1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> study the distribution of Hang Seng index returns by the nonparametric kernel density estimation, which exhibits the fat tail characteristic. Shi &amp; Huang <xref rid="pone.0068238-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> use the kernel density estimation method to analyze the dynamic economic growth at the provincial level in China from 1978 to 2007. Their research indicates that the growth distribution at provincial level has the trend of bimodal distribution, which is especially obvious in 1999. In this paper, we use kernel density estimation to fit the distribution of the bimodal or multimodal samples of recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows. In Part 2.1 the recovery rate and sources of data are introduced. Part 2.2 introduces the Beta distribution estimation method <xref rid="pone.0068238-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> with five different shapes. In Part 2.3 we introduce properties of estimation of the kernel density and several ways to figure out the bandwidth of the kernel density. In Part 2.4, the Chi-square test is introduced <xref rid="pone.0068238-Camblor1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Part 3 shows the results. It contains the study of fitting the curves to the recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds (from Moody’s Investors Service) for the years 2009–2011 by histogram, Beta distribution estimation and kernel density estimation. We favor Beta distribution estimation over histogram in our study. Kernel density estimation depicts the bimodal or multimodal distributions of recovery rates while beta distribution estimation cannot. In addition, we test whether the kernel density estimation can fit the distribution of the recovery rate. Part 4 concludes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>1. Data of Recovery Rate</title><p>Recovery is usually measured by two indicators: the ultimate recovery rate – value of assets that the creditors eventually retrieve, and the price of debt after default. Prices of defaulted assets only exist in the defaultable security market in public, but some of the tradable bonds can also offer the data of their prices after default in private. In addition, default debt prices should be discounted, however, as default bonds generally lack liquidity, it is very difficult to calculate the ultimate recovery rates. In this paper we collect the data of recovery rates of corporate loans from year 2010 to year 2011 <xref rid="pone.0068238-Sharon1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0068238-Sharon2" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and those of corporate bonds from year 2009 to year 2011 for analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>2. Beta Distribution Estimation</title><p>The common Beta density function is defined as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e010"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e010.jpg"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>Where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e011.jpg"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e012.jpg"/></inline-formula> means a Beta function, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e013.jpg"/></inline-formula> means a Gamma function.</p><p>The shape of Beta distribution is based on values of parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e014.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e015.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the distribution is bell shaped;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e016.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the distribution is U shaped;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e017.jpg"/></inline-formula> the distribution is J shaped;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e018.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the distribution is inverse J shaped;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic toggle="yes">if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e019.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the distribution is an uniform distribution;</italic>
</p></list-item></list><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g001">Figure 1</xref> Shows the different shapes of Beta distribution from simulation by Matlab7.6 software.</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Beta distribution curves are different for the different input of the parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e001.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</title><p>The bell shaped curve is simulated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e002.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The U shaped curve is simulated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e003.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The J shaped curve is simulated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e004.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The inverse J shaped curve is simulated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e005.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The uniform distribution is simulated by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e006.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The relationships between statistics such as mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e020.jpg"/></inline-formula> and variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e021.jpg"/></inline-formula> and the parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e022.jpg"/></inline-formula> are stated as follows:<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e023"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e023.jpg"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e024"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e024.jpg"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>3. Kernel Density Estimation</title><sec id="s2c1"><title>3.1 Definition of kernel density estimation</title><p>Kernel density estimation is a particular nonparametric technique to estimate the underlying density as a weighted average of local functions centered at each sample point. It can asymptotically converge to any density function. Suppose <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e025.jpg"/></inline-formula> are samples from population <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e026.jpg"/></inline-formula>, n is the number of samples. If there is a bounded function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e027.jpg"/></inline-formula> satisfying: <italic toggle="yes">1)</italic>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e028.jpg"/></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">; 2) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e029.jpg"/></inline-formula>;</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">3)</italic>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e030.jpg"/></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">4) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e031.jpg"/></inline-formula>;</italic> The<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e032"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e032.jpg"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e033.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the kernel density estimation, where <italic toggle="yes">K</italic> is a kernel function, <italic toggle="yes">h</italic>&gt;0 is a smoothing parameter called the bandwidth and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the number of samples. There are many common types of kernel function in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0068238-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Expressions of common kernel density functions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0068238-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kernel density function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniform</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triangle</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gaussian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epanchnikov</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double exponential</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cosine arch</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U(−1,1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1−|t|)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N(0,1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e007.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e008.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e009.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>In this paper, we choose the Gaussian kernel density, and its expression is<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e034"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e034.jpg"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Putting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0068238.e034">Equation (5</xref>) into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0068238.e032">Equation (4</xref>), we have<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e035"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e035.jpg"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0068238.e035">Equation (6</xref>) is the final Gaussian kernel density function.</p></sec><sec id="s2c2"><title>3.2 Bandwidth estimation</title><p>The bandwidth <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> plays a paramount role in the estimation compared with the form of <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. Martin <xref rid="pone.0068238-Martin1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> believes that if <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is large, the estimation will be over-smooth, and vice versa. There are three main standards to decide the bandwidth</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">1) Mean square error, MSE</italic>
</p><p>
<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e036"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e036.jpg"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">2) Integral mean square error is adopted when the density is continuous, MISE</italic>
</p><p>
<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e037"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e037.jpg"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">3) Asymptotic integral mean square error, AMISE</italic>
</p><p>
<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e038"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e038.jpg"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>Also there are many other methods to choose the bandwidth. Most of these methods are based on the idea of minimizing the MSE or the MISE. The following methods <xref rid="pone.0068238-Mugdadia1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> are often used to select the bandwidth for:</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">4) Least-squares cross-validation.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">5) Biased cross-validation.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">6) Plug-in bandwidth selection.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">7) Smoothed cross-validation</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">8) Root-n bandwidth selection</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">9) The Contrast Metho</italic>d</p><p>As <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> become larger, <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> becomes smaller. However, if <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is too small, it reduces the accuracy of the estimation. On the other hand, if <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is too large, its estimated curve will be too smooth. In most cases, MSE and MISE are used most commonly.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>4. Chi-square Goodness-of-fit Test</title><p>In order to assess whether the qualitative data fit the kernel density distribution, We adopt Chi-square goodness-of-fit test to test the results. The test is performed by grouping the data into bins, calculating the observed and expected counts for the bins, and computing the chi-square test statistic shown as<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e045"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e045.jpg"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>Where k means the sample can be divided into k bins or intervals, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e046.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the observed counts and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e047.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the expected counts in bin <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>. Suppose <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e048.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The null hypothesis means that the frequency in each interval equals that of corresponding kernel distribution. If the p-value is below the significance level (we often choose 5% or 10%), the null hypothesis can be rejected and the kernel density estimation doesn’t quite fit the curve of the recovery rates of municipal bonds. If the result is above the significance level, we have no reason to reject the null hypothesis<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e049"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e049.jpg"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>Where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e050.jpg"/></inline-formula> stand for the value of bin edges, n is the number of observations in the sample. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e051.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the cumulative density function of the kernel distribution.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>1. Histograms of Recovery Rates</title><p>By sorting the data from the Moody’s analysis report, we get 58 effective observations of recovery rates of corporate loans from year 2010 to 2011 and 282 ones of corporate bonds from year 2009 to 2011. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0068238-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Statistics of sample recovery rates.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0068238-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skewness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kurtosis</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery rates of defaulted corporate loans from year 2010 to 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5574</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1706</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5603</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery rates of defaulted corporate bonds from year 2009 to 2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3895</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0898</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4672</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0161</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t002">Table 2</xref> exhibits the main characteristics of the sample of recovery rates. Meanwhile their histograms are given as follows (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g002">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>It is the histogram of 58 effective observations of recovery rates of corporate loans from year 2010 to 2011.</title><p>The data comes from the Moody’s analysis report.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0068238-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>It is the histogram of 282 observations of recovery rates of corporate bonds from year 2009 to 2011.</title><p>The data comes from the Moody’s analysis report.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>The histogram of defaulted loans’ recovery rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) demonstrates two peaks, where a bimodal characteristic can be seen that the probabilities of full recovery rates ranging from 0.9 to 1 and low ones from 0.1 to 0.2 are both very high. Also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows that 4 peaks exist at the intervals of 0 to 0.1, 0.2 to 0.3, 0.4 to 0.5 and 0.8 to 0.9. As we know, the number of default events has increased since the financial crisis, and individuals have different abilities to repay their loans and bonds. However, it used to be rare to have so many default events.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>2. Beta Distribution Estimation of the Recovery Rate</title><p>A common method to estimate the distribution of recovery rates is Beta distribution, which forms a smooth curve compared with the histogram. Through the data of recovery rates of defaulted corporate loans, we get the mean which equals 0.5574 and the variance is 0.1003. Inputting the outcome above into the <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0068238.e023">Equations (2</xref>) and (3) leads to values of parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e052.jpg"/></inline-formula>, being 0.9797 and 0.7712, respectively. By Matlab7.6 software <xref rid="pone.0068238-Su1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, we get the simulated distribution of the real recovery rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The Beta distribution estimation cannot fit the bimodal distribution of defaulted loans’ recovery rates. Meanwhile, we can get the value of parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e053.jpg"/></inline-formula> of defaulted bonds’ recovery rates, which are 0.9797 and 0.7712 respectively. Besides, we get simulated distribution of recovery rates in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g005">Figure 5</xref>. It also illustrates that Beta distribution estimation can partly describe the distribution of recovery rates but cannot fit its multiple peaks characteristic.</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The red curve the result of Beta simulation of defaulted corporate loans’ recovery rates.</title><p>It well simulates the bimodal distribution of the recovery rates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0068238-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The red curve the result of Beta simulation of defaulted corporate bonds’ recovery rates.</title><p>It well simulates the multimodal distribution of the recovery rates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>As is shown above, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g004">figure 4</xref>, distribution of corporate loans’ recovery rates has two peaks but it is known that the five kinds of beta estimation results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g001">Figure 1</xref>) don’t fit the bimodal distribution. When it comes to distribution of corporate bonds’ recovery rates, it is obvious that the multiple-peaks in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g005">Figure 5</xref> are beyond the ability of the Beta estimation which can only simulate one peak. So it can’t be a perfect tool to depict bimodal and multimodal distributions of the defaulted corporate recovery rates. The Gaussian kernel density estimation is introduced to solve this problem.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>3. Kernel Density Estimation of the Recovery Rate</title><p>The finger rule has been used in the analysis of recovery rates of bank loans, see Servigny <xref rid="pone.0068238-Arnaud1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> for example. It is stated as:<disp-formula id="pone.0068238.e054"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e054.jpg"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e055.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the sample standard deviation and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the observed number. In this paper, the finger rule is adopted to estimate the bandwidth we need and then we put the value of <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0068238.e035">Equation (6</xref>). As to defaulted corporate loans’ recovery rates, the number of observations is 58 and the standard deviation is 0.3168. So the bandwidth <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> of this sample is 0.0624, derived through the finger rule. The bandwidth of the kernel is a free parameter which exhibits a strong influence on the resulting estimator. To illustrate its effect, the three kinds of Gaussian kernel density estimations are demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g006">Figure 6</xref> with bandwidths of 0.0208, 0.0624 and 0.1873 respectively.</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>The blue is the kernel density estimation of defaulted corporate loans’ recovery rates with bandwidth of 0.0624.</title><p>The green curve’s bandwidth is 0.1873.The red one is 0.0208.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g006">Figure 6</xref> leads to a conclusion that the larger the bandwidth is, the smoother the curve is. The green curve with the largest bandwidth is much flatter than the other two with 1/3 <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">h</italic>. The curve with bandwidth of 1/<italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is much steeper and exhibits multiple peaks while the one with 3 <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is too flat to depict the bimodal characteristics of corporate loans’ recovery rate. So the curve with bandwidth <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> best demonstrates the recovery rate’s distribution with two peaks and this proves that the bandwidth selection method we choose is appropriate. As for defaulted corporate bonds, number of observations is 282 and standard deviation is 0.2997, so the bandwidth h is 0.0314. Through Matlab7.6 software, we get its fitting curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g007">Figure 7</xref>). As we can see, the bonds’ recovery rates exhibit several peaks according to its density histogram. Combining the kernel density estimation curve into it, we find that the curve of the kernel density estimation has perfect fit to the distribution of the bonds’ recovery rate.</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>The red curve is the simulation by kernel density estimation with bandwidth of 0.0314.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>4. The Comparison of Gaussian Kernel Density Estimation and Beta Distribution Estimation of the Recovery Rates</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g008">Figure 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g009">Figure 9</xref> illustrate the differences between the two methods in terms of fitting of the curve to recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds.</p><fig id="pone-0068238-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>The red curve is the <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> shaped through the Beta distribution estimation of recovery rates of corporate loans.</title><p>The blue one is simulated by the kernel density estimation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g008.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0068238-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>The red curve is the inverse <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> shaped through the Beta distribution estimation of recovery rates of corporate bonds.</title><p>The blue one is simulated by the kernel density estimation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.g009.jpg"/></fig><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g008">Figure 8</xref>, compared with Beta distribution estimation, Gaussian kernel density distribution estimation result exhibits two peaks while the Beta distribution estimation results only show a <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> shape curve, which contradicts the original data of recovery rates. And also in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068238-g009">Figure 9</xref>, the beta distribution estimation result is an inverse <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> curve which cannot depict the multimodal distribution of recovery rates. So the kernel density estimation really better fits the distributions of the bimodal or multimodal samples with data of recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>5. Chi-square Goodness-of-fit Test Result</title><p>To assess whether the qualitative data fit the kernel density distribution, a Chi-square goodness-of-fit test is used. In the case of recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds, effective observations for the two samples are 58 and 282. At the same time, we choose 5 bins and 10 bins for each sample, because there exists one variable <italic toggle="yes">h</italic>, their degrees of freedom are <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e056.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e057.jpg"/></inline-formula> respectively. We get the results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t003">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t004">Table 4</xref> by R.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0068238-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Chi-square test of the estimation of recovery rates of defaulted corporate loans.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0068238-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e039.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0,0.2]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.2,0.4]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.4,0.6]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.6,0.8]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.8,1]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e040.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e041.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8417</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8286</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8864</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9997</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4438</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Pearson’s Chi-squared test.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>X-squared = 0.227238, df = 3, p-value = 0.973077.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0068238-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068238.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Chi-square test of the estimation of recovery rates of defaulted corporate bonds.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0068238-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0068238.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">i</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e042.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0,0.1]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.1,0.2]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.2,0.3]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.3,0.4]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.4,0.5]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.5,0.6]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.6,0.7]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.7,0.8]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.8,0.9]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.9,1]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e043.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0068238.e044.jpg"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.919</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.663</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.417</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.195</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.881</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.454</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.426</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.379</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.276</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Pearson’s Chi-squared test.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>X-squared = 6.13297, df = 8, p-value = 0.63234.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As we can see in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t003">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0068238-t004">4</xref>, p-values are larger than 5% significance level, so we can not reject the null hypothesis. It means that the kernel density estimator can quite fit the curve to recovery rates of corporate loans and bonds.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results find that the distribution of recovery rates display a new characteristic in the recent data and offer a new method, kernel density estimation, to estimate the distribution of the recovery rates. As we all know, the recovery rate is essential for managers and government officials to estimate the loss of their portfolios and the amount of insurance reserves. To ignore the randomness of the recovery rate by assuming it to be a constant may lower the default risk. Nowadays, financial agents have started paying more attention to management of recovery rates.</p><p>We find that corporate loans’ recovery rates follow a bimodal distribution and corporate bonds’ recovery rates have multiple-peaks. In the past years, especially before 2008, since economies were growing well, there were not too many default events, so the default probability was low and recovery rates were quite high. However, since the outbreak of the financial crisis, default events have increased, different individuals have different abilities to repay the debts. So the data we study shows a bimodal and multimodal characteristics.</p><p>We find the former two common ways to estimate the recovery rates are out of use because of the new characteristic of the recovery rates, so we introduce a new kernel density estimation to overcome it. In extant research, people always treat it as a statistical category and relatively haven’t paid too much attention. In our paper we test the two common ways on research of the distribution of recovery rate and then raise the new method, Gaussian Kernel density estimation. One is to utilize statistical methods such as histogram to estimate the distribution. The other is to parametrically estimate its density function that is set initially. Beta distribution is the most common distribution assumption in many models such as CreditMetrics by J.P.Morgan, Portfolio Manager by KMV and Losscalc by Moody’s. Combining with the data from Moody’s investor services, we find that histogram is a rough depiction and Beta distribution estimation has a main defect that it loses efficacy with the bimodal and multimodal curves. However, the Gaussian kernel density estimation, a nonparametric estimation methodology, offsets the imperfection. Finally, we prove this perspective and testify the hypothesis by the Chi-square test.</p><p>So by statistical simulation of the distribution of recovery rates with the data from Moody’s investor report, we compare the kernel density estimation with Beta distribution. We find that the kernel density estimation is better than the Beta distribution estimation while the data show bimodal or multiple-peaked characteristics, especially when the economy is in distress. And while the default events are increasing, the kernel density estimation will be beneficial for supervisors to precisely evaluate the loss of portfolio and allocate economic capital.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Matteo Convertino and the anonymous journal reviewers for advice and input into the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0068238-Arnaud1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arnaud DS, Olivier R (2004) Measuring and Managing the Credit Risk. New York: McGraw-Hill Companies.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Wang1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The double Beta model of recovery rate in credit risk management</article-title>. <source>Chinese Journal of Management Science 6</source>
<volume>(12)</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Hu1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu Y, Perraudin W (2002) The dependence of recovery rates and defaults. Working paper, Birkbeck College.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Rosch1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheule</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A multifactor approach for systematic default and recovery risk</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Fixed Income</source>
<volume>15(2)</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Qu1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Analysis and Application Research on Nonparametric Density Estimation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Shengyang Agriculture University</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Chen1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Recovery rate Models Based on General Beta Regression for Non-performing Loan</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Statistics and Management</source>
<volume>30(5)</volume>: <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>823</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Frye1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Depressing recoveries</article-title>. <source>Risk</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Pykhtin1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pykhtin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Unexpected recovery risk</article-title>. <source>Risk</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Andersen1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidenius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Extension to the Gaussian Copula: Random recovery and random factor loadings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Credit Risk</source>
<volume>1(1)</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Dullmann1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dullmann K, Trapp M (2004) Systematic risk in recovery rates an empirical analysis of US corporate credit exposures. Working paper: 2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Liu1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Kernel density estimation of stock returns distribution and Monte Carlo simulation test- comparison study based on data after the introduction of price limit system</article-title>. <source>The world economy</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Zhen1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Application of nonparametric kernel density estimation in the Hang Seng index yield distribution</article-title>. <source>Statistics and decision</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Shi1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dynamic analysis of China provincial economy increase based on kernel density estimation</article-title>. <source>Economic survey</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Camblor1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Camblor</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>K-Sample test based on the common area of kernel density estimators</article-title>. <source>Journal of statistical planning and inference</source>
<volume>138</volume>: <fpage>4006</fpage>–<lpage>4020</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Sharon1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sharon O, David C, Albert M (2011) Corporate Default and Recovery Rates, 1920–2010. Moody’s investors service: 18–21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Sharon2"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sharon O, David C, Albert M (2012) Corporate Default and Recovery Rates, 1920–2011. Moody’s investors service: 23–25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Martin1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>An optimal local bandwidth selector for kernel density estimation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Planning and Inference</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Mugdadia1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mugdadia</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A bandwidth selection for kernel density estimation of functions of random variables</article-title>. <source>Computational Statistics &amp; Data Analysis</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0068238-Su1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Su JM, Zhang LH (2004) Application of Matlab tool kit. Beijing: Publishing House of Electronics Industry.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>