
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Carcinog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">138</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">carcinog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101153623</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Journal of Carcinogenesis</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-3163</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3030761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3030761.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3030761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3030761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297922</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1477-3163.75723</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JC-10-2</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Zoledronic acid directly suppresses cell proliferation and induces apoptosis in highly tumorigenic prostate and breast cancers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almubarak</surname><given-names initials="H">Hussain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names initials="A">Antonia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaisuparat</surname><given-names initials="R">Risa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="M">Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meiller</surname><given-names initials="TF">Timothy F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheper</surname><given-names initials="MA">Mark A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mscheper@umaryland.edu">mscheper@umaryland.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">University of Maryland and the Marlene and Stewart Greenebaum Cancer Center, 650 W. Baltimore St., Baltimore, MD 21201, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Chulalongkorn University, 254 Phyathai Rd., Patumwan, Bangkok, Thailand 10330</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">193794</issue-id><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-04 01:25:13.847"><day>04</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2011 Almubarak</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="JC-10-2.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.carcinogenesis.com/content/10/1/2">This article is available from: http://www.carcinogenesis.com/content/10/1/2</self-uri><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="J Carcinog" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4360551"><article-title>Zoledronic acid directly suppresses cell proliferation and induces
apoptosis in highly tumorigenic prostate and breast cancers:
Retraction</article-title><volume>14</volume><date><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><elocation-id>2</elocation-id><source>Journal of Carcinogenesis</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4360551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25788867</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>Bisphosphonates (BPs) were designed for the prevention of skeletal-related events secondary to bone metastases. The purpose of this study was to show that zoledronic acid (ZA) directly eradicates highly tumorigenic and potentially metastatic cancer cells.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>Human prostate and breast highly tumorigenic (PC3, MCF 7) and low- or non-tumorigenic (LNCaP, MCF 10a) cell lines, respectively, were exposed to different concentrations of ZA (0-10 μM). Reverse transcriptase double quantitative polymerase chain reaction was used for quantitative gene expression analysis. Apoptosis and cell proliferation were determined using microscopic observation and MTS assays. Western blot was used to confirm the translational effects of apoptotic genes on protein expression.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Human prostate and breast highly tumorigenic (PC3, MCF 7) and low- or non-tumorigenic (LNCaP, MCF 10a) cell lines, respectively, showed multiple genes demonstrating differential expressions, including TRAF, TRADD, BCL2, CASPASES and IAP families. Increasing ZA concentrations showed a greater concentration-time response on cell proliferation and apoptosis in the highly tumorigenic cells. These results were confirmed by both reversing and enhancing the effect of ZA on cell proliferation with caspase 3, 7 or survivin siRNA, respectively. Pro-apoptotic proteins bax and caspase 2, 3, 7 and 9 were up-regulated, while the anti-apoptotic proteins bcl2, birc3 and survivin were down-regulated only in the highly tumorigenic cells.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>This explains the ability of ZA to inhibit bony metastasis in highly tumorigenic cells compared with the low- or non-tumorigenic cells through a significant decrease in cell proliferation and increase in apoptosis through gene-regulated and translational-mediated down-regulation of survivin coupled with the inhibition of caspase 3 or 7. This has significant implications toward understanding the pharmacophysiology of BPs in metastasis and supports the clinically observed effect of BPs when administered adjunctively with anticancer drugs such as cyclophosphamide/methotrexate/5-fluorouracil, epirubicin in combination with cyclophosphamide or docetaxel, and doxorubicin.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Apoptosis</kwd><kwd>bisphosphonate</kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd><kwd>metastasis</kwd><kwd>zoledronic acid
</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1-1"><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>In the United States, prostate cancer is the most common cancer in men (aside from skin cancer) and is the second leading cause of cancer-related deaths in the United States. About one in six men (192,280 in the US in 2009) will be diagnosed with prostate cancer during their lifetime, with 27,360 dying of their disease; therefore, comprising 10% of cancer-related deaths in men.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Similar to breast cancer, bone is the most common site for metastasis, and its involvement is a major cause of morbidity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] Breast cancer is the number one cancer in women. According to the National Institute of Health and the National Cancer Institute, one in every eight women has a risk of developing cancer over their lifetime (194,280 in the US in 2009).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Most of the deaths (40,610 in the US in 2009) associated with breast cancer are the result of metastasis and its physiologic effects on morbidity and mortality.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Bone is the most common metastatic site, with 65-75% of the women having metastatic lesions to the skeleton.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]</p><p>Once either of these malignancies metastasize to bone, therapy is mostly palliative to improve the patent's quality of life and to reduce morbidity where possible.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>] Among the treatments currently being used as preventatives are bisphosphonates (BPs), a vital component in the management of skeletal-related events (SRE).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>] BPs, such as zoledronic acid (ZA), are shown to decrease and postpone the onset of SREs, reduce tumor-induced hypercalcemia and relieve bone pain. BPs have a strong affinity for hydroxyapatite and are known to concentrate within bone, and shift bone turnover by inhibiting osteoclasts and promoting osteoblastic activity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] It is this function, along with altered cytokine and growth factor expression, that is thought to inhibit the migration, adhesion, invasion and proliferation of tumor cells.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>]</p><p>More recently, studies have begun to focus on the ability of BPs to inhibit highly tumorigenic cells. There are several studies supporting the anti-tumor and the anti-metastatic effects of BPs.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>] These studies focus mainly on the reduction of metastatic bone disease by mediating osteoclast-focused bone resorption as well as the direct effect of inhibiting tumor cell adhesion to bone.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>] This process is shown to occur via either the induction of apoptosis of osteoclasts, inhibition of growth factors, inhibition of angiogenesis and/or immunomodulation through the induction of γ/δ T-cells stimulation of both the innate and the adaptive immune responses.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>] Moreover, BPs in animal models have also shown variable direct anti-tumor effects in a few cancers, including melanoma and cervical cancer models, suggesting that BPs may have direct anti-tumor potentials, leading some to suggest that BPs may prove to be useful agents as chemotherapeutics.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>]</p><p>In this current study, we prove that ZA exerts greater anti-tumor effects on highly tumorigenic cells (PC3, MCF 7) compared with low- or non-tumorigenic (LNCaP, MCF 10a) cells by inhibiting cell proliferation and inducing apoptosis in a survivin, caspase 3 and 7-dependent manner.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Cell lines and cell cultures</title><p>All experiments were performed using established human prostate cancer cell lines (PC3 and LNCaP) and human breast cancer and breast epithelial cell lines (MCF 7 and MCF 10a), respectively. We examined both an MCF 7 cell line originally acquired from ATCC in 1990 and a new MCF 7 cell line acquired in 2010, to account for variability in <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 3</italic> expression over cell line passages. These cells were selected as representatives of highly tumorigenic (PC3, MCF 7) and low- or non-tumorigenic (LNCaP, MCF 10a) cells, respectively. MCF 7, PC3 and LNCaP cells were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 units of penicillin, 100 μg/ml streptomycin and 1.0 mg/ml of hydrocortisone (Sigma Chemical Company, St. Louis, MO, USA). MCF 10a cells were cultured in MEBM medium with MEGM SingleQuot additives (BPE 13 mg/ml, hydrocortisone 0.5 mg/ml, hEGF 10 μg/ml and insulin 5 mg/ml) (Lonza, Walkersville, MD, USA) and cholera toxin 100 ng/ml. (Calbiochem-EMD4, San Diego, CA, USA). The cells were cultured at 37°C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> air atmosphere until confluent and sub-cultured using a disaggregation assay with trypsin (0.1%) and EDTA (0.01%) in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; pH 7.5). For all experiments, cells were grown in 6-, 24- or 96-well plates, and grown to 80% confluence. Control cells (NM) for all experiments were treated with the infusion solution alone in normal media (non-calcium containing infusion solution, 0.36% saline). All experiments were performed in triplicate and repeated on two separate occasions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Drug treatments</title><p>ZA injectable acquired from leftover infusions (Zometa<sup>®</sup> ; Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corp, East Hanover, NJ, USA) was used for all experiments at concentrations of 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM up to 24 h (pre-concentration baseline plasma level is 1 μM). The concentrations were selected because they are clinically relevant in patients receiving ZA as representative of the lower limits of estimated plasma concentrations following a 15-min infusion (infusion solution, 0.36% saline).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>] Cells were visualized, photographed and assayed during the 24-h treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Direct microscopic observation</title><p>PC3, LNCaP, MCF 7 or MCF 10a cells were either left untreated (normal media or normal media with infusion solution, 0.36% saline) or exposed to ZA 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM diluted in non-calcium containing infusion solution and were examined for up to 24 h on a Zeiss Axiovert 135 microscope, with images captured using a digital Nikon capture system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>RT<sup>2</sup> Profiler<sup>tm</sup> polymerase chain reaction (PCR) array (PAHS-012A/ PAHS-027A)</title><p>Cells were treated with either infusion solution alone as control or ZA 5 μM in normal infusion solution for 24 h and washed twice with PBS, followed by lysis using trypsin (0.1%) and EDTA (0.01%) in PBS pH 7.5. Total RNA was isolated using RNAqueous Kit<sup>®</sup> as per manufacturer′s instructions (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA) and integrity and concentration were determined spectrophotometrically. A total of 1 μg of RNA was used with the RT <sup>2</sup> First Strand kit (C-03) (Superarray, Fredrick, MD, USA) with the addition of 2 μl of 2GE (5X gDNA elimination buffer). The RNA was incubated at 42°C for 5 min and placed on ice for 1 min. RT cocktail of 4 μl of BC3 (5Χ RT buffer 3), 1 μl of P2 (primer and external control mix), 2 μl RE3 (RT enzyme mix) and 3 μl of RNase-free water was added to each sample. The mixture was centrifuged, incubated at 42°C for 15 min and then heated at 95°C for 5 min and placed on ice.</p><p>PCR was performed using 25 μl of the following mixture: 1275 μl of 2X SuperArray RT <sup>2</sup> qPCR Master Mix, 102 μl diluted first strand cDNA synthesis reaction and 1173 μl of double-distilled water in the wells of a 96-well microtiter plate. The amplification process included one cycle for 10 min at 95°C, 40 cycles for 15 s at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles for 1 min at 60°C. Thermal cycling and fluorescence detection were performed using an ABI 5700 Prism (PE Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The signals of the target cDNAs were normalized by comparison with the housekeeping genes (GAPDH, Actin, reverse transcription control and positive PCR control) supplied within the 96-well microtiter plate. The normalized amount of each target mRNA present in each cell line was calculated by designating cells growing in normal medium with infusion solution without drug addition as a calibrator using a comparative Ct method following PE Biosystems protocols. Final calculations were made using a web-based PCR array data analysis tool (Superarray, Fredrick, MD, USA) with 1-fold difference set as baseline; however, only those over 1.5-fold were considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Cell proliferation</title><p>Cells were plated in 96-well plates using a density of 2,500 cells/well, and allowed to grow to 80% confluency. Subsequently, either infusion solution alone (control) or ZA 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM in infusion solution were added to the normal growth medium and incubated for 24 h. In separate experiments using the same control as above or ZA concentrations as above, caspase 3, 7 or survivin SignalSilence<sup>®</sup> siRNA or scrambled control for each siRNA (Cell Signaling, Beverly, MA, USA) were added at 5 nM to 25 μl of media (Invitrogen), with the addition of 4 μl plus regent (Invitrogen), and allowed to incubate for 15 min, while 1 μl lipofectamine 2000 reagent (Invitrogen) was added to 25 μl of the media and incubated for 15 min. The siRNA was combined with the lipofectamine 2000 reagent and incubated for an additional 15 min at room temperature. The combined mix was then added to the cells, which were incubated at 37°C at 5% CO<sub>2</sub> , followed by the addition of normal medium or the various ZA treatments for 24 h. Transfection efficiency was evaluated by immunofluorescence analysis. The cells were washed and subjected to the Cell Titer 96<sup>®</sup> AQ<sub>ueous</sub> Non-Radioactive MTS [3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium)] Cell Proliferation Assay (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), which was read at a wavelength of 490 nm, using a 96-well Dynatech MR4000 Microplate Palate Reader (Dynatech, Chantilly, VA, USA). The percentage of cell growth was determined by setting as 100% the growth of control cells treated only with infusion solution in normal media. All analyses were performed in triplicate and repeated on separate occasions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Cells were treated with either normal medium with infusion solution or ZA at 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM for 24 h. Cells	 ice-cold PBS, followed by lysis with buffer (62.5 mM tris pH 6.8, 2% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 1% β-mercaptoethanol and 33 ml dH<sub>2</sub>O) for 10 min at 4°C. The wells were scraped and the recovered cell products were centrifuged at 40,000 g for 5 min. The recovered proteins were measured and equalized using a Bio-Rad Protein Assay (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA, USA) as per the manufacturer's instructions. Western blot analysis was performed using a polyclonal traf2 (C192), bcl2 (#2876), Bax (#2772), caspase 7 (#9492), caspase9 (Asp330) antibody or a monoclonal caspase 3 (3G2) antibody (Cell Signaling, Beverly, MA, USA), a polyclonal traf4 (ALX-210-026) antibody (Alexis Biochemicals/Enzo, Farmingdale, NY, USA), a polyclonal bclxl (H-62) antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), a polyclonal survivin (ab469) antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), a monoclonal caspase2 (ICH1 L) or polyclonal birc3 (HPA002317) and actin (AC-40) antibody (Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA). Actin antibody was used as a loading control.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For all measurements, as needed, a t-test was employed to assess the statistical significance of the treated groups versus the control groups and applied to standard error measurements. Additionally, to analyze the proliferation data, a one-way ANOVA and Tukeys HSD statistics were applied. A statistically significant difference was considered to be present at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="result" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-8"><title>ZA-induced apoptosis and cell growth inhibition</title><p>Physical signs of apoptosis in the individual highly tumorigenic prostate cancer cell line PC3 and low-tumorigenic cell line LNCaP exposed to 0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM of ZA were determined microscopically. PC3 cells initially showed apoptotic effects, including rounding, balling up and fragmentation at 1 μM, with increasing apoptotic effects seen in a dose-dependent manner, with the greatest effects seen at 5 and 10 μM[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>]. In contrast, LNCaP cells showed no significant difference with increasing ZA concentrations, showing only minimal changes at 5 and 10 μM [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Microscopic apoptosis analysis: (a) microscopic images of apoptosis in human prostate highly tumorigenic PC3 cells using either treatment with normal media with infusion solution (NM-Control) or zoledronic acid (ZA) at 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM; showing the rounding, balling up and fragmentation of cells starting at 1 μM, with apoptotic effects seen in a dose-dependent manner, with the greatest effects seen at 5 and 10 μM (arrows) (×400 magnification). (b) Microscopic images of apoptosis in human low tumorigenic LNCaP cells using either treatment with normal media with infusion solution (NM) or ZA at 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM; showing no significant difference with increasing ZA concentrations, showing only minimal changes at 5 and 10 μM (arrows). Cells were observed over 24 h, with images taken at 24 h (original magnification, ×400)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The highly tumorigenic breast cancer cell line MCF 7 acted comparable to the PC 3 cells, showing apoptotic effects of cell rounding and fragmentation beginning at 3 μM and progressing in a dose-dependent manner up to 10 μM. This was not the case in the non-tumorigenic cell line MCF 10a, which showed similar effects to the LNCaP cells, being relatively unaffected by ZA. (Data not shown.)</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>RT<sup>2</sup> Profiler<sup>tm</sup> PCR array</title><p>RT<sup>2</sup> profiler array analyses of highly tumorigenic (PC3, MCF 7) and low- or non-tumorigenic (LNCaP, MCF 10a) prostate and breast cell lines treated with 5 μM of ZA for 24 h demonstrated differential regulation of apoptotic genes. Many of the apoptotic genes that were significantly up- or down-regulated were among several families known to be members of the extrinsic (<italic toggle="yes">TRAF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">DEATH DOMAIN</italic>) and intrinsic (<italic toggle="yes">BCL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IAP</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE</italic>) pathways. Differences in the expression of several genes were observed between the highly tumorigenic and low- or non-tumorigenic cells. Among the most consistent genes over/under-expressed in these highly tumorigenic versus low- or non-tumorigenic cell lines (PC3, MCF 7 vs. LNCaP, MCF 10a) were <italic toggle="yes">TRAF</italic> family members: <italic toggle="yes">TRAF2</italic> (2.69,1.68 vs. 1.81, 1.39), <italic toggle="yes">TRAF4</italic> (1.71, 1.72 vs. 1.63, -1.83) and <italic toggle="yes">TRADD</italic> (1.12, 1.81 vs. -1.92, -1.86); <italic toggle="yes">BCL2</italic> family members: <italic toggle="yes">BCL2</italic> (1.26, 2.22 vs. 2.35, 1.13), <italic toggle="yes">BCLXL</italic> (-2.6, -1.47 VS 1.75, 1.25) and <italic toggle="yes">BAX</italic> (2.0, 1.03 vs. -2.35, 1.45); <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE</italic> family members: <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 2</italic>  (2.08, 2.28 vs. -2.77, 1.36), <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 3</italic> (2.48, 1.15 vs. -1.66, &lt;1.0,), <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 7</italic> (1.28, 2.08 vs. 1.18, 1.85) and <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 9</italic> (1.67, 1.09 vs. -2.4, &lt;1.0); <italic toggle="yes">IAP</italic> family members: <italic toggle="yes">BIRC3</italic> (-2.14, 2.01 vs. 1.69, &lt;1.0) and <italic toggle="yes">BIRC5</italic> (survivin) (-4.53, -2.11 vs. 1.96, 1.57).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Cell proliferation</title><p>MTS assay results for prostate cancer cell lines showed a dose- and time-dependent response curve for the highly tumorigenic PC3 cells, having a gradual decrease in cell proliferation with the increasing ZA concentration and exposure time [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>]. The PC3 cells showed a significant decrease in cell proliferation starting at 6 h at 10 μM, followed by 12 h at 3 μM and, finally, for all doses at 24 and 48 h. The low-tumorigenic LNCaP cell line showed only a significant decrease in proliferation starting at 24 and 48 h and, mainly, at the higher ZA concentrations of 5 and 10 μM [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Cell proliferation: assessment of human prostate (PC3, LNCaP) and breast (MCF 7, MCF 10a) cancer cell proliferation using MTS assay following 6, 12, 24 or 48 h treatment compared with control cells and normal media with infusion solution (NM). (a, c) Decrease in tumor cell proliferation in a dose- and time-dependent manner in PC3 and MCF 7 cells following exposure to NM, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 µM zoledronic acid (ZA) compared with control cells (NM). (b, d) Minimal decrease in tumor cell proliferation in LNCaP and MCF 10a cells following exposure to NM, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 µM ZA compared with control cells (NM), showing that only high doses and long time periods decreased cell proliferation. Error bars indicate the standard errors of the means. The growth of control cells (NM) was set to 100%. *Statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) differences compared with control cells</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The MTS assay results for the breast cell lines demonstrated similar trends, with the highly tumorigenic MCF 7 cells showing both a dose- and time-response curve with ZA treatment, while non-tumorigenic MCF 10a cells were more resistant[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref> and [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">d</xref>].The MCF 7 cell line showed a significant decrease starting at 12 h at 1-10 μM, 24 h at 3-10 μM and 48 h at all doses. The MCF 10a cell line only showed a significant drop at 48 h at 5 μM and 10 μM.</p><p>Additional proliferation assays were performed at 48 h in the presence of increasing concentrations of ZA alone in the presence of control-scrambled siRNA or increasing ZA concentrations in the presence of caspase 3, 7 or survivin siRNA. The knock down of caspase 3 rescued the down-regulation of cell proliferation and resulted in levels near the control (NM) in both the highly tumorigenic PC3 (0.25 μM:107.9, 0.5 μM:99.9, 1 μM:106.4, 3 μM:101.2, 5 μM:89.4, 10 μM:85.9 and low-tumorigenic LNCaP cells (0.25 μM:88.1, 0.5 μM:103.4, 1 μM:99.7, 3 μM:100.1, 5 μM:91.8, 10 μM:90.4) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref> and [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">b</xref>]. Significant differences from increasing doses of ZA alone were noted in the PC3 cells at 1 μM, 3 μM, 5 μM and 10 μM ZA doses (P &lt; 0.05). On the other hand, knock down of survivin resulted in a further decrease in the cell proliferation in both PC3 cells (0.25 μM:69.4, 0.5 μM:58.1, 1 μM:52, 3 μM:47.5, 5 μM:44.5, 10 μM:45.4) and LNCaP cells (0.25 μM:88.1, 0.5 μM:90.9, 1 μM:78.9, 3 μM:69.4, 5 μM:83.1, 10 μM:80.5) Significant decreases from ZA treatment alone were noted in the PC3 cells at 1 μM, 3 μM, 5 μM and 10 μM concentrations of ZA plus survivin siRNA (P &lt; 0.05).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Alteration of cell proliferation: human prostate (PC3, LNCaP) and breast (MCF 7, MCF 10a) cancer cells following 48 h of treatment with normal media with infusion solution (NM) or 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM zoledronic acid (ZA) or these treatments combined with siRNA against caspase 3, 7 or survivin. (a, c) Decrease in cell proliferation in a dose- and time-dependent manner in PC3 and MCF 7 cells following exposure to 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM ZA compared with the control cells (NM). Caspase 3 siRNA signifi cantly reversed the effects of ZA on cell proliferation, starting at ZA concentrations of 1 μM in PC3 cells and Caspase 7 siRNA signifi cantly reversed the effects of ZA on cell proliferation, starting at ZA concentrations of 10 μM in MCF 7 cells compared with cells treated with ZA alone. Survivin siRNA showed a significant additional decrease in cell proliferation starting at ZA 1 μM in PC3 cells compared with cells treated with ZA alone. MCF 7 cells showed a decrease in cell proliferation at higher ZA concentrations; however, this was not significant. (b, d) Minimal decrease in tumor cell proliferation in a dose- and time-dependent manner in LNCaP and MCF 10a cells following exposure to 0.25, 0.5, 1, 3, 5 or 10 μM ZA compared with control cells (NM). Results demonstrate that caspase 3 siRNA in LNCaP cells significantly reversed the effects of ZA on cell proliferation at ZA concentrations of 5 and 10 μM. Survivin siRNA showed no significant additional decrease in cell proliferation. The growth of control cells (NM) was set to 100%. *Statistically significant (P &lt; 0.05) differences compared with control cells (NM) for ZA only and control-scrambled siRNA for Caspase 3, 7 and survivin treated. †Statistically significant (P &lt; 0.05) differences following siRNA treatment compared with ZA treatment on a dose-dependent basis</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>In the MCF 7 and 10a cells, the use of caspase 7 or 3 siRNA, respectively, rescued the down-regulation of cell proliferation seen with increasing concentrations of ZA: MCF 7 cells (0.25 μM:100, 0.5 μM:89.1, 1 μM:96.5, 3 μM:85.3, 5 μM:85.7, 10 μM:85.2) and MCF 10a cells (0.25 μM:98.2, 0.5 μM:98, 1 μM:100.1, 3 μM:103.2, 5 μM:101.2, 10 μM:99.4)[<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">D</xref>]. Significant reversal of cell proliferation was noted for MCF 7 cells at 10 μM and for MCF 10a cells at 5 μM and 10 μM concentrations of ZA (P &lt; 0.05). The addition of survivin siRNA with increasing ZA concentrations resulted in a further decrease of cell proliferation; however, only at the higher ZA levels: MCF 7 cells (0.25 μM:94.3, 0.5 μM:95.7, 1 μM:83.5, 3 μM:70.4, 5 μM:65.5, 10 μM:57.7) and MCF 10a cells (0.25 μM:98.2, 0.5 μM:98, 1 μM:87.4, 3 μM:81.4, 5 μM:75.11, 10 μM:76.5). The rescue with caspase 3 was significantly greater in the MCF 10a cells, while the reduction in cell proliferation was greater in the MCF 7 cells treated with ZA and survivin siRNA inhibition.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Several apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins were consistently affected by various concentrations of ZA in the highly tumorigenic versus low- or non-tumorigenic cell lines, showing consistent results with the RNA arrays. Following 24 h of exposure to normal media with infusion solution or 0.5, 1, 3, 5 and 10 μM doses of ZA, several apoptotic proteins were differentially expressed in the highly tumorigenic PC3 cell line versus the low-tumorigenic LNCaP cell line [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>], including an increase in the cleavage of caspase 2, 3 and 9 proteins and an increase in the expression levels of bax in PC3 cells with increasing doses of ZA, while the LNCaP cells showed only a slight increase in the cleavage of caspase 2 and 9 and maintenance of a constant level of expression of bax. Additionally, several anti-apoptotic proteins showed decreased expression in PC3 cells, the expression of bcl2 and bclxl proteins decreasing with increasing concentrations of ZA. However, there was no change in the LNCaP cell line. Survivin, an inhibitor of apoptosis (IAP), revealed a significant decreased expression at the 5 and 10 μM concentrations of ZA in PC3 cells, in contrast to LNCaP cells, where survivin expression showed a minimal change. Another member of the IAP family, birc3, showed decreased expression in the presence of higher concentrations of ZA in the PC3 cell line, while in the LNCaP cell line, its expression remained relatively constant. Surface death domain proteins, members of the traf family, revealed a gradual increase in traf2 expression with high ZA concentrations in the PC3 cell line, although there was only a slight increase in traf4 expression with the expression of traf4 falling off at 10 μM of ZA. This contrasts with the LNCaP cell line, where the expression of both traf2 and traf4 remained constant.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis: assessment of human prostate cancer cells (a) PC3 and (b) LNCaP demonstrating that following 24 h of exposure to normal media with infusion solution (NM) or 0.5, 1, 3, 5 and 10 μM doses of zoledronic acid (ZA), several apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins were differentially expressed in the highly tumorigenic PC3 cell line. Several apoptotic proteins were over-expressed, including bax and the increased cleavage of caspase proteins 2, 3 and 9, with increasing dose of ZA. Additionally, several anti-apoptotic proteins were downregulated in PC3 cells, including bcl2, bclxl, survivin and birc3. Surface death domain proteins, traf2 and 4 showed minimal change. Actin was used as the loading control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Similarly, apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins were consistently affected by ZA in the highly tumorigenic MCF 7 versus non-tumorigenic MCF 10a cell lines, consistent with the RNA arrays following 24 h of exposure to normal media with infusion solution or 0.5, 1, 3, 5 and 10 μM doses of ZA [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>]. Here, the MCF 7 cells showed an increase in the activity of apoptotic proteins, including the cleavage of caspase proteins 2, 7 and 9, and the gradual expression of bax with increasing ZA concentration, while MCF 10a cells showed minimal effect. Moreover, the expression of the anti-apoptotic protein bcl2 showed a decrease in protein expression, while bclxl remained constant with increasing concentrations of ZA in MCF 7 cells. However, both remained unchanged in MCF 10a cells. Survivin showed a dramatic dose-dependent decrease in the expression in MCF 7 cells, but remained stable in MCF 10a cells. The protein birc3 was down-regulated with increasing doses of ZA in both the MCF 7 and MCF 10a cell lines. As for the surface death domain proteins, members of the traf family in the MCF 7 cell line showed an up-regulation of traf 4, while traf 2 expression remained constant. On the other hand, MCF 10a cells revealed a decrease in the protein expression of traf2. Actin served as an independent control for all Western blots.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis: assessment of human breast cancer cells (a) MCF 7 and (b) MCF 10a demonstrating that following 24 h of exposure to normal media with infusion solution (NM) or 0.5, 1, 3, 5 and 10 μM doses of ZA, several apoptotic and anti-apoptotic proteins were differentially expressed in the highly tumorigenic MCF 7 cell line. Several apoptotic proteins were overexpressed, including the increased cleavage of caspase proteins 2, 7 and 9 with increasing dose of ZA. Additionally, several anti-apoptotic proteins were down-regulated in MCF 7 cells, including bcl2, survivin and birc3. Surface death domain protein, traf4 showed up-regulation in MCF 7 cells. Actin was used as the loading control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study provides proof that ZA has the potential to directly inhibit cell proliferation while inducing apoptosis in highly tumorigenic, highly proliferative cancer cells, similar to other chemotherapeutics used in prostate and breast cancer.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>] Our microscopic examination studies clearly demonstrated that ZA induced a dose-dependent increase in the levels of apoptosis in the highly tumorigenic PC3 and MCF 7 cell lines, while the low-tumorigenic, LNCaP and non-tumorigenic MCF 10a cells showed apoptosis resistance at comparable concentrations. These findings are consistent with recent clinical studies (AZURE trial), indicating that the combination of chemotherapy and ZA could possibly provide direct anti-tumor effects.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>]</p><p>Cell proliferation assays confirmed our findings from apoptosis assays. Here, the highly tumorigenic cells (PC3, MCF 7) demonstrated a combined dose and time response concentration curve, while the low-tumorigenic and non-tumorigenic cells (LNCaP and MCF 10a, respectively) showed resistance to the effects of ZA on cell proliferation. Moreover, inhibiting the terminal effectors of apoptosis, caspase 3 and caspase 7, allowed for the rescue of cell proliferation in the highly tumorigenic cell lines, while inhibiting survivin, an inhibitor of apoptosis, further increased the effects of ZA on these cell lines. This effect was mitigated in the low- and non-tumorigenic cells. This suggests that the molecular mechanisms associated with apoptosis and cell proliferation within the highly tumorigenic PC3 and MCF 7 cell lines are more sensitive to ZA than the low- and non-tumorigenic LNCaP and MCF 10a lines, respectively. Taken together, ZA was effective in preventing cell proliferation and inducing apoptosis within the highly tumorigenic cell lines. These results support the specificity of ZA as an inhibitor of metastatic and highly tumorigenic cancer formation, not only by affecting bone turnover but also by directly affecting metastatic and highly tumorigenic cells.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>]</p><p>In order to determine the molecular signaling pathways involved in the ZA-induced down-regulation of cell proliferation and up-regulation of apoptosis, we compared the array findings with translational effects on protein expression. The RT<sup>2</sup> profiler gene expression analysis demonstrated a differential expression in genes of the extrinsic (<italic toggle="yes">TRAF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">DEATH DOMAIN</italic>) and intrinsic (<italic toggle="yes">BCL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IAP</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE</italic>) apoptotic pathways for all cell lines. Thus, the differential gene expression played a role in driving decreased cell proliferation and increased apoptosis in highly tumorigenic cell lines PC3 and MCF 7 cells in comparison with the low- and non-tumorigenic cell lines LNCaP and MCF 10a in the presence of ZA.</p><p>When we evaluated the highly tumorigenic cell lines (PC3 and MCF 7), the extrinsic apoptotic pathway showed an up-regulation of <italic toggle="yes">TRAF2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TRAF4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TRADD</italic> on the RNA side, while the translational protein expression profile showed an increased regulation of <italic toggle="yes">TRAF2</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">PC3</italic> and an increased regulation of TRAF4 in MCF 7 cells. The intrinsic apoptotic pathway had a more dramatic correlation. Here, the pro-apoptotic genes included <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">7</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">9</italic>, which showed a greater up-regulation on the RNA level. This correlated directly with a translational increase in cleaved caspase 2, 3, 7 and 9 and activation in these highly tumorigenic cells. Conversely, when we examined the anti-apoptotic genes <italic toggle="yes">BCL2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BCLXL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SURVIVIN</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BIRC3</italic>, we found that all were significantly down-regulated in the PC3 cells, while only <italic toggle="yes">BCLXL</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SURVIVIN</italic> were down-regulated in the MCF 7 cells. On the translational side, all proteins were down-regulated to a greater extent than the low- or non-tumorigenic cell lines, with the exception of <italic toggle="yes">BCLXL</italic>.</p><p>The uncoupling of transcription and translation explains the limited conflict between the RT<sup>2</sup> profiler experiment and the Western blot analysis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>] Interestingly, prior studies have shown a reduction in <italic toggle="yes">BCL2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BCLXL</italic> and an increase in <italic toggle="yes">BAX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">9</italic> expression in the presence of a third-generation BP (ZA) in metastatic cancer cell lines, suggesting that the principal target of ZA is the inhibition of the mevalonate pathway, which in turn would modulate the <italic toggle="yes">BCL2</italic> gene family leading to mitochondrial-dependent apoptosis and the down-regulation of IAPs.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>] This study shows that in highly tumorigenic prostate and breast cancer cell lines, this occurs in a <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 3 (PC3)</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CASPASE 7 (MCF 7)</italic>-dependent manner, while in low- and non-tumorigenic cells, this phenomenon is reversed. This effect is proven by the fact that the addition of siRNA against caspase 3 in PC3 or caspase 7 in MCF 7 significantly reversed the effects of ZA, again supporting the specificity of the effects.</p><p>Additionally, we have shown that survivin, which is consistently over-expressed in metastatic tumors and is well known to play a role in the inhibition of apoptosis of tumor cells, is down-regulated in highly tumorigenic cells secondary to ZA treatment in a dose- and time-dependent manner.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>] Recently, survivin, a member of the inhibitor of apoptosis family, along with birc3 was shown to be a considerable marker in the identification of breast cancer metastasis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>] Further, survivin has been determined to be a prognostic marker and therapeutic target for metastatic prostate cancer. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>] Therefore, the down-regulation of survivin and its family member birc3 may prove to have significant clinical benefits. In fact, the addition of siRNA inhibition of survivin resulted in an additional down-regulation of cell proliferation in highly tumorigenic cells.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>]</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Our research demonstrates that ZA suppresses cell proliferation and induces apoptosis at both the transcriptional and the translational levels in highly tumorigenic prostate and breast cancer cell lines in a survivin- and caspase 3 or 7-dependent manner. Conversely, the low- and non-tumorigenic cell lines are resistant, lacking a down-regulation of these genes, both transcriptionally and translationally. Therefore, ZA is shown to not only potentially inhibit the metastasis of prostate and breast cancer by preventing their ability to invade bone but also in a direct manner by inhibiting cell proliferation and inducing apoptosis of metastatic/highly tumorigenic cancer cells. Further research is certainly needed to elucidate the exact mechanism and signaling pathways by which ZA acts on highly tumorigenic cells, to determine future interventional implications.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-6"><title>DECLARATION OF COMPETING INTERESTS</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-7"><title>AUTHOR'S PROFILE</title><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g006.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Hussain Almubarak,</bold> is a graduate of College of Dentistry, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. He earned his D.D.S. degree in the year of 2000. He had worked as private practitioner before he joined the National Guard Hospitals, Eastern Province, Saudi Arabia in 2004. He is currently a graduate student and Ph.D. candidate in the department of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences, Dental School, University of Maryland, Baltimore.</p><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g007.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Timothy F. Meiller,</bold> is Professor of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences at the Baltimore College of Dental Surgery and Professor of Oncology in the Program of Oncology at the Marlene and Stewart Greenebaum Cancer Center of the University of Maryland Medical Center in Baltimore. He has held his position at the University for 34 years, teaching and carrying out research protocols related to Oral Medicine and the management of oral complications in medically compromised patients. He serves as the Director of the Oral Medicine Program in the Dental School and at the Greenebaum Cancer Center. Dr. Meiller is a graduate of Johns Hopkins University and the University of Maryland Dental and Graduate Schools holding a DDS and a PhD in Immunology/Virology. He is a Diplomate of the American Board of Oral Medicine. He is currently engaged in ongoing investigations into opportunistic microbial infections and mucosal immunity dysfunction in oral complications associated with cancer therapies.</p><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g008.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Mark A. Scheper,</bold> is an assistant professor in the Department of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences - Dental School, associate member, University of Maryland Marlene and Stewart Greenebaum Cancer Center Program in Oncology, and a Full member, University of Maryland Graduate School. He has B.S. Xavier University, Cincinnati, OH; D.D.S, Ohio State University, Columbus, OH; Certificate in Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology, University of Maryland, Baltimore; and Ph.D. in Oral Health Sciences, University of Maryland, Baltimore. He is a diplomat of American Board of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology and a fellow of American Academy of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology. The research conducted in his laboratory focuses on the cell signaling pathways in head and neck cancer and premalignant lesions. Dr. Scheper has contributed to many publications and has received many academic awards.</p><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g009.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Ming Zhang,</bold> is currently a Research Assistant in The Department of Oncology and Diagnostic Science, Dental School University of Maryland, Baltimore. 1990-2004: She was a Research Fellow, Department of Microbiology, Dental School, University of Maryland, Baltimore. 1985- 1989: She was an Ophthalmologist at the Research Institute of Eye Diseases in Shenyang, P.R.China. 1985: M.D. from China Medical University. Shenyang, P. R. China. Ming has multiple publications in various journals.</p><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g010.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Risa Chaisuparat,</bold> Dr. Chaisuparat graduated from Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand. In 2006, she was certified in oral and maxillofacial pathology, Department of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences, Dental School, University of Maryland, Baltimore. In 2009, she earned her Ph.D. Certificate in experimental pathology, Dental School, University of Maryland, Baltimore. She is a diplomat of American Board of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology and a fellow of American Academy of Oral and Maxillofacial Pathology. She has contributed to many publications. Currently, she is a faculty member in Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</p><p><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JC-10-2-g011.jpg"/></p><p><bold>Dr. Antonia Jones,</bold> started practicing orthodontics in July 2010. She is a native of Chesapeake, VA, graduating as valedictorian from Hickory High School. She continued her studies at the University of VA where she double majored in Chemistry and Biology, graduating with distinction. Dr. Jones earned her Doctorate of Dental Surgery, as well as her Master of Science and certificate in orthodontics from the University of Maryland Dental School. She is a member of the American Dental Association, the American Association of Orthodontists, the American Association of Women Dentists, the Virginia Association of Orthodontists, and the Virginia Dental Association.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2009</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2009</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.20006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphosphonates: mechanism of action and role in clinical practice</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>2008</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1032</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4065/83.9.1032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2667901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyseng-Williamson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zoledronic acid: A review of its use in breast cancer</article-title><source>Drugs</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2661</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19093706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/0003495-200868180-00010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wonderling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the role of bisphosphonates in metastatic disease</article-title><source>Health Technol Assess</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3310/hta8040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphosphonates for breast cancer</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><comment>CD003474</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD003474.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16034900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-tumour effects of bisphosphonates: What have we learned from in vivo models?</article-title><source>Curr Cancer Drug Targets</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/156800909789760339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemons</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant bisphosphonate therapy for breast cancer patients: Standard of care or future direction?</article-title><source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.critrevonc.2009.03.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verdijk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolbers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of bisphosphonates on breast cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2007</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16621245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2006.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caraglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naviglio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Addeo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbruzzese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zoledronic acid: an unending tale for an antiresorptive agent</article-title><source>Expert Opin Pharmacother</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20001436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1517/14656560903485664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virzi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fratto</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoldo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabbatini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Can we consider zoledronic acid a new antitumor agent.Recent evidence in clinical setting?</article-title><source>Curr Cancer Drug Targets</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20088792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/156800910790980223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mystakidou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsouda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parpa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelekis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galanos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlahos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized, open label, prospective study on the effect of zoledronic acid on the prevention of bone metastases in patients with recurrent solid tumors that did not present with bone metastases at baseline</article-title><source>Med Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15965284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1385/MO:22:2:195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aviles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castaneda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta-Guzman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitumor effect of zoledronic acid in previously untreated patients with multiple myeloma</article-title><source>Med Oncol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17848748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF02698044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skerjanec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berenson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Major</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of zoledronic acid in cancer patients with varying degrees of renal function</article-title><source>J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12616668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0091270002239824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bisphosphonates to prevent skeletal complications in men with metastatic prostate cancer</article-title><source>J Urol</source><year>2003</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>S55</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><comment>discussion S57-58</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14610411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.ju.0000095102.34708.bc</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coxon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oades</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colston</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zoledronic acid induces apoptosis and inhibits adhesion to mineralized matrix in prostate cancer cells via inhibition of protein prenylation</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15217454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1464-4096.2004.04831.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodwell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of adding zoledronic acid to neoadjuvant chemotherapy on tumour response: Exploratory evidence for direct anti-tumour activity in breast cancer</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20234364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bjc.6605604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2853093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clyburn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefley</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased anti-tumour effects of doxorubicin and zoledronic acid in prostate cancer cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>: supporting the benefits of combination therapy</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19730863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00280-009-1106-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce Alberts</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology of the cell</article-title><source>Garland Science;</source><year>2002</year><edition>4th</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magae</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuruga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induction of mitochondria-dependent apoptosis through the inhibition of mevalonate pathway in human breast cancer cells by YM529: A new third generation bisphosphonate</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2007</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17316980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2007.01.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schimmer</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitor of apoptosis proteins: translating basic knowledge into clinical practice</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>7183</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15492230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-1918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngan</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer cells survive with survivin</article-title><source>Cancer Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1709</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18537980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2008.00870.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11159325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zohny</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shinawi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of survivin and Bcl-2 homologous antagonist/Killer mRNA in detection of bone metastasis in patients with breast cancer</article-title><source>Med Oncol</source><year>2010</year><comment>in press</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12032-010-9724-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siedow</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemierko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Survivin is a potential mediator of prostate cancer metastasis</article-title><source>Int J Radiate Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2010</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1095</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2009.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4348096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaffaroni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting survivin in cancer therapy: Pre-clinical studies.Apoptosome, biomedical and life sciences, USA</article-title><source>Springer Science</source><year>2010</year><fpage>147</fpage><fpage>68</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donovan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survivin: A new target for anti-cancer therapy</article-title><source>Cancer Treatment Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctrv.2009.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19559538</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>