
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3665802</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3665802.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3665802</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3665802</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23724014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-02211</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Stem Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell Differentiation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Stem Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neurons</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurogenesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neurobiology of Disease and Regeneration</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parkinson Disease</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conversion of Human Umbilical Cord Mesenchymal Stem Cells in Wharton’s Jelly to Dopamine Neurons Mediated by the Lmx1a and Neurturin <italic toggle="yes">In Vitro</italic>: Potential Therapeutic Application for Parkinson’s Disease in a Rhesus Monkey Model</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Stem Cell and Gene Therapy for Parkinson’s Disease</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="M">Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="M">Maosheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wanpu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhanlong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="D">Donghong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuaiyao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaonan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Medical Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Science and Peking Union Medical College, Yunnan Engineering Research Center of Vaccine Research and Development on Severe Infectious Diseases, Kunming, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>The First People's Hospital in Yunnan Province, Kunming, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pant</surname><given-names initials="AB">Aditya Bhushan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Indian Institute of Toxicology Research, India</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>lihj6912@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HL. Performed the experiments: MY YZ Wanpu Wang XW S. Li. Analyzed the data: MY MS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: Wenju Wang ZH S. Lu DT. Wrote the paper: MY.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">222430</issue-id><elocation-id>e64000</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Yan et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yan et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0064000.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7605703"><article-title>Retraction: Conversion of human umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells in Wharton’s jelly to dopamine neurons mediated by the Lmx1a and Neurturin <italic toggle="yes">In Vitro</italic>: Potential therapeutic application for Parkinson’s disease in a rhesus monkey model</article-title><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><date><day>2</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>e0242032</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0242032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7605703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33137132</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>hUC-MSCs hold great promise <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> neuronal differentiation and therapy for neurodegenerative disorders including Parkinson’s disease. Recent studies provided that Lmx1α play an important role in the midbrain dopamine cells differentiation. Neurturin is desired candidate gene for providing a neuroprotective to DA neurons. In this study, we investigated a novel neuronal differentiation strategy <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with Lmx1α and NTN. We transferred these two genes to hUC-MSCs by recombinant adenovirus combined with Lmx1α regulatory factor and other inductor to improve the efficiency of inducing. Then those induced cells were implanted into the striatum and substantia nigra of MPTP lesioned hemi-parkinsonian rhesus monkeys. Monkeys were monitored by using behavioral test for six months after implantation. The result showed that cells isolated from the umbilical cord were negative for CD45, CD34 and HLA-DR, but were positive for CD44, CD49d, CD29. After those cells were infected with recombinant adenovirus, RT-PCR result shows that both Lmx1α and NTN genes were transcribed in hUC-MSCs. We also observed that the exogenous were highly expressed in hUC-MSCs from immunofluorescence and western blot. Experiments <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> have proved that secretion NTN could maintain the survival of rat fetal midbrain dopaminergic neurons. After hUC-MSCs were induced with endogenous and exogenous factors, the mature neurons specific gene TH, Pitx3 was transcripted and the neurons specific protein TH, β-tubulinIII, NSE, Nestin, MAP-2 was expressed in those differentiated cells. In addition, the PD monkeys, transplanted with the induced cells demonstrated the animals’ symptoms amelioration by the behavioral measures. Further more, pathological and immunohistochemistry data showed that there were neuronal-like cells survived in the right brain of those PD monkeys, which may play a role as dopaminergic neurons. The findings from this study may help us to better understand the inside mechanisms of PD pathogenesis and may also help developing effective therapy for Parkinson’s disease.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was financially supported by the Research Fund for Doctor Innovation of Beijing Union Medical College (2011-1001-32); Science and Technology Project of Yunnan Province (2012AE001, 2007C0012Z); National Natural Science Foundation of China (30971003). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Parkinson disease (PD) is a neurodegenerative disorder in the elderly whose symptoms of tremor, rigidity, bradykinesia and postural instability are caused primarily by the degeneration of dopamine (DA) neurons in the substantia nigra <xref rid="pone.0064000-Vernier1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Prakash1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Prakash2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>The current existence therapies mostly confined to relieve symptoms but not fundamentally restore the lesion side function and loss of efficacy with disease progression <xref rid="pone.0064000-Morris1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Therefore, a therapy, which is safe and the functional recovery of the nigrostriatal system, is critical in clinical treatment of PD.</p><p>Since only HSCs are widely used, but all other celluar therapy with SCs are experimental. In the search for a renewable source of dopamine-producing, human fetal brain tissue <xref rid="pone.0064000-Stromberg1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, embryonic stem cells <xref rid="pone.0064000-Schulz1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, and neural SCs/progenitors <xref rid="pone.0064000-Ostenfeld1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> have been investigated. However, technical and ethical difficulties limited the application of this therapy <xref rid="pone.0064000-Doi1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Hall1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. During the last few years isolations of adult mesenchymal stem cell from different sources have been reported <xref rid="pone.0064000-daSilvaMeirelles1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Shih1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Zuk1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The MCSs derived from umbilical cord tissue have low immunogenicity and contain few immune cells. Previously studys demonstrated that human umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells (hUC-MSCs) could be induced to differentiate into neuron-like cells. Sarugaser et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Sarugaser1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and Karahuseyinoglu et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Karahuseyinoglu1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> showed the isolation, culturing and differentiation behavior of human perivascular umbilical cells and obtained osteogenic nodules. Datta et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Datta1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, Fu et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Fu1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and weiss et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> demonstrated the differentiation capacity of hUC-MSCs into dopaminergic neurons and better than bone marrow derived MSCs.</p><p>The LIM homeobox transcription factors 1 alpha (Lmx1α) is sufficient and required to trigger midbrain dopamine (mDA) neurons differentiation. It is accepted by most research that fully compatible dopaminergic differentiation requires extrinsic cues provided by signaling molecules such as sonic hedgeho (SHH) and the fibroblast growth factor (FGF-8) <xref rid="pone.0064000-Cai1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Friling1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Andersson1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Ran Brazilay et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Barzilay1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> reported that <italic toggle="yes">Lmx1α</italic> forced expression, together with extrinsic signaling molecule is sufficient to produce cells that expressed high level of TH, the rate-limiting enzyme in dopamine synthesis, and secreted significantly higher levels of dopamine.</p><p>Neurturin (NTN) is a potent trophic factor for dopaminergic neurons. NTN enhances dopaminergic neurons survival, prevents the loss of damaged nigral dopamine neurons in an animal model of PD and restores the neuronal micro-environment <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0064000-Kotzbauer1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Kordower1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.</p><p>We hypothesized that hUC-MSCs infected with adenoviral vectors expressing Lmx1α and NTN and cultured in chemical micro-environment could be transdifferentiated to undertake neuronal differentiation pathways. In this study, we examed the effects of promoting the differentiation potential and trophic effects on endogenous neural stem cells by continuous NTN and nutritional factors secretion in the transplanted neural-like cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Collection and use of human umbilical cord was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Institute of Medical Biology (YISHENGLUNZI [2011] 16), and was provided following caesarian section with written informed consent.</p><p>The recombinant adenoviruses Ad-NTN and Ad-Lmx1α were provided by the Laboratory of Molecular Biology at the Institute of Medical Biology of the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences.</p><sec id="s2a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All animal experimental procedures were carried out in strict accordance with the National Institute of Health Guidelines for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. The animal experiments were approved by the Ethics Committee of Animal Care &amp; Welfare, Institute of Medical Biology, CAMS (Permit Number: SYXK (dian)2010-0007), in accordance with the animal ethics guidelines of Chinese National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) and the Office of Laboratory Animal Management of Yunnan Province, China. Non-human primates were kept in a single cage and bred according to the guidelines of the Experimental Animals Ethics Committee of Institute of Medical Biology Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (Permit Number SCXK-2005-0005). We injected penicillin to monkeys for diminishing inflammation after surgery. Rhesus monkeys were euthanized by an overdose of injection anaesthetic (sodium pentobarbital, 10 mg/kg). All efforts were made to minimize the number of animals used and their suffering. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Gorska1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>The rats we were obtained from Institute of Medical Biology of Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences. After the experiments rats were euthanized by dislocation of cervical vertebra; fetuses were euthanized by decapitation.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Isolation and Expansion of hUC-MSCs</title><p>Human umbilical cords were obtained from healthy full-term caesarian section births and aseptically store at 4°C PBS containing 1% antibiotics of penicillin and streptomycin. The cord was rinsed several times to drained blood from vessels and cords. Then cut it into 2–3 cm length and rinsed again. Umbilical arteries and veins were removed, and the remaining tissues were transferred to a sterile container and were dicied into small fragments in the PBS. The explants were transferred to flask contain minimum essential medium (α-MEM) along with 15% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and incubated at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The medium was replaced every five days. The cells were reached 60%–70% confluence then transferred it to 6-well plates supplemented with 20 µM BrdU. After 48 h incubation, the cells were rinsed with PBS and fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde/0.2% Trinton-X 100/PBS for 30 min at 4°C and then treated with pre-cooled methanol for 10 min at 4°C. The cells were rinsed with PBS, subsequently treated with 2 M hydrogen chloride (HCl) for 20 min at 37°C and rinsed with PBS. Then the sample blocked with 2% bovine serum albumin (BSA) in PBS for 30 min at 37°C. Cells were incubated overnight at 4°C with the primary antibody (anti-BrdU mouse monoclonal antibodiy, ZSGB-BIO ORIGENE, diluted in 1∶50). The next day, cells were rinsed with PBS, then incubated with secondary antibody diluted in 2% BSA/0.2 Tween-20/PBS for 30 min at 37°C and counterstained DAPI (4′, 6-Diamidino-2-Phenylindole Dihydrochloride, Sigma-Aldrich) for 2 min at room temperature. The testing cells were observed under fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>To stain the hUC-MSCs, the cells were lifted with 0.125% trypsin. The digested cells were washed with PBS and resuspended into a single cell suspension at a concentration of 10<sup>6</sup>/mL. The suspension cells were stained with the following labeled antibody: CD45-PerCP, CD34-PE, CD49d-PE, CD29-PE, CD44-PE and HLA-DR-FITC (BD Pharmingen), incubated in the dark for 30 min at room temperature and then analyzed by means of a FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Transmission Electron Microscopy</title><p>The hUC-MSCs were detached with 0.125% trypsin and fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde in PBS for 2 h. Cells were rinsed with 0.1 M PBS and fixed in 1% osmic acid fixative for 3 h at 4°C. Cells underwent sequential dehydration for 15 min in 50%, 70% and 90% ethanol, a 1∶1 mixture of 90% ethanol and 90% acetone and then 90% acetone. The above steps were all operated at 4°C. Cells were washed with 100% acetone at room temperature for three times. Cells were embedded in epoxy resin, and cut it into 50–60 nm slices. The slices were double stained with 3% uranyl acetate-lead citrate and observed under TEM at 80 kV.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Adipogenic Differentiation Potential</title><p>hUC-MSCs were transferred to 6-well plates(1×10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) with cover slips cultured with MEM-α containing 15% FBS. When the cells reached 90% confluence, the medium was replaced with high-glucose Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s Medium(H-DMEM) containing 10% FBS, 1 µM dexamethasone (ENZO), 10 µg/mL insulin and 0.5 mM 3-isobuty-1-methylxanthine (Sigma). Four days later, the medium was replaced with H-DMEM containing 10% FBS and 200 µM indomethacin (Sigma-Aldrich). After four days inducing, the medium was replaced with H-DMEM containing 10% FBS, 1 µM dexamethasone, 10 µg/mL insulin, 0.5 mM 3-isobuty-1-methylxanthine and 200 µM indomethacin. The medium was replaced every four days. After 21 days of adipogenic stimulation, cells were rinsed with PBS, fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde at room temperature and incubated for 30 min with oil red O to stain lipid vacuoles and treated with hematoxylin (Beytime) to stain nuclei.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Osteogenic Differentiation Potential</title><p>hUC-MSCs were transferred to 6-well plates(1×10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) with cover slips cultured with MEM-α containing 15% FBS. When the cells reached 60%–70% confluence, the medium was replaced with H-DMEM containing 10% FBS, 10 nM dexamethasone, 10 mM β-glycerophosphate disodium salt hydrate and 150 µM L-ascorbic acid-2-phosphate (Sigma-Aldrich). Medium was changed every four days. After 21 days of osteogenic stimulation, cells were rinsed with PBS, fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde at room temperature and incubated for 30 min with alizarin red to stain calcium nodules. Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity was assayed by means of the GENMED alkaline phosphatase activity staining kit (GENMED Scientifics, Inc.).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>RT-PCR Analysis of the Transcription of the NTN and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs</title><p>hUC-MSCs were transferred to a flask (1×10<sup>6</sup> cells per well) and adenovirus was added in culture medium at multiplicity of infection (MOI, the appropriate dose for the virus between the number of infected cells and the virus titer) of 5 for 48 h. Total RNA was extracted from control cells and treated cells (Ad-NGFpreNTN and Ad-Lmx1α infected) with the use of the RNA extraction kit (OMEGA) as described by the supplier. RNA was reverse-transcribed with the use of M-MuLV reverse transcriptase in a 20 µL volume containing 0.2 µg Oligo (dT), 400 µmol/L dNTP and buffers supplied by the manufacture. With the above cDNA (1 µg) as a template, the sequences were used in the Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was showed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064000-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0064000-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Primers sequences used in reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction and Real-time PCR.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0064000-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence(5′-3′)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">β-actin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">GGCATCCTCACCCTGAAGTA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">GGGGTGTTGAAGGTCTCAAA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NGFpreproNTN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">TGTCCATGTTGTTCTAC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">TTACACGCAGGCGCACTC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lmx1α</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">CTAAGATGTGAAGTAAG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">CTAAGATGTGAAGTAAG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">GCACCTTCGCGCAGTTC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">CCCGAACTCCACCGTGAA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">β-tubulinIII</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">CGTGCCTCGAGCCATTCT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">GCCCCCTCCGTGTAGTGA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">AGACCACCATTGACGACTCC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">TCTCCGAGCTTCCTTTTCAG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">CCCACTACGGAGCCTACATCTT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">CAATGGCGTAGGCCAGTTTC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lmx1β</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">TGTGCAAGGGTGACTACGAGAA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">TTCATGTCCCCATCTTCATCCT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Msx1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">CTCCCTGAGTTCACTCTCCG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">CAGGAGACATGGCCTCTAGC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pitx3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">GGACTAGGCCCTACACACAGA</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">TCCGCGCACGTTTATTTC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foxα2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">TTCAGGCCCGGCTAACTCT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">AGTCTCGACCCCCACTTGCT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurrl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward:CGAAACCGAAGAGCCCACAGGA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">GGTCATAGCCGGGTTGGAGTCG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NES</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">TTCACAGCCAATGTAGGGAT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">ATGGGACAAGAGCAAAGCAC</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nestin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: <named-content content-type="gene">AGACTCTTCCCGACTCCACT</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: <named-content content-type="gene">CATCCGCAAACCCATCAG</named-content>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EN1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward:TGGGTGTACTGCACACGTTATTC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse:GGAACTCCGCCTTGAGTCTCT</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Immunofluorescence Detected the Expression of NTN and Lmx1α hUC-MSCs</title><p>hUC-MSCs were transferred to 6-well plates (1×10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) with cover slips and adenovirus (Ad-NGFpreproNTN, Ad-Lmx1α) was added in culture medium at MOI of 5 for 48 h. The cells were rinsed with PBS and fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde containing 0.2% Triton X-100 at 4°C for 30 min, Subsequently fixed with precooled methanol for 10 min at 4°C. After washing with PBS, samples were incubated with antibodies (NTN: Mouse Anti-Human Neurturin Monoclonal Antibody,R&amp;D,1∶100; Lmx1α: Rabbit Anti-Human Lmx1α Monoclonal Antibody,Santa Cruz,1∶50) for 90 min at 37°C. Then rinsed the cells and incubated with the secondary antibody(NTN: FITC Labeled Rabbit Anti-Mouse IgG Secondary Antibody,KPL,1∶250; Lmx1α: anti-rabbit IgG-DylightTM549, RockLand immunochemicals, 1∶3000) for 30 min at 37°C. The cells were observed under a fluorescence microscope. hUC-MSCs without any treated were as control group.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Western Blotting Detection of Lmx1α Expression and Mature NTN Secretion</title><p>Adenovirus (Ad-NGFpreproNTN, Ad-Lmx1α) was added at MOI of 5 for 48 h. The condition medium and cells were harvested after adenovirus infection. The normal cells were as control group. These samples were separated by SDS-PAGE (12% gel) and transferred to PVDF membranes.</p><p>The membranes were blocked at 37°C for 2 h with nonfat milk in PBS. Membranes were incubated with primary antibodies (NTN:Goat Anti-Human Neurturin Polyclonal Antibody,R&amp;D,1∶250; Lmx1α: Rabbit Anti-Human Lmx1α Monoclonal Antibody,Santa Cruz,1∶50) for 2 h at 37°C, after washed three times the membranes were incubated for 2 h at 37°C with approximate horseradish peroxidase (HRP) conjugated secondary antibodies (NTN: Rabbit anti-Goat IgG Secondary antibody,KPL,1∶2000; Lmx1α: Goat anti-Rabbit IgG Secondary antibody,KPL,1∶2000). After washing, blots were visualized using DAB chromogenic reagent. The molecular weight of the analyzed proteins was estimated using PageRuler Prest Protein Ladder (Therom).</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>ELISA Detection of the Extracellular Secretion of NTN by hUC-MSCs</title><p>The medium was collected after hUC-MSCs infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN at 24 h, 48 h, 72 h and 96 h. Control group was normal hUC-MSCs culture medium. The 96-well palte was incubated with coating buffer overnight at 4°C. The samples were washed three times with PBS-T (containing 0.5% Tween-20) and blocked with 3% BSA in PBS-T for 2 h at 37°C. After washing, each sample was incubated with primary antibody (Goat Anti-Human Neurturin Polyclonal Antibody, R&amp;D, 1∶2000) for 1 h at 37°C. Then the plate was rinsed three times and incubated again with secondary antibody (Rabbit anti-Goat IgG Secondary antibody, KPL, 1∶2500) for 1 h at 37°C. The samples were visualized using TMB (3, 3′, 5, 5′-Tetramethylbenzidine) for 15 min at room temperature. The results of densitometry measurement were statically analyzed by student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test.</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>The Bioassay of the Neurons Survival Promoting Activity of NTN</title><p>Sprague Dawley (SD) rats that had been pregnant for 14 days were sacrificed by dislocation of cervical vertebra. The abdominal cavity was opened under aseptic conditions and put the uterus in a sterile dish containing precooled Hank’s Balanced Salt Solution (HBSS). Then removed the fetal rats carefully and opened the cranial cavity with forceps and the entire brain was dissected after clearing the meninges and blood vessels. The ventral midbrain area was removed and cut into pieces in precooled HBSS solution. The pieces were digested with 0.125% trypsin for 20 min before adding culture medium to terminate the digestion. Cells were dispersed by repeated pipetting. Digested cells were added to 6-well plates coated with poly-L-lysine with coverglasses, followed by incubation at 37°C with 5% CO for 24 h. The culture medium was together with the condition mediun and Neural Basal plus B27 seurm free supplements. The control group was supplemented with the culture supernatant from control hUC-MSCs. The DA neurons were incubated and the medium was replaced by half ervery three days. After 21day’s observation, immunohistochemisty was performanced to assay the DA neuros.</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>Differentiation of hUC-MSC into Dopaminergic Neurons Like Cells</title><p>To differentiated hUC-MSCs into a dopaminergic neurons like cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, hUC-MSCs were transferred to 6-well plates with cover slips (1×10<sup>5</sup> cells per well). hUC-MSCs were infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN at MOI of 6 for 24 h. Subsequently the cells were infected with Ad-Lmx1α at MOI of 5 for 24 h. Then, the medium was replaced with neuronal pre-induction medium, consisting of MEM-α (20% FBS) medium with a cocktail of bFGF (Millpore) and β-mercaptoethanol (Sigma-Aldrich). Cells were induced for 24 h and replaced with neuronal induction medium, containing MEM-α (15% FBS) medium with a cocktail of bFGF, β-mercaptoethanol, SHH (R&amp;D), FGF-8(R&amp;D), RA (Sigma-Aldrich). Seven days later, the medium was replaced with the final induction medium, consisting of MEM-α (5% FBS) medium with a cocktail of bFGF, β-mercaptoethanol, SHH, FGF-8, RA. The neuronal indction medium was replaced every seven days. As a control, hUC-MSCs were also cultured with growth medium alone, without added adenovirus or induction medium.</p><sec id="s2l1"><title>Real-time PCR analysis</title><p>Total RNA was isolated with the use of the RNA extraction kits (OMEGA) as described by the supplier. RNA was reverse-transcribed with the use of M-MuLV reverse transcriptase in a 20 µL volume containing 0.2 µg Oligo (dT), 400 µmol/L dNTP and buffers supplied by the manufacture. With the above cDNA (1 µg) as a template, real-time PCR was performed with the use of SsoFast™ EvaGreen Supermix (Bio-Rad) and run on a CFX96™ real-time system instrument and software (Bio-Rad). Sequences of the primers are show in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064000-t001">Table 1</xref>. The mRNA level relative to that of β-actin was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="s2l2"><title>Immunofluorescence staining</title><p>For immunofluorescence staining, the induced cells were fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde containing 0.2% Triton X-100 for 30 min at 4°C. They were then fixed with pre-cooled methanol for 10 min at 4°C and subsequently blocked with 2% BSA in PBS for 30 min at 37°C. Cells were incubated with the following specific primary antibodies diluted in PBS: TH (Rabbit anti-Human TH,Millipore,1∶1000), NSE (Rabbit anti-Human/Monkey neuron-specific enolase,Thermo Fisher Scientific,60 µL/mL), Nestin (Anti-Nestin,miliipore,1∶200), β-tubulinIII (Anti-Tubulin, beta III isoform, C-terminus,millipore, 1∶100)and MAP-2 (Rabbit anti-human microtubule-associated protein 2,Cell Signaling Technology, 1∶50). The next day, the cells were washed and appropriate secondary antibodies including anti-mouse IgG, FITC (KPL) and anti rabbit IgG, FITC (Chemicon) were incubated for 30 min at 37°C. The negative controls were processed identically to the test sample.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2m"><title>Animal Model Study</title><sec id="s2m1"><title>Establishment of a semi-parkinsonian animal model</title><p>Monkeys were anesthetized with hydrochloric acidulated ketamine (10 mg/kg) for inducement and sodium pentobarbital (20 mg/kg) for maintenance. The right carotid artery was exposed by surgery, and the common carotid artery was injected with 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine hydrochloride (MPTP-HCL,GBICO, 0.6 mg/kg), while the external carotid artery was being blocked.</p></sec><sec id="s2m2"><title>Stereotaxic surgery</title><p>Nine hemiparkinsonism monkeys were selected and randomly divided into three groups: the test group, which was injected with induced cells, the control group, which was injected with HBSS and the normal group. Before the stereotaxic injection, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) was conducted to locate the target sites (caudate nucleus, putamen and substantia nigra). All test monkeys were injected by the same parameters (CA: AP = 27 mm, ML = −5.5 mm and DV = 21 mm; PU: AP = 22 mm, ML = −11.5 mm and DV = 25 mm; and SN: AP = 9 mm, ML = −5 mm and DV = 33.5 mm) <xref rid="pone.0064000-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. After anesthesia with hydrochloric acidulated ketamine and sodium pentobarbital was given, monkeys were fixed in a surgical frame. The cells culture medium was added BrdU to label the hUC-MSCs. The injection dosage was 10<sup>7</sup> per pore. For the control group, the HBSS injection dosage was 50 µL.</p></sec><sec id="s2m3"><title>Behavioral analysis by the parkinson’s disease rating scale</title><p>Parkinsonian behavior was evaluated by Kordower et al. <xref rid="pone.0064000-Kordower1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, with modifications (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0064000-t002">Table 2</xref>) including tremor, grait, hypokinesia, balance and so forth. The evaluation was conducted 3 times per week. An average score was calculated and ayalyzed by means of the student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0064000-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Unified Parkinson’s Disease Rating Scale.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0064000-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">NO:</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date: Recorder: Designed by:</td><td colspan="11" align="left" rowspan="1">Comment:</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Items</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detail Instruction For Rating Scale</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Week</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Week</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facial Expression(0–3)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Slight but definitely abnormal diminution of facial expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Moderate hypomania; lips parted some of time</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3 = Masked of fixed facial with severe of complete loss of facial expression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tremor(0–3)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Slight-low amplitude</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Moderate amplitude, present most of the time</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3 = Severe-high amplitude, virtually continuous, interferes with function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posture(0–2)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal Erect</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Stopped</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Face down</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gait(0–5)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal, use all 4 limbs smoothly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = One side circling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Walk slowly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3 = Markedly impaired, able to ambulate but very slowly and with effort</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">4 = Severe decrease in ability to ambulate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">5 = Unable to ambulate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross Motor Skills (Left and right upper limbs) (0–4)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal use limbs through a wide range of motion and activities</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Noticeable decrease in capability to use limb, but used consistently</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Severe decrease in capacity to use limb, rarely used</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3 = Unable or refuse to use limb(will use for walking)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">4 = Unable to use limb including walking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defense Reaction(0–2)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal; Response to an attack actively</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Response to an attack with only a simple action or passively</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Without any response to an attack</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balance(0–2)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal balance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Mild loss of balance on arising or with movement, holds onto cage for support</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Major lapses in balance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Freezing(0–2)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Absent</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Present for up to 10 s</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Present for over 10 s</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypokinesia(0–2)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0 = Normal amount of movements</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1 = Moderate decrease in the amount of movements</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2 = Essentially no movement (akinetic)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Rating Scale</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Sum all the scores in each items</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Average/week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2m4"><title>R-(−) apomorphine-induced rotation</title><p>A characteristic of the hemiparkinsonian state is rotation induced by R-(−) apomorphine (2 mg/kg, GBICO), a dopamine agonist. The induced rotations were examined after administration of the cell therapies to evaluate the recovery of DA neurons on the lesioned sides. The number of rotations of each animal was recorded and analyzed by means of the student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test.</p></sec><sec id="s2m5"><title>Histological evaluation of recovery</title><p>About six months after treatment, the monkeys were sacrificed with the method of euthanasia. Brains were removed and fixed with paraformaldehyde for seven days. The tissues were sectioned in paraffin (7 µm) by a sliding microtome.The sections were incubated with the primary antibody mouse anti-monkey TH (1∶2000) and mouse anti-BrdU (1∶50), followed by treatment with HRP-labeled secondary antibodies.</p><p>Grafted cells, which were labeled with BrdU, were detected in the right side substantia nigra of cell therapy monkeys (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g020">Fig. 20</xref> C) and the left side had no significantly staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g020">Fig. 20</xref> D). In the HBSS group there were not significantly staining in the left side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g020">Fig. 20</xref> A) and the lesion side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g020">Fig. 20</xref> B).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Characteriztion of Cultured hUC-MSCs</title><p>About 3×10<sup>6</sup> hUC-MSCs were collected from 20 cm of umbilical cord. Seven days after isolation, hUC-MSCs adhered and displayed a fibroblast-like appearance. Ten days later, they started to proliferate rapidly and reached 80% confluence within 2–3 weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g001">Fig. 1</xref> A). The cells isolation <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> was stabled through 7 passages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g001">Fig. 1</xref> B). An amplification index assay indicated that 90% of DAPI-positive cells were BrdU positive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g002">Fig. 2</xref> A, B), confirming the capacity of hUC-MSCs for self-proliferation.</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Expansion of hUC-MSCs cultured <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</title><p>(A) Morphology of hUC-MSCs primary cultured for 20 days. Scale bar: 40 µm. (B) Morphology of hUC-MSCs cultured at the 7<sup>th</sup> generation. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064000-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Characterizaton and proliferation index of hUC-MSCs cultured in growth medium.</title><p>(A) hUC-MSCs counterstain with BrdU. (B) hUC-MSCs counterstain with DAPI. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>FACS analysis demonstrated that hUC-MSCs were stained positive for CD29, CD44 and CD49d but negative for CD45, CD34 and HLA-DR. The CD45 negative cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g003">Fig. 3</xref> A), 82.76% were CD29+HLA-DR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g003">Fig. 3</xref> C), 81.25% were CD49d+HLA-DR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g003">Fig. 3</xref> D), 66.75% were CD44+HLA-DR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g003">Fig. 3</xref> B) and 99.38% were CD34+HLA-DR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g003">Fig. 3</xref> E).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Flow cytometry analysis for immunophenotypic characterization of hUC-MSCs.</title><p>The cells were stained with antibodies against CD29, CD49d, CD44, CD45, CD34 and HLA-DR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Ultrastructural of hUC-MSCs</title><p>The hUC-MSCs were sphere-like (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> A), and the surface of the cells membrane had many microvilli-like protrusions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> C). Cells had a large nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio, and the nuclei were oval or irregular with nuclear fussion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> D). The nuclear outer membrane was visibled and contained ribosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> E). The heterochromatin was distributed around the nucleus, which contained greater amount of enchromatin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> B), rough endoplasmic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> C) and concentration mitochondria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g004">Fig. 4</xref> F). The result indicated that hUC-MSCs were primitive, metabolically active and poorly differentiated.</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Ultrastructural characteristics of hUC-MSCs were detected by TME.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Differentiation Capacity and Plasticity of hUC-MSCs</title><sec id="s3d1"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> differentiation into adipogenic cells</title><p>Adipocytic phenotypes in induced hUC-MSCs were first signaled by the appearance multisized, most cells became round or cuboid and retracted their cellular extensions during induction, although a few retained their fusiform shape. After 5 days of adipogenic differentiation, tiny intracytoplasmic droplets could be observed. After 21 days adipogenic differentiation, most cultivation cells were became larger and the number of lipid droplets in cytoplasm increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g005">Fig. 5</xref> A). The effectiveness of differentiation was assessed by histochemical staining. In the adipogenic differentiated cells, red stained intracellular vacuoles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g005">Fig. 5</xref> C). Control hUC-MSCs were only visibly stained with hematoxylin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g005">Fig. 5</xref> B).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Differentiation of hUC-MSCs into adipocytes <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</title><p>(A) The lipid droplet of cells cultured in adipogenic medium for 21 days. (B) Staining was not observed in control hUC-MSCs cultured in growth medium. (C) Oil red O staining of the lipid droplet of cells cultured in adipogenic medium. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d2"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> differentiation into osteogenic cells</title><p>After osteogenic induction, most cells became proximity to each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g006">Fig. 6</xref> A, D). After 21days induction, alizarin red stained obvious calcium deposits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g006">Fig. 6</xref> B), whereas noninduced cells did not exhibit any calcium deposits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g006">Fig. 6</xref> C). ALP activity revealed blue-black stained in induced cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g006">Fig. 6</xref> E), whereas non induced cells did not exibit any ALP activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g006">Fig. 6</xref> F).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Differentiation of hUC-MSCs into osteoblasts <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</title><p>(A, D) Morphology of hUC-MSCs cultured in osteogenic medium for 21 days. (B, E) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> differentiation of hUC-MSCs into osteoblasts, were shown by positive alizarin red (B) and ALP staining (E) of calcified extracellular matrix. (C, F) Staining was not observed in control hUC-MSCs cultured in growth medium. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Transcription of NTN and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs after Recombinant Adenoviruses</title><p>After infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN and Ad-Lmx1α for 48 h, the RT-PCR results shown that NTN and Lmx1α were transcripted in the cells infected with adenoviruses, but they were not transcripted in the control hUC-MSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g007">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>The transcription of NTN and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs was analyzed by RT-PCR.</title><p>Lane 1, the PCR product of Lmx1α in Ad-Lmx1α infected hUC-MSCs. Lane 2, the PCR product of β-actin in Ad-Lmx1α infected hUC-MSCs. Lane 3, the product of NTN in Ad-NGFpreproNTN infected hUC-MSCs. Lane 4, the product of β-actin in Ad-NGFpreproNTN infected hUC-MSCs. Lane 5, the product of Lmx1α in control hUC-MSCs. Lane 6, the product of NTN in control hUC-MSCs. Lane 7, the product of β-actin in control hUC-MSCs, DNA marker DL,2000.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Identification of NTN and Lmx1α Protein Expression in hUC-MSCs and the Secretion of NTN</title><p>Immunofluorescence results showed that NTN and Lmx1α proteins were expressed at high level in infected hUC-MSCs: NTN was expressed in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g008">Fig. 8</xref> C), whereas Lmx1α was expressed in the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g008">Fig. 8</xref> A). These two proteins were not detected in control hUC-MSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g008">Fig. 8</xref> B, D).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>The expression of NTN and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs was analyzed by immunofluorescence.</title><p>(A) The expression of Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs infected with Ad-Lmx1α. (B) The expression of Lmx1α in control hUC-MSCs. (C) The expression of NTN in hUC-MSC infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN. (D) The expression of NTN in control hUC-MSCs. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g008.jpg"/></fig><p>From WB result we found that the band with a strong signal appearing in the membrane at approximately 12 kDa which characterized as NTN was observed in cytoplasm and culture medium (24 kDa was dimmer of mature NTN) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g009">Fig. 9</xref>). However, the expression of Lmx1α was only be detected in cytoplasm (36 kDa) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g010">Fig. 10</xref>). The expression of these two proteins was not detected in control group.</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Detection of the expression of NTN and secretion of NTN in conditioned medium by western blot.</title><p>Lane 1, was loaded with the cell lysis infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN. Lane 2, was loaded with the medium harvested from Ad-NGFpreproNTN infection. Lane 3, was loaded with the cell lysis from control hUC-MSCs. Lane 4, was loaded with the medium from control hUC-MSCs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g009.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064000-g010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Detction of the expression of Lmx1α by western blot.</title><p>Lane 1, was loaded with the cell lysis infected with Ad-Lmx1α. Lane 2, was loaded with the medium infected with Ad-Lmx1α. Lane 3, was loaded with the cell lysis from control hUC-MSCs. Lane 4, was loaded with the medium from control hUC-MSCs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g010.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>ELISA Detection of NTN Secretion</title><p>The student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test compared the means of OD<sub>450</sub> between the conditional medium and the control medium, there were significant difference between these two groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g011">Fig. 11</xref>).The expression of NTN at 48 h was higher than 24 h, 72 h and 96 h. These results indicated that NTN be secreted into the culture medium.</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption><title>Detection of NTN secretion in 24 h, 48 h, 72 h and 96 h of hUC-MSCs infected with Ad-NGFpreproNTN and control hUC-MSCs by ELISA (* p&lt;0.05).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g011.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3h"><title>Identification the Bioactivity of NTN</title><p>Isolated neuronal cells were strong light refraction and slender axons. These cells were co-cultured with B27 and conditional medium. Cells in the experimental group were treated with NTN-conditioned medium were alived after 21 days cultured, according to observations, these cells exhibited neuronal morphology and the survival rate was 80% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g012">Fig. 12</xref> B). In contrast, a large number of cells in the control group were shrunk, and there were few surviving cells with intact morphology after 21 days cultured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g012">Fig. 12</xref> A). Immunohistochemistry showed TH expressed in the treated group, suggesting that the surviving cells were dopaminergic neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g012">Fig. 12</xref> C).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g012" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g012</object-id><label>Figure 12</label><caption><title>The culture of neurons derived from embryonic 14.5 rat ventral mesencephalic progenitors test.</title><p>(A) The neurons cultured in neural basal (2% B27) alone. Neurons are most dead. (B, C) the neurons cultured in neural basal (2% B27) and NTN condition medium (1∶1). The result of TH immunohistochemistry reveals some neurons are alive and grow well. Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g012.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3i"><title>Identification of Inducing hUC-MSCs</title><sec id="s3i1"><title>Real-time PCR detected the neuron-specific genes</title><p>After 21 days induction, the transcriptional levels of TH, Msx-1, Nestin, MAP-2, Lmx1β, Foxα2, Pitx3, DAT, β-tubulin III, Nurrl and EN1 were significantly upregulated. The upregulation of TH suggested the cells had been induced to dopaminergic neurons. Nestin is a marker that is specifically expressed in neuronal precursor cells, and these results showed that the transcription of <italic toggle="yes">nestin</italic> was significantly reduced on the 21<sup>st</sup> day induction, suggested the induced cells were going to differentiate into mature neurons. It is also worth mentioned that the NSE transcription level was similar between cells before and after induction, suggesting that genes were expressed highly in uninduced cells. The statistical analysis (student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test) revealed significant difference in the transcriptional levels of 11 genes (TH, Msx-1, nestin, MAP-2, Lmx1β, Foxα2, Pitx3, DAT, β-tubulin III, Nurrl and EN1) between cells induced for 21 days and normal cells, and between cells induced for 21 days and cells induced for 7 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g013">Fig. 13</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g013" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g013</object-id><label>Figure 13</label><caption><title>The specific mRNA of induced hUC-MSCcs.</title><p>Transcription of neural-specific genes like TH, Msx-1, Nestin, MAP-2, Lmx1β, Foxα2, Pitx3, DAT, β-tubulin III, Nurrl, EN1 and NES was analyzed by real-time PCR. All samples were normalized with β-actin (* p&lt;0.05 compared with non-induecd cells; # p&lt;0.05 compared with cells induced for 7 days).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g013.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3i2"><title>Immunofluorescence detection of neuron-specific protein expression</title><p>After seven days induction, immunofluorescence was able to detect expression of the neuronal precursor cell-specific protein nestin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g014">Fig. 14</xref> F) but not the expression of proteins specific for mature neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g014">Fig. 14</xref> G, H, I, J). After 21 days of induction, the immunofluorescence results revealed the expression of proteins specific for mature neurons, including NSE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> F), MAP-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> H), β-tubulinIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> G) and the dopaminergic neuron-specific antigen TH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> J), whereas the nestin expression level was significantly decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> I). The expression of these mature proteins was not detected in the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g015">Fig. 15</xref> A, B, C, D; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g014">Fig. 14</xref> A, B, C, D, E).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g014" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g014</object-id><label>Figure 14</label><caption><title>The expression of neural-specific marker containing TH, β-tubulinIII, MAP-2, NSE, Nestin and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs induced 7 days was analyzed by immunofluorescence.</title><p>Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g014.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064000-g015" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g015</object-id><label>Figure 15</label><caption><title>The expression of neural-specific marker containing TH, β-tubulinIII, MAP-2, NSE, Nestin and Lmx1α in hUC-MSCs induced 21 days was analyzed by immunofluorescence.</title><p>Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g015.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3j"><title>Effect of Induced hUC-MSCs in Parkinsonian Rhesus Monkeys</title><sec id="s3j1"><title>Behavioral evaluation</title><p>We found that all monkeys who were lesioned by MPTP displayed acute symptoms with reduced motor movements and facial expressions. After the administration of therapeutic cells, instant behavior restorations were observed in cell therapy group. One weeks after therapy, the monkeys injected with cells not only made more vigorous movements, but also show good balance ability and had no handicap in the motor movements in this entire experiment cours. However, the monkeys in the control group displayed no significant behaviors recovery expressed as reduced movement, loss of facial expression and holding the cage for balance.</p><p>One week after surgery, behavior changes were evaluated by the UPDRS. The evaluation was conducted three times a week and last for six months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g016">Fig. 16</xref> A). Significant difference was observed in behavior rating scores between cell therapy group and HBSS control group. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g016">Fig. 16</xref> B).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g016" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g016</object-id><label>Figure 16</label><caption><title>Establishiment and behavioral assessment of experimental animals.</title><p>(A) Evaluation of the behavior restoration of the normal group, HBSS group and cell transplanted therapy group (n = 3). (B) Comparison of the behavior recovery rating score between the HBSS group and cell therapy group. (n = 3, * p&lt;0.05 compared with cell therapy group; # p&lt;0.05 compared with cell therapy group).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g016.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3j2"><title>Effect of Apomorphine-induced rotation</title><p>Apomorphine was injected from the fourth week after the model was established, and the results were shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g017">Fig. 17</xref> A. The rotation rate of the experimental animals in the cell transplantation group was reduced to 16 turns/min in the fourth week, whereas that of the HBSS group was increased to 34 turns/min. Following five months therapy, the cell therapy group animals could control their rotation behavior and stop rotation in 10 min. The final rotation rate in cell therapy group was 5 turns/min. In HBSS group, the animals could not control their rotaion behavior and the final rating was 40 turns/min. There was significant difference in rotation rating scores between cell therapy group and HBSS group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g017">Fig. 17</xref> B).</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g017" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g017</object-id><label>Figure 17</label><caption><title>Establishiment and behavioral assessment of experimental animals.</title><p>(A) The apomorphine-induced revolution of the experimental animals in the therapy group and HBSS group. (B) Statistical illustration of the cycle per minute the monkeys revolved, induced by apomporphine (n = 3, * p&lt;0.05 compared with cell therapy group; # p&lt;0.05 compared with cell therapy group).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g017.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3j3"><title>Histological assessment</title><p>In HBSS group, TH positive neurons in the lesioned substantia nigra side were more or less lost (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g018">Fig. 18</xref> A). However, there were many TH positive cells in the left side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g018">Fig. 18</xref> B). Moreover, we have examined histopathological section of substantia nigra by HE staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g019">Fig. 19</xref> A, B), the results were the same as TH immunohistochemical. However, the cell therapy group has a greater color reactive area and intensity compared to HBSS group, which indicated that the neuroprotection effect from NTN delivered by Ad-NTN has protected the DA neurons which were lesioned by MPTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g018">Fig. 18</xref> C, D). The HE staining results were also showed in the right substantia nigra have a small number of neurons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g019">Fig. 19</xref> C) but were fewer than the left side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064000-g019">Fig. 19</xref> D). The surviving neurons on the right side show normal morphology and only a few showed pyknosis.</p><fig id="pone-0064000-g018" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g018</object-id><label>Figure 18</label><caption><title>Immunohistochemistry of the TH-positive cells in the substantia nigra of the monkeys in two groups.</title><p>Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g018.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064000-g019" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g019</object-id><label>Figure 19</label><caption><title>Hematoxylin and eosin (HE) staining of the substantia nigra of the monkeys in two groups.</title><p>Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g019.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064000-g020" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064000.g020</object-id><label>Figure 20</label><caption><title>Immunohistochemistry of the BrdU-ir cells in the substantia nigra of the monkeys in two groups.</title><p>Scale bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0064000.g020.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>It has been reported that the human umbilical cord contained abundant of MSCs <xref rid="pone.0064000-Sarugaser1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Kestendjieva1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Wang2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Covas1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Different culture methods were used to guide cells to express neuronal phenotypes <xref rid="pone.0064000-Fu1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, endothelial phenotypes of myocardial cells markers <xref rid="pone.0064000-Rao1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Kadivar1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>.The facts explained that these cells have multi-differentiation potential. The current methods used for the isolation of hUC-MSCs mainly include the enzyme digestion and the tissue explant adherent. The enzyme digestion has the advantage of rapid isolation, but the enzyme system may degrade the outer leaflet of the cell membrane, and damage cells if improper control of time. So we utilized the tissue explant adherent method to isolate hUC-MSCs. The hUC-MSCs obtained in this study showed similar to previous reports: including cell morphology, immunophenotype, cell proliferative and differentiation potential.</p><p>Studies have suggested that stem cells could be induced and played a role as engineered cells to release neurotrophic factors, providing neuronal protection and promote self-healing <xref rid="pone.0064000-Kitayama1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0064000-Shan1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Cells therapy is undoubtedly the most promsing therapeutic approach for PD. The aim of this study was to replace lost neurons and restore the net work of striatal dopaminergic nerve terminals in PD. So we focused on inducing the hUC-MSCs into dopaminergic neurons. After inducing, Real-time PCR results showed that the transcriptional level of the Msx1 gene was upregulated after inducing. The Msx1 and Lmx1α genes were played important roles in the midbrain dopaminergic neurons during embryonic development, the upregulation of Msx1 expression resulted in a transcriptional cascade, leading to the induced cells into mature dopaminergic neurons expressing Pitx3 and TH. In the present studies, NTN secreted by hUC-MSCs was abled to enhance dopaminergic neurons survival and play a nutritive role in sensory neurons. In other words, NTN was abled to prevent the deterioration of induced neurons derived from hUC-MSCs.</p><p>Lmx1α is presumed to be the first expressed intrinsic dopaminergic determinant. We hypothesized the expression of endogenous transcription factors (upregulation of Lmx1α and NTN genes) could activate the SHH/Lmx1α pathways involved in neuronal development. It has also been reported that transplated cells to substantia nigra and striatum together can enhance recovery in PD model <xref rid="pone.0064000-Bjorklund1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. So we choose to transplant induced cells into the substantia nigra, the caudate nucleus and putamen to alleviate the symptoms of PD.</p><p>The animal experiment results indicated that the obvious behavioral recovery was not observed in HBSS control group. The symptoms of control monkeys get worsen. The symptoms in cell therapy animals were gradually alleviated. TH immunohistochemistry results also demonstrated that there were surviving neurons in the lesioned side substantia nigra of the cell therapy group and there were no significant difference between the caudate nucleus and the putamen. These results were the same as PD clinically pathological changes. In this study, the grafted cells which were labeled with BrdU were detected in the right side of substantia nigra. These results were also indicated that the transplanted cells were survival; on the one hand, transplanted neural-like cells are capable of replacing lost neurons and restoring the lost net work of striatal dopaminergic nerve terminals in PD. On the other hand, transplanted neural-like cells are capable of promoting the differentiation potential and providing trophic effects on endogenous neural stem cells probably through their continuous NTN and nutritional factors secretion. The furtuer secretion of NTN by induced DA neurons could provide neurons nutritional protection on the cells differentiated by induced cells and neural stem cells and form a virtuous circle.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we induced hUC-MSCs into neuron-like cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> that are able to secret dopamine. In addition, we transplanted those cells into the brains of PD monkeys. These neuron-like cells could perform the physiological functions of dopaminergic neurons and may play a therapeutic role to ameliorate the symptoms of PD. We believe the results from this study would provide the basis for developing novel cell therapy for PD in future.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Huaisheng Shi and Jinyuan Wu for assistance with image capture during the expriments.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0064000-Vernier1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vernier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Callier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snapyan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wersinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The degeneration of dopamine neurons in Parkinson’s disease: insights from embryology and evolution of the mesostriatocortical system</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>1035</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1196/annals.1332.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Prakash1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wurst</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Development of dopaminergic neurons in the mammalian brain</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16389456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-005-5387-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11136411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Prakash2"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wurst</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genetic networks controlling the development of midbrain dopaminergic neurons</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<volume>575</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1113/jphysiol.2006.113464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1819467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Morris1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>A review of some aspects of the pharmacology of levodopa</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Neurol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">386308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Stromberg1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stromberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bygdeman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seiger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Human fetal substantia nigra grafted to the dopamine-denervated striatum of immunosuppressed rats: evidence for functional reinnervation</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2879264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0304-3940(86)90632-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Schulz1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noggle</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmarini</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiler</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Differentiation of human embryonic stem cells to dopaminergic neurons in serum-free suspension culture</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1218</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2004-0114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Ostenfeld1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ostenfeld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prowse</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linskens</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jauniaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Human neural precursor cells express low levels of telomerase in vitro and show diminishing cell proliferation with extensive axonal outgrowth following transplantation</article-title>. <source>Exp Neurol</source>
<volume>164</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10877932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/exnr.2000.7427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Doi1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morizane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onoe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prolonged maturation culture favors a reduction in the tumorigenicity and the dopaminergic function of human ESC-derived neural cells in a primate model of Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/stem.1060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Hall1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Embryonic stem cells and Parkinson’s disease: cell transplantation to cell therapy</article-title>. <source>Ann Acad Med Singapore</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18392292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-daSilvaMeirelles1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva Meirelles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chagastelles</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells reside in virtually all post-natal organs and tissues</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source>
<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>2204</fpage>–<lpage>2213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16684817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.02932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Shih1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of neurogenic mesenchymal stem cells in human scalp tissue</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1012</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15941858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2004-0125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Zuk1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zuk</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashjian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Ugarte</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Human adipose tissue is a source of multipotent stem cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>4279</fpage>–<lpage>4295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12475952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1091/mbc.E02-02-0105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC138633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Sarugaser1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sarugaser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lickorish</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baksh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Human umbilical cord perivascular (HUCPV) cells: a source of mesenchymal progenitors</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2004-0166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Karahuseyinoglu1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karahuseyinoglu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cinar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akay</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Biology of stem cells in human umbilical cord stroma: in situ and in vitro surveys</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2006-0286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Datta1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pulikkot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Neuronal plasticity of human Wharton’s jelly mesenchymal stromal cells to the dopaminergic cell type compared with human bone marrow mesenchymal stromal cells</article-title>. <source>Cytotherapy</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>918</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/14653249.2011.579957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Fu1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Conversion of human umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells in Wharton’s jelly to dopaminergic neurons in vitro: potential therapeutic application for Parkinsonism</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2005-0053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Weiss1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medicetty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bledsoe</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rachakatla</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Human umbilical cord matrix stem cells: preliminary characterization and effect of transplantation in a rodent model of Parkinson’s disease</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16223852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2005-0330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Cai1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>German</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enikolopov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The role of Lmx1a in the differentiation of human embryonic stem cells into midbrain dopamine neurons in culture and after transplantation into a Parkinson’s disease model</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18832589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2008-0734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Friling1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Friling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebsgaard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Efficient production of mesencephalic dopamine neurons by Lmx1a expression in embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>7613</fpage>–<lpage>7618</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0902396106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2671325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Andersson1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tryggvason</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alekseenko</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Identification of intrinsic determinants of midbrain dopamine neurons</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>124</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2005.10.037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Barzilay1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barzilay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Zur</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bulvik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melamed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Offen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Lentiviral delivery of LMX1a enhances dopaminergic phenotype in differentiated human bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells Dev</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19298173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/scd.2008.0138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Kotzbauer1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kotzbauer</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lampe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heuckeroth</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Creedon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Neurturin, a relative of glial-cell-line-derived neurotrophic factor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>384</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8945474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/384467a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Kordower1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Kordower JH, Herzog CD, Dass B, Bakay RA, Stansell J 3rd, et al</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Delivery of neurturin by AAV2 (CERE-120)-mediated gene transfer provides structural and functional neuroprotection and neurorestoration in MPTP-treated monkeys</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source>
<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17192932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ana.21032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Gorska1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gorska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Principles in laboratory animal research for experimental purposes</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Monit</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11208307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Wang1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The delivery of tyrosine hydroxylase accelerates the neurorestoration of Macaca Rhesus model of Parkinson’s disease provided by Neurturin</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
<volume>524</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22766137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neulet.2012.06.063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Kestendjieva1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kestendjieva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kyurkchiev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsvetkova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehandjiev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Characterization of mesenchymal stem cells isolated from the human umbilical cord</article-title>. <source>Cell Biol Int</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>724</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18396423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cellbi.2008.02.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Wang2"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells in the Wharton’s jelly of the human umbilical cord</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1330</fpage>–<lpage>1337</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2004-0013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Covas1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Covas</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siufi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orellana</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Isolation and culture of umbilical vein mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>. <source>Braz J Med Biol Res</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1179</fpage>–<lpage>1183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/s0100-879x2003000900006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Rao1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Stem cells and aging: expanding the possibilities</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11322994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0047-6374(01)00224-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Kadivar1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kadivar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khatami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortazavi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shokrgozar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taghikhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>In vitro cardiomyogenic potential of human umbilical vein-derived mesenchymal stem cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>340</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16378596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.12.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Kitayama1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kitayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onitsuka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Assessing an eating disorder induced by 6-OHDA and the possibility of nerve regeneration therapy by transplantation of neural progenitor cells in rats</article-title>. <source>Nihon Shinkei Seishin Yakurigaku Zasshi</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17633522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Shan1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Enhanced de novo neurogenesis and dopaminergic neurogenesis in the substantia nigra of 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine-induced Parkinson’s disease-like mice</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1280</fpage>–<lpage>1287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1634/stemcells.2005-0487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1840319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0064000-Bjorklund1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindvall</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cell replacement therapies for central nervous system disorders</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10816308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/75705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>