
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">582</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0372763</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3526052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3526052.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3526052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3526052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22966070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db11-1388</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1388</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Obesity Studies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tub Has a Key Role in Insulin and Leptin Signaling and Action In Vivo in Hypothalamic Nuclei</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names initials="PO">Patrícia O.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quaresma</surname><given-names initials="PGF">Paula G.F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caricilli</surname><given-names initials="AM">Andrea M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names initials="AC">Andressa C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guadagnini</surname><given-names initials="D">Dioze</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morari</surname><given-names initials="J">Joseane</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names initials="L">Laís</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ropelle</surname><given-names initials="ER">Eduardo R.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheira</surname><given-names initials="JBC">José Barreto C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velloso</surname><given-names initials="LA">Lício A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names initials="MJA">Mario J.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Internal Medicine, State University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Mario J.A. Saad, <email>msaad@fcm.unicamp.br</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">217438</issue-id><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-12 13:25:15.480"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="137.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="137.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Diabetes" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5082414"><article-title>Expression of Concern. Tub Has a Key Role in Insulin and Leptin Signaling
and Action In Vivo in Hypothalamic Nuclei. Diabetes 2013;62:137–148. DOI:
<related-article ext-link-type="doi" related-article-type="object-of-concern" xlink:href="10.2337/db11-1388">10.2337/db11-1388</related-article></article-title><volume>65</volume><issue>4</issue><date><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage><source>Diabetes</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5082414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208021</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Diabetes" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6905472"><article-title>Statement of Retraction. Tub Has a Key Role in Insulin and Leptin Signaling and Action In Vivo in Hypothalamic Nuclei. Diabetes 2013;62:<related-article ext-link-type="doi" page="137" related-article-type="retracted-article" vol="62" xlink:href="10.2337/db11-1388">137–148</related-article>. DOI: 10.2337/db11-1388</article-title><volume>66</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><source>Diabetes</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6905472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28188142</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Mutation of <italic toggle="yes">tub</italic> gene in mice induces obesity, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">tub</italic> could be an important regulator of energy balance. In the current study, we investigated whether insulin, leptin, and obesity can modulate Tub in vivo in hypothalamic nuclei, and we investigated possible consequences on energy balance, neuropeptide expression, and hepatic glucose metabolism. Food intake, metabolic characteristics, signaling proteins, and neuropeptide expression were measured in response to fasting and refeeding, intracerebroventricular insulin and leptin, and Tub antisense oligonucleotide (ASO). Tub tyrosine phosphorylation (Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr) is modulated by nutritional status. Tub is a substrate of insulin receptor tyrosine kinase (IRTK) and leptin receptor (LEPR)–Janus kinase 2 (JAK2) in hypothalamic nuclei. After leptin or insulin stimulation, Tub translocates to the nucleus. Inhibition of Tub expression in hypothalamus by ASO increased food intake, fasting blood glucose, and hepatic glucose output, decreased O<sub>2</sub> consumption, and blunted the effect of insulin or leptin on proopiomelanocortin, thyroid-releasing hormone, melanin-concentrating hormone, and orexin expression. In hypothalamus of mice administered a high-fat diet, there is a reduction in leptin and insulin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr and nuclear translocation, which is reversed by reducing protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B expression. These results indicate that Tub has a key role in the control of insulin and leptin effects on food intake, and the modulation of Tub may contribute to insulin and leptin resistance in DIO mice.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Leptin and insulin signal adiposity to the hypothalamus and inhibit feeding, in part by reducing the expression of orexigenic neuropeptides and increasing the expression of anorexigenic neuropeptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). However, the network of signaling proteins induced by these hormones is not completely understood.</p><p>The protein Tub is primarily expressed in the central nervous system and has been implicated in energy balance homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). Mice with a spontaneous mutation of the <italic toggle="yes">tub</italic> gene were called “tubby” mice and had development of late-onset obesity, insulin resistance, and sensory impairments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p><p>Inactivation of the <italic toggle="yes">tub</italic> gene by gene targeting is sufficient to induce the same phenotype as tubby mice; this suggests that the loss of Tub protein function is responsible for the tubby mice phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Functions of Tub protein have been evaluated in only a few studies. Boggon et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>) suggested that the highly conserved COOH-terminal portion of the protein is a DNA-binding structure and that the NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal portion may be a regulator of transcription. They observed that on serotonin activation of 5-HT2c receptors, there was a translocation of Tub protein from the plasma membrane to the cellular nucleus of primary cultured neurons, suggesting that Tub may function as a transcription factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>).</p><p>In addition to being a transcription factor, in vitro studies suggested that Tub might act as an adaptor protein downstream of the insulin receptor-signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Moreover, it was also demonstrated that insulin induced Tub tyrosine phosphorylation in 3T3-L1 adipocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Together, these studies suggest that Tub is a substrate of the insulin receptor, at least in vitro. However, the role of Tub in insulin action and signaling in vivo has not yet been clarified.</p><p>In the hypothalamus, neuron populations of the arcuate nucleus (Arc), ventromedial hypothalamus, paraventricular nucleus (PVN), and lateral hypothalamus (LH) are responsive to insulin and leptin. Insulin acts through the insulin receptor (IR), which is a protein with endogenous tyrosine kinase activity, and in the hypothalamus insulin signals through IRS/PI3k/Akt/Foxo1 to control food intake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p><p>Leptin signals through the recruitment of the JAK2 to the leptin receptor (LEPR), where it phosphorylates several tyrosine residues on the LEPR. Signal transducer and activator of transcription (STAT) 3 proteins bind to the phosphorylated LEPR and are phosphorylated by JAK2. Phosphorylated STAT3 is translocated to the nucleus, where it is thought to bind to specific DNA sequences to regulate neuropeptide expression. Both leptin and insulin change the membrane potential of target neurons to control their firing rate, as well as neuropeptide and neurotransmitter release. In parallel, leptin and insulin signaling directly control transcription of neuropeptides in multiple hypothalamic nuclei. In the Arc, leptin and insulin increase the transcription of proopiomelanocortin (POMC), which is an anorexigenic neuropeptide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>) and inhibit transcription of agouti-related peptide (AgRP) and neuropeptide Y (NPY), which are orexigenic neuropeptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). In the PVN, insulin and leptin induce an increase in thyroid-releasing hormone (TRH) expression, which is a positive regulator of energy expenditure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). In the ventromedial hypothalamus, steroidogenic factor 1--expressing neurons respond to insulin and leptin to regulate food intake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>) and, in the LH, both hormones decrease the release of melanin-concentrating hormone (MCH) and orexin neuropeptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p>However, it has not yet been investigated whether, in the hypothalamus, insulin and leptin can modulate Tub phosphorylation and nuclear translocation, or whether this control might influence the expression of neuropeptides in physiologic conditions and also in obesity. In the current study, we investigated whether insulin, leptin, and obesity can modulate Tub in vivo in hypothalamic nuclei, and we investigated possible consequences on energy balance, neuropeptide expression, and hepatic glucose metabolism.</p><sec id="s1"><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>All experiments were approved by the Ethics Committee of the State University of Campinas. Eight-week-old male C57BL/6 mice obtained from the University of Campinas, São Paulo, Brazil, were assigned to receive a standard rodent chow or a high-fat diet (HFD) as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and water ad libitum. For fasting and refeeding experiments, fasted (24 h) mice were allowed to refeed for 1 h or 2 h, and hypothalamic nuclei were dissected for protein studies, as described. All feeding tests were conducted between 8:00 <sc>a.m.</sc> and 10:00 <sc>a.m.</sc></p><sec id="s2"><title>Intracerebroventricular cannulation.</title><p>Anesthetized mice were stereotaxically instrumented (Ultra Precise model 963; Kopf) to implant stainless steel cannulas (26-gauge; Plastics One) in the right lateral ventricle. The coordinates used from the bregma were: anterior/posterior, −0.5 mm; lateral, −1.3 mm; and dorso/ventral, −2.2 mm. Mice were single-housed after surgery and were allowed to recover for 5–7 days. The correct implantation of cannulas was checked by 10 ng angiotensin II intracerebroventricular (ICV) injection, which elicits an intake of water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). Animals that did not reach this criterion were excluded from the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Hypothalamic nuclei dissection.</title><p>Arc, medial hypothalamus (MH; ventromedial and dorsomedial), PVN, and LH were quickly dissected in a stainless steel matrix with razor blades as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>) and frozen in liquid nitrogen for further protein studies.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ICV injections.</title><p>To determine if insulin or leptin induces Tub tyrosine phosphorylation in vivo, overnight fasted mice fed chow or HFD received an ICV injection of insulin (human recombinant insulin; Eli Lilly, Indianapolis, IN) or recombinant leptin (Calbiochem, San Diego, CA), and hypothalamic nuclei were quickly dissected and frozen in liquid nitrogen for further protein studies. The time and dose responses to ICV insulin or leptin on Tub tyrosine phosphorylation were also investigated. To inhibit Tub (5′AGG AAC ACC TTC TTG CCA T 3′) or protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B (PTP1B) (5′CCC AGC AGC GGC TTC TGC AT 3′) expression in the hypothalamus, we developed antisense oligonucleotide (ASO) and administered them by ICV injections in mice fed chow or fed HFD, respectively. Both ICV ASO treatments were administered twice per day (8:00 <sc>a.m.</sc> and 5:00 <sc>p.m.</sc>) for 5 days. Body weight, epididymal fat mass, cumulative food intake, 4-h to 8-h food intake in response to ICV insulin and leptin, fasting blood glucose and blood glucose levels in response to pyruvate (pyruvate test) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>), and PEPCK expression in fasting livers were measured in Tub ASO-treated mice. We also determined O<sub>2</sub> consumption and respiratory exchange rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Akt, FoxO1, JAK2, and STAT3 phosphorylation in response to ICV insulin or leptin, respectively, were evaluated as described.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting.</title><p>A pool of five to eight of each nucleus (Arc, MH, PVN, LH) was homogenized in extraction buffer. Immunoprecipitation (IP) and immunoblotting were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37"><bold>37</bold></xref><bold>–</bold><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39"><bold>39</bold></xref>) using the following antibodies: antiphosphotyrosine, anti-IRβ (α-IR), anti-Tub (M-19), anti-β actin, anti-JAK2, anti-Akt, anti-STAT3, anti-FoxO1, anti-PTP1B, and anti-PEPCK (H-300) antibodies from Santa Cruz Technology (Santa Cruz, CA); and antipAkt Ser473, antipSTAT3, antipJAK2, and antipFoxO1 antibodies from Cell Signaling.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><bold>Coimmunoprecipitation and tyrosine kinase assay using Tub as a substrate</bold>.</title><p>The protocol described was adapted for ICV injections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). Briefly, a low dose of insulin (0.2 μg) or leptin (0.1 ng) was injected into the lateral ventricle to trigger IR and JAK2 autophosphorylation. After 7–10 min, Arc, MH, PVN, and LH were dissected and homogenized in extraction buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) for IR or JAK2 IP. In another group of animals, Arc, MH, PVN, and LH were dissected without insulin or leptin stimulation and samples underwent IP with anti-Tub antibody. Samples were collected on protein A-Sepharose and combined as followed: IP IR plus IP Tub and IP JAK2 plus IP Tub. Then, the kinase activity was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><bold>Translocation of Tub from plasma membrane to the nucleus in hypothalamic nuclei</bold>.</title><p>Fasted animals received an ICV injection of insulin or leptin or acetylcholine (Ach) (100 µmol/L; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). The specific phospholipase Cβ (PLCβ) inhibitor U73122 (1 μmol/L; Sigma-Aldrich) was previously injected to block Tub nuclear translocation induced by the hormones. The <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U73343">U73343</ext-link> (1 μmol/L; Sigma-Aldrich), which weakly inhibits PLCβ, was injected as a negative control. Hypothalamic nuclei or whole hypothalamus were quickly dissected and frozen in liquid nitrogen for further processing. A pool of 20 hypothalamic nuclei or a pool of four hypothalami were used for plasma membrane and nucleus separation as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). The procedure was performed at 4°C. Plasma membrane and nucleus fractions were analyzed by IP and immunoblotting with anti-Tub (M-19) antibody.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>RNA extraction and real-time PCR.</title><p>Random fed or fasted (24 h) mice treated for 5 days with Tub ASO or sense received ICV insulin or leptin injection, and the hypothalami or hypothalamic nuclei were harvested after 6 h, quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at −80°C for processing. Total RNA was obtained using RNeasy Mini Kit (Cat. 74106; Qiagen). Real-time PCR was performed using TaqMan RT-PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) in an Mx3000P thermocycler (Stratagene). The Mx3000P software was used to calculate the cycle threshold for each reaction. Relative expression levels were determined using the comparative cycle threshold method with normalization of target gene expression levels to <italic toggle="yes">18s</italic>. Primers and probes were purchased from Applied Biosystems and were described as TRH, Mm01182425_g1; NPY, Mm00445771_m1; AgRP, Mm00475829_g1; POMC, Mm00435874_m1; MCH, Mm01242886_g1; and Ore, Mm01964031_s1 for mouse. The polymerase chain reaction conditions were 2 min at 50°C, 10 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles at 95°C for 15 s and 60°C for 60 s. Real-time data were analyzed using the engine provided by Applied Biosystems.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Protein tyrosine phosphatase activity assay in immunoprecipitated Tub.</title><p>Protein tyrosine phosphatase (PTPase) activity was measured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>Results are expressed as means ± SD. Significance was determined using two-tailed Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test or one-way or two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttest, as appropriate, and differences were considered significant if <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05. We used GraphPad Prism (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s11"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s12"><title>Tub protein is expressed in hypothalamic nuclei and is regulated by fasting and refeeding.</title><p>Previous studies have shown that Tub is expressed in the central nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Here, we confirmed that Tub was expressed in multiple hypothalamic nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 1.</label><caption><p>Expression of Tub, effect of nutritional states, and effect of insulin and leptin on Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in hypothalamic nuclei. <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>: Representative blots of Tub protein expression in hypothalamic nuclei, including Arc, MH, PVN, LH, white adipose tissue (WAT), and liver. <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>: Effect of fasting (24 h) and refeeding on Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in hypothalamic nuclei. Mice were killed at 10 min (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) or at 7 min (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) after hormone injections to determine the dose-response of ICV insulin or leptin on Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr. The different doses of insulin were: 0, 0.02, 0.2, and 2.0 μg; the different doses of leptin were: 0, 0.1, 1.0, 10, and 100 ng. To determine the time-course of Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in response to insulin (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) or leptin (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>), we used 2-µg (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) and 10-ng (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) doses, and mice were killed at different time points: 5, 10, and 15 min for insulin or 2, 5, 7, 10, 15, and 20 min for leptin. <italic toggle="yes">G</italic>: Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr is increased in response to ICV insulin (2 µg) or leptin (10 ng) in hypothalamic nuclei. Data are presented as means ± SD from 8 mice per nucleus or whole hypothalamus from 8 to 10 mice. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttest was used. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. other groups, †<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. fast. α-PY, antiphosphotyrosine; ICV, ICV injection; IB, immunoblotting.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>The Tub protein abundance was not different in hypothalamic nuclei after fasting and refeeding states. However, Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr was strongly induced after 1 h of refeeding, followed by a decrease after 2 h of refeeding in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH in control mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Insulin and leptin induce Tub tyrosine phosphorylation in hypothalamic nuclei in a time-dependent and dose-dependent manner.</title><p>Insulin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr was dose-dependent. The presence of phosphorylated Tub was detectable after ICV injection of as little as 0.02 μg insulin, half-maximal stimulation occurred with 0.2 μg of the hormone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>), and maximal stimulation was observed with 2.0 μg insulin (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3). Insulin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr occurred after 5 min of ICV insulin injection, and the maximal phosphorylation was observed at 10 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></xref>). The presence of phosphorylated Tub was detectable after ICV leptin injection of as little as 0.1 ng leptin, and the maximal stimulation was observed with 10.0 ng leptin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">E</italic></xref>). Leptin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr occurred after 2 min of ICV leptin injection, and the maximal phosphorylation was observed at 7 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">F</italic></xref>).</p><p>Next, we compared the maximal effect of insulin and leptin in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH hypothalamic nuclei, and the results showed that in all these nuclei insulin or leptin induced similar increases in Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Tyrosine kinase assay of IR and JAK2 using Tub as a substrate.</title><p>The IR kinase activity was increased significantly in Arc lysates after ICV insulin in vivo and there was a further increase after ATP addition in vitro in mice fed chow. Most importantly, Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr was increased in Arc of mice injected with a low dose of insulin, with a further increase after ATP addition in vitro, demonstrating enhanced IR kinase activity with Tub. These results were also demonstrated in MH, PVN, and LH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 2.</label><caption><p>Tyrosine kinase assay of IR and JAK2 using Tub as a substrate. <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>: 0.2 μg insulin or (B) 0.1 ng leptin was injected into lateral ventricle to increase IR or LEPR-associated JAK2 phosphorylation, respectively. Hypothalamic nuclei were dissected, and IP was performed with anti-IR antibody for insulin-stimulated mice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7) or anti-JAK2 antibody for leptin-stimulated mice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5). In another group of animals (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7), hypothalamic nuclei were dissected without insulin or leptin stimulation, and samples underwent IP with anti-Tub antibody. After combining IP samples (IR with Tub) for insulin-stimulated mice or (JAK2 with Tub) for leptin-stimulated mice, they were incubated with ATP and blotted with antiphosphotyrosine (α-PY). Representative blots show insulin-induced IR and Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr--induced and leptin-induced JAK2 and Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH of mice fed chow. ICV, ICV injection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig2.jpg"/></fig><p>Similarly to insulin, JAK2 kinase activity was increased significantly in Arc lysates in response to leptin injection, as demonstrated by an increase in JAK2 autophosphorylation. The addition of Tub to the reaction also demonstrated that after leptin injection, Tub was a substrate of JAK2 tyrosine kinase in this nucleus. These results were also demonstrated in MH, PVN, and LH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). We reprobed the membranes and confirmed that the bands blotted with antiphosphotyrosine antibody were IR, JAK2, and Tub (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>ICV insulin or leptin stimulation induces the nuclear translocation of Tub in hypothalamic nuclei.</title><p>Previous studies suggest that Tub acts as a transcription factor that can translocate from the plasma membrane to the nucleus after G-protein activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). Here, we observed that ICV insulin induced the nuclear translocation of Tub after 15 min in Arc, MH, and LH, and this translocation was maximal after 30 min in these nuclei. In PVN, insulin-induced Tub translocation was delayed compared with other nuclei and was evident at 90 min after the hormone injection. Leptin also was able to induce Tub nuclear translocation in Arc, MH, LH, and in PVN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></xref>). In Arc, MH, and LH, leptin-induced Tub nuclear translocation was observed at 7 min, but in PVN the maximal translocation was observed 20 min after leptin. We blotted 30 μg of protein from the plasma membrane and nucleus with anti-IR and anti-TATA-box antibodies, respectively, as controls for these preparations (data not shown).</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 3.</label><caption><p>Tub nuclear translocation in response to hormones in hypothalamic nuclei. A pool of 20 mice was used for each time point (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). Arc, MH, PVN, and LH were dissected from the same mice, and the plasma membrane and nucleus fractions were obtained from the same samples. <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>: Whole hypothalami of 14 mice were used. Plasma membranes and nuclear lysates underwent IP and were blotted (IB) with anti-Tub antibody. Tub nuclear translocation in response to ICV (2 μg) insulin (0, 15, 30, 90 min) or (10 ng) leptin (0, 7, 20 min) was investigated in Arc (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>), MH (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), PVN (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>), and LH (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) of mice on chow. Tub nuclear translocation in response to ICV (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) 100 μmol/L acetylcholine (Ach) (0, 30, 120 min), (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) 1 μmol/L specific PLCβ inhibitor (U73122) plus Ach (0, 10, 30, 120 min), (<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>) 1 μmol/L unspecific PLCβ inhibitor (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U73343">U73343</ext-link>) plus Ach (0, 10, 30, 120 min), U73122 plus insulin (0, 30, 120 min) (<italic toggle="yes">H</italic>), and U73122 plus leptin (0, 120 min) (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>) were investigated in the hypothalamus of mice fed chow diet. U73122 and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U73343">U73343</ext-link> inhibitors were administered 30 min before hormone injections. ICV, ICV injection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig3.jpg"/></fig><p>Previous data showed that Ach stimulates translocation of Tub in Neuro-2A cells, and this involves PLCβ, which is blocked by a specific PLCβ inhibitor (U73122). We investigated whether Ach is able to induce Tub translocation in vivo in the hypothalamus of mice fed chow. We injected Ach (100 µmol/L) alone or U73122 before Ach ICV injection, or <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U73343">U73343</ext-link>, which weakly inhibits PLCβ, as a negative control. We observed that Ach induced Tub nuclear translocation, an effect that was blocked by U73122, but not by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="U73343">U73343</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). To investigate whether insulin- or leptin-induced Tub translocation also involved PLCβ, we injected insulin or leptin in mice previously treated with ICV U73122. The results showed that U73122 blocked insulin-induced and leptin-induced Tub translocation in vivo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">H</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic></xref>). It is interesting that ICV Ach altered TRH expression in the hypothalamus. Further, insulin or leptin induced an increase in POMC and TRH and a reduction in orexin or MCH expression, respectively. The ICV U73122 injection before Ach or insulin or leptin blunted these effects on neuropeptides (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db11-1388/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Metabolic characteristics of mice treated with Tub ASO.</title><p>Control mice treated for 5 days with Tub ASO had a decrease of 80–90% in Tub expression in the hypothalamus compared with sense-treated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>). Mice treated with ASO had higher body weight and epididymal fat mass associated with an increase in food ingestion compared with sense-treated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></xref>). Additionally, there was a decrease in O<sub>2</sub> consumption without changes in the respiratory exchange rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">E</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">F</italic></xref>). There was also an increase in fasting blood glucose levels in ASO-treated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). Furthermore, we observed higher blood glucose levels after pyruvate intraperitoneal injection at 15 and 30 min and enhanced PEPCK expression in fasting livers of mice treated with ASO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">H</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic></xref>). These differences persisted in pair-fed mice (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db11-1388/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></ext-link>).</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 4.</label><caption><p>Metabolic characteristics of mice treated with Tub ASO<italic toggle="yes">.</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>: ICV injection of Tub ASO for 5 days decreases 80–90% of Tub expression in the hypothalamus compared with sense controls. Body weight (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), epididymal fat mass (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>), and cumulative food intake (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) are enhanced in Tub ASO-treated mice. O<sub>2</sub> consumption (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) is decreased in Tub ASO-treated mice without change in respiratory exchange rate (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) (RER). Fasting blood glucose (<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>), blood glucose after a pyruvate load (<italic toggle="yes">H</italic>), and PEPCK protein expression (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>) are enhanced in mice treated with Tub ASO. For pyruvate tolerance test, we injected 2 g/kg sodium pyruvate (intraperitoneal) in fasted mice, and blood glucose levels were measured using a glucometer at 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, and 120 min. Data are presented as means ± SD from 8–10 mice. Two-tailed Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (<italic toggle="yes">A–C</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> G</italic>) or one-way ANOVA (<italic toggle="yes">D, F, I</italic>) or two-way ANOVA (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>) with Bonferroni posttest were used. *<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. sense.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Food intake and hypothalamic neuropeptide expression in response to insulin or leptin in mice treated with Tub ASO.</title><p>The anorexigenic effect of ICV insulin or leptin was measured by recording 4-h and 8-h food intake. Food intake was reduced in response to ICV insulin or leptin in mice treated with sense, but not in mice treated with ASO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 5.</label><caption><p>Food intake and hypothalamic neuropeptide expression in response to insulin or leptin in mice treated with Tub ASO. The 4-h (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) or 8-h (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) food intake in response to ICV insulin or leptin is impaired in mice treated for 5 days with Tub ASO. <italic toggle="yes">C–I</italic>: Neuropeptide expression (mRNA levels) in response to ICV insulin and leptin are altered in the hypothalamus of ASO-treated mice. <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>: Akt and Foxo1 phosphorylation are increased in response to ICV insulin in the hypothalamus of Tub ASO-treated mice. <italic toggle="yes">L</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>: JAK2 and STAT3 phosphorylation in response to leptin are increased in the hypothalamus of ASO-treated mice. Data are presented as means ± SD from 8–10 mice. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttest was used. Sense: ASO control. *<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. sense; †<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. saline sense; ‡<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. saline and insulin sense; §<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. saline, insulin, and leptin sense; ‖<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. fed; ¶ vs. fast; # vs. fast with insulin (fast + I) and fast with leptin (fast + L) sense; ** vs. fast + L sense. AU, arbitrary units; ICV, ICV injection; Sal, saline; ins, insulin; lep, leptin; NPY, neuropeptide Y; AgRP, agouti-related peptide.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig5.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, we investigated whether ASO treatment for 5 days affects the influence of insulin or leptin on neuropeptide expression in the hypothalamus. As expected, fasting increased the expression of NPY, AgRP, MCH, and orexin, and insulin or leptin was able to markedly reduce expression of these neuropeptides in sense-treated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). However, in mice treated with ASO, leptin-induced reduction of MCH mRNA was blunted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">F</italic></xref>) and insulin-induced reduction of orexin was also blunted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). In contrast, fasting decreased the expression of POMC and TRH, and insulin or leptin increased the expression of these neuropeptides in mice treated with sense; however, in mice treated with ASO, leptin-induced or insulin-induced increases were blunted for POMC and TRH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">E</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H</italic></xref>).</p><p>In mice treated with ASO, insulin-induced Akt and Foxo1 phosphorylation and leptin-induced JAK2/STAT3 tyrosine phosphorylation were not altered, indicating that the blunted insulin and leptin effects on food intake in mice treated with ASO are independent from these pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5I–L</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Insulin- and leptin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in hypothalamic nuclei is blunted in DIO mice.</title><p>We next investigated the modulation of insulin-induced or leptin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in obese mice. Acute treatment with ICV insulin increased Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH from control mice, and this effect was reduced in mice fed a HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>). Similarly, ICV injection of leptin increased Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH in control mice, and this effect was blunted in mice fed a HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Insulin-induced or leptin-induced Tub nuclear translocation was blunted in the hypothalamus of DIO mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F6" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 6.</label><caption><p>Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr and translocation in response to insulin and leptin are impaired in mice fed HFD. Representative blots (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5 each nucleus) show insulin- (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and leptin-induced (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH of mice fed chow or HFD. A pool of 20 mice was used for each time point. Plasma membranes and nuclear lysates underwent IP and were blotted (IB) with anti-Tub antibody. Tub nuclear translocation in response to ICV insulin (0, 15, 30, 90 min) or leptin (0, 7, 20 min) is investigated in the hypothalamus of mice fed a HFD. Data are presented as means ± SD. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttest was used. α-PY, antiphosphotyrosine; *<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. fast on chow diet.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig6.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title>PTP1B may play a role in the regulation of Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in hypothalamic nuclei from DIO mice.</title><p>Because PTP1B dephosphorylates proteins that bind the IR and JAK2, we next investigated if insulin and leptin can induce an increase in Tub/PTP1B association in hypothalamic nuclei using coimmunoprecipitation. Our data showed that after these hormones were injected, there was an increase in Tub/PTP1B interaction in all hypothalamic nuclei investigated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></xref>). In addition, we investigated Tub/PTP1B association in mice fed a HFD, after leptin insulin infusion, and the results showed that in obese mice there was a marked increase in Tub/PTP1B association in response to insulin and leptin in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">D</italic></xref>). Then, we treated mice with ICV PTP1B ASO for 5 days, which decreased PTP1B protein level in the hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">E</italic></xref>), and we measured PTPase activity associated with PTP1B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">F</italic></xref>) and with Tub (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). We observed an increase in PTP1B and Tub associated with PTPase activity in the hypothalamus of mice fed a HFD, and this result was blunted by PTP1B-ASO treatment, suggesting that PTP1B may have phosphatase activity with Tub (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">F</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">G</italic></xref>). Furthermore, we investigated the modulation of insulin-induced or leptin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr levels in mice fed a HFD. The results showed that the reduction in PTP1B protein level in hypothalamus was accompanied by an increase in Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr levels after leptin or insulin ICV treatment in DIO mice, suggesting that PTP1B may have a role in the dephosphorylation of Tub (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7<italic toggle="yes">H</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F7" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 7.</label><caption><p>Tub/PTP1B association in response to insulin or leptin is higher in hypothalamic nuclei of mice fed a HFD. <italic toggle="yes">A–D</italic>: Representative blots show Tub/PTP1B association in response to ICV insulin (2 µg) or leptin (10 ng) in mice fed chow. This effect is greater in mice fed a HFD in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH of mice fed chow and HFD. <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>: PTP1B expression is reduced in mice fed a HFD treated with PTP1B ASO for 5 days. <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>: PTPase activity is increased by HFD and is reduced by PTP1B ASO treatment in mice fed a HFD. <italic toggle="yes">G</italic>: Tub associated with PTPase activity is greater in mice fed a HFD and is decreased by PTP1B ASO treatment. In this experiment, hypothalami were homogenized and centrifuged, and the supernatants were immunoprecipitated with anti-Tub antibody. Then, immune complexes were incubated with pp60c-src COOH-terminal phosphoregulatory peptide (TSTEPQpYQPGENL; Biomol) for 1 h at 30°C. To determine PTPase activity in a spectrophotometer, 40-μL aliquots with 100 μL Biomol Green reagent (Biomol) were used. <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>: Tub tyrosine phosphorylation in response to insulin or leptin is higher in mice fed a HFD treated with PTP1B ASO than in sense-treated mice. Data are presented as means ± SD from five mice per nucleus. One-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttest was used. *<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. sense, †<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 vs. mice fed chow treated with sense, ‡<italic toggle="yes">P &lt;</italic> 0.05 PTP1B ASO groups. PTP1B, protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B; Sense, ASO control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig7.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s20"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The results of the current study demonstrate that Tub is a direct substrate of insulin and leptin in vivo. Because the insulin receptor has tyrosine kinase activity, it induced Tub tyrosine phosphorylation directly; however, for leptin, similar to other substrates, it uses JAK2 as a kinase to induce Tub phosphorylation in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH. Our data also show that Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr is decreased during fasting and increased after refeeding, indicating that Tub is regulated by nutritional status. The combination of an increase in cumulative food intake, lower anorexigenic effect of insulin and leptin, and reduced O<sub>2</sub> consumption may contribute to explain enhanced adiposity in mice treated with Tub ASO.</p><p>Previous data showed that Tub overexpression, restricted to the Arc by a herpes simplex viral system, had no effect on food intake in rats fed chow, suggesting that Tub expression beyond normal may not be functional (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). Here, we demonstrate that the inhibition of Tub expression by ASO in all hypothalamic nuclei enhanced food intake and adiposity. It is possible that the manipulation of the amount of Tub only in neurons from one nucleus induced such a discrepant result. The regulation of food intake and adiposity is made by an interaction of different kinds of neurons in multiple brain regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). The response is variable and depends on which neuron is targeted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). The effect of Tub inhibition on the control of metabolism seen in our experiments with ASO may be a reflection of the circuit of leptin-responsive and insulin-responsive neurons in multiple hypothalamic nuclei. Further, although Tub acts as a transcription factor moving from the plasma membrane to the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>), it was not shown in this previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>) whether the elevated amount of Tub altered the translocation of Tub from the plasma membrane to the nucleus.</p><p>The results of the current study showed that after insulin and leptin stimulation, there was a clear translocation of Tub from the plasma membrane to the nucleus in the Arc, MH, PVN, and LH being slower in PVN. The delay in insulin- and leptin-induced Tub translocation in the PVN cannot be related to a lack of these hormones penetration into the area because PVN, as well as Arc, is periventricular. The IR expression in PVN is higher than in LH, but PVN has the lowest LEPR expression of all other nuclei, which may contribute to explaining the delay in leptin-induced Tub translocation in this nucleus. In addition, PVN receives neuronal projections from Arc; thus, we can speculate that modulation of neural activity in Arc induced by insulin or by leptin might delay the effect of these hormones on Tub translocation in PVN.</p><p>Previously, it was demonstrated that activation of G-protein αq by Ach releases Tub from the plasma membrane through the action of PLCβ, triggering translocation of Tub to the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). In this regard, our data suggest that insulin and leptin also use PLCβ to induce Tub translocation, because an inhibitor of PLCβ was able to block the effects of insulin and leptin on Tub translocation. Here, we demonstrated that after reduction in Tub protein expression, insulin or leptin was unable to increase the mRNA of POMC in Arc or the mRNA of TRH in PVN. Furthermore, insulin and leptin were unable to decrease the mRNA of orexin and MCH, respectively, in LH, suggesting that Tub may have a role modulating neuropeptides expression.</p><p>The inhibition of Tub protein expression in mice treated with ASO induced an increase in fasting blood glucose, hepatic glucose production, and the PEPCK expression of the liver in mice fed a chow diet. This phenomenon seems to be independent of changes in body weight or food intake, because it persists in pair-fed mice. These data suggest that in parallel to control energy balance, Tub in the hypothalamus may play a role in the regulation of hepatic glucose metabolism.</p><p>Resistance to leptin and insulin signaling is likely to play a central role in obesity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>). Our data showing a reduction in Tub tyrosine phosphorylation and nuclear translocation in response to insulin or leptin may contribute to hypothalamic insulin and leptin resistance in mice fed a HFD.</p><p>In the current study, we observed that Tub associates with PTP1B, and this interaction is increased in mice fed a HFD. Further, we observed that there was an increase in Tub associated with PTPase activity in the hypothalamus of mice fed a HFD, and this result was blunted by PTP1B-ASO treatment, suggesting that Tub may be a PTP1B substrate. This event could be one of the molecular mechanisms by which leptin-induced or insulin-induced Tub tyrosine phosphorylation is blunted in mice fed a HFD, suggesting that in addition to dephosphorylating IR, IRS-1, and JAK2, PTP1B also may have phosphatase activity with Tub.</p><p>In summary, our data provide evidence that Tub is a substrate of IRTK and LEPR-associated JAK2 in vivo in hypothalamic nuclei. After leptin or insulin injection, Tub translocates to the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>), and this is associated with altered POMC, TRH, MCH, and orexin mRNA levels. The reduction in Tub protein expression in the hypothalamus by Tub ASO treatment increases food intake, adiposity, fasting blood glucose, and hepatic glucose production, and decreases O<sub>2</sub> consumption, suggesting that Tub has a key role in the control of insulin and leptin effects on energy balance and glucose metabolism. In the hypothalamus of mice fed a HFD, there is a marked reduction in leptin- and insulin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr and translocation to the nucleus, which was accompanied by an increase in Tub/PTP1B interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>). These results demonstrate that Tub is part of the hypothalamic insulin and leptin signaling in vivo that acts independently of Akt/Foxo1 and STAT3 pathways, and its regulation has marked effects on metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F8" fig-type="figure" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIG. 8.</label><caption><p>Tub signaling in the context of other energy balance pathways. <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>: Insulin receptor has tyrosine kinase activity and is able to induce PI3K/Akt/Foxo1 pathway activation, altering transcription of neuropeptides involved in the regulation of energy balance. Because LEPR has no tyrosine kinase activity, it recruits JAK2. The LEPR/JAK2 complex binds and activates STAT3, which migrates to the nucleus, regulating feeding through neuropeptide expression. Here, we suggest that phosphorylated IR and JAK2 are also able to induce Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr and translocation to the nucleus, accompanied by changes in neuropeptide expression and regulation of energy balance. In addition, we demonstrate that acetylcholine stimulates translocation of Tub via PLCβ in vivo and insulin-induced and leptin-induced Tub translocation may occur via PLCβ. <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>: Furthermore, in obesity insulin-induced or leptin-induced Tub-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-tyr in Arc, MH, PVN, and LH are blunted in parallel to enhanced PTP1B activation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="137fig8.jpg"/></fig></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains Supplementary Data online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db11-1388/-/DC1">http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db11-1388/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This work was supported by FAPESP (Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo; 2008/55674-8), Sao Paulo, Brazil, CNPq (Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico) Universal (480131/2009-0), and by INCT (Instituto Nacional Ciência e Tecnologia de Obesidade e Diabetes; 573856/2008-7).</p><p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p><p>P.O.P. performed experiments and wrote the manuscript. P.G.F.Q., A.M.C., A.C.S., D.G., J.M., and L.W. performed experiments. E.R.R., J.B.C.C., and L.A.V. contributed to discussion and reviewed the manuscript. M.J.A.S. also wrote the manuscript. M.J.A.S. and P.O.P. are the guarantors of this work and, as such, had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p>The authors acknowledge the technical assistance of Luis Janieri, Jósimo Pinheiro, Lígia Parreira Muniz, and Ramon Henrick Zorzeto dos Santos from the Department of Internal Medicine, State University of Campinas.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belgardt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüning</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>CNS leptin and insulin action in the control of energy homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>1212</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21070248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05799.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheira</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torsoni</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cross-talk between the insulin and leptin signaling systems in rat hypothalamus</article-title>. <source>Obes Res</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15761162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/oby.2005.7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The NPY/AgRP neuron and energy homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>Suppl 5</issue>):<fpage>S56</fpage>–<lpage>S62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11840217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.ijo.0801915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baskin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Food intake and the regulation of body weight</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.psych.51.1.255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belgardt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüning</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hormone and glucose signalling in POMC and AgRP neurons</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>587</volume>:<fpage>5305</fpage>–<lpage>5314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19770186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1113/jphysiol.2009.179192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2793863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koritschoner</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Dolado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Thyroid hormone regulates the obesity gene tub</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11415982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/embo-reports/kve107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1083901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambright</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tissenbaum</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An endocytic pathway as a target of tubby for regulation of fat storage</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17762880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.embor.7401055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2002550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snieder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiri-Sverdlov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>TUB is a candidate gene for late-onset obesity in women</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17955208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-007-0851-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vliet-Ostaptchouk</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onland-Moret</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiri-Sverdlov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Polymorphisms of the TUB gene are associated with body composition and eating behavior in middle-aged women</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e1405</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18183286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0001405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2157487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fat (fat) and tubby (tub): two autosomal recessive mutations causing obesity syndromes in the mouse</article-title>. <source>J Hered</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2250094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a111019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heikenwälder</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koritschoner</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pajer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cloning, expression and regulation of the avian tubby-like protein 1 (tulp1) gene</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0378-1119(01)00578-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleyn</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovats</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of the mouse obesity gene tubby: a member of a novel gene family</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81104-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahly</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobetz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prominent neuronal-specific tub gene expression in cellular targets of tubby mice mutation</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1437</fpage>–<lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9700199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/7.9.1437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Ploeg</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence of altered hypothalamic pro-opiomelanocortin/ neuropeptide Y mRNA expression in tubby mice</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Mol Brain Res</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9729427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0169-328x(98)00150-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of the mouse and human TUSP gene, a novel member of the tubby superfamily</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11595174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0378-1119(01)00582-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noben-Trauth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naggert</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A candidate gene for the mouse mutation tubby</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>380</volume>:<fpage>534</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8606774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/380534a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naggert</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noben-Trauth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular characterization of TUB, TULP1, and TULP2, members of the novel tubby gene family and their possible relation to ocular diseases</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>3128</fpage>–<lpage>3133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.94.7.3128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC20333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seburn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechtel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Defective carbohydrate metabolism in mice homozygous for the tubby mutation</article-title>. <source>Physiol Genomics</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00239.2005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reduced activity without hyperphagia contributes to obesity in Tubby mutant mice</article-title>. <source>Physiol Behav</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18619628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.physbeh.2008.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2643381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bäckberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madjid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogren</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Down-regulated expression of agouti-related protein (AGRP) mRNA in the hypothalamic arcuate nucleus of hyperphagic and obese tub/tub mice</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Mol Brain Res</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15193430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molbrainres.2004.03.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stubdal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Targeted deletion of the tub mouse obesity gene reveals that tubby is a loss-of-function mutation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10629044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.20.3.878-882.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC85204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boggon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Implication of tubby proteins as transcription factors by structure-based functional analysis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>286</volume>:<fpage>2119</fpage>–<lpage>2125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10591637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.286.5447.2119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapeller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of tub and its association with Src homology 2 domain-containing proteins implicate tub in intracellular signaling by insulin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>24980</fpage>–<lpage>24986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10455176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.274.35.24980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stretton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litherland</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moynihan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajduch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hundal</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expression and modulation of TUB by insulin and thyroid hormone in primary rat and murine 3T3-L1 adipocytes</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>390</volume>:<fpage>1328</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19887065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.10.147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Modulation of insulin receptor, insulin receptor substrate-1, and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase in liver and muscle of dexamethasone-treated rats</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>2065</fpage>–<lpage>2072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7691892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI116803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC288376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardini</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figlewicz</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Distribution of insulin receptor substrate-2 in brain areas involved in energy homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>1112</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16925984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.brainres.2006.06.109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belgardt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rother</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>PDK1 deficiency in POMC-expressing cells reveals FOXO1-dependent and -independent pathways in control of energy homeostasis and stress response</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18396135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cmet.2008.01.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Monitoring FoxO1 localization in chemically identified neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>13640</fpage>–<lpage>13648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4023-08.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2615536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Forkhead protein FoxO1 mediates Agrp-dependent effects of leptin on food intake</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>534</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16604086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm1392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Role of hypothalamic Foxo1 in the regulation of food intake and energy homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>901</fpage>–<lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16783365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nn1731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minokoshi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollenberg</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Leptin signaling targets the thyrotropin-releasing hormone gene promoter in vivo</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>2221</fpage>–<lpage>2227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2003-1312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sixteen years and counting: an update on leptin in energy balance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>2087</fpage>–<lpage>2093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21633176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI45888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3104762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>MG</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>Outstanding Scientific Achievement Award Lecture 2010: deconstructing leptin: from signals to circuits</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>2708</fpage>–<lpage>2714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20980468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/db10-1118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2963524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klöckener</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belgardt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>High-fat feeding promotes obesity via insulin receptor/PI3K-dependent inhibition of SF-1 VMH neurons</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>911</fpage>–<lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nn.2847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3371271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zigman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Leptin directly activates SF1 neurons in the VMH, and this action by leptin is required for normal body-weight homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.12.021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Meyenn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfrum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of adaptive behaviour during fasting by hypothalamic Foxa2</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>462</volume>:<fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19956259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature08589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ropelle</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mourão</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor (PD153035) improves glucose tolerance and insulin action in high-fat diet-fed mice</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>2910</fpage>–<lpage>2919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19696185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/db08-0506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2780887</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6973588"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5482084"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirabara</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>L-glutamine supplementation induces insulin resistance in adipose tissue and improves insulin signalling in liver and muscle of rats with diet-induced obesity</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1949</fpage>–<lpage>1959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17604977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-007-0723-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zecchin</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparetti</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Western diet modulates insulin signaling, c-Jun N-terminal kinase activity, and insulin receptor substrate-1ser307 phosphorylation in a tissue-specific fashion</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>1576</fpage>–<lpage>1587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15591151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2004-0767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minokoshi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alquier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>AMP-kinase regulates food intake by responding to hormonal and nutrient signals in the hypothalamus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>428</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15058305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature02440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puigserver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cdc2-like kinase 2 is an insulin-regulated suppressor of hepatic gluconeogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cmet.2009.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2807620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheira</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Novel signal transduction pathway for luteinizing hormone and its interaction with insulin: activation of Janus kinase/signal transducer and activator of transcription and phosphoinositol 3-kinase/Akt pathways</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2002-220706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>GLUT4 ablation in mice results in redistribution of IRAP to the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>284</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11394912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/bbrc.2001.4994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauli</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ropelle</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Selective modulation of the CAP/Cbl pathway in the adipose tissue of high fat diet treated rats</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>580</volume>:<fpage>4889</fpage>–<lpage>4894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2006.08.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taghibiglou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashid-Kolvear</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Iderstine</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatic very low density lipoprotein-ApoB overproduction is associated with attenuated hepatic insulin signaling and overexpression of protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B in a fructose-fed hamster model of insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M106737200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Picardi</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calegari</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>PdeO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Reduction of hypothalamic protein tyrosine phosphatase improves insulin and leptin resistance in diet-induced obese rats</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>3870</fpage>–<lpage>3880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/en.2007-1506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2488223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boggon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>G-protein signaling through tubby proteins</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>292</volume>:<fpage>2041</fpage>–<lpage>2050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11375483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1061233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Figlewicz</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumaier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Catabolic action of insulin in rat arcuate nucleus is not enhanced by exogenous “tub” expression</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>286</volume>:<fpage>E1004</fpage>–<lpage>E1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpendo.00427.2003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalheira</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Selective impairment of insulin signalling in the hypothalamus of obese Zucker rats</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1629</fpage>–<lpage>1640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-003-1246-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Haschimi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierroz</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hileman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjørbaek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flier</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Two defects contribute to hypothalamic leptin resistance in mice with diet-induced obesity</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1827</fpage>–<lpage>1832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10862798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI9842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC378516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>