
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Surgery</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Surgery</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0417347</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0039-6060</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-7361</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3331939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3331939.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3331939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3331939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS353567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22284765</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surg.2011.12.014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS353567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA353567</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Liposome-Encapsulated Curcumin Suppresses Neuroblastoma Growth Through Nuclear Factor-κB Inhibition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names initials="WS">W. Shannon</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denbo</surname><given-names initials="JW">Jason W.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saab</surname><given-names initials="KR">Karim R.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names initials="AL">Adrianne L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names initials="CY">Catherine Y.</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="J">Junfang</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names initials="CL">Christopher L.</given-names></name><degrees>BS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names initials="LM">Lawrence M.</given-names></name><degrees>Ph.D</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names initials="AM">Andrew M.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Department of Surgery, St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital, Memphis, Tennessee
</aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Department of Surgery, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, Tennessee
</aff><aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Department of Pathology, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, Tennessee
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Address correspondence to:</bold> Andrew M. Davidoff, MD, Department of Surgery, St Jude Children’s Research Hospital, 262 Danny Thomas Place, Memphis, Tennessee 38105. Phone: 901-595-4060; Fax: 901-595-6621; <email>Andrew.davidoff@stjude.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>151</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">209209</issue-id><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-05 22:06:41.443"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2011 Mosby, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-353567.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Surgery" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4880022"><article-title>Retraction notice to “Liposome-encapsulated curcumin suppresses neuroblastoma growth through nuclear factor-<italic toggle="yes">?</italic>B inhibition” [j.surg 151 (2012) 736–744]</article-title><volume>159</volume><issue>2</issue><date><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><source>Surgery</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4880022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27144251</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Background</title><p id="P1">Nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) has been implicated in tumor cell proliferation and survival, and tumor angiogenesis. We sought to evaluate the effects of curcumin, an inhibitor of NF-κB, on a xenograft model on disseminated neuroblastoma.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P2">For in vitro studies, neuroblastoma cell lines, NB1691, CHLA-20, and SK-N-AS, were treated with varying doses of liposomal curcumin. Disseminated neuroblastoma was established in vivo by tail vein injection of NB1691-luc cells into SCID mice which were then treated with 50mg/kg/day of liposomal curcumin 5 days/week intraperitoneal.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P3">Curcumin suppressed NF-κB activation and proliferation of all neuroblastoma cell lines in vitro. In vivo, curcumin treatment resulted in a significant decrease in disseminated tumor burden. Curcumin treated tumors had decreased NF-κB activity and an associated significant decrease in tumor cell proliferation and an increase in tumor cell apoptosis, as well as a decrease in tumor VEGF levels and microvessel density.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P4">Liposomal curcumin suppressed neuroblastoma growth, with treated tumors showing a decrease in NF-kB activity. Our results suggest that liposomal curcumin maybe a viable option for the treatment of neuroblastoma that works via inhibiting the NF-κB pathway.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="United States">National Cancer Institute : NCI</funding-source><award-id>R01 CA133322-01A1 || CA</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="United States">National Cancer Institute : NCI</funding-source><award-id>P30 CA021765-30 || CA</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="United States">National Cancer Institute : NCI</funding-source><award-id>P01 CA023099-30 || CA</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S5"><title>Background</title><p id="P5">Neuroblastoma is an aggressive malignancy of the sympathetic nervous system and is the most common solid extracranial tumor of childhood.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> Children with high-risk neuroblastoma have a very poor prognosis, with the 5-year disease free survival rate being between 25%-35%, despite aggressive multi-modality therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> This highlights the need for new therapeutic strategies.</p><p id="P6">The nuclear factor-kappaB (NF-κB) family of transcription factors regulates expression of genes that affect multiple biological processes, including immune and inflammatory responses, developmental processes, cellular growth, and apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> NF-κB is tightly regulated by interactions with inhibitory IκB proteins.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> In most cells, NF- κB is bound to the IκB-complex in the cytoplasm and is inactive.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> The canonical and non-canonical pathways to NF-κB activation have a common upstream regulatory step which involves activation of the IκB kinase (IKK) complex. This activation results in IKK-mediated, phosphorylation-induced degradation of the IκB inhibitor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> Degradation of the IκB inhibitor allows NF-κB dimers to translocate into the nucleus and activate specific target genes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> Under physiological conditions, the NF- κB pathway is generally inactive in normal cells, except neurons, B cells, and thymocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>, but has been shown to be constitutively active in many cancer cell lines including human neuroblastoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup></p><p id="P7">Curcumin (diferuloylmethane), a polyphenol and the active component of turmeric, a medicinal compound first used for its anti-inflammatory properties, has been shown to suppress NF-κB activity and down regulate expression of NF-κB regulated gene products known to regulate cell proliferation, invasion, angiogenesis, metastasis and apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> In this current study, we evaluated the in vitro and in vivo antitumor activity of liposomal curcumin against human neuroblastoma. We demonstrated that curcumin inhibits neuroblastoma NF-κB activity in vitro and in a murine model of disseminated neuroblastoma. The inhibition of NF-κB activity in the animal model was associated with suppression of tumor growth, inhibition of angiogenesis, and increased tumor cell apoptosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S6"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S7"><title>Cell lines</title><p id="P8">The NB1691 (P. Houghton, Columbus, Ohio), SK-N-AS (American Type Culture Collection, Manassas, Virginia), and CHLA-20 (C.P. Reynolds, Lubbock, Texas) human neuroblastoma cells were used. These cells were engineered to constitutively express firefly luciferase as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Curcumin preparation</title><p id="P9">1, 2-Dimyristoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DMPC) and 1, 2-dimyristoylsn-glycero-3-[phosphor-rac- (1-gylcerol)] (DMPG) were obtained as dry powder from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, Alabama). Curcumin (ACROS, Morris Plains, New Jersey), dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO), and tert-butanol were obtained from Sigma Chemical Company (St. Louis, Missouri). The lyophilization process involved several steps. A 10:1 total lipid to curcumin ratio (weight/weight) was used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> Curcumin was dissolved in DMSO at 50mg/ml and the lipid was dissolved 9:1 (DMPC:DMPG) in 20mg/ml tert-butanol. Aliquots of this solution were placed in lyophilization vials frozen at −20°C and then lyophilized to remove all DMSO and tert-butanol. The lyophilized powder was stored at −20°C.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Alamar blue cell viability assay</title><p id="P10">The effects of increasing doses of curcumin on cell viability were determined by Alamar Blue Viability Assay using the manufacturer’s instructions (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California). Alamar blue solution was added to treated cells and after 4 hours the absorbance was read on a Synergy 2 Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (Biotek, Winooski, Vermont). The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Annexin V and cell cycle analysis</title><p id="P11">To analyze the effects of curcumin on cell cycle and apoptosis in these cell lines, cells were treated with 10 mol of liposomal curcumin for 48 hours, after which time cells were analyzed by flow cytometry for DNA content and Annexin V staining.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Nuclear factor KappaB reporter assay</title><p id="P12">NB1691 cells were transduced to stably express a NF-kB luciferase reporter. A 1.9kb fragment of the plasmid pGL4.32 luc2 NF-κB (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin) containing the NF-κB response elements was excised using <italic toggle="yes">Eco53KI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">EagI</italic> and ligated onto the CL20c-MSCV plasmid backbone. These cells were plated at a density of 5,000 cells/well in a 96 well plate and then treated with varying concentrations of lyophilized curcumin and after 3 hours of incubation, a set of plates was stimulated with 10ng/mL TNFα (Promega) for 30 minutes. Following this, the media was then removed and replaced with 1:100 15mg/mL luciferin containing media. The plate was allowed to incubate for 5 minutes and then read on a Synergy 2 Multi-Microplate Reader.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Nuclear protein extraction</title><p id="P13">For in vitro analysis of NF-κB activity, neuroblastoma cells were treated with 5 mol liposomal curcumin for 3, 24, 48 and 72 hours. After various time points, a set of plates was stimulated with 10ng/mL TNFα for 30 minutes. Cell nuclei were isolated using Affymetrix Nuclear Extraction Kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, California). Nuclear extracts and all working reagents were prepared per manufacturer’s protocol. For tumors, nuclear extraction was again done using the Affymetrix Nuclear Extraction Kit, starting with 0.5 grams of tissue.</p><p id="P14">Nuclear protein concentration was quantified using Pierce BCA Protein Assay Kit (Thermo Scientific, Rockford, Illinois) following manufacturer’s guidelines. Aliquots of each nuclear extract were stored at −80°C until use.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay</title><p id="P15">To determine the effect of curcumin on NF-κB activation, an electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) was performed on nuclear extracts after liposomal curcumin treatment following the protocol by Promega Gel Shift Assay Systems (Promega). Briefly, nuclear extracts were incubated with a <sup>32</sup>P-end-labed double-stranded NF-κB oligonucleotide containing a tandem repeat consensus sequence of 5′-AGT TGA GGG GAC TTT CCC AGG C-3′. Subsequently, all samples were electrophoresed through a 4% Acrylamide gel. Dried gels were visualized, and radioactive bands were quantified by a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics, Sunnyvale, California) using ImageQuant 5.2 software (Molecular Dynamics)</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Animal model</title><p id="P16">All murine experiments were performed in accordance with a protocol approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital. A disseminated model of neuroblastoma was established by injecting 2 × 10<sup>6</sup> NB1691-luc cells via tail vein into 4- to 6-week old male CB-17 SCID mice (Taconic, Hudson, New York). Two weeks after tail vein injection, animals were imaged using IVIS Imaging System 100 Series (Xenogen Corporation, Alameda, California) as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Living Image Software (Xenogen) was used to analyze tumor bioluminescence. Animals were divided into 2 groups (n=10 per group) with equivalent tumor burden (≈4.90 × 10<sup>7</sup> photons/second). The treatment group received 50mg/kg of liposomal curcumin intraperitoneal 5 days/week and the control group received empty liposome intraperitoneal 5 days/week. For real-time in vivo assessment of tumor burden, bioluminescence imaging was performed biweekly. At the end of 3 weeks, all animals were sacrificed.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Real time polymerase chain reaction analysis</title><p id="P17">Assay-on-demand gene expression primer and probe sets for human vascular endothelial growth factor and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (Hs00173626_m1, and Hs99999905_m1); Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California) were used for real-time PCR as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Tumor immunohistochemistry</title><p id="P18">Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded, 4 m thick tumor sections were stained with rat antimouse CD34 (RAM 34; PharMingen, San Diego, California) antibodies as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Apoptosis in tumors was determined by terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated dUTP nick end labeling using a commercially available <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> apoptosis detection kit (Serologicals, Billerica, Massachusetts) as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Tumor cell proliferation was analyzed by staining formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded sections (4 μm) with anti-Ki67 (rabbit monoclonal clone SP6; Neomarkers, Fremont, California). Results were expressed as percentage of Ki-67 positive cells ± SE per 400x magnification.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P19">Continuous variables are reported as mean ± SEM and were compared using an unpaired Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. A p value of less than .05 was considered significant. Data was analyzed and graphed using Sigma Plot (Version 9; SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S18"><title>Results</title><sec id="S19"><title>Liposomal curcumin inhibits the proliferation and survival of neuroblastoma cell lines in vitro</title><p id="P20">The effect of curcumin on proliferation was assessed on the human neuroblastoma cell lines NB1691, CHLA-20 and SK-N-AS. Exposure to liposomal curcumin inhibited neuroblastoma cell proliferation in all 3 cell lines in a concentration and time -dependent manner. 96 hour IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations varied from 10.57 mol for CHLA-20 to 17.97 mol for SK-N-AS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The anti-proliferative effects of liposomal curcumin were equivalent to free curcumin, confirming that there was no loss in curcumin’s potency during liposomal formulation. The neuroblastoma cell lines were also treated with empty liposome; no anti-proliferative effects were seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p id="P21">The effect of curcumin on cell cycle distribution and apoptosis was next assessed. Plated cells were treated for 48 hours with 10 mol of curcumin prior to FACS cell cycle and Annexin V analysis. All three neuroblastoma cell lines treated showed an increase in the percentage of cells in the G2/M phase of cell cycle. Curcumin treatment resulted in an 8.7%, 11.3%, and 13.7% increase in the number of cells in the G2/M phase of cell cycle (p = 0.007, p = 0.002, and p = 0.008) in the NB1691, SK-N-AS, and CHLA-20, respectively. Curcumin treatment resulted in 6.7, 4.83 and 5.87% increase in the percentage of Annexin V-positive apoptotic cells (p = 0.01, p= 0.02, and p = 0.03) in the NB1691, SK-N-AS and CHLA-20 cell lines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Thus curcumin treatment appeared to inhibit tumor cell proliferation by causing G2/M phase cell cycle arrest and inducing apoptosis.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Liposomal curcumin inhibits NF-κB activation in neuroblastoma cell lines</title><p id="P22">To determine the effect on NF-κB activity by liposomal curcumin, an NF-κB gene reporter assay was assessed using NB1691 cells modified to express a dual-luciferase NF-κB reporter (luc). Untreated NB1691 NF-κB-luc cells had a relative luciferase unit (RLU) of 5,796 per well. Curcumin decreased NF-κB activation in a dose dependent manner. (p = 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). NF-κB activity was also determined by EMSA which showed a decrease in activity in a time dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). After 72 hours of curcumin treatment, there was an 85.4%, 80%, and 74.5% decrease in NF-κB activity compared to control cells in the NB1691, CHLA-20, and SK-N-AS cell lines, respectively.</p><p id="P23">Cellular stresses such as irradiation and chemotherapy have been shown to increase NF-κB activity. Therefore, we next sought to examine the effects of curcumin together with TNFα, a known activator of NF-κB, to determine whether curcumin pretreatment could prevent NF-κB activation by adjuvant therapies. This was again done using both NB1691 NF-κB (luc) cells and by EMSA. NB1691 NF-κB (luc) cells stimulated with TNFα had a 438% increase in RLU per well (23,962 RLU/well), while cells that were pretreated with 10 μmol curcumin before the addition of TNFα showed a significant decrease in RLU (p &lt; 0.0001). Cells that were treated with 25 mol curcumin 3 hours before the addition of TNFα showed no induction of NF-κB activity (98% of control). Cells that were pretreated with 100 mol of curcumin before TNFα stimulation had a RLU of 80% of control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Next, we examined the effects of the combination of curcumin and TNFα by EMSA. TNFα induced a 33.3% increase in NF-κB activity relative to control cells based on band quantification. Curcumin inhibited the TNFα-induced activation of NF- κB when added 3 hours before TNFα; there was no increase in NF-κB activity when curcumin was added 24 hours before TNFα. We performed supershift with antibodies directed to specific NF-κB subunits to determine which components of the NF-κB complex were involved in its activation. The supershift assay showed that TNFα increases neuroblastoma NF-κB activity through the canonical pathway, specifically through increases in the p50 and p65 subunits; curcumin blocked the p50 and p65 subunit activation as seen by antibody shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Liposomal curcumin inhibits neuroblastoma tumor xenograft growth in a disseminated murine model</title><p id="P24">We next evaluated the effects of curcumin in a model of disseminated neuroblastoma. Fourteen days after NB-1691 tumor cell inoculation, animals were divided into a control group (n=10) and a treatment group (n=10), with equal tumor burden based on bioluminescence imaging. (4.89 ± 0.89 × 10<sup>7</sup> vs 4.91 ± 0.78 × 10<sup>7</sup> photons per second, p= 0.98). Mice in the treatment group received 50mg/kg of curcumin via intraperitoneal injection 5 days a week and the control group received empty liposome via intraperitoneal injection 5 days a week. After 3 weeks of therapy, control animals appeared ill and cachetic (animal weight 21.95 ± 0.5 grams) compared to those in the treatment group (animal weight 25.99 ± 0.86 grams, p= 0.0002). Real time assessment of tumor burden demonstrated significantly less disease in curcumin treated mice (7.43 ± 1.0 × 10<sup>9</sup> photons/second) compared to control mice (3.0 ± 0.4 × 10<sup>10</sup> photons/second, p=0.00003) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Due to the extent of disease in the control group, animals in both groups were sacrificed for further evaluation and comparison of disease burden on day 35 after tumor cell injection. Upon necropsy, mice in the control group were found to have bulky tumor replacement of the liver, kidney, and lungs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>) compared to those in the treatment group (liver weight 6.15 ±.83 grams vs 2.58 ±.23, p=0.00002; kidney weight .233 ± .025grams vs .166 ± .016, p= .0005, lung weight .158 ±.01 grams vs .111 ± .024grams, p=0.0004). Hematoxylin and eosin staining of these organs further demonstrated the tumor growth restriction within mice treated with curcumin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Thus, curcumin was able to cause a significant decrease in tumor burden compared to the control group in a disseminated neuroblastoma model.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Liposomal curcumin inhibits NF-κB activity in neuroblastoma murine tumors</title><p id="P25">EMSA was used to evaluate the effect of curcumin on NF-κB activity in treated tumors. NF-κB activity was inhibited in curcumin treated tumors compared to control tumors, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) being diminished by 26.2%, thus, confirming that lyophilized curcumin treatment is effective in decreasing NF-κB activity in vivo.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Liposomal curcumin inhibits tumor cell proliferation and increases tumor cell apoptosis</title><p id="P26">The effect of curcumin on tumor cell proliferation and apoptosis was assessed by Ki67 and TUNEL staining. The percentage of proliferating tumor cells was significantly decreased in tumors treated with curcumin (68.1 ± 3.4%) compared to control tumors (78.5% ± 2.82%, p=0.006) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). There was also a significant increase in tumor cell apoptosis as assessed by TUNEL staining in the curcumin-treated group (15.87 ± 4.9 per 1000 cells) compared to the control group (6.09 ± 2.6 per 1000 cells, p=0.0003) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). Thus, curcumin-treated tumors have a decrease in cell proliferation and an increase in tumor cell apoptosis, which are both known to be regulated by NF-κB.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Liposomal curcumin also inhibits angiogenesis in vivo</title><p id="P27">NF- κB has been to shown to play a key role in regulating the expression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF). We examined the effects of curcumin-mediated NF-κB inhibition on VEGF expression by RT-PCR analysis and found that curcumin treated tumors showed a 29.7% decrease in VEGF gene expression as compared to control tumors (p=0.005). We further examined the effect of curcumin-mediated NF-κB inhibition on the tumor vasculature by CD34 immunohistochemistry staining. Curcumin treated tumors had a significant decrease in tumor vascular endothelial cells (12,988 ± 4,173 CD34 pixels/hpf) compared to control (38,045 ± 16,182 CD34 pixels/hpf, p=0.0004) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). These data suggest that there is a loss of the more immature vessels through VEGF inhibition in curcumin treated tumors.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S25"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P28">Neuroblastoma frequently presents with metastatic disease, with 5 year disease free survival rates ranging between 25%-35%. Despite advances in multi-modality therapy, many children with advanced neuroblastoma face a poor prognosis and so new treatment strategies are needed.</p><p id="P29">The data presented here demonstrate that curcumin has significant anti-tumor activity against human neuroblastoma. In vitro all three cell lines tested demonstrated a dose-dependent and time-dependent decrease in cell proliferation after being treated with curcumin. There was also a time-dependent decrease in tumor cell NF-κB activity when cells were treated with curcumin doses less than their IC<sub>50</sub>.</p><p id="P30">In addition to the effects in vitro, curcumin had significant activity against neuroblastoma in vivo, significantly restricting tumor growth in a murine disseminated disease model. In addition to diminished bioluminescence signal, the curcumin-treated mice had significantly less tumor burden at necropsy than did the control group. There was bulky tumor replacement in the liver, kidney and lungs of the control group compared to the treated group.</p><p id="P31">NF-κB regulates the expression of genes that induce cell proliferation, invasion, angiogenesis, metastasis as well as suppress of apoptosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> The curcumin treated tumors had a decrease in NF-κB activity as compared to control tumors demonstrated by NF-κB DNA binding activity. Immunohistochemical analysis confirmed inhibition of cell proliferation and induction of apoptosis in curcumin treated tumors compared to the control group. Immunohistochemistry also confirmed inhibition of angiogenesis as seen by the decrease in the endothelial cell count in the treatment group as compared to the control group.</p><p id="P32">Based on the role that NF-κB plays in cell proliferation, promoting tumorigenesis, and inhibiting apoptosis, it is an attractive clinical therapeutic agent. Radiation therapy and several chemotherapeutic agents including doxorubicin, daunomycin, vincristine, and vinblastine have been reported to induce NF-κB activation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> Based on curcumin’s ability to block the TNFα-mediated increase NF-κB activity, further investigation is needed in using curcumin as an adjuvant therapy with radiation therapy and chemotherapeutic agents.</p><p id="P33">In conclusion, curcumin has significant activity against human neuroblastoma in vitro as well as in clinically relevant murine model of disseminated disease. The data here suggest that targeting the inhibition of the NF-κB pathway is a promising new way to treat a difficult disease and that further research and clinical trials are warranted.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S26"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to extend special thanks to Dorothy Bush of St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital for her assistance with all immunohistochemistry.</p><p>This work was supported by the Assisi Foundation of Memphis, the US Public Health Service Childhood Solid Tumor Program Project Grant No. CA23099, the Cancer Center Support Grant No. 21766 from the National Cancer Institute, Grant No. CA133322 from National Cancer Institute, and by the American Lebanese Syrian Associated Charities (ALSAC).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p content-type="publisher-disclaimer" id="P34">This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Reference List</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in neuroblastoma</article-title><source>N.Engl.J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>2202</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20558371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra0804577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3306838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonizzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The two NF-kappaB activation pathways and their role in innate and adaptive immunity</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.it.2004.03.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction: The Rel/NF-kappaB signal transduction pathway</article-title><source>Semin.Cancer Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9299583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/scbi.1997.0056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The NF-kappa B and I kappa B proteins: new discoveries and insights</article-title><source>Annu.Rev.Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8717528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.14.1.649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aravindan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhusoodhanan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin inhibits NFkappaB mediated radioprotection and modulate apoptosis related genes in human neuroblastoma cells</article-title><source>Cancer Biol.Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cbt.7.4.5534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear factor-kappa B: a transcription factor for all seasons</article-title><source>Expert.Opin.Ther.Targets</source><year>2007</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17227227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1517/14728222.11.2.109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shishodia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueso-Ramos</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Curcumin suppresses the paclitaxel-induced nuclear factor-kappaB pathway in breast cancer cells and inhibits lung metastasis of human breast cancer in nude mice</article-title><source>Clin.Cancer Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>7490</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16243823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-05-1192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shishodia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potdar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gairola</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin (diferuloylmethane) down-regulates cigarette smoke-induced NF-kappaB activation through inhibition of IkappaBalpha kinase in human lung epithelial cells: correlation with suppression of COX-2, MMP-9 and cyclin D1</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12807725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgg078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shishodia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin (diferuloylmethane) inhibits constitutive NF-kappaB activation, induces G1/S arrest, suppresses proliferation, and induces apoptosis in mantle cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Biochem.Pharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>700</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bcp.2005.04.043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargrove</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo bioluminescence imaging for early detection and monitoring of disease progression in a murine model of neuroblastoma</article-title><source>J Pediatr Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1172</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17618876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2007.02.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braiteh</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurzrock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Liposome-encapsulated curcumin: in vitro and in vivo effects on proliferation, apoptosis, signaling, and angiogenesis</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16092118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.21300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spurbeck</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enforced expression of tissue inhibitor of matrix metalloproteinase-3 affects functional capillary morphogenesis and inhibits tumor growth in a murine tumor model</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2002</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>3361</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood.V100.9.3361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamner</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IFN-beta restricts tumor growth and sensitizes alveolar rhabdomyosarcoma to ionizing radiation</article-title><source>Mol.Cancer Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20197402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-09-0800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shishodia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear factor-kappaB activation mediates cellular transformation, proliferation, invasion angiogenesis and metastasis of cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Treat.Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/1-4020-7847-1_8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pro-apototic and anti-apoptotic effects of tumor necrosis factor in tumor cells. Role of nuclear transcription factor NF-kappaB</article-title><source>Cancer Treat.Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16209064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/0-387-24361-5_5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bednarski</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coombe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active roles for inhibitory kappaB kinases alpha and beta in nuclear factor-kappaB-mediated chemoresistance to doxorubicin</article-title><source>Mol.Cancer Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1827</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18644995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-08-0321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2581801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of NF-kappaB activation and function by topoisomerase II inhibitors</article-title><source>BMC.Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16630341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2407-6-101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1459870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yacoub</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contessa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amorino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stress and radiation-induced activation of multiple intracellular signaling pathways</article-title><source>Radiat.Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1667/0033-7587(2003)159[0283:sariao]2.0.co;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Effects of curcumin on tumor cell viability</title><p>(A) Dose-dependent decrease in tumor cell viability in all 3 neuroblastoma cell lines tested (NB-1691, CHLA-20, SK-N-AS). The IC50s varied from 10.57 mol for CHLA-20 to 17.97 mol for SK-N-AS. (B) Treatment of all three cell lines with empty liposome had no effect. (C) No significant differences were found in cell viability when NB1691 cells were treated with liposomal curcumin versus curcumin dissolved in DMSO.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effects of curcumin on cell cycle and apoptosis</title><p>(A) Curcumin treated cells showed an increased percentage of cells in the G2/M phase of cell cycle compared to control cells. (B) Curcumin treatment resulted in an increase in Annexin V-positive apoptotic cells.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effects of curcumin on NF-κB in vitro</title><p>(A) NB1691 NF-kB luc cells showed a dose dependent decrease in NF-kB activity after 3 hours of treatment. (B) Pretreating NB1691 NF-κB luc cells with curcumin before being stimulated with TNFα prevented NF-κB activation. (C-E) All three cell lines (NB1691, CHLA-20, SK-N-AS, respectively) were treated with 5 mol of curcumin for 3 hours, 24 hours, 48 hours and 72 hours. EMSA showed time dependent inhibition of NF-κB activity in all three cell lines. (F) NB1691 cells stimulated with TNFα showed an increase in NF-κB activity, that was abrogated when curcumin was added 24 hours before TNFα. Antibody supershift shows that TNFα induced NF-κB complexes contains the p50 and p65 subunits.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effect of curcumin on tumor burden in a murine model of disseminated neuroblastoma</title><p>Bioluminescence imaging showed a reduction in tumor burden in the mice with disseminated neuroblastoma after 3 weeks of curcumin therapy. *p value = 0.00003. Also shown are representative photographs of bioluminescence in treat and control mice.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Effects of curcumin treatment on disseminated tumor burden</title><p>(A) After 3 weeks of treatment, control mice appeared ill and cachetic compared to treatment group. At necropsy, the control group was found to have bulky tumor replacement of the liver compared to treatment group. *p value = 0.00003, **p value = 0.00002 (B) The control group also had significant tumor replacement in the kidney and the lung compared to treatment group *p value = 0.0005, **p value = 0.0004 (C) Hematoxylin and eosin staining of representative kidney and lung sections. Magnification 200x (D) EMSA shows diminished activity in curcumin treated tumors</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Curcumin treatment decreased tumor cell proliferation and increased tumor cell apoptosis</title><p>(A) Quanitative assessment of tumor cell proliferation (Ki-67 staining) and apoptosis (TUNEL staining). *p value = 0.006 **p value = 0.0003 (B-C) Representative images of Ki67 staining of control and treated tumor, respectively, (D-E) Representative images of TUNEL staining of control and treatment tumor, respectively. Magnification 400x.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0006.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Curcumin inhibits tumor angiogenesis</title><p>A) VEGF was assessed by RT-PCR. Curcumin treated tumors showed a significant decrease in VEGF levels. *p value = 0.005. (B) Tumor endothelial cell density was assessed by CD34 immunohistochemistry. Curcumin treated tumors showed a signficant decrease tumor vascular endothelial cells. *p value = 0.0003. (C-D) Representative images of CD34 immunohistochemistry of control and treated tumors, respectively. Magnification 400x.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-353567-f0007.jpg"/></fig></floats-group></article>