
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3575387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3575387.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3575387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3575387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23441162</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-27259</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunologic Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunoassays</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Major Histocompatibility Complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Endothelial Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject><subject>Signal Transduction</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Cardiovascular</subject><subj-group><subject>Vascular Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Rheumatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Scleroderma</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>HLA-B35 and dsRNA Induce Endothelin-1 via Activation of ATF4 in Human Microvascular Endothelial Cells</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">ATF4 Activates ET-1 Gene</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenna</surname><given-names initials="S">Stefania</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrobak</surname><given-names initials="I">Izabela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farina</surname><given-names initials="GA">G. Alessandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Pascual</surname><given-names initials="F">Fernando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names initials="S">Santiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafyatis</surname><given-names initials="R">Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scorza</surname><given-names initials="R">Raffaella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trojanowska</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Arthritis Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Centro de Biología Molecular “Severo Ochoa” (CSIC/UAM), Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Referral Center for Systemic Autoimmune Diseases, Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico and University of Milan, Milan, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feghali-Bostwick</surname><given-names initials="C">Carol</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Pittsburgh, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>trojanme@bu.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interest exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: S. Lenna GAF FR-P SL RL RS MT. Performed the experiments: S. Lenna IC GAF. Analyzed the data: S. Lenna IC GAF FR-P S. Lamas RL RS MT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FR-P S. Lamas. Wrote the paper: S. Lenna MT.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">219104</issue-id><elocation-id>e56123</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 01:25:11.020"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Lenna et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lenna et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0056123.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7580888"><article-title>Retraction: HLA-B35 and dsRNA Induce Endothelin-1 via Activation of ATF4 in Human Microvascular Endothelial Cells</article-title><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><date><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>e0241404</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0241404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7580888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33091055</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Endothelin 1 (ET-1) is a key regulator of vascular homeostasis. We have recently reported that the presence of Human antigen class I, HLA-B35, contributes to human dermal microvascular endothelial cell (HDMEC) dysfunction by upregulating ET-1 and proinflammatory genes. Likewise, a Toll-like receptor 3 (TLR3) ligand, Poly(I:C), was shown to induce ET-1 expression in HDMECs. The goal of this study was to determine the molecular mechanism of ET-1 induction by these two agonists. Because HLA-B35 expression correlated with induction of Binding Immunoglobulin Protein (BiP/GRP78) and several heat shock proteins, we first focused on ER stress and unfolded protein response (UPR) as possible mediators of this response. ER stress inducer, Thapsigargin (TG), HLA-B35, and Poly(I:C) induced ET-1 expression with similar potency in HDMECs. TG and HLA-B35 activated the PERK/eIF2α/ATF4 branch of the UPR and modestly increased the spliced variant of XBP1, but did not affect the ATF6 pathway. Poly(I:C) also activated eIF2α/ATF4 in a protein kinase R (PKR)-dependent manner. Depletion of ATF4 decreased basal expression levels of ET-1 mRNA and protein, and completely prevented upregulation of ET-1 by all three agonists. Additional experiments have demonstrated that the JNK and NF-κB pathways are also required for ET-1 upregulation by these agonists. Formation of the ATF4/c-JUN complex, but not the ATF4/NF-κB complex was increased in the agonist treated cells. The functional role of c-JUN in responses to HLA-B35 and Poly(I:C) was further confirmed in ET-1 promoter assays. This study identified ATF4 as a novel activator of the ET-1 gene. The ER stress/UPR and TLR3 pathways converge on eIF2α/ATF4 during activation of endothelial cells.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health, National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS) P50 AR060780 to MT and RL, Scleroderma Foundation grants to MT and AF, and by a grant from Gruppo Italiano per la Lotta alla Sclerodermia (GILS) to SL. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Endothelin-1 (ET-1) is a potent vasoconstrictor and one of the key regulators of vascular homeostasis. ET-1 dysfunction is associated with a number of pathological conditions including hypertension, atherosclerosis, cardiovascular disorders, and cancer <xref rid="pone.0056123-Kawanabe1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Shao1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Tsui1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Under physiological conditions, ET-1 is produced in small amounts mainly in endothelial cells (ECs). However in pathophysiological conditions, its production is stimulated in a large number of different cell types, including endothelial cells, vascular smooth muscle cells, cardiac myocytes, and inflammatory cells such as macrophages and leukocytes. In addition to its main role as a vasoconstrictor, ET-1 also contributes to inflammation, as well as fibrosis during various pathophysiological processes.</p><p>Extensive studies of ET-1 gene expression have led to characterization of the signaling pathways and transcription factors involved in its regulation <xref rid="pone.0056123-RodriguezPascual1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Stow1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. A complex network consisting of the common and tissue specific transcription factors responding in the coordinated fashion to physiological and pathological stimuli have been shown to regulate ET-1 expression in a cell type and context specific manner. One of the main regulatory factors is a FOS/JUN complex that binds to an activator protein 1 (AP-1) response element located at a -108 bp in the ET-1 promoter region. This site mediates upregulation of the ET-1 gene by phorbol esters, Angiotensin II, Thrombin, and High-density lipoprotein (HDL), which stimulate AP-1 in a Protein kinase C (PKC)-dependent manner. On the other hand, Leptin activates AP-1 through the Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and extracellular-signal-regulated kinases 1/2 (Erk1/2) pathways. AP-1 in cooperation with GATA-binding factor 2 (GATA2) is also required for the basal transcription of the ET-1 gene in endothelial cells, while other members of the GATA family regulate ET-1 expression in other cell types. Additional important transcription binding sites include hypoxia response element, Hypoxia-inducible factors (HIF-1), transforming growth factor β (TGF-β)/Smad response element, which have been also described to cooperate with AP-1 to induce ET-1 <xref rid="pone.0056123-RodriguezPascual2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, as well as the Nuclear factor κB (NF-κB) binding site that mediates responses to inflammatory cytokines. Other cell type specific response elements have also been characterized <xref rid="pone.0056123-Aitsebaomo1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Endoplasmic Reticulum (ER) stress is defined as accumulation of unfolded or misfolded proteins in the ER, triggering an adaptive program called the unfolded protein response (UPR). The UPR alleviates ER stress by suppression of protein synthesis, facilitation of protein folding via induction of ER chaperones, and reinforced degradation of unfolded proteins. Three major transmembrane transducers of ER stress have been identified in the ER. Those are the RNA-dependent protein kinase-like ER kinase (PERK), activating transcription factor 6 (ATF6), and inositol-requiring ER-to-nucleus signal kinase 1α (IRE1α). Activation of PERK leads to phosphorylation of the eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2α (eIF2α), causing general inhibition of protein synthesis. In response to ER stress, ATF6 transits to the Golgi where it is cleaved by the proteases Site-1 protease (S1P) and Site-2 protease (S2P), yielding a free cytoplasmic domain which functions as an active transcription factor. Similarly, activated IRE1α catalyzes removal of a small intron from an X-box-binding protein 1 (XBP1) mRNA. This splicing event produces an active transcription factor XBP1. If the cell fails to deal with the protein-folding defect and restore homeostasis, a pro-apoptotic CCAAT/−enhancer-binding protein homologous protein (CHOP)-mediated pathway is initiated <xref rid="pone.0056123-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p><p>There is extensive evidence that ER stress/UPR is closely linked to the inflammatory pathways through activation of the two key inflammatory mediators, JNK and NF-κB <xref rid="pone.0056123-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Rath1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> Recent studies have also revealed that UPR and innate immune pathways share common mediators <xref rid="pone.0056123-Gargalovic1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-He1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. It was shown that stimulation of the Toll-like receptor (TLR) 2 or TLR4 leads to selective activation of the IRE1a/XBP1 pathway, contributing to the optimal and sustained production of proinflammatory cytokines in macrophages <xref rid="pone.0056123-Martinon1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. However, activation of the IRE1α/XBP1 pathway by these TLR agonists did not lead to expression of the genes typically regulated by these mediators during ER stress, suggesting an alternative utilization of the components of the UPR pathways. The specific mechanisms involved in these atypical responses are still not well understood and require further investigation.</p><p>We have recently shown that ectopic expression of HLA-B35, an antigen associated with SSc in Choctow Indians <xref rid="pone.0056123-Arnett1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and SSc-PAH in Italian patients <xref rid="pone.0056123-Santaniello1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Scorza1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, led to a significant increase of ET-1 and a decrease of eNOS in cultured endothelial cells (ECs) <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. In addition to ET-1, we have also observed upregulation of interferon-regulated genes and other inflammatory genes in ECs expressing HLA-B35. Furthermore, expression of HLA-B35, but not a control antigen HLA-B8, potently upregulated several cellular chaperones including BiP, HSP70 and HSP40, suggesting an activation of ER stress/UPR in these cells. However, other UPR genes such as ERO1 (ER oxidoreductin 1), and PDI (protein disulphide isomerase), which are involved in oxidative protein folding, as well as a pro-apoptotic UPR mediator, CHOP were not upregulated, consistent with activation of an adaptive phase of the UPR. Relevant to these findings Farina et al have reported upregulation of ET-1 in response to a synthetic analog of dsRNA, Poly(I:C), in dermal endothelial cells and fibroblasts <xref rid="pone.0056123-Farina1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Given the recently uncovered cross-talk between the UPR and the innate immune pathways, the goal of this study was to further investigate whether common mediators are involved in ET-1 gene regulation in response to these stimuli. Here we report that induction of ER stress or stimulation with Poly(I:C) activate the eIF2α-ATF4 pathway and promote formation of the ATF4/c-JUN complexes. This protein complex in concert with the NF-κB pathway activates ET-1 gene transcription in endothelial cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Reagents</title><p>Thapsigargin (TG) was purchased by Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Poly(I:C) was purchased by InvivoGen (San Diego, CA). Tissue culture reagents, EBM kit by Lonza (Walkersville, MD). The protease inhibitor cocktail set III and phosphatase inhibitor cocktail set II were purchased from Calbiochem (San Diego, CA). Enhanced chemiluminescence reagent and bicinchoninic acid protein assay reagent were obtained from Pierce Chemical Co. (Rockford, IL). TRI Reagent was purchased from the Molecular Research Center Inc. (Cincinnati, OH).</p><p>For western blot, antibodies were used as followed: goat ATF4 and rabbit ATF6 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Clara, CA) at a 1∶500 dilution; rabbit pPERK and PERK (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Clara, CA) at a 1∶500 dilution, rabbit p-eIF2α and mouse eIF2α Ab (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Clara, CA) at 1∶500 dilution; rabbit cJun and rabbit NF-κBp65 Ab (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Clara, CA) at a 1∶500 dilution; monoclonal β-actin Ab (Sigma-Aldrich) at 1∶5000 dilution and mouse Lamin A/C at 1∶1000 dilution.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Human dermal microvascular endothelial cells (HDMECs) were isolated from human foreskins using the protocol of Richard et al <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Upon informed consent and in compliance with the Institutional Review Board of Human studies, written approval was obtained from Perinatal Committee (IRB number H-29190) of Boston University Medical School. Briefly, primary cultures of human foreskins were established after the removal of epidermis. Such cultures consist of a mixture of HDMECs, dermal fibroblasts, and some keratinocytes. Subconfluent cultures were treated with tumor necrosis factor-α for 6 h to selectively induce the expression of E-selectin in HDMECs. HDMECs were then purified using magnetic beads coupled to an anti-E-selectin monoclonal antibody. First passage cultures usually consist of &gt;99% HDMECs. A second immunomagnetic purification step ensures homogenous population of HDMECs suitable for long term culturing. Purity of the HDMEC cultures was evaluated using anti-CD31 and anti-von Willebrand factor antibodies. These cells were cultured on collagen-coated 6-well plate in EBM medium supplemented with 10% FBS, EC growth supplement mix at 37°C under 5% CO2 in air. The culture medium was changed every other day. HDMECs harvested between passage 2 and 6 were used for experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Adenoviral Constructs</title><p>An adenoviral vector expressing HLA-B35 (or Ad-B8) and control green fluorescent protein (Ad-Go) were generated as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The dose used to transduce human dermal microvascular endothelial cells was 10 multiplicities of infection of the adenovirus (MOI). ECs grown in a 6-well dish were transduced with Ad (Ad-B35/GFP, -B8/GFP, and -GFP), after 48 h cells were collected for RNA analyses or for Western blot.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Real-time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using the guanidiniumthiocyanate-phenol-chloroform method, concentration and purity was determined by measuring OD at 260 and 280 nm using a spectrophotometer. RNA was reversibly transcribed by aid of the first-strand cDNA Synthesis Kit for RT-PCR (Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN). To avoid amplification from traces of possible DNA contamination in the RNA isolation, PCR primers were designed to span introns. All primers were checked for specificity by Blast search. Real-time RT-PCR was performed using IQ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) and MyiQ Single-Color Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad). The amount of template used in the PCR reactions was cDNA corresponding to 200 ng reverse-transcribed total RNA. DNA polymerase was first activated at 95°C for 3 min, denatured at 95°C for 30 s, and annealed/extended at 61°C for 30 s, for 40 cycles according to the manufacturer's protocol. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value. The primers are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0056123-t001">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0056123-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Primer sequences for quantitative PCR.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0056123-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-PPET-1</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-gctcgtccctgatggataaa-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ccatacggaacaacgtgct-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-ATF4</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-tggctggctgtggatgg-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-tcccggagaaggcatcct-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-ATF6</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ttttagcccgggactctttc-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-tcagcaaagagagcagaatcc-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-XBP1u</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ccttgtagttgagaaccagg-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-gggcttggtatatatgtgg-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-XBP1s</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ggtctgctgagtccgcagcagg-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-gggcttggtatatatgtgg-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-PKR</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-tgttgggatggatttgattatg-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-gaaaaggcacttagtctttgacct-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Human-βactin</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-aatgtcgcggaggacctttgattgc-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-aggatggcaagggacttcctgtaa-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mouse-ATF4</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-gagcttcctgaacagcgaagtg-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-tggccacctccagatagtcatc-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mouse-βactin</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ctaaggccaaccgtgaaaag-3′</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-accagaggcatacagggaca-3′</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Immunofluorescence Staining on Adherent Cell Cultures</title><p>Cultured HDMECs grown on collagen-coated cover slips were transduced with Adenovirus carrying HLA-B35 (Ad-B35/GFP), Ad-B8/GFP and Ad-G0/GFP (virus control) for 48 hours. Treated cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 minutes followed by incubation with 0.15 M Glycine for 30 min. Non-specific protein binding was blocked with 3% BSA for 1 h. Next, cells were incubated at 4°C overnight with primary mouse monoclonal MHC class I Ab (W6/32) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Clara, CA) at a 1∶500 dilution. After washing, cell cultures were incubated with Alexa fluor 594 donkey anti-mouse (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY) antibody for 1.5 h. Cells were mounted on slides using Vectashield with DAPI (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA) and examined using a FluoView FV10i confocal microscope system (Olympus, Center Valley, PA) at 488 nm (green), 594 nm (red) and 405 nm (blue).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p>Cells were collected and washed with PBS. Cell pellets were suspended in lysis buffer containing 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 15 mM NaCl,1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 1% Triton X-100, 2.5 mM sodium pyrophosphate, and 1 mM glycerophosphate with freshly added phosphatase inhibitors (5 mM sodium fluoride and 1 mM Na3VO4) and a protease inhibitor mixture (Sigma-Aldrich). Protein concentration was quantified using the BCA Protein Assay kit (Pierce). Equal amounts of total proteins per sample were separated via SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes (Bio-Rad). Membranes were blocked in milk in TBST overnight at 4°C and probed with primary Ab overnight at 4°C. After TBST washes, membranes were probed with HRP-conjugated secondary Ab against the appropriate species for 1–2 h at room temperature. Protein levels were visualized using ECL reagents (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>ET-1 Bio-assay</title><p>The ET-1 bioassay was performed according to the protocol supplied with the kit from Assay Designs (cat no. 900-020A). Standards and samples were incubated in supplied pre-coated 96-well plate, washed, incubated with horse radish peroxidase labeled anti- ET-1 antibody and washed again before adding the provided TMB substrate and measuring the absorbance.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>siRNA Experiments</title><p>HDMECs were trasfected with either siRNA specific to human ATF4 (ON-TARGET plus SMARTpool, Dharmacon RNA Technologies, CO), PKR (Santa Cruz biotechnology, CA) or negative-control siRNA (Qiagen, Chatsworth, CA) at concentration of 20 nM using HiPerfect reagent (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. After 48 hours, RNA was extracted and Real-time PCR was performed.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Inhibitor Experiment</title><p>HDMECs were incubated in the presence of the 25 nM of JNK SP600125 or NF-κB SN50 inhibitor (Enzo Life Sciences, Farmingdale, NY) for 3 hours before treatment. After 48 hours, RNA and protein were extracted.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Co-Immunoprecipitation</title><p>Cell lysates were prepared after appropriate treatment in radioimmune precipitation buffer. For immunoprecipitation of cJUN (or NF-κB p65), antibody was added to 300 µg of precleared cell lysate, and complex formation was carried out at 4°C overnight. The protein-antibody complexes were recovered using protein G-Sepharose beads for 2 h at 4°C. The immunoprecipitates were washed four times in radioimmune precipitation buffer, eluted by boiling for 5 min in 2× SDS sample buffer, and analyzed by Western blot with anti-ATF4 antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Santa Cruz, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>Plasmids, Transient Transfections and Luciferase Assay</title><p>Luciferase reporters driven by −650-bp and −193-bp fragments (representing the wildtype and mutated AP-1 site) of the human ET-1 promoter described previously 1. Transient transfections of promoters were performed in HDMECs seeded into 6-well plates using Fugene6 (Roche Applied Science) according to the manufacturer's instructions. After overnight incubation, cells were treated and then further incubated for 24 h. The cells were harvested and assayed for luciferase reporter activity using the Promega luciferase assay kit according to the manufacturer's instructions. Promoter/reporter plasmids were cotransfected with pCMV-βGal (Clontech), which was used to adjust for differences in transfection efficiencies between samples. Cells were harvested and Luciferase activity of the promoter was assayed using Promega Luciferase assay kit. Values given are means ± standard errors of triplicate assays from three individual experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>In vivo Administration of Poly(I:C)</title><p>C57Bl/6 WT and C57Bl/6 TICAM/TRIF −/− mice were obtained from The Jackson Laboratory; C57Bl/6 IFNAR1−/− mice were provided by Dr John Sprent. All of the experiments were performed under the guidelines of the Boston University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. Osmotic pumps designed to deliver Poly(I:C) (0.5 mg/ml in PBS, 0.1 mg total dose in 200 µl released over 7 days, Alzet) or PBS were implanted subcutaneously on the back in 6–10-weekold mice. After 7 days mice were killed and skin (∼1 cm2) surrounding the pump outlet was homogenised in Trizol for preparation of RNA, then minced and disrupted using a Polytron homogeniser and processed according to the manufacturer's protocol.</p><p>This study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The protocol was approved by the Committee on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of the Boston University (Permit Number: AN-14942.2012.01). All surgery was performed under sodium pentobarbital anesthesia, and all efforts were made to minimize suffering.”.</p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title>Immunostaining</title><p>Skin sections biopsies from healthy individuals and limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis (lcSSc) patients including 8 patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension (lcSSc-PAH) based on echoradiography and right heart catheterization and 11 patients without PAH (lcSSc-noPAH) and 5 healthy controls were provided by the Boston University Core Centers (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bu.edu/sscores/">http://www.bu.edu/sscores/</ext-link>); IRB: H31–506. Patient information is included in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0056123-t002">Table 2</xref>. Immunohistochemistry was performed on formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue sections using a Vectastain ABC kit (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, 8-micrometer-thick sections were mounted on APES (amino-propyl-triethoxy-silane)-coated slides, deparaffinized with Histo-Clear (National diagnostic, Atlanta GA), and rehydrated through a graded series of ethanol. Endogenous peroxidase was blocked by incubation in 0.3% hydrogen peroxide for 15 minutes and incubated with blocking buffer for 1 hour. The sections were then incubated overnight at 4°C with antibody against ATF4 (Abcam, Cambridge, MA) diluted 1∶500 in blocking serum, followed by the incubation with secondary antibody. The concentration of primary antibody was first tested to determine the optimal sensitivity range. The immunoreactivity was visualized with diaminobenzidine (Vector laboratories, Burlingame, CA) and the sections were counterstained with hematoxylin.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0056123-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Clinical and hemodynamic data of study subjects.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0056123-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DiseaseDuration</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCWP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PASP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATF4 staining</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 years 1 month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no medications</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no medications</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">no medications</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9–10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sildenafil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 years 8 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cept revatio</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prednisone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc PAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">viagra</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myocophenolate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>++</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prednisone, mycophenolate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hydroxychloroquine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyclophosphamide</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytoxan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lcSSc NoPAH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>PAP = pulmonary artery pressure. PCWP = pulmonary capillary wedge pressure. PASP = pulmonary artery systolic pressure.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>− indicates no staining or little staining in &lt;10% of the cells.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>+ indicates faint, partial staining in &gt;20% of the cells.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>++ indicates light to moderate stain in &gt;50% of the cells.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>+++ indicates bright staining in &gt;50% of the cells.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2n"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Student's t test analysis was performed to determine statistical significance. Values less than or equal to 0.05 were considered statistically significant. All experiments were repeated at least three times using independently isolated endothelial cell cultures.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>ER Stress and Poly(I:C) Activate Common ER Stress/UPR Pathways in HDMECs</title><p>In the initial experiment we compared the effects of HLA-B35 with a known ER stress inducer, thapsigargin (TG), and a TLR3 agonist, Poly(I:C), on the expression of ET-1 mRNA and protein in primary dermal microvascular endothelial cells (HDMECs). HLA-B35 was expressed using adenoviral delivery as previously described <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. To control for the presence of adenoviral genes we used adenovirus expressing a closely related antigen, HLA-B8, as well as an empty virus. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g001">Fig. 1a</xref>, HLA-B35 and Poly(I:C) upregulated (pre-pro-endothelin-1) PPET-1 mRNA levels with a similar potency 7-fold ±0.58, p  = 0.05 vs 8-fold±0.25, p = 0.05, respectively, while TG was a stronger inducer of PPET-1 (26-fold ±0.75, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.001). Ad-HLA-B8, as well as an empty virus vector (data not shown) did not affect PPET1 mRNA expression. To verify that the increase in PPET-1 mRNA corresponds to an increase of the bioactive 21-aa ET-1 peptide, we measured levels of ET-1 protein in supernatants of Ad-B35 (and Ad-B8), TG and TLR ligand-treated ECs. Consistent with the mRNA measurements ER stress inducers increased ET-1 protein levels (Ad-B35, 3.5-fold±0.6, p = 0.05 and TG, 5.3-fold±0.80, p = 0.05). Similarly, Poly(I:C) induced ET-1 protein by 3.7-fold±0.98 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g001">Fig. 1b</xref>). PPET-1 mRNA expression was further enhanced by a combination of HLA-B35, and to a lesser degree TG, and Poly(I:C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g001">Fig. 1c</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>HLA-B35, TG, and Poly(I:C) upregulate ET-1 mRNA and protein in HDMECs.</title><p>Upregulation of PPET-1 mRNA after HLA-B35 (or HLA-B8), TG, or Poly(I:C) treatments alone (a) or in combination (c) in HDMECs. Confluent dishes of HDMECs were transduced with 10 MOI of Adenovirus encoding HLA-B35/GFP (Ad-HLA-B8/GFP) for 48 h or treated with 10pM TG, or 2.5 µg/µl Poly(I:C) for 24 hours. Total RNA was extracted and mRNA levels of PPET-1 were quantified by quantitative RT-PCR. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value. (b) Bioactive 21-aa ET-1 peptide in HDMECs after Ad-B35/GFP (Ad-B8/GFP), TG, or Poly(I:C) treatment. ET-1 protein was measured by ELISA in the supernatants. The average protein concentration for each group is represented as a bar ± SE. *p  = 0.05; **p  = 0.001 <bold>(d)</bold> Immunofluorescence was performed using mouse monoclonal MHC class I Ab (W6/32) in HDMECs transduced with HLA-B35 (Ad-B35/GFP), Ad-B8/GFP and Ad- G0/GFP (virus control). Left column DAPI, middle column GFP, right column HLA. Bar: 100 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>To further determine if HLA-B35 mediates its effects via peptide binding to the antigen-binding groove we utilized mouse monoclonal anti-MHC class I blocking antibody (W6/32). HDMECs transduced with Ad-HLA-B35/GFP and HLA-B8/GFP for 24 hours were treated with increasing dose of W6/32 (0.1–10 µg/ml) for the following 24 hours. Treatment with antibody did not affect ET-1 mRNA levels, suggesting that HLA-B35 does not modulate ET-1 through peptide binding to the antigen-binding groove (supplemental data, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0056123.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). To determine subcellular localization of ectopic HLA-B35 we performed immunofluorescence staining using HDMECs transduced with Ad-HLA-B35/GFP, Ad-HLAB8/GFP and Ad-G0/GFP (virus control) for 48 hours. Spotty positive staining was observed in the cytoplasm primarily around the nucleus, suggesting ER retention of the HLA-B35 and HLA-B8. Together, these data suggest that HLA-B35 is primarily retained in the ER, where it might induce ER stress and UPR. Interestingly, although HLA-B8 displayed a similar cellular distribution, expression of HLA-B8 was not associated with upregulation of BiP and other heat shock proteins <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The specific structural determinants of HLA-B35 that may explain its biological effects are currently not known.</p><p>To further characterize the nature of the HLA-B35-mediated ER stress, we examined the effect of HLA-B35 (or HLA-B8), TG, and Poly(I:C) on the mRNA expression of the three main UPR mediators, transcription factors ATF4, ATF6 and XBP1. ATF4 mRNA levels were significantly increased in response to the HLA-B35 and Poly(I:C) treatment, while TG was a less potent inducer of ATF4 mRNA under this experimental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>). When Poly(I:C) was used in combination with the ER stress inducers, a further upregulation of ATF4 mRNA was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>). Furthermore, both HLA-B35 and TG moderately increased spliced (active) form of the transcription factor XBP1 (XBP1s), while TLR3 had no effect on the XBP1 splicing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g002">Fig. 2c</xref>). In contrast, the expression level of ATF6 was not responsive to any of these treatments in HDMECs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g002">Fig. 2d</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>ER stress and Poly(I:C) activate selected ER stress/UPR pathways.</title><p>ATF4 (a, b), XBP1 splicing (c) and ATF6 (d) mRNA levels in HDMECs treated with HLA B35 (HLA-B8), TG, and Poly(I:C) alone or in combination. Confluent dishes of HDMECs were transduced with 10 MOI of Ad-B35/GFP (or Ad- B8/GFP) for 48 h treated with 10pM TG, or 2.5 µg/µl Poly(I:C) for 24 hours. Total RNA was extracted and mRNA levels of transcription factors were examined by quantitative RT-PCR. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Since nuclear translocation of ATF4 is indicative of its activation status, we examined nuclear extracts for the presence of ATF4 by western blot. Nuclear ATF4 was examined at various time points (15 min. to 6 hours) after TG and Poly(I:C) treatments and 24 hours post infection with HLA-B35 or HLA-B8 adenoviruses. Nuclear ATF4 was rapidly increased (15–30 min) after TG and Poly(I:C) treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g003">Fig. 3a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g003">Fig. 3b</xref>). Likewise, HLA-B35 markedly increased nuclear presence of ATF4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g003">Fig. 3c</xref>). Furthermore, increased phosphorylation of the upstream activators of ATF4, PERK and eIF2α, was observed in response to these treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g003">Fig. 3, right panel</xref>s). Consistent with the mRNA data, nuclear levels of ATF6 remained unchanged. Together, these results demonstrate that ATF4 is activated in a similar manner by ER stress/UPR and Poly(I:C) in endothelial cells.</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>ER stress and Poly(I:C) activate ATF4 nuclear translocation and enhance phosphorylation of PERK and eIF2α.</title><p>ATF4<bold>,</bold> pPERK/PERK, and p-eIF2α<bold>/</bold>eIF2α protein levels in HDMECs after treatment with 10pM TG (a), 2.5 µg/µl Poly(I:C) (b), or transduction with 10 MOI of HLA-B35 or HLA-B8 Ads for 48 hours (c). 20 µg of nuclear extract were separated via 15% SDS-PAGE for ATF4 and 10% SDS-PAGE for ATF6. 20 µg of total cellular proteins were separated via 15% SDS-PAGE for pPERK/PERK and 10% SDS-PAGE for peIF2α/eIF2α, then transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane. The blots were probed overnight with primary Abs at 4°C. As a control for equal protein loading, membranes were stripped and reprobed for Lamin A/C or β-actin. Representative blots from at least three independent experiments are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>PKR Mediates Activation of the ET-1 Gene in Response to Poly(I:C)</title><p>Protein kinase RNA-activated (PKR) is activated by dsRNA and plays an important role in the IFN signaling <xref rid="pone.0056123-Pfaller1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Similar to PERK, activated PKR induces phosphorylation of eIF2α and a subsequent ATF4 nuclear translocation. To clarify whether activation of PKR is involved in the ET-1 upregulation by Poly(I:C) treatment, we used siRNA approach to knock down PKR. Initial experiments have established an optimal dose and time for PKR siRNA to achieve maximal inhibition of the PKR mRNA level. Treatment of HDMECs with 20 nM of PKR siRNA for 48 hours resulted in depletion of PKR mRNA levels (around 50%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4a</xref>). Following 24 hour incubation with siRNA, cells were treated with Poly(I:C) for additional 24 hours. Under these conditions basal PPET-1 gene expression was downregulated by the siRNA treatment, suggesting that PKR contributes, in part, to the constitutive expression of ET-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4b</xref>). Furthermore, depletion of PKR almost completely abrogated Poly(I:C)-induced stimulation of PPET-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4b</xref>). Interestingly, depletion of PKR upregulated phosphorylated eIF2α (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4c</xref>), as well as nuclear ATF4 level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4d</xref>) in unstimulated cells, suggesting that without activation, PKR may negatively regulate this pathway. However, in the Poly(I:C)-stimulated cells phosphorylation of eIF2α was abrogated and the ATF4 nuclear level was markedly decreased. These results suggest that PKR mediates ET-1 upregulation in response to Poly(I:C) in HDMECs.</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Poly(I:C) induces ET-1 gene through the PKR-dependent activation of the eIF2α/ATF4 pathway.</title><p>80% confluency, HDMECs were treated with 20 nM PKR siRNA (siSCR) with or without Poly(I:C) treatment (a and b). Total RNA was extracted and mRNA level of PKR (a) and PPET1 (b) were quantified by quantitative RT-PCR. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value. 20 µg of nuclear extract were separated via 15% SDS-PAGE for ATF4 (c), 20 µg of total cell lysate were separated via 10% SDS-PAGE for peIF2α/eIF2α (d), then transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane. The blots were probed overnight with primary Abs at 4°C. As a control for equal protein loading, membranes were stripped and reprobed for Lamin A/C or β-actin. Representative blots of at least three experiments are shown. (e) Expression of ATF4 by real-time PCR analysis of skin mRNA from C57B1/6 WT (n = 10), C57B1/6 IFNAR1−/− (n = 8) and C57B1/6 TRIF/TICAM −/− (n = 6) mice 1 week after subcutaneous insertion of osmotic pumps containing Poly(I:C). Fold-change shown in the graphs is normalized to mRNA expression by one of the control mice. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.001 (f) ATF4 protein expression in dermal biopsies obtained from C57Bl/6 WT mice 1 week after subcutaneous insertion of osmotic pumps containing Poly(I:C) or PBS (as control), and processed for immunohistochemistry as described under Methods. Representative images of microvessels from PBS and Poly(I:C) skin is shown. Bar: 20 µm, 10 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>We next investigated whether ATF4 is involved in regulation of ET-1 in the Poly(I:C)-treated mice. It has been previously reported that mice receiving continuous Poly(I:C) injection through the osmotic pump for 7 days showed highly increased expression of ET-1 <xref rid="pone.0056123-Farina1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In addition, this response was abrogated in the TIR-domain-containing adapter-inducing interferon β/Toll-interleukin 1 receptor domain (TIR)-containing adaptor molecule-1 (TRIF/TICAM) deficient mice, and only partially inhibited in the interferon-α/β receptor (IFNAR)-1 deficient mice, indicating that ET-1 induction following Poly(I:C) stimulation is mediated by TLR3. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4e</xref>, expression of ATF4 closely correlated with the previously shown ET-1 expression in the Poly(I:C) treated mice <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Increased expression of ATF4 mRNA was also observed in the Poly(I:C) treated WT mice, but this response was significantly decreased in the TRIF/TICAM−/− mice [WT Poly(I:C) vs TRIF/TICAM−/− Poly(I:C) p = 0.001]. On the other hand, depletion of IFNAR1 had only a modest, non-significant inhibitory effect on the Poly(I:C)-induced ATF4 mRNA level in comparison to WT mice. We next examined the distribution of ATF4 protein in the mouse skin by immunohistochemistry. Analyses of skin showed ATF4 staining in vascular endothelial cells in mouse skin after 1 week of Poly(I:C) infusion, and no staining in PBS infused skin. Unfortunately there were only few visible vessels in the sections analyzed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g004">Fig. 4f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>ATF4 is Required for the Upregulation of ET-1 in Response to HLA-B35/ER Stress and Poly(I:C) in HDMECs</title><p>In order to determine whether ATF4 is directly involved in the regulation of ET-1 gene we employed a siRNA approach to knock down ATF4. Initial experiments established an optimal dose and time for the ATF4 siRNA to achieve maximal inhibition of endogenous ATF4 mRNA level. Treatment of HDMECs with 20 nM ATF4 siRNA for 48 hours resulted in depletion of ATF4 mRNA levels (up to 50–60%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g005">Fig. 5a</xref>). Under these conditions basal expression levels of ET-1 mRNA and protein were also consistently decreased by ∼30% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g005">Fig. 5c and d</xref>). Following 24 hour incubation with siRNA, cells were treated with Ad-B35/GFP (or Ad-B8), TG and Poly(I:C) for additional 24 hours. Depletion of ATF4 completely abolished upregulation of ET-1 mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g005">Fig. 5b</xref>) and protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g005">Fig. 5c</xref>) in response to these treatments, suggesting that ATF4 is required for these responses.</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>ER stress and Poly(I:C) upregulate ET1 via ATF4.</title><p>80% confluency, HDMECs were treated with 20 nM ATF4 siRNA (or siSCR) prior to treatment with HLA-B35 (HLA-B8), TG, or Poly(I:C). Total RNA was extracted and mRNA level of ATF4 (a) and PPET-1 (b) were quantified by quantitative RT-PCR. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value. (c) ET-1 protein was measured by ELISA in the supernatants (n = 2). The average ET-1 protein concentration for each group is represented as a bar ± SE. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.001. (d) ATF4 protein expression in human skin microvessels. Lesional skin biopsies were obtained from patients with lcSSc (with and without PAH) and healthy controls, and processed for immunohistochemistry as described under Methods. Representative images of microvessels from healthy control and lcSSc patients are shown; similar immunostaining pattern was observed in control and lcSSc skin biopsies. Bar: 50 µm, 10 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>We next examined the distribution of ATF4 protein in the human skin by immunohistochemistry. Analyses of skin microvessels showed heteregoneus distribution of ATF4, with some vessels exhibiting strong endothelial cell nuclear staining, while other vessels were negative for ATF4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g005">Fig. 5d</xref>). The number of positive vessels also varied between different individuals. Because patients with SSc have elevated circulating levels of ET-1 <xref rid="pone.0056123-Sulli1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> we also analyzed skin samples obtained from 19 patients with limited cutaneous SSc (lcSSc), including 8 patients with PAH (lcSSc-PAH), and 11 lcSSc-noPAH. Similar to healthy control skin, endothelial cell expression of ATF4 varied between the patients, however there was no overall difference in the intensity or staining pattern between lcSSc and healthy individual biopsies. We did not have information regarding the level of circulating ET-1 or the presence of HLA-B35 antigen in this group of patients. Together, these data indicate that ATF4 is highly expressed in a subset of dermal microvessels, where it is likely involved in responses to various environmental stimuli.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>JNK and NF-κB Contribute to the ER Stress and Poly(I:C) Induction of ET-1</title><p>JNK and NF-κB pathways have been previously reported to contribute to the ET-1 gene expression in response to various stimuli <xref rid="pone.0056123-RodriguezPascual1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Stow1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. To determine if JNK and NF-κB contribute to the upregulation of ET-1 in response to ER stress and TLR3 agonists, cells were treated with HLA-B35, TG, and Poly(I:C) in the presence or absence of the pharmacological inhibitors of these pathways. Treatment with JNK inhibitor (SP6001, 25 nM) resulted in down regulation of the basal and agonist-induced PPET-1 mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g006">Fig. 6a</xref>, top panel). On the other hand<bold>,</bold> basal expression of PPET-1 mRNA was not affected by the NF-κB inhibitor (SN50, 25 nM), however stimulation of PPET1 by HLA-B35, TG, and Poly(I:C) was completely inhibited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g006">Fig. 6b</xref>, top panel <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/jid/journal/v128/n8/full/jid200839a.html">http://www.nature.com/jid/journal/v128/n8/full/jid200839a.html</ext-link> - <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g001">fig. 1</xref>). Similar results were observed at the protein levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g006">Fig. 6a and b</xref>, bottom panels). Interestingly, while stimulation of ET-1 by HLA-B35 or TG was similarly affected by the inhibitors of the JNK and NF-κB pathways, Poly(I:C) stimulation of ET-1 was particularly sensitive to depletion of the NF-κB pathway, suggesting that NF-κB plays a predominant role in activation of the ET-1 gene by Poly(I:C) in HDMECs.</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>JNK and NF-κB contribute to the ER stress and Poly(I:C) induction of ET-1.</title><p>Cells were treated with 25 nM of JNK (a) or NF-κB (b) inhibitors for 3 hours before HLA-B35 (HLA-B8), TG, or Poly(I:C) treatments. Total RNA was extracted and mRNA levels of PPET-1 were quantified by quantitative RT-PCR (top panel). ET-1 protein was measured by ELISA in the supernatants (bottom panel). The average protein concentration for each group (n = 2) is represented as a bar ± SE *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>  = 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>ATF4/c-JUN Complexes Mediate ET-1 Induction by ER Stress and Poly(I:C)</title><p>ET-1 gene promoter contains binding sites for a number of transcription factors, however using bioinformatics tools we were unable to locate consensus ATF4 binding site within the promoter region. Based on the previous report identifying ATF4 as a partner of c-JUN in a two-hybrid screen <xref rid="pone.0056123-Kato1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, we asked whether ATF4 could form protein complexes with c-JUN in HDMECs. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g007">Fig. 7a</xref>, ATF4/c-JUN complexes were present in unstimulated cells and were increased upon stimulation with HLA-B35, TG, and Poly(I:C). While, we could also detect formation of the ATF/NF-κB complexes in unstimulated cells, formation of these complexes was not affected by the agonists (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g007">Fig. 7b</xref>), suggesting that formation of the ATF4/c-JUN complexes is not simply driven by the elevated levels of ATF4 in stimulated cells.</p><fig id="pone-0056123-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056123.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Transcriptional upregulation of ET-1 by ER stress and Poly(I:C) is mediated through the ATF4/cJUN complex.</title><p>Cell lysates from the HLA-B35 (HLA-B8), TG, or Poly(I:C) treated HDMECs were immunoprecipitated with cJUN (a) or NF-κB p65 antibodies (b) and then analyzed for ATF4 by western blot. Cells were transfected with the luciferase reporter driven by the −650/+172–bp fragment of the human ET-1 promoter (c) or with the −193-bp ppET-1-prom-luc construct (wild type) or constructs with specific mutations in the AP-1 binding site (d). 24 hours post transfection with the indicated plasmids, cells were stimulated with HLA-B35 (HLA-B8) Ads, TG and Poly(I:C) for an additional 24 h. Transfections were normalized using pSVgalactosidase control vector. Basal and induced luciferase activity was measured by luminometry. The graph represents fold change in promoter activity in response to various treatments in comparison with control promoter, which was arbitrarily set at 1. (e) Schematic diagram showing PKR and PERK induced activation of the eIF2α-ATF4 axis followed by the protein complex formation with c-JUN and induction of the ET-1 gene transcription through the AP1 response element.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0056123.g007.jpg"/></fig><p>We next utilized human ET-1 promoter constructs consisting of the −650/+172–bp fragment fused to the luciferase reporter gene to confirm functional role of ATF4 in regulation of the ET-1 gene. Transcriptional activation of the ET-1 promoter was observed after treatment with HLA-B35, TG, and Poly(I:C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g007">Fig. 7c</xref>). To analyze whether AP1 binding site was required for the regulation of ET-1 transcription, cells were transfected with the 193-bp ET-1-prom-luc construct (wild type) or the same construct carrying mutated AP-1 binding site. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g007">Fig. 7d</xref>, mutation in the AP1 binding site reduced the ER stress and Poly(I:C) induction of the ET-1 promoter. These results support the functional role of the AP1 complex in the ER stress and Poly(I:C)-mediated induction of the ET-1 gene expression.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we show for the first time that ATF4 is a novel regulator of the ET-1 gene in endothelial cells. ATF4 contributes to the basal expression of ET-1 and is required for the induction of ET-1 in response to both ER stress and dsRNA. Our results strongly suggest that activation of the eIF2α/ATF4 pathway leads to increased formation of the ATF4 protein complexes with c-JUN, which, in turn, activate ET-1 transcription through the AP1 response element. ER stress inducers, including HLA-B35 and TG, as well as dsRNA, also upregulate mRNA and protein expression of ATF4, thus further amplifying this signaling pathway (see diagram, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0056123-g007">Fig. 7e</xref>). Additional experiments show that NF-κB, which is also activated by the ER stress and dsRNA in HDMECs, contributes to the activation of ET-1 gene expression. Interestingly, although, ATF4 forms protein complexes with NF-κB in HDMECs, formation of these complexes was not increased by the stimuli used in our study. Since NF-κB plays a key role in activation of the ET-1 gene by cytokines, it is possible that the ATF4/NF-κB complexes are involved in those responses. Together, this study identifies ATF4 as a key mediator of ET-1 gene activation in response to cellular stress.</p><p>ATF4 is a short-live, basic region-leucine zipper (bZip) protein that belongs to a family of the ATF/CREB transcription factors <xref rid="pone.0056123-Ameri1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Under normal physiological conditions translation of the ATF4 protein is inefficient due to the presence of a short open reading frame in its 5′ untranslated region; however ATF4 protein translation is facilitated by various stress conditions that trigger global inhibition of protein synthesis <xref rid="pone.0056123-Ameri1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Such conditions, including ER stress, viral infection, nutrient starvation, and low levels of heme induce activation of distinct protein kinases that in turn lead to phosphorylation of a common downstream mediator, eIF2αβresulting in translational repression. The known kinases that phosphorylate eIF2α include ER stress induced PERK, dsRNA induced PKR, as well as GCN2 (general control non repressed 2) and heme regulated inhibitor, HRI <xref rid="pone.0056123-Ameri1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Here we show that stimulation of ET-1 in response to Poly(I:C) is mediated by PKR. In a related study Gargalovic et al have reported activation of the eIF2α-ATF4 in human atherosclerotic lesions and in cultured aortic endothelial cells exposed to oxidized phospholipids <xref rid="pone.0056123-Gargalovic1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. The authors demonstrated that ATF4 contributed to the upregulation of several inflammatory cytokines in cultured aortic endothelial cells. ATF4 was also upregulated by herpesvirus 8 infection and contributed to proangiogenic response via MCP1 upregulation <xref rid="pone.0056123-Caselli1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Furthermore, rapid induction of ATF4 has been observed in smooth muscle cells (SMCs) in the medial compartment of balloon injured rat carotid arteries <xref rid="pone.0056123-Malabanan1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Additional studies with cultured SMCs have demonstrated that Fibroblast growth factors (FGF)-2 and mechanical injury stimulate ATF4 levels, and that ATF4 is required for the FGF-2 mediated upregulation of Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)-A <xref rid="pone.0056123-Malabanan1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Our study indicates that ET-1 is among the target genes positively regulated by the eIF2α-ATF4 axis in response to ER stress in endothelial cells. Collectively, these studies support a key role for the eIF2α-ATF4 pathway in response to vascular injury <xref rid="pone.0056123-Malabanan2" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>TLR3 is recognized by viral double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) or its synthetic analog, Poly(I:C), and is expressed on the cell membrane or in the intracellular vesicles, depending on the cell type <xref rid="pone.0056123-Kawai1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Ligand binding to the dimerized TLR3, leads to recruitment of an adaptor protein TRIF/TICAM, which functions as a platform for binding of additional signaling molecules and activation of type I interferon and NF-κB pathways <xref rid="pone.0056123-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Previous studies have shown that activation of TLR3 signaling is harmful to endothelial cells by promoting inflammatory and atherogenic response <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and causing impairment of vessel regeneration in vivo <xref rid="pone.0056123-Zimmer1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Elevated levels of TLR3 were found on fibroblasts, immune and endothelial cells in SSc skin biopsies, thus implicating this pathway in the pathogenesis of SSc <xref rid="pone.0056123-Agarwal1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-vanBon1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. This study extends previous work from our group that demonstrated activation of the markers of vascular injury by dsRNA/Poly(I:C) and potential role of the TLR3 signaling to the pathogenesis of SSc <xref rid="pone.0056123-Lenna1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Several studies have shown that activation of the TLR3 signaling pathway leads to impairment of the endothelial cell function including activation of proinflammatory and pro-atherosclerotic mechanisms <xref rid="pone.0056123-Doukas1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Shibamiya1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. ER stress/UPR, as well as the activation of the innate immunity pathways has been implicated in the pathogenesis of several inflammatory diseases <xref rid="pone.0056123-Rath1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0056123-Martinon1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, however the role of these pathways in PAH and in SSc-related vasculopathy has not yet been explored.</p><p>Endothelial cells constitute a first line of defense protecting tissues from injury. Elevated production of ET-1 is a common characteristic associated with endothelial cell dysfunction in various pathological conditions, including pulmonary arterial hypertension <xref rid="pone.0056123-Chan1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Previous studies have shown that HLA-B35 is associated with an increased risk for developing PAH in patients with scleroderma (SSc) <xref rid="pone.0056123-Scorza1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. The current study further supports the potential pathogenic role of HLA-B35 in upregulating ET-1 production and clarifies the molecular mechanism involved in this process in endothelial cells. In addition, this study raises an intriguing possibility that chronic activation of the eIF2α/ATF4 pathway could contribute to the disease pathogenesis. Although, we were able to demonstrate, activation of ATF4 in selected skin biopsies of patients with lcSSc, absence of full clinical data, including levels of circulating ET-1 and presence of HLA-B35 antigen, precluded proper analyses of these samples. This limitation may be addressed in future studies with a larger set of fully characterized samples from patients with lcSSc.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0056123.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Treatment with mouse monoclonal anti-MHC class I blocking antibody did not affect ET-1 and ATF4 mRNA levels in HDMECs transfected with HLA-B35.</bold> PPET-1 (right panel) and ATF4 (left panel) mRNA after HLA-B35 (or HLA-B8) treatments with increasing dose of mouse monoclonal anti-MHC class I blocking antibody (W6/32) in HDMECs. Confluent dishes of HDMECs were transduced with 10 MOI of Adenovirus encoding HLA-B35/GFP (Ad-HLA-B8/GFP) for 24 h and then with increasing dose of W6/32 (0.1–10 µg/ml) for the following 24 hours. Total RNA was extracted and mRNA levels of PPET-1 and ATF4 were quantified by quantitative RT-PCR. Expression of the housekeeping gene β-actin served as an internal positive control in each assay performed. After measurement of the relative fluorescence intensity for each sample, the amount of each mRNA transcript was expressed as a threshold cycle value.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0056123.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0056123-Kawanabe1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kawanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nauli</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Endothelin</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20848158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-010-0518-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3141212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Shao1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wort</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The role of endothelin-1 in the pathogenesis of pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Res</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21419223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2011.03.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Tsui1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi-Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 in peripheral arterial disease: a potential role in muscle damage</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Res</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21382494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2011.02.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-RodriguezPascual1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Pascual</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Busnadiego</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lagares</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Role of endothelin in the cardiovascular system</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Res</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2011.01.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Stow1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stow</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wingo</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Endothelin-1 gene regulation</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20837776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1096/fj.10-161612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3005421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-RodriguezPascual2"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Pascual</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Redondo-Horcajo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Functional cooperation between Smad proteins and activator protein-1 regulates transforming growth factor-beta-mediated induction of endothelin-1 expression</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1288</fpage>–<lpage>1295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12764024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.RES.0000078491.79697.7F</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Aitsebaomo1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aitsebaomo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kingsley-Kallesen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quertermous</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Vezf1/DB1 is an endothelial cell-specific transcription factor that regulates expression of the endothelin-1 promoter</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>276</volume>: <fpage>39197</fpage>–<lpage>39205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M105166200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Zhang1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>From endoplasmic-reticulum stress to the inflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>454</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18650916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2727659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Rath1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Inflammation and cellular stress: a mechanistic link between immune-mediated and metabolically driven pathologies</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nutr</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21547407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00394-011-0197-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Gargalovic1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gargalovic</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gharavi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The unfolded protein response is an important regulator of inflammatory genes in endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2490</fpage>–<lpage>2496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16931790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.ATV.0000242903.41158.a1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-He1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Viruses, endoplasmic reticulum stress, and interferon responses</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16397582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.cdd.4401833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Martinon1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martinon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glimcher</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>TLR activation of the transcription factor XBP1 regulates innate immune responses in macrophages</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni.1857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3113706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Arnett1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arnett</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moulds</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bias</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Increased prevalence of systemic sclerosis in a Native American tribe in Oklahoma. Association with an Amerindian HLA haplotype</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1362</fpage>–<lpage>1370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8702445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.1780390814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Santaniello1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Santaniello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonioli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>HLA-B35 upregulates the production of endothelin-1 in HLA-transfected cells: a possible pathogenetic role in pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source>Tissue Antigens</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16948645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1399-0039.2006.00657.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Scorza1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scorza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caronni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bazzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nador</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beretta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Post-menopause is the main risk factor for developing isolated pulmonary hypertension in systemic sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>966</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12114278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2002.tb04221.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Lenna1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lenna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapanadze</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>HLA-B35 upregulates endothelin-1 and downregulates endothelial nitric oxide synthase via endoplasmic reticulum stress response in endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>184</volume>: <fpage>4654</fpage>–<lpage>4661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.0903188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3836507</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8459722"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Farina1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>York</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lafyatis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>dsRNA activation of endothelin-1 and markers of vascular activation in endothelial cells and fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/ard.2010.132464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3086552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Lenna2"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<article-title>Lenna S, Townsend DM, Tan FK, Kapanadze B, Markiewicz M, et al. HLA-B35 upregulates endothelin-1 and downregulates endothelial nitric oxide synthase via endoplasmic reticulum stress response in endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>184</volume>: <fpage>4654</fpage>–<lpage>4661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.0903188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3836507</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8459722"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Pfaller1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaller</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase PKR and RNA adenosine deaminase ADAR1: new roles for old players as modulators of the interferon response</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Immunol</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21924887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.coi.2011.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3190076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Sulli1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sulli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soldano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzorni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montagna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Secchi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Raynaud's phenomenon and plasma endothelin: correlations with capillaroscopic patterns in systemic sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19369451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3899/jrheum.081030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Kato1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomizawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Presence of activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4) in the porcine anterior pituitary</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source>
<volume>154</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10509809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0303-7207(99)00078-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Ameri1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ameri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Activating transcription factor 4</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17466566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2007.01.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Caselli1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caselli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grigolato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Luca</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4) is upregulated by human herpesvirus 8 infection, increases virus replication and promotes proangiogenic properties</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>
<volume>157</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22016052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00705-011-1144-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Malabanan1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malabanan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanellakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bobik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khachigian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Activation transcription factor-4 induced by fibroblast growth factor-2 regulates vascular endothelial growth factor-A transcription in vascular smooth muscle cells and mediates intimal thickening in rat arteries following balloon injury</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.107.168682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Malabanan2"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malabanan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khachigian</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Activation transcription factor-4 and the acute vascular response to injury</article-title>. <source>J Mol Med (Berl)</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20306012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00109-010-0615-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Kawai1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The role of pattern-recognition receptors in innate immunity: update on Toll-like receptors</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20404851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni.1863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Yu1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Toll-like receptor, RIG-I-like receptors and the NLRP3 inflammasome: key modulators of innate immune responses to double-stranded RNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21466970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cytogfr.2011.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3109132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Zimmer1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asdonk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Motz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Activation of endothelial toll-like receptor 3 impairs endothelial function</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>
<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>1358</fpage>–<lpage>1366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21493895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.111.243246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Agarwal1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Toll-like receptor 3 upregulation by type I interferon in healthy and scleroderma dermal fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>R3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21223583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/ar3221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3241348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-vanBon1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Bon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radstake</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>An update on an immune system that goes awry in systemic sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Rheumatol</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21885976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/BOR.0b013e32834b0dac</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Doukas1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doukas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mordes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Polyinosinic:polycytidylic acid is a potent activator of endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<volume>145</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7518192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1887295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Shibamiya1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shibamiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hersemeyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt Woll</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sedding</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A key role for Toll-like receptor-3 in disrupting the hemostasis balance on endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>714</fpage>–<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18971420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2008-02-137901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0056123-Chan1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loscalzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pathogenic mechanisms of pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>. <source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17950310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2007.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2234575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>