
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">349</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plospath</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101238921</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3868539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3868539.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3868539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3868539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24385907</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-13-00276</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Toxin-Antitoxin Module of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Promotes Virulence in Mice</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Toxin-Antitoxin Modules in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Virulence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De la Cruz</surname><given-names initials="MA">Miguel A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="W">Weidong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farenc</surname><given-names initials="C">Carine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gimenez</surname><given-names initials="G">Grégory</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names initials="D">Didier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cambillau</surname><given-names initials="C">Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names initials="JP">Jean-Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Méresse</surname><given-names initials="S">Stéphane</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Aix-Marseille University, CIML, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>CNRS, UMR 7280, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>INSERM, U631, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Aix-Marseille University, AFMB, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>CNRS, UMR 7257, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>URMITE, CNRS-IRD UMR 6236, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names initials="MA">Matthew A.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Utah, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>meresse@ciml.univ-mrs.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MADlC CF GG DR CC JPG SM. Performed the experiments: MADlC WZ CF CC SM. Analyzed the data: MADlC WZ CF GG DR CC JPG SM. Wrote the paper: MADlC CF GG CC SM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ecorrected"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">230795</issue-id><elocation-id>e1003827</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-24 13:25:13.230"><day>24</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 De la Cruz et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>De la Cruz et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS Pathog" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7577456"><article-title>Retraction: A Toxin-Antitoxin Module of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Promotes Virulence in Mice</article-title><volume>16</volume><issue>10</issue><date><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>e1009031</elocation-id><source>PLoS Pathogens</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1009031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7577456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33085722</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Toxin-antitoxin (TA) modules are widely prevalent in both bacteria and archaea. Originally described as stabilizing elements of plasmids, TA modules are also widespread on bacterial chromosomes. These modules promote bacterial persistence in response to specific environmental stresses. So far, the possibility that TA modules could be involved in bacterial virulence has been largely neglected, but recent comparative genomic studies have shown that the presence of TA modules is significantly associated with the pathogenicity of bacteria. Using <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> as a model, we investigated whether TA modules help bacteria to overcome the stress conditions encountered during colonization, thereby supporting virulence in the host. By bioinformatics analyses, we found that the genome of the pathogenic bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium encodes at least 11 type II TA modules. Several of these are conserved in other pathogenic strains but absent from non-pathogenic species indicating that certain TA modules might play a role in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> pathogenicity. We show that one TA module, hereafter referred to as <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>, plays a transient role in virulence in perorally inoculated mice. The use of a transcriptional reporter demonstrated that bacteria in which <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is strongly activated are predominantly localized in the mesenteric lymph nodes. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> was shown to be important for the survival of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> in these peripheral lymphoid organs. These data indicate that the transient activation of a type II TA module can bring a selective advantage favouring virulence and demonstrate that TA modules are engaged in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> pathogenesis.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the ANR (ANR-09-BLAN-0296-01), CNRS, INSERM, Aix-Marseille Université and the Fondation Méditerranée Infection. MADlC was funded by the Fondation Infectiopole-Sud and the CONACYT. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="ppat-1003827-box001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec id="s1a"><title>Authors Summary</title><p>Bacteria have the capacity to rapidly adapt to and survive ever-changing environments. This aptitude is essential for a foodborne pathogen that upon ingestion by a host, and in a short period of time, will switch from a free-living state in the contaminated food to a parasitic existence in a host. During this process, the pathogen has to face various destructive surroundings such as the gastric acid of the stomach, the antimicrobiotic activities of the intestinal milieu, or the host immune defences. This raises the question of how a pathogen achieves this rapid adaptation. Bacteria are capable of regulating their biochemical activity with the help of self-toxins. These toxins are normally associated with an antitoxin that limits their toxic activity. In response to unfavourable environmental conditions, the toxin is rapidly freed from the antitoxin and slows down the biological activity of the bacterium. This makes the bacterium less sensitive to harmful environments. In the present study, we investigated whether the bacterial pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> possesses similar self-protecting systems and if they are necessary for virulence. We found that these systems are present in pathogenic species of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and help the bacterium establish an infection.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec id="s2"><title>Introduction</title><p>Prokaryotic genomes contain toxin–antitoxin (TA) loci that induce cell dormancy in response to various stresses <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Gerdes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. This is mediated by the toxin components that target essential cellular processes, such as DNA replication, mRNA stability or protein synthesis (for review see <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>). Five types of TA systems have been described. In type I and III, the antitoxin is a RNA molecule that either regulates toxin gene expression (type I) or forms a complex with the toxin protein and inhibits its activity (type III) <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Fineran1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The recently described type IV and V systems refer to protein-protein modules in which the antitoxin masks the toxin activity either by interfering with binding of the toxin to its target (type IV) <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Masuda1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> or by cleaving specifically the toxin mRNA (type V) <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. In type II modules, toxin and antitoxin are proteins that are co-transcribed from an operon. By binding its cognate toxin, the antitoxin blocks the toxin activity. Very often, the antitoxin binds to a palindromic stretch within the promoter region and represses the transcription of the operon. Environmental conditions that favour the degradation of the labile antitoxin raise the level of free toxin and also relieve the expression inhibition of the TA locus. This regulation loop maintains a high level of free toxin as long as the conditions supporting the antitoxin degradation are sustained.</p><p>Type II TA modules are widely prevalent in prokaryotes. In 2009, a genomic analysis in 750 complete genomes of archaea and bacteria discovered previously unnoticed protein families that are homologous to toxins and antitoxins of known type II TA and highlighted their exceptional mobility <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Makarova1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. A comprehensive search on 2181 prokaryotic genomes detected more than 10000 sequences that were grouped within toxin (12) and antitoxin (20) super-families <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Leplae1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. These systems have been proposed to be beneficial in hostile conditions by favouring persistence <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Lewis1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. However, the circumstances under which TA modules are activated and support bacterial persistence remain poorly understood.</p><p>A study published in 2005 established that TA modules are abundant in free-living prokaryotes but rare in obligate host-associated organisms <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. It led to the conclusion that TA modules are stress-response elements that increase the fitness of free-living prokaryotes. However, more recent data reported the presence of TA modules in pathogenic intracellular bacteria <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Leplae1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and a significant association with the pathogenicity of epidemic bacteria <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Georgiades1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> contains more than 60 TA systems, while the saprophytic <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> has only two <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Ricketsia</italic> spp., which are obligate intracellular pathogens, possesses up to 32 TA modules <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Leplae1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and are capable of inducing host cell death in a TA-dependent manner <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Audoly1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Elsewhere it has been established that TA modules can promote the colonization of the mouse bladder or kidneys by an uropathogenic strain of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Norton1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Hence, there is increasing evidence that TA modules are related to bacterial pathogenicity and involved in host-pathogen interactions.</p><p>Salmonellae are Gram-negative bacteria responsible for severe gastroenteritis and systemic infections in humans. These bacteria are widespread and commonly found in the intestinal tract of cold- and warm-blooded animals and in the environment where their association with protozoa such as amoebae is thought to favour persistence and transmission <xref rid="ppat.1003827-DouesnardMalo1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Bleasdale1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Salmonellae must therefore have evolved mechanisms to rapidly adapt to the multitude of environmental conditions encountered either as free-living organism or as a pathogen in association with a host. The present study investigated the presence of type II TA loci in strains of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and their possible role in virulence.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Identification of type II TA modules in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium</title><p>Bioinformatics analysis using the RASTA-Bacteria webtool <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Sevin1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> and BLASTP of already identified toxins and antitoxins confirmed the presence of eleven type II TA modules in the <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium) genome, nine located on the chromosome and two in the virulence plasmid (pSLT) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1003827-t001">Table 1</xref>). They belong to five distinct super-families of toxins (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1003827-t001">Table 1</xref>) <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Jrgensen1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Two of these modules (STM2954.1N-STM2955.S, STM4032.2N-STM4033) have been previously identified in <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium LT2 <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, while the <italic toggle="yes">vapBC</italic> locus (STM 3033-STM3034) has been shown to be a bona fide type II TA loci <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Winther1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Of note, we could not establish any correspondence between six other TA modules described in the afore-mentioned study <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> and the other TA modules described herein.</p><table-wrap id="ppat-1003827-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Identification and family distribution of <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium TA loci.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="ppat-1003827-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Module (The gene of the operon coding for the toxin is underlined)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homologue (based on the toxin)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superfamily</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM1550</underline>-STM1551</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">relEB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Gotfredsen1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM2954.1N</underline>-STM2955.S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">mazEF</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MazF</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Aizenman1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM3033</underline>-STM3034</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">vapBC</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. flexneri</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VapC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Winther1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM3516</underline>-STM3517</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">dinJ</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">yafQ</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Motiejnait1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM3558</underline>-STM3559</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">phd</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">doc</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Hazan1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM3777</underline>-STM3778</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">relEB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Gotfredsen1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STM4030.S-<underline>STM4031</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">higBA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">V. cholerae</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard2" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>STM4032.2N</underline>-STM4033</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">higBA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Pandey1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STM4449-<underline>STM4450</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">relEB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RelE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Gotfredsen1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSLT027-<underline>PSLT028</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ccdAB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcdB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Afif1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>PSLT106</underline>-PSLT107</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">vapBC</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. flexneri</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VapC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Winther1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The genus <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> comprises two species, <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic>. The majority of human infections are caused by various serovars of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> while <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic> does not cause disease in mammals <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Bumler1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. We used BLASTP of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium chromosomal toxins and genomic context analyses to examine sequenced genomes of Salmonellae for homologs of these TA systems. Using an in-house R script <xref rid="ppat.1003827-RDC1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, we performed a hierarchical clustering based on the Euclidean distance for the presence or absence of TA modules in the studied genomes as illustrated in the heatmap in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1A</xref>. The clustering of bacteria in the horizontal dendrogram indicates the presence of two main clusters. The first cluster consists of serovars of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic>, which are associated with warm-blooded host, that have between five and eight of the nine chromosomal TA modules found in <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> Typhimurium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Interestingly, four of these TA modules are present in all serovars of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic>. The second cluster comprises subspecies <italic toggle="yes">houtenae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">arizonae</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic>, which infect cold-blooded animals and the non-pathogenic species <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic>. The subspecies <italic toggle="yes">houtenae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">arizonae</italic> present a low number of modules (two and four, respectively), while none are present in <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic>. These analyses indicate that TA modules detected in <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium are more prevalent in strains associated with warm-blooded hosts as compared to strains that infect cold-blooded animals. They also suggest a role in pathogenesis since these TA modules are absent from the non-pathogenic species <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic>.</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Conservation of TA modules across the genus <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The toxins of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium TA modules were subjected to BLASTP against various <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> strains. Serovars of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic> are coloured in red. <italic toggle="yes">Arizonae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">houtenae</italic> subspecies of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> are coloured in blue. The non-pathogenic species <italic toggle="yes">bongori</italic> is coloured in green. All sequences were taken of NCBI and ColiBASE databases. Gene products were clustered according to their presence (black) or absence (light grey). Incomplete modules are indicated in dark grey. (<bold>B</bold>) Genetic organization of the STM4031-STM4030.S and STM4032.2N-STM4033 modules in <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium chromosome. Toxin genes are coloured in blue and antitoxin genes in green. A single gene, STM4032 (in orange), separates the two TA modules. The promoter regions of the TA operons are shown as a blow-up. Putative transcriptional start sites are shown as broken arrows. Start sites of the first gene in the TA operons are shown in green bold letters. Putative −10 and −35 sequences are boxed. Palindromic sequences that are putative antitoxin binding sites are shown as opposing arrows.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>The toxin components of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> are moderately toxic or non toxic for <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> grown in artificial media</title><p>To assess the putative functions of these modules, we expressed the predicted toxins in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> from an inducible promoter. The growth in Luria-Bertani (LB) broth of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains was measured over a period of 8 hours. A group of five proteins (group 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2A</xref>) exerted a strong bacteriostatic effect in E. coli. The expression of seven other putative toxins (group 2) only slightly attenuated bacterial growth, suggesting that these proteins are either not toxins or that their toxicity is limited in a heterologous expression system.</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effect of toxins and antitoxins on bacterial growth.</title><p>Bacteria were grown at 37°C in LB broth and the optical density was monitored (<bold>A</bold> &amp; <bold>C</bold>) or the colony forming units (CFU) were enumerated (<bold>B</bold>). (<bold>A</bold>) Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> toxins over-expression on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> growth. BL21(DE3) cells were transformed with an empty pDEST17 (ctrl) or derived plasmids carrying the putative <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium toxin genes. Toxin expression was induced by adding 1 mM IPTG 2 hr after inoculation. Group 1: STM2954.1n, STM3516, STM3558, PSLT028. Group 2: STM1550, STM3033, STM3777, STM4031, STM4032.2N, STM4450, PSLT106. (<bold>B</bold> &amp; <bold>C</bold>) Growth kinetics of wild-type (WT) and <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium. When indicated, strains were complemented with pDEST49-derivative vectors for the expression of SehA, SehB or SehD under the control of the arabinose-inducible promoter.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, we focused our studies on TA modules present in all <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> strains capable of infecting warm-blooded animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). More precisely, we targeted STM4031-STM4030.S and STM4032.2N-STM4033, which presented a close chromosomal location, being separated by a single unrelated gene, and encode transcripts on opposite chromosome strands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><p>STM4031-4030.S encodes proteins presenting 40% and 46% identity with HigB and HigA from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (Taxonomy ID 83333), respectively. The product of STM4032.2N presents 72% identity with HigB of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (Taxonomy ID 561). While both STM4030.S and STM4033 products possess an HTH-XRE DNA binding domain that is found in type II antitoxins, they do not present significant shared similarity (7.7% identity). Likewise, the toxic components (STM4031 and STM4032.2N) show only 11.6% identity and none exerted strong toxicity in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (Group 2 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). We renamed these TA gene locus <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><underline>S</underline>almonella <underline>e</underline>nterica</italic>
<underline>H</underline>ig-like) modules. Hence, STM4031-STM4030.S and STM4032.2N-STM4033 correspond to <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>We examined the chromosomal location and organization of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> locus in several strains of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>. A bioinformatics analysis revealed that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> are not present in genomic islands, yet a cluster of genes similar to that found in S. Typhimurium was present in all strains of the species <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic> (except <italic toggle="yes">arizonae</italic> in which <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is missing), (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s001">Figure S1</xref>). This cluster of genes has a conserved chromosomal location and is missing in the species <italic toggle="yes">bongori</italic>.</p><p>We generated various <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium mutants of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> and evaluated the impact of these deletions on bacterial growth. While deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">higA</italic> antitoxin gene in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-FivianHughes1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio cholerae</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Budde1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> or <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Hood1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> is lethal, we were able to generate <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> mutants deleted of either antitoxin gene. A mutant deleted of the gene coding for the SehB antitoxin (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic>) formed tiny colonies on agar plates and grew slower than the wild-type strain in LB broth, while over-expression of the SehA toxin limited the growth of the wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). No growth change was observed in absence of the toxin (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic>) or in absence of the module (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>). Thus, the bacteriostatic effect was observed where there was excess of toxin or in the absence of antitoxin, suggesting that SehAB functions as a toxin-antitoxin system. The growth defect of <italic toggle="yes">ΔsehB</italic> was complemented by plasmid for the expression of the antitoxin (pSehB) under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">ara</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). Of note this complementation was also observed in absence of arabinose probably because of low level of expression. Remarkably, a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> mutant over-expressing SehB grew faster and to a higher density than the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). This suggests that SehA limits the growth of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium in a way that might reflect the topological organization of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> operon in which the SehA toxin is transcribed first and may therefore be more abundant than its cognate antitoxin. However, wild-type and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> strains had similar growth curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2B</xref>) and a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> strain over-grew when its cognate antitoxin was over-expressed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s002">Figure S2A</xref>). These data indicate that the SehB antitoxin not only neutralizes its cognate toxin, but is also beneficial for <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> growth in a toxin-independent manner.</p><p>The Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehC</italic>, Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehD</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> mutant strains were indistinguishable from the parental strain indicating that the toxin component is not limiting bacterial growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s002">Figure S2B</xref>). However, over-expression of the SehD antitoxin was able to partially complement for the absence of SehB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). Therefore we tested if SehD supported the growth of a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> mutant, as this mutant was unexpectedly viable. This hypothesis was tested by deleting <italic toggle="yes">sehD</italic> in a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> strain. We obtained a viable mutant deleted of both antitoxin genes (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehD</italic>) indicating that SehD is not required for <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> growth in absence of SehB and <italic toggle="yes">vice versa</italic>. Altogether, these results indicate that, in LB broth, the SehC toxin does not impair <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium growth while SehA exerts a non-lethal toxicity that is neutralized by its cognate antitoxin.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>The antitoxin components of SehAB and SehCD repress their own transcription</title><p>We undertook a biochemical and biophysical characterization of SehAB and SehCD and checked whether these modules regulate their own expression by binding palindromic sequences in their promoter region as expected for type II TA systems <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. We found two perfect or near perfect palindromic sequences in the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoter regions, which overlap with the putative −35 and/or −10 sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). To test whether SehB and SehD repress the expression of their operons, we generated plasmid-based transcriptional reporters by fusing the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoter regions to the <italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic>mut3a gene. Bacteria carrying these reporter constructs were grown in LB broth and the fluorescence level of bacteria was monitored by flow cytometry <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Aussel1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. The expressions of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> transcriptional fusions were 50- and 10-fold increased, respectively, in the absence of their relevant antitoxin or module, whereas the absence of the cognate toxin alone did not modify GFP expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). By combining transcriptional reporters, mutants and plasmids we found that SehB does not repress SehCD expression and <italic toggle="yes">vice versa</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s003">Figure S3</xref>). This was predictable given that palindromic sequences and the nucleotide sequences between the palindromes are distinct in <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoter regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g001">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>SehB and SehD antitoxins bind to their promoter region.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expressions of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> are de-repressed in absence of their relevant antitoxin. <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium wild-type (WT) and various mutant strains carrying a transcriptional fusion <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> were grown in LB broth and samples were taken at 4 hr post-inoculation. The relative fluorescence intensity of bacteria was determined by flow cytometry. Between 5000 and 10.000 bacteria were analysed to calculate the mean GFP/bacterium. (<bold>B</bold>) The SehB antitoxin binds specifically to its promoter region. An Electrophoretic mobility shift assay was carried out by incubating 100 ng PCR products covering <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> (22.5 nM) or STM3558-59 (20 nM) promoter regions and increasing amounts [His]<sub>6</sub>-SehB as indicated. The complexes were separated on 6% polyacrylamide gels and DNA stained. (<bold>C</bold>) Surface Plasmon Resonance analysis of the binding of purified SehB to immobilized dsDNA. Sensorgrams for the interaction of various concentrations of SehB (62.5, 125, 250, 500 and 1000 nM) with immobilized DNA (300 resonance units). Inset shows fitting curve for equilibrium binding that resulted in a K<sub>D</sub> of 150±30 nM. (<bold>D</bold>) SehA is pulled-down by SehB. Purified GST or GST-SehB were incubated with an extract a <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells over-expressing [His]<sub>6</sub>-SehA or [His]<sub>6</sub>-SehC. After washing, proteins bound to glutathione-beads were separated by SDS-PAGE and analysed either by Coomassie blue staining of the acrylamide gel or by electrotransfer on a PVDF membrane and Western Blotting using an anti-[His]<sub>6</sub> antibody.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, we investigated if the antitoxin-mediated repression was due to direct binding of antitoxins to their promoter regions <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. We performed electrophoresis mobility shift assays (EMSA) using purified [His]<sub>6</sub>-tagged versions of antitoxins and PCR products covering the promoter regions of the operons. Both antitoxins specifically bound to their respective <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> promoter region in a concentration-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figures 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s004">S4</xref>), but not to the STM3559-58 promoter region used as a control. SehB and SehD bound with high affinity since the formation of the promoter DNA-antitoxin complexes reached a plateau below 250 and 500 nM, respectively. By comparison, the binding saturation of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> HigA to its promoter required one hundred times more concentrated protein <xref rid="ppat.1003827-FivianHughes1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. We used Surface Plasmon Resonance to better characterize the interaction between SehB and its promoter region. We immobilized a biotinylated DNA oligomer corresponding to the sequence of the first palindrome of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> promoter on a streptavidin chip, and assayed the binding of purified SehB. We measured a K<sub>D</sub> of 150±30 nM, thus confirming the high affinity of SehB for this palindromic sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figure 3C</xref>).</p><p>Using size-exclusion chromatography coupled with online multiangle laser light scattering (ultra-violet light absorbance and refractive index detectors) we characterized the formation of complexes between the SehAB proteins and the DNA palindromic sequence. We observed that purified SehB formed a stable dimer at 32 kDa (theoretical mass 31.4 kDa) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s005">Figure S5</xref>). In the presence of DNA, we observed a mass of 34.4 kDa for the antitoxin dimer, of 14.6 KDa (theoretical mass 14.0 kDa) for the dsDNA, and of 49 kDa for the complex. We found that purified SehA formed a tetramer and higher aggregate but we were unsuccessful at reconstituting a toxin-antitoxin or a ternary complex using these purified proteins. However, GST-SehB specifically pulled-down [His]<sub>6</sub>-SehA from a bacterial extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). This indicates that proteins of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> module are capable of interacting. We concluded that repression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> transcription is mediated by the binding of either the SehAB toxin-antitoxin complex or the SehB homo-dimer to its promoter region.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Transcription of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> locus is modulated by environmental conditions</title><p>Antitoxins of type II systems are believed to be more prone to proteolytic degradation than their cognate toxins. It results in increased availability of toxins as well as increased transcription of TA operons. In order to compare the stability of SehA and SehB, we constructed <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium strains chromosomally expressing either SehA-3XFLAG or SehB-3XFLAG. These strains were grown for 6 hours in minimal medium after which protein synthesis was blocked with chloramphenicol. The level of pre-existing FLAG-tagged SehA and SehB was monitored during 60 min by Western Blotting. While the SehA toxin was remarkably stable, we noticed a marked decrease in SehB antitoxin signal during this period of time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). This result shows that SehB is labile as compared to SehA. Next, we determined if the transcriptional activity of <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> loci is modulated in response to conditions encountered during interactions with animal cells. Wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium and <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> locus mutant strains carrying <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic> transcriptional reporters were used to infect RAW 264.7 mouse macrophages. These strains were also grown in minimal medium, which is known to induce the expression of genes necessary for intracellular survival/replication <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Linehan1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. As control, we used a transcriptional reporter for <italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic>, which is required for intracellular replication and is up-regulated in these growth conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). As compared to bacteria grown in LB broth, fluorescence resulting from expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> in wild-type <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> increased significantly both in minimal medium (4.3 times) and in macrophages (3 times) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). We observed a very similar profile of transcriptional activity in the absence of SehA, thus confirming that the toxin does not play a significant role in the regulation of the operon activity. As shown previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g003">Figure 3A</xref>), the transcriptional activity of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> increased dramatically in the absence of the antitoxin (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic>) or the full module (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>). Yet, in spite of the strong de-repression due to the absence of the antitoxin, <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> expression was still approximately 1.5 times more increased in mutant strains grown in minimal medium as compared to LB broth. These results suggest that in addition of the repression mediated by the antitoxin, the transcriptional activity of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> promoter is controlled by additional regulatory elements which are at least partly dependent on environmental conditions. The expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic> increased about three and 1.5 times in bacteria grown in minimal medium or in macrophages, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoter was insensitive to the absence of either or both SehAB proteins. We concluded that the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> loci responds to conditions encountered inside host cells, therefore suggesting this module might influence the intracellular growth of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium.</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Regulation of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoters and role of SehAB proteins in intracellular replication.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) SehB is prone to degradation. Strains expressing chromosomally SehB-3XFLAG or SehA-3XFLAG were grown for 6 hours in minimal medium. 100 µg/ml chloramphenicol was then added and samples were taken at the indicated times. The presence of remaining SehA and SehB was analysed by Western Blotting using an anti-FLAG antibody. (<bold>B</bold> &amp; <bold>C</bold>) Expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> is de-repressed in minimal medium and inside mouse macrophages. Wild-type (WT) <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium and <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains carrying the transcriptional fusion <italic toggle="yes">sifA-gfp</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic> were grown in LB broth, minimal medium (MM) or inside RAW 264.7 mouse macrophages. Bacteria were collected at 4 (LB) or 16 (MM) hours post-inoculation or extracted from macrophages 16 hours post-infection. The relative GFP fluorescence intensity of bacteria was determined by flow cytometry. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is dispensable for intracellular replication. C57BL/6 bone marrow-derived macrophages were infected with wild-type (WT) or various <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains. Δ<italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">ssaV</italic> strains were used as controls. Cells were lysed at 2, 8 and 14 hr post-infection for enumeration of intracellular bacteria. A representative experiment is shown. The graph values are the mean colony forming units (CFU) per well ± SD of triplicates. The “fold replication” for the presented experiment was calculated as a ratio of the intracellular bacteria between 14 and 2 hr. The “normalized replication” represent the fold increase calculated as a ratio of the intracellular bacteria between 16 and 2 hr and normalized to that of the wild-type strain (100%). Values are means ± SD of 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> are dispensable for intracellular replication</title><p>Cell lines and primary cells were used to investigate the potential role of <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> modules in intracellular replication of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>. Bone marrow-derived macrophages (BMM) were infected with <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains and the numbers of intracellular bacteria were determined at 2, 8 and 14 hours post-infection. We also calculated the relative fold increase of intracellular bacteria between 2 and 14 h post-infection with respect to the wild-type strain (100%). As expected, we observed at 14 hours post-infection a dramatic replication defect for the control Δ<italic toggle="yes">ssaV</italic> mutant strain <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Hensel1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). Bacteria deleted of <italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Stein1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> presented a moderate intracellular replication defect (relative fold increase of 48±6% and 43±3%, respectively). Mutants deleted for <italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> or the full module (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>) replicated similar to the wild-type strain, indicating that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is dispensable for replication inside BMM.</p><p>The intracellular replication of <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> mutants was also tested in human HeLa cells and RAW 264.7 mouse macrophages. We also observed in these cell lines a moderate intracellular replication defect for the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> mutant while deletion of either or both <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> genes had no effect (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s006">Figure S6A</xref>). Strains over-expressing either antitoxin replicated more than twice as much as the control, whether the absence or presence of their cognate toxin or module (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s007">Figure S7</xref>).</p><p>Next we tested whether the replication defect of a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> antitoxin mutant could be attributed, at least in part, to a direct toxic effect of the SehA toxin on eukaryotic cells. Infected macrophages were stained with fluorescent markers for death and early apoptosis and analyzed by flow cytometry. Infection by <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> increased the percentage of cells positive for both markers from about 1 to 10%, no matter which strain was used (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s008">Figure S8</xref>). These results indicate that the presence of high level of free SehA toxin in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> does not impact the viability of infected cells.</p><p>We concluded that i) SehAB and SehCD are dispensable for intracellular replication, ii) Over-expression of either antitoxin confers to <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> an intracellular hyper-replicative phenotype similar to that observed in LB broth, and iii) The moderate intracellular growth defect of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> strain is likely nonspecific and rather results from a general growth defect for this strain.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>SehAB is a virulence factor in perorally inoculated mice</title><p>We compared the virulence of wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">seh</italic> mutant strains in mice by performing mixed infections. As controls, we again used the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">ssaV</italic> strains that respectively, are moderately and highly attenuated in this model <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Shea1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>–<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Beuzn1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Groups of C57BL/6 mice were inoculated intraperitoneally with different two strain combinations (1∶1 mix) and bacteria were recovered from mouse spleens after 2 days to determine the competitive index (CI) <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Beuzn2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. We found that the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> antitoxin mutant is highly attenuated with respect to the wild-type strain (CI = 0.02±0.01). Remarkably, this attenuation is more pronounced and similar to that observed with the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic> (CI = 0.16±0.05) and Δ<italic toggle="yes">ssaV</italic> strains (CI = 0.01±0.003) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). Complementation with a plasmid for the expression of SehB allowed the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> mutant to recover virulence (CI = 0.75±0.2), while the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains displayed a wild-type level of virulence. These results demonstrate that, while the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> module is dispensable for systemic infection, SehA exerts <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> a very strong toxic action that is neutralized by its cognate antitoxin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5A</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is transiently involved in Salmonella virulence upon peroral inoculation.</title><p>Mice were inoculated intraperitoneally (<bold>A</bold>) or perorally (<bold>B</bold> &amp; <bold>C</bold>) with a 1∶1 mixture of two <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> strains as indicated. C57BL/6 mice we used, except for panel C for which 129S2 and C57BL/6 mice were infected as indicated. Spleens were harvested two days (<bold>A</bold>), five days (<bold>B</bold>) or at various times (<bold>C</bold>) post-inoculation and bacteria were enumerated. The lowest and highest total CFU/organ in each group of CI were in (<bold>B</bold>) WT <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> : Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>, 8.7×10<sup>5</sup>–2.3×10<sup>7</sup>; Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic>, 2.3×10<sup>5</sup>–1.9×10<sup>8</sup>; Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic>, 4.3×10<sup>3</sup>–2.5×10<sup>7</sup>; Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> pSehAB, 5.2×10<sup>4</sup>–1.3×10<sup>8</sup>; Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>, 6×10<sup>5</sup>–1.4×10<sup>7</sup>; (<bold>C</bold>) WT <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> in 129S2: Day 5, 2.8×10<sup>3</sup>-1.3×10<sup>4</sup>; day 14, 3.6×10<sup>4</sup>-6×10<sup>4</sup>; day 18, 2.5×10<sup>4</sup>-1.2×10<sup>6</sup>; in C57BL/6: 8.7×10<sup>5</sup>-6.2×10<sup>6</sup>. Each symbol represents a mouse and horizontal bars correspond to the means ± SD. A one-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used to determine whether a CI was significantly different of one, and unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests to determine whether two values were significantly different. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values: ns, not significant; *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; **, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.01; ***, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, we tested if this module could play a role in mice inoculated by the natural route. We found that by peroral inoculation, a strain deleted of <italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> also presents a strong virulence defect (CI = 0.16±0.06) while bacteria deleted of the toxin are unaffected (CI∼1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Interestingly, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> strain is significantly attenuated (CI∼0.50) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5B and 5C</xref>) but complemented by a plasmid expressing SehAB under its natural promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). We also examined the role of SehAB in 129S2 mice carrying wild-type alleles of Nramp1. 129S2 mice have been used to develop a model of persistent <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium infection <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Ruby1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Monack1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> and we took advantage of the prolonged survival of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>-infected 129S2 mice to analyze the evolution of the CI with time. At five days post-inoculation, a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> strain presented in 129S2 mice an attenuation (CI = 0.64±0.24) similar to that observed in C57BL/6 mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). Surprisingly, this value did not decrease to a great extent with time but rather tended to reach a plateau (CI = 0.41±0.05 at day eighteen post-inoculation, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). These results suggest that after an initial deficiency in establishing an infection by the natural route, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant is able to persist as well as the wild-type strain. It confirms that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> does not play a significant role in the systemic infection. Rather, this module is involved in the early phase of peroral infection.</p><p>Strains deleted of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> or of both <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> were not significantly different in their virulence attenuation when given perorally to C57BL/6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). This indicates that the <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> module, whose toxin does not seem to be active in mice (Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehD</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g005">Figure 5A</xref>), does not contribute significantly to <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> virulence in the mouse model.</p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is highly transcribed in mesenteric lymph nodes and is required for survival of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> in these organs</title><p>The attenuation of a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant suggested that upon peroral inoculation <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> encounters conditions favouring the enhanced transcription of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> locus. To confirm this, we inoculated mice with wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium carrying a transcriptional reporter for <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic>). Bacteria extracted from various organs were examined for the expression of GFP by flow cytometry and compared to reference strains grown in LB broth. Most <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> extracted from the mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN) of perorally inoculated mice showed GFP fluorescence levels (blue curve, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6A</xref>) that were slightly higher than that of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium grown in LB broth (green curve, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). This indicates that the majority of bacteria in the MLNS exhibit slightly higher expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>. Yet, we also observed in MLNs a second population with a mean GFP fluorescence similar to that observed for the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> strain grown in LB broth (red curve, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). This population, hereafter referred to as GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria, corresponded to <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> in which expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is de-repressed. This GFP<sup>high</sup> population although not exceeding 5% of the total <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> population, was however significantly more prevalent in spleens and MLNs of mice inoculated <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the peroral route (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). The mean fluorescence of total bacteria was also significantly increased in populations extracted from perorally but not from intraperitoneally inoculated mice, when compared to bacteria grown in LB broth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). Finally, in perorally inoculated mice, the mean fluorescence of GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria was significantly higher in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> extracted form MLNs in comparison to their corresponding spleens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). Considering that having crossed the intestinal barrier the bacteria will reach the MLNs before the spleen <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Carter1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, these results indicate that activation of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> module is an early event in the process of infection through oral ingestion. To further emphasise this point we also analysed the consequences of the deletion of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> on the virulence attenuation of bacteria present in various organs. We found that the CI of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> strains is much lower in MLNs (0.05±0.03) as compared to the spleen (0.51±0.19) and the liver (0.32±0.02) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1003827-g006">Figure 6D</xref>). These results reveal that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is especially important for the survival of bacteria in MLNs.</p><fig id="ppat-1003827-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003827.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is highly transcribed in a small population of bacteria upon peroral inoculation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) C57BL/6 mice were inoculated intraperitoneally or perorally as indicated with wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium carrying a transcriptional fusion <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic>. The relative GFP fluorescence intensity of bacteria extracted from the spleen or MLNs was determined by flow cytometry. Between 5000 and 10.000 bacteria were analysed for each sample. (<bold>A</bold>) A small population of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> extracted from infected mice are highly fluorescent. Bacteria were extracted from MLNs of a mouse five days post-peroral inoculation. Bacteria were analyzed by flow cytometry for GFP fluorescence (blue) and compared to bacteria used for the inoculation (green) and, as control, with a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> strain (red). Bacteria extracted from MLNs contain a population expressing a high level of GFP (GFP<sup>high</sup>). (<bold>B</bold>) The percentage of GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria is significantly higher in mice inoculated perorally <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> intraperitoneally. Bacteria were extracted from spleens or MLNs of mice inoculated intraperitoneally or perorally and the percentages of GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria were determined. (<bold>C</bold>) The mean GFP fluorescence of total and GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria is significantly increased in bacteria extracted from perorally inoculated mice and significantly higher in MLN <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> spleen. The mean GFP fluorescence was normalized to that of bacteria used for inoculation. (<bold>D</bold>) The CI of wild-type versus Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is lower for the population of bacteria extracted from MLNs. C57BL/6 mice were inoculated perorally with a 1∶1 mixture of wild-type and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> strains. Spleen, liver, MLNs and the small intestine (S. I.) were collected five days post-inoculation and bacteria were enumerated. Each symbol represents a mouse, and horizontal bars correspond to the means ± SD. The lowest and highest total CFU/organ in each group of CI were in : spleen, 8.8×10<sup>6</sup>-7.5×10<sup>7</sup>; Liver, 7×10<sup>7</sup>-2.1×10<sup>8</sup>; MLNs, 6.5×10<sup>4</sup>-1.9×10<sup>5</sup>; S. I., 7.1×10<sup>5</sup>-5×10<sup>6</sup>. (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) A one-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was used to determine whether a value was significantly different of one and an unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests to determine whether two values were significantly different. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values: ns, not significant; *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; **, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.01; ***, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Type II TA modules are inhibitors of translation that induce bacterial dormancy. Being in a dormant state helps bacteria to survive harmful environments. For example, type II TA modules favour resistance to antibiotics <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Gerdes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. This study presents evidence that virulent strains of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> possess multiple TA systems and shows that one of these is beneficial in the early phase of infection by the natural route.</p><p>We ascertained the presence of eleven type II TA modules in <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium and examined the presence of homologous genes across Salmonellae. A heatmap generated using both strains and TA gene modules highlighted a set of four TA that are found across serovars of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> infecting warm-blooded animals. In contrast, non-pathogenic species and strains of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic>, which are associated with cold-blooded animals, possess no or low numbers of TA modules found in <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> Typhimurium, respectively. Interestingly, previous data extracted from a transcriptional profile of intracellular <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Eriksson1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> showed that the expression of the eleven TA modules is induced during infection of mouse macrophages, thus highlighting the possible involvement of these modules during the interaction with host cells.</p><p>It is important to note that the present study did neither perform an exhaustive review of TA modules in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonellae</italic>, nor investigate whether the non-pathogenic species <italic toggle="yes">S. bongori</italic> or strains infecting cold-blooded animals have specific TA module repertoires. It is very likely that other TA systems exist and will be discovered as illustrated by the recently published study by Slattery et al. <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Slattery1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>
</p><p>These TA operons, which are part of the prokaryotic mobilome <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Koonin1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, are likely to have been acquired by horizontal transfer and positively selected because of their advantage for pathogenesis. Strikingly, the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> loci delineate a gene cluster that has a conserved location on chromosomes of various virulent strains of <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic>. This suggests that a common ancestor of the <italic toggle="yes">enterica</italic> species has acquired this cluster as a block, and provides further indication that these TA modules play a role in virulence.</p><p>We found that a mutant deleted of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is attenuated for virulence in mice inoculated perorally but fully virulent in mice inoculated intraperitoneally. This is reminiscent to what has been observed for the SP1-encoded type three secretion system <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Galn1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, which helps <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> to cross the intestinal barrier. Thus, <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> is likely to play a role in an early step of the infection process that is temporally localized between the arrival of the bacterium in the stomach and the triggering of a systemic infection. Interestingly, the CI in spleens of perorally inoculated mice was the same at 5 and 18 days post-infection, thus confirming that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> plays a transient role and is not involved in the systemic phase of the infection. The stomach and the gut are aggressive environments in which the activation of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> might favour persistence. Peyer's patches are preferential sites for <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> to cross the intestinal barrier <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Jones1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Lelouard1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. MLNs into which Peyer's patches are drained are central sites for the induction of the mucosal immune response and possess an important antibacterial arsenal. Thus, another possibility is that <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> helps <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> to survive the biochemical stresses (NO, antibacterial peptide…) and/or the innate immune cellular defences present in the subepithelial environment. Indeed, this possibility is supported by the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> with high <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> promoter activity in MLNs and by the low CI of a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant in these peripheral lymphoid organs. The association of these data suggests that an up-regulation of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> promoter helps <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> to survive the detrimental environment of the MLNs.</p><p>Five days post-inoculation we detected in MLNs a maximum of five percent of GFP<sup>high</sup> bacteria. We cannot exclude the possibility that the activation of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> occurs earlier and in a larger part of the bacterial population. However, our attempts to detect fluorescent bacteria in mice at earlier times post-inoculation were unsuccessful because the number of bacteria present in the various organs was too low.</p><p>The HigB toxin of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> K12 cleaves mRNAs positioned at the ribosomal A-site and stops translation <xref rid="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. The mechanism of action of the SehA toxin is unknown but, considering it shares 40% identity with HigB, these toxins are likely to have similar targets. However, our results indicate that SehA activity is dependent on an additional mechanism. Indeed, a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> strain, which expresses a high level of free toxin, presents only a partial growth defect in LB broth or in cultured cells but is severely impaired for virulence in the mouse model. Interestingly, a previous screen performed in a mouse model selected STM4030 (<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic>) among the most important genes for virulence <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Chaudhuri1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Altogether, this indicates that the toxin itself is necessary but not sufficient to limit bacterial growth and that an additional factor synergizes with SehA activity under conditions of mouse infection. This might be an activator/inhibitor factor whose association/dissociation with the toxin is controlled by environmental conditions encountered in mice. This factor is operational in intraperitoneally inoculated mice although a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> remains fully virulent under these conditions of infection. Overall it suggests that activation of the SehA toxin and transcription of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> locus are not triggered by the same environmental conditions.</p><p>In general toxins and antitoxins form hetero-oligomers that are toxin-inhibiting complexes that can bind their promoter region <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Mat1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. We could not reconstitute a SehAB toxin-antitoxin complex using purified proteins. In addition, we observed an aggregation of purified SehA, which might result from non-native folding and could explain its lack of interaction with the antitoxin. Nevertheless SehA was specifically pulled-down by SehB from a bacterial extract, indicating that SehA and SehB are likely to form a canonical type II TA complex.</p><p>Stress conditions leading to the de-repression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> are poorly mimicked in cultured cells. This is shown by the limited activation of the <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> promoter and by the absence of growth defect in the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant. This suggests that this locus does not support the survival/replication of intracellular bacteria. Another possibility is that cultured cells and bone marrow-derived macrophages are not representative of cell types encountered by <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> during the early phase after oral inoculation. <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> might help the bacterium to survive bactericidal activity mediated by immune cells that are recruited to the infection sites. Supporting this observation is the fact that <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> are not killed and can survive in dendritic cells. Of note, this survival is independent of virulence factors known to be important in macrophages <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Niedergang1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.</p><p>We could not find any phenotype associated with <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic>. Nevertheless, this locus like <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>, is conserved among pathogenic strains of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> indicating its importance for the general fitness of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> locus might for example, be necessary for interactions with another warm-blooded <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> host.</p><p>The present study supports the idea that type II TA modules sustain <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> virulence. Likewise, <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> contains many more TA systems than the saprophytic <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>, leading to the suggestion that TA modules play a role in virulence by supporting the long-term dormancy of the pathogen in macrophages <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Ramage1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. TA systems of extra-intestinal pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> have recently been shown to also impact the persistence of bacteria within host tissues <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Norton1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus, it is more and more apparent that TA systems are important elements in the virulence of bacterial pathogens. The next challenge will be to understand the signalling and biochemical processes supporting the full activation of the SehA toxin and when and where the conditions necessary for this activation are encountered in the course of oral inoculation. Finally, it will be essential to evaluate the importance and role of other type II TA modules in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> pathogenicity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s5"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s5a"><title>Ethic statement</title><p>Animal experimentation was conducted in strict accordance with good animal practice as defined by the French animal welfare bodies (Law 87–848 dated 19 October 1987 modified by Decree 2001-464 and Decree 2001-131 relative to European Convention, EEC Directive 86/609). All animal work was approved by the Direction Départementale des Services Vétérinaires des Bouches du Rhône (authorization number 13.118 to S.M.).</p></sec><sec id="s5b"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in Table S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s009">Text S1</xref>. Strains were cultured in LB broth (Difco) or minimal medium (M9, glycerol 0.2%, MgSO<sub>4</sub> 1 mM, CaCl<sub>2</sub> 200 mM, thiamine 1 mg/ml, casamino acids 1 mg/ml. Ampicillin (50 µg/ml), kanamycin (50 µg/ml), tetracycline (10 µg/ml) and chloramphenicol (50 µg/ml) were added when required. Bacterial suspensions were prepared from overnight LB broth cultures that were centrifuged and resuspended in fresh LB broth or minimal medium to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 1. Then, 250 ml-flasks containing 50 ml of LB broth or minimal medium were inoculated with 1 ml of the bacterial suspensions and incubated at 37°C in a shaking incubator at 200 rpm.</p></sec><sec id="s5c"><title>Toxin-antitoxin databases and identification</title><p>Using RASTA webtool and standard BLASTP, we searched the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium genome for sequences coding for toxins and antitoxins belonging to the seven known type II TA super families: vapBC, relEB, parED, mazEF, phd-doc, ccdAB and higAB. In addition, we used others type II toxin-antitoxin sequences described for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> (yafNO, hicAB, yefMyoeB, mqsRA, chpBIchpBK, rnlAB). For TA identification, the protein set from a whole genome was first arranged by genome coordinates. Each protein in our TA databases was then used in a BLASTP query. A hit was defined as a match to a query protein with an E-value threshold of 10<sup>−5</sup>, which should cover at least 70% of the TA with more than 30% identity. Lastly, a TA module was recognized if two contiguous proteins in the genome were possible toxin and antitoxin as suggested by the results of a BLASTP. In addition to BLASTP, we used the TBLASTN algorithm to search for the presence of toxin and antitoxin genes. Genomic locations of TA modules encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> sequenced strains were obtained from NCBI.</p></sec><sec id="s5d"><title>Construction of mutant strains</title><p>Non-polar gene-deletion mutants were generated by the lambda Red recombinase system <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Datsenko1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, using gene-specific primer pairs to amplify pKD4 kanamycin or pKD3 chloramphenicol resistance genes as shown in Table S2 in Text in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s009">Text S1</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> mutants were transformed with the pCP20 plasmid to excise the antibiotic cassette. This excision was performed for the Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant, which was then transformed with pK3-SehAB for the expression of SehAB under its natural promoter, and for <italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic>::3XFLAG and <italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic>::3XFLAG. Gene deletions were checked by PCR.</p></sec><sec id="s5e"><title>Construction of plasmids</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic> transcriptional fusions were generated by cloning PCR products corresponding to the respective promoter regions into pFPV25 <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Valdivia1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref> (see primers in Table S2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s009">Text S1</xref>). These PCR products were digested with EcoRI and BamHI and ligated to pFPV25 digested with the same enzymes. For <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> expression, PCR products corresponding to <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> toxins were cloned in pDEST-17 using the Gateway system (Invitrogen, Ltd., Paisley, U.K.). <italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehD</italic> antitoxin genes were cloned both into pBAD-DEST49 and pMPM-K6. For pMPM-K6, primers contained the NcoI (5′)/HindIII (3′) restriction sites. The resulting PCR products were digested with NcoI and HindIII and ligated into pMPM-K6 <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Mayer1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> digested with the same restriction enzymes, generating the plasmids pK6-SehB and pK6-SehD. These plasmids contain the antitoxin genes under an arabinose inducible promoter. The <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> locus was cloned in the pMPM-K3 plasmid for the expression of SehAB with its own promoter. The PCR product resulting from the amplification of chromosomal DNA of 12023 with the primers STA1T-EcoRI-5 and STA1T-HINDIII-3 was digested with HindIII and ligated into pMPM-K3 previously digested with SmaI-HindIII, generating the pK3-SehAB. All constructs were confirmed by DNA sequencing. Plasmids used in this study are listed in Table S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003827.s009">Text S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s5f"><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA)</title><p>EMSA experiments were performed as described previously <xref rid="ppat.1003827-DelaCruz1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. PCR products corresponding to <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> promoter regions were the same as used to generate <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic>. These fragments (100 ng), were mixed with increasing concentrations of [His]<sub>6</sub>-tagged SehB or SehD in PBS/50% glycerol. They were incubated 30 min at room temperature and then separated by electrophoresis in 6% polyacrylamide gels in Tris-borate-EDTA buffer. The DNA bands were visualized by staining with ethidium bromide.</p></sec><sec id="s5g"><title>Eukaryotic cells and culture conditions</title><p>RAW 264.7 and HeLa cell lines were grown in DMEM (GibcoBRL) supplemented with 10% foetal calf serum (FCS; GibcoBRL), 2 mM nonessential amino acids, and glutamine (GibcoBRL) at 37°C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="s5h"><title>Bacterial infection and replication assays</title><p>Bone marrow-derived macrophages, HeLa and RAW 264.7 macrophage were grown, infected and treated as previously described <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Schroeder1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s5i"><title>Analysis of SehAB proteins degradation and western blot analysis</title><p>Bacteria expressing SehA-3XFLAG or SehB-3XFLAG from the chromosome were grown during 6 h in minimal medium. Then, protein synthesis was stopped by addition of 100 µg/ml chloramphenicol, and samples were removed at the indicated time points. SehAB proteins were detected by Western Blotting using a monoclonal anti FLAG-tag antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) and a polyclonal goat-anti mouse IgG HRP conjugate (Sigma–Aldrich).</p></sec><sec id="s5j"><title>Competitive index</title><p>Eight- to ten-week-old C57BL/6 or 129S2 mice were inoculated intraperitoneally or perorally with equal amounts of two bacterial strains for a total of 10<sup>5</sup> bacteria per mouse. The spleens were harvested 2 or 5 days after inoculation, as indicated, and homogenized. Bacteria were recovered and enumerated after plating a dilution series onto LB agar with the appropriate antibiotics. Competitive indexes (CI) were determined for each mouse <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Beuzn2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. The CI is defined as the ratio between the mutant and wild-type strains within the output (bacteria recovered from the mouse after infection) divided by their ratios within the input (initial inoculum). Statistical analyses were performed using Prism (GraphPad, San Diego, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s5k"><title>Flow cytometry analysis of bacteria extracted from synthetic medium, macrophages or mouse organs</title><p>Bacteria grown in synthetic medium (LB broth or MM) or extracted from infected cells or mouse organs were treated and analyzed by flow cytometry as previously described <xref rid="ppat.1003827-Aussel1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Chromosomal location of </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic></bold>
<bold> and </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic></bold>
<bold> loci in different </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic></bold>
<bold> strains en species.</bold> This graph is a representation of the chromosomal region on either side of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehBC</italic> loci. The genes are coloured function of their GC%. <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> are indicated in blue and red circles, respectively. This image was performed using <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.xbase.ac.uk">http://www.xbase.ac.uk</ext-link>.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s001.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Effect of toxins and antitoxins on </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic></bold>
<bold> growth.</bold> Strains were grown in LB broth and optical density was monitored at 600 nm every hour. (<bold>A</bold>) Over-expression of SehB is beneficial for <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> growth even in absence of its cognate toxin (SehA). Growth kinetics of a Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> mutant strain of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium over-expressing or not SehB. (<bold>B</bold>) The toxin component of SehCD does limit the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> in LB broth. Growth kinetics of wild-type (WT) and <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> mutant strains of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s002.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>SehB does not repress </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic></bold>
<bold> expression and conversely.</bold> Expression of <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">gfp</italic> is unaffected by the absence (<bold>A</bold>) or the over-expression (<bold>B</bold>) of SehD and <italic toggle="yes">vice versa</italic>. Wild-type <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. Typhimurium (WT) (<bold>A &amp; B</bold>) or antitoxin mutant strains (<bold>A</bold>) carrying a transcriptional reporter <italic toggle="yes">sehAB-gfp</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sehCD-gfp</italic> and over-expressing SehB or SehD under the control of an <italic toggle="yes">ara</italic> promoter were grown in LB broth and the samples were taken at 4 hr post-inoculation. The relative fluorescence intensity of bacteria was determined by flow cytometry and used to calculate the mean GFP fluorescence/bacterium.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s003.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>SehD binds to its promoter region.</bold> Electrophoretic mobility shift assays were carried out by incubating 100 ng PCR products covering <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> (16.9 nM) or STM3559-58 (20 nM) promoter regions and increasing amounts [His]<sub>6</sub>-SehD as indicated. The complexes were separated on 6% polyacrylamide gels and DNA stained.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s004.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Stoichiometry of the SehB-DNA complex.</bold> Purified SehB was subjected to size-exclusion chromatography coupled to MALS/RI/UV detectors as described in the Supporting Information. The absorption at 280 nm of SehB without DNA (AT, red line) and with DNA (green line) and the molar mass (black line), derived from refractive index measurements, were plotted as a function of the elution time. Molar mass values at the absorption peaks are indicated, with those resulting from protein-conjugate analysis in parenthesis.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s005.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic></bold>
<bold> and </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic></bold>
<bold> are dispensable for replication in cultured cells.</bold> Mouse RAW 264.7 macrophages (<bold>A</bold>) or human HeLa cells (<bold>B</bold>) were infected with wild-type (WT) or various <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> mutant strains. Δ<italic toggle="yes">sifA</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">ssaV</italic> strains were used as controls. Cells were lysed at 2 and 16 hr post-infection for enumeration of intracellular bacteria. The values shown represent the fold increase calculated as a ratio of the intracellular bacteria between 16 and 2 hr and normalized to that of the wild-type strain (100%). Values are means ± SD of 3 independent experiments. One-way ANOVA and Tukey post-tests were used to determine whether the values were significantly different. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values: ns, not significant; *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; ***, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.0005.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s006.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p>
<bold>SehB and SehD are beneficial for <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> Typhimurium intracellular replication.</bold> RAW 264.7 macrophages were infected with various bacteria. The values are the fold increase calculated as a ratio of the intracellular bacteria between 16 and 2 hr and normalized to that of the wild-type strain or control strain containing the empty vector (pDEST49). Arabinose was added to the medium 1 hr post-infection as indicated. Fold increase of wild-type (<bold>A</bold>) or Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehB</italic> mutant (<bold>B</bold>) strains over-expressing or not SehB or SehD. STM3559 and PSLT027 antitoxins were over-expressed as controls. (<bold>C</bold>) Fold increase of wild-type, Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehA</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains over-expressing or not SehB. (<bold>D</bold>) Fold increase of wild-type, Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehC</italic> and Δ<italic toggle="yes">sehCD</italic> mutant strains over-expressing or not SehD.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s007.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic></bold>
<bold> does not influence the viability of infected mouse macrophages.</bold> Raw 264.7 cells were infected with wild-type or various <italic toggle="yes">sehAB</italic> mutant strains expressing GFP. Cells were infected at a MOI of 25 and for 30 min with bacteria grown overnight in minimal medium, fixed at 16 hours post-infection and labelled with fluorescent annexin V and Aqua Dead. Cells were analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentages of annexin V-positive, Aqua Dead-positive, double-positive and double-negative among GFP-positive cells are indicated (in red).</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s008.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1003827.s009" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Supporting protocols and tables.</bold> Protocols for 1) Protein production for biochemical/biophysical studies; 2) Multiangle light scattering; 3) Surface Plasmon Resonance. Table S1: <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> strains and plasmids used in this study; Table S2: Oligonucleotides used in this study.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1003827.s009.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Julie P.M. Viala for the kind gift of the <italic toggle="yes">sifA-gfp</italic> transcriptional reporter, Kristine von Bargen and Sean Hanniffy for critical reading of the manuscript, and Jorge A. Girón for his support.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1003827-Gerdes1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bacterial persistence and toxin-antitoxin Loci</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-micro-092611-150159">10.1146/annurev-micro-092611-150159</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22994490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-micro-092611-150159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Yamaguchi1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Toxin-antitoxin systems in bacteria and archaea</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132412">10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132412</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22060041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Fineran1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fineran</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blower</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foulds</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The phage abortive infection system, ToxIN, functions as a protein-RNA toxin-antitoxin pair</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>894</fpage>–<lpage>899</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0808832106">10.1073/pnas.0808832106</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19124776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0808832106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2630095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Masuda1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Awano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K-P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>YeeU enhances the bundling of cytoskeletal polymers of MreB and FtsZ, antagonizing the CbtA (YeeV) toxicity in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2012.08068.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2012.08068.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22515815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2012.08068.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Wang1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osbourne</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A new type V toxin-antitoxin system where mRNA for toxin GhoT is cleaved by antitoxin GhoS</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nchembio.1062">10.1038/nchembio.1062</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22941047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nchembio.1062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3514572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Makarova1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Makarova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive comparative-genomic analysis of type 2 toxin-antitoxin systems and related mobile stress response systems in prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Biol Direct</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6150-4-19">10.1186/1745-6150-4-19</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19493340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1745-6150-4-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2701414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Leplae1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leplae</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geeraerts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hallez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guglielmini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Diversity of bacterial type II toxin-antitoxin systems: a comprehensive search and functional analysis of novel families</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>5513</fpage>–<lpage>5525</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr131">10.1093/nar/gkr131</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21422074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkr131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3141249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Lewis1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Persister cells, dormancy and infectious disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1557">10.1038/nrmicro1557</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrmicro1557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Pandey1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Toxin-antitoxin loci are highly abundant in free-living but lost from host-associated prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gki201">10.1093/nar/gki201</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15718296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gki201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC549392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Georgiades1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiades</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genomes of the most dangerous epidemic bacteria have a virulence repertoire characterized by fewer genes but more toxin-antitoxin modules</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e17962</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0017962">10.1371/journal.pone.0017962</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21437250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0017962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3060909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Audoly1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Audoly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincentelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edouard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiades</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mediannikov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effect of rickettsial toxin VapC on its eukaryotic host</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e26528</fpage> Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov.gate1.inist.fr/pubmed?term=Effect%20of%20Rickettsial%20Toxin%20VapC%20on%20Its%20Eukaryotic%20Host">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov.gate1.inist.fr/pubmed?term=Effect%20of%20Rickettsial%20Toxin%20VapC%20on%20Its%20Eukaryotic%20Host</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22046301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0026528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3203148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Norton1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Toxin-Antitoxin Systems Are Important for Niche-Specific Colonization and Stress Resistance of Uropathogenic Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002954</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1002954">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002954</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3464220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-DouesnardMalo1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Douesnard-Malo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daigle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Increased persistence of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhi in the presence of Acanthamoeba castellanii</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>7640</fpage>–<lpage>7646</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.00699-11">10.1128/AEM.00699-11</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21926221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.00699-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3209172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Bleasdale1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bleasdale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jagannathan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birtles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Salmonella pathogenicity island 2-encoded type III secretion system is essential for the survival of Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium in free-living amoebae</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1793</fpage>–<lpage>1795</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/AEM.02033-08">10.1128/AEM.02033-08</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19168655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.02033-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2655480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Sevin1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sevin</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barloy-Hubler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>RASTA-Bacteria: a web-based tool for identifying toxin-antitoxin loci in prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>R155</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2007-8-8-r155">10.1186/gb-2007-8-8-r155</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17678530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/gb-2007-8-8-r155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2374986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Jrgensen1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskolska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>HicA of Escherichia coli defines a novel family of translation-independent mRNA interferases in bacteria and archaea</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>1191</fpage>–<lpage>1199</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01013-08">10.1128/JB.01013-08</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19060138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.01013-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2631989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Winther1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ectopic production of VapCs from Enterobacteria inhibits translation and trans-activates YoeB mRNA interferase</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>918</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06694.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06694.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06694.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Bumler1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bäumler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The record of horizontal gene transfer in Salmonella</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0966-842X(97)01082-2">10.1016/S0966-842X(97)01082-2</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9263410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0966-842X(97)01082-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-RDC1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">RDC T (2010) R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-FivianHughes1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fivian-Hughes</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Analyzing the regulatory role of the HigA antitoxin within Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>192</volume>: <fpage>4348</fpage>–<lpage>4356</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00454-10">10.1128/JB.00454-10</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.00454-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2937366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Budde1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waldor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a higBA toxin-antitoxin locus in Vibrio cholerae</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.00909-06">10.1128/JB.00909-06</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17085558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.00909-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1797405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Hood1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Güvener</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carl</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A type VI secretion system of Pseudomonas aeruginosa targets a toxin to bacteria</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chom.2009.12.007">10.1016/j.chom.2009.12.007</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20114026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chom.2009.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2831478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Aussel1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aussel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hébrard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guilhon</surname><given-names>A-A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viala</surname><given-names>JPM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Salmonella detoxifying enzymes are sufficient to cope with the host oxidative burst</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07611.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07611.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21362067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07611.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Linehan1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Linehan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rytkönen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SlyA regulates function of Salmonella pathogenicity island 2 (SPI-2) and expression of SPI-2-associated genes</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>4354</fpage>–<lpage>4362</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.73.7.4354-4362.2005">10.1128/IAI.73.7.4354-4362.2005</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.73.7.4354-4362.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1168564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Hensel1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hensel</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Genes encoding putative effector proteins of the type III secretion system of Salmonella pathogenicity island 2 are required for bacterial virulence and proliferation in macrophages</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9786193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.01047.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Stein1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zwick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Portillo</surname><given-names>FG-D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Identification of a Salmonella virulence gene required for formation of filamentous structures containing lysosomal membrane glycoproteins within epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.1996.tb02497.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1996.tb02497.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.1996.tb02497.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Shea1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beuzon</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gleeson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Influence of the Salmonella typhimurium pathogenicity island 2 type III secretion system on bacterial growth in the mouse</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9864218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.67.1.213-219.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC96299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Henry1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couillault</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rockenfeller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucrot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Salmonella effector protein PipB2 is a linker for kinesin-1</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>13497</fpage>–<lpage>13502</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0605443103">10.1073/pnas.0605443103</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16938850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0605443103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1569191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Beuzn1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beuzón</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>In vivo genetic analysis indicates that PhoP-PhoQ and the Salmonella pathogenicity island 2 type III secretion system contribute independently to Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium virulence</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>7254</fpage>–<lpage>7261</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/IAI.69.12.7254-7261.2001">10.1128/IAI.69.12.7254-7261.2001</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11705895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.69.12.7254-7261.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC98809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Beuzn2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beuzón</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Use of mixed infections with Salmonella strains to study virulence genes and their interactions in vivo</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>1352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11755424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1286-4579(01)01496-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Ruby1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Salmonella's long-term relationship with its host</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2012.00332.x">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2012.00332.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22335190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2012.00332.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Monack1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Monack</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Salmonella typhimurium persists within macrophages in the mesenteric lymph nodes of chronically infected Nramp1+/+ mice and can be reactivated by IFNgamma neutralization</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>199</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1084/jem.20031319">10.1084/jem.20031319</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20031319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2211772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Carter1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>The route of enteric infection in normal mice</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4596512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.139.5.1189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2139651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Eriksson1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>JCD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Unravelling the biology of macrophage infection by gene expression profiling of intracellular Salmonella enterica</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03313.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Slattery1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Victorsen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hillman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Isolation of highly persistent mutants of Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium reveals a new toxin-antitoxin module</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>195</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>657</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.01397-12">10.1128/JB.01397-12</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23204462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.01397-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3562109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Koonin1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genomics of bacteria and archaea: the emerging dynamic view of the prokaryotic world</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>6688</fpage>–<lpage>6719</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkn668">10.1093/nar/gkn668</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18948295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkn668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2588523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Galn1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galán</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curtiss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Cloning and molecular characterization of genes whose products allow Salmonella typhimurium to penetrate tissue culture cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>6383</fpage>–<lpage>6387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2548211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.86.16.6383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC297844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Jones1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Salmonella typhimurium initiates murine infection by penetrating and destroying the specialized epithelial M cells of the Peyer's patches</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>180</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8006579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.180.1.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2191576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Lelouard1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lelouard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bovis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mugnier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chollat-Namy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pathogenic bacteria and dead cells are internalized by a unique subset of Peyer's patch dendritic cells that express lysozyme</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>138</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>84.e1–3</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/j.gastro.2009.09.051">10.1053/j.gastro.2009.09.051</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2009.09.051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Three new RelE-homologous mRNA interferases of Escherichia coli differentially induced by environmental stresses</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06969.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06969.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19943910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06969.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2814082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Chaudhuri1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pleasance</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Northen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive identification of Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium genes required for infection of BALB/c mice</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000529</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000529">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000529</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19649318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2712085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Mat1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maté</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincentelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cambillau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of the DNA-bound VapBC2 antitoxin/toxin pair from Rickettsia felis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr1167">10.1093/nar/gkr1167</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkr1167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3326315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22140099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Brown1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grigoriu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Three dimensional structure of the MqsR:MqsA complex: a novel TA pair comprised of a toxin homologous to RelE and an antitoxin with unique properties</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000706</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000706">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000706</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20041169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2791442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Niedergang1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Niedergang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirard</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraehenbuhl</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Entry and survival of Salmonella typhimurium in dendritic cells and presentation of recombinant antigens do not require macrophage-specific virulence factors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>14650</fpage>–<lpage>14655</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.97.26.14650">10.1073/pnas.97.26.14650</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.97.26.14650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC18973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Ramage1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ramage</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive functional analysis of Mycobacterium tuberculosis toxin-antitoxin systems: implications for pathogenesis, stress responses, and evolution</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000767</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000767">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000767</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20011113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2781298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Datsenko1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in Escherichia coli K-12 using PCR products</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>: <fpage>6640</fpage>–<lpage>6645</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.120163297">10.1073/pnas.120163297</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.120163297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC18686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Valdivia1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Bacterial genetics by flow cytometry: rapid isolation of Salmonella typhimurium acid-inducible promoters by differential fluorescence induction</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8930920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1996.00120.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Mayer1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A new set of useful cloning and expression vectors derived from pBlueScript</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>163</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7557476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0378-1119(95)00389-n</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-DelaCruz1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>De la Cruz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Mora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guadarrama</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores-Valdez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>LeuO antagonizes H-NS and StpA-dependent repression in Salmonella enterica ompS1</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>743</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05958.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05958.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17908208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.05958.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Schroeder1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Chastellier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guilhon</surname><given-names>A-A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The virulence protein SopD2 regulates membrane dynamics of Salmonella-containing vacuoles</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001002</fpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1001002">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001002</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20664790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2904799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Gotfredsen1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gotfredsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Escherichia coli relBE genes belong to a new toxin-antitoxin gene family</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage>–<lpage>1076</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9767574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.00993.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Aizenman1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aizenman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg-Kulka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>An Escherichia coli chromosomal “addiction module” regulated by guanosine [corrected] 3″,5-″bispyrophosphate: a model for programmed bacterial cell death</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>6059</fpage>–<lpage>6063</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.93.12.6059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC39188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Motiejnait1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Motiejūnaitė</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armalytė</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markuckas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sužiedėlienė</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Escherichia coli dinJ-yafQ genes act as a toxin-antitoxin module</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>268</volume>: <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6968.2006.00563.x">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2006.00563.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17263853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2006.00563.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Hazan1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hazan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reches</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg-Kulka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Postsegregational killing mediated by the P1 phage “addiction module” phd-doc requires the Escherichia coli programmed cell death system mazEF</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>183</volume>: <fpage>2046</fpage>–<lpage>2050</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/JB.183.6.2046-2050.2001">10.1128/JB.183.6.2046-2050.2001</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.183.6.2046-2050.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC95101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-ChristensenDalsgaard2"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen-Dalsgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Two higBA loci in the Vibrio cholerae superintegron encode mRNA cleaving enzymes and can stabilize plasmids</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>
<comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05385.x">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05385.x</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17020579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05385.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1003827-Afif1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Afif</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couturier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Melderen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The ratio between CcdA and CcdB modulates the transcriptional repression of the ccd poison-antidote system</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02492.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>