
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3162572</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3162572.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3162572</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3162572</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21887248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-08791</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Death</subject><subject>Cell Growth</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Resveratrol and Black Tea Polyphenol Combination Synergistically Suppress Mouse Skin Tumors Growth by Inhibition of Activated MAPKs and p53</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Combined Resveratrol and BTP Inhibit Skin Tumors</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names initials="J">Jasmine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="M">Madhulika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names initials="AK">Amit Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhui</surname><given-names initials="K">Kulpreet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names initials="P">Preeti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names initials="PK">Pranav Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yogeshwer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Proteomics Laboratory, Indian Institute of Toxicology Research, Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), Uttar Pradesh, India</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashanchi</surname><given-names initials="F">Fatah</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">George Mason University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yogeshwer_shukla@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JG YS. Performed the experiments: JG MS AKS KB PR PKC. Analyzed the data: JG MS KB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YS. Wrote the paper: JG MS YS.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">199013</issue-id><elocation-id>e23395</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>08</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>George et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0023395.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6474622"><article-title>Retraction: Resveratrol and Black Tea Polyphenol Combination Synergistically Suppress Mouse Skin Tumors Growth by Inhibition of Activated MAPKs and p53</article-title><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><date><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><elocation-id>e0215980</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6474622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31002738</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Cancer chemoprevention by natural dietary agents has received considerable importance because of their cost-effectiveness and wide safety margin. However, single agent intervention has failed to bring the expected outcome in clinical trials; therefore, combinations of chemopreventive agents are gaining increasing popularity. The present study aims to evaluate the combinatorial chemopreventive effects of resveratrol and black tea polyphenol (BTP) in suppressing two-stage mouse skin carcinogenesis induced by DMBA and TPA. Resveratrol/BTP alone treatment decreased tumor incidence by ∼67% and ∼75%, while combination of both at low doses synergistically decreased tumor incidence even more significantly by ∼89% (p&lt;0.01). This combination also significantly regressed tumor volume and number (p&lt;0.01). Mechanistic studies revealed that this combinatorial inhibition was associated with decreased expression of phosphorylated mitogen-activated protein kinase family proteins: extracellular signal-regulated kinase 1/2, c-Jun N-terminal kinase 1/2, p38 and increased in total p53 and phospho p53 (Ser 15) in skin tissue/tumor. Treatment with combinations of resveratrol and BTP also decreased expression of proliferating cell nuclear antigen in mouse skin tissues/tumors than their solitary treatments as determined by immunohistochemistry. In addition, histological and cell death analysis also confirmed that resveratrol and BTP treatment together inhibits cellular proliferation and markedly induces apoptosis. Taken together, our results for the first time lucidly illustrate that resveratrol and BTP in combination impart better suppressive activity than either of these agents alone and accentuate that development of novel combination therapies/chemoprevention using dietary agents will be more beneficial against cancer. This promising combination should be examined in therapeutic trials of skin and possibly other cancers.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Since early in the history of medicine, an association between diet and cancer has persisted. The most consistent findings on diet as a determinant of several types of cancers risk prevention is the association with consumption of fruits and vegetables <xref rid="pone.0023395-deKok1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. To date, hundreds of natural or synthetic compounds have been found to possess promising cancer chemopreventive actions. When reviewing the literature on the effects of several dietary agents in animal and in vitro studies, there is ample evidence that specific antioxidants and other phytochemicals present in foods of plant origin protect against genotoxicity and other cancer-initiating or -promoting processes <xref rid="pone.0023395-Gromadzinska1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Akesson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>The concept of using a combination of agents for cancer chemoprevention has recently received much attention. Considerable evidence from laboratories studies suggests that combinations of chemopreventive agents can be more effective for the prevention of cancer than any single constituent. Recently, Xu et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> showed that combination treatment of curcumin and green tea catechins prevent dimethylhydrazine-induced colon carcinogenesis rat model more potently than each of the compounds alone. In another recent study, genistein-selenium combination significantly inhibited growth of LNCaP and PC3 cells in a dose- and time-dependent manner by decreasing matrix metalloproteins-2 levels <xref rid="pone.0023395-KumiDiaka1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Zhou et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> identified the possible chemopreventive effects of soy and tea components on prostate tumor progression in in vivo. The combination of both synergistically inhibited final tumor weight and metastasis and significantly reduced serum concentrations of testosterone and dihydrotestosterone. Our laboratory is actively investigating the hypothesis that combinations of food-based cancer prevention strategies will be a highly effective strategy for the reduction of carcinogenesis. During this course we have investigated that combination of pomegranate fruit extract and diallyl sulfide synergistically inhibited mouse skin tumor growth through reduce proliferation, inhibition of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPKs) and nuclear factor- kappa B (NF-κB) signaling and induction of apoptotic cell death <xref rid="pone.0023395-George1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Now, we have chosen to focus our experimental efforts on resveratrol and black tea polyphenol (BTP), two foods frequently cited to protect humans from skin carcinogenesis <xref rid="pone.0023395-Ndiaye1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Sil1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>Resveratrol (3,4,5-trihydroxy-trans-stilbene), a natural plant polyphenol is widely present in foods such as grapes, wine and peanuts. One of the most striking biological activities of resveratrol intensely investigated during the last years has been its anti-cancer and anti-inflammation properties. These properties were first appreciated when Jang et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Jang1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> demonstrated that resveratrol possesses cancer-chemopreventive and cytostatic properties via the three major stages of carcinogenesis, i.e. initiation, promotion and progression. Since then, there has been a flurry of papers reporting the implication of resveratrol in cancer chemoprevention through a wide range of actions <xref rid="pone.0023395-Hsieh1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Most of the cancer chemopreventive evidence for resveratrol is well documented in various cancers such as those of hepatocellular, lung, skin and prostate by multiple regulatory mechanisms <xref rid="pone.0023395-Bishayee1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Roy1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Seeni1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Kundu et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kundu1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> showed that resveratrol exert anti-tumor promoting in the 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol 13-acetate (TPA)- induced mouse skin carcinogenesis model suppression of cyclooxygenase-2 expression by blocking the activation of MAPKs and activator protein. Previously study from our laboratory have reported that resveratrol-induces apoptosis in 7, 12-dimethylbenz[a]anthracene (DMBA)-initiated and TPA promoted, mouse skin tumors through cell cycle arrest, activation of p53 activity and alteration of apoptosis-related proteins <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kalra1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p><p>Tea, the most widely consumed beverage has received a great deal of attention because of its polyphenolic constituents known to have strong antioxidants and inhibitory activity against tumorigenesis <xref rid="pone.0023395-Weisburger1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Many studies have demonstrated the anti-inflammatory and anti-tumor effects of BTP; it can inhibit proliferation and metastasis and induce apoptosis in various malignant tumors, including skin cancer, by modulating several different signal pathways <xref rid="pone.0023395-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Weisberger1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Roy2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Epidemiological studies on black tea and cancer are limited, but several investigators have demonstrated positive correlations between black tea consumption and a lower incidence of breast <xref rid="pone.0023395-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> and ovarian <xref rid="pone.0023395-Baker1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> cancer. BTP treatment has been shown to induce apoptosis in prostate cancer cells by induction of p53, down-regulation of NF-κB activity, causing a change in the ratio of pro-and anti-apoptotic proteins and inhibiting expression of activated MAPKs <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kalra2" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>It is clear that resveratrol and BTP independently have biological activities for cancer prevention purposes, however, productive application of these two compounds in combination to exert synergistic effects against cancer inflammation and growth of tumor warrants further studies. Therefore, multiple properties of resveratrol and BTP in cancer prevention lead us to assume a more benefit in combining these two agents rather than the single agents for cancer prevention and therapy. Thus the present study was designed to investigate whether resveratrol in combination with BTP at low doses synergistically suppress the DMBA-initiated, TPA- promoted two-stage mouse skin tumors. Our results clearly demonstrate that a combination of resveratrol and BTP can synergistically inhibit the development and progression of mouse skin tumors then their solitary treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Materials</title><p>DMBA, TPA, resveratrol, β-actin (clone AC-74) and propidium iodide (PI) were purchased from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, USA). Annexin-V and PI fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) detection Kit was purchased from BD (San Jose, CA, USA). Purified BTP (&gt;98% pure) was kindly gifted by M/S Indfrag company, Bangalore, India. Hydroxylapatite and N, N-dimethylformamide was purchased from Sisco Research Laboratory (Mumbai, India). The mouse monoclonal total and phospho specific antibodies for p38, p53, c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK1/2) (Thr183/Tyr185), p44/42 MAPK (Thr202/Tyr204) i.e extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK1/2) were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, USA). Proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) antibody was obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA). The rabbit anti-mouse or goat anti-rabbit horse radish peroxidase (HRP) conjugate secondary antibodies were obtained from Bangalore Genei (Bangalore, India). The poly(vinylidene) fluoride (PVDF) membranes were obtained from Millipore (Billerica, MA, USA). Other used chemicals were of analytical grade and procured locally.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Animals and treatments</title><p>Male, Balb/c mice (15–18 g body weight [b. wt.]) were obtained from the Indian Institute of Toxicology Research (Lucknow, India) animal breeding colony. Prior ethical approval for the experiments was obtained from institutional ethical committee. All animals were quarantined in polypropylene cages under standard laboratory conditions (temperature 23±2°C, relative humidity 55±5%, 12/12 h light/dark cycle) and were fed solid pellet diet (Ashirwad, Chandigarh, India) and water ad libitum. After a week of acclimatization animals were used for further experiments.</p><p>Long term animal bioassay: For treatment, animals were randomly divided into 6 groups consisting 25 animals in each. Animals of all groups were carefully shaved on dorsal skin in the interscapular region of 2 cm<sup>2</sup>. DMBA (tumor initiator), TPA (tumor promoter) and resveratrol were dissolved in acetone. In brief, treatment was given as described below for 18 weeks of duration to attain the entire period of skin tumorigenicity:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
<bold>Group I</bold>- No treatment was given to the animals and served as untreated controls.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group II</bold>- DMBA+TPA (animals were treated with single topical application of DMBA (52 µg/animal), one week later followed by topical application of TPA (5 µg/animal) thrice in a week throughout the experimental period and served as positive controls).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group III</bold>- Acetone+Resveratrol+BTP (200 µL acetone was applied topically followed by topical treatment of 50 µM/animal resveratrol to each animal and 0.2% BTP was given as sole source of drinking fluid thrice a week).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group IV</bold>- DMBA+TPA+resveratrol (50 µM/animal resveratrol was given topically to the animals as mentioned in group III, rest of the treatments was same as in group II).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group V</bold>- DMBA+TPA+BTP (treatment of DMBA was similar as in group II after a week followed by TPA application and 0.2% BTP supplementation as in group II and III, respectively).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group VI</bold>- DMBA+TPA+resveratrol+BTP (DMBA and TPA application was same as in group II, resveratrol (25 µM/animal) application and BTP (0.1%) supplementation as in group III).</p></list-item></list><p>During treatment period animals were carefully observed for any change in b. wt., fluid/food intake and development of skin tumor. Tumors &gt;1 mm in diameter were considered in the cumulative number if they persist for 2 weeks or more. After completion of 18 weeks of treatments duration, the regression of pattern of tumors in terms of both number and volume were recorded up to 26 weeks in the animals of groups IV, V and VI (bearing tumor or not). These were divided into 3 subgroups and treatment schedule was as follow:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
<bold>Group IV A - VI A</bold>: comprises animals' without tumor and no further treatment was given to these groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group IV B and C</bold>- comprises tumor bearing animals' and treatment of TPA+resveratrol and only TPA was withdrawn, respectively.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group V B and C</bold>- comprises tumor bearing animals' and treatment of TPA+BTP and only TPA was withdrawn, respectively.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group VI B and C</bold>- comprises tumor bearing animals' and treatment of TPA+resveratrol+BTP and only TPA was withdrawn, respectively.</p></list-item></list><p>After completion of the study period (26 weeks), all the animals of groups IV–VI (A–C) were first examined for tumor volume/number regression and thereafter sacrificed. Tumor volume was calculated per mouse in each group using formula V = D×d2×π/6, where D = bigger dimension and d = smaller dimension. Skin from the painted area (with or without tumors) was excised out, cleaned, snap frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at −80°C until further use.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Synergy between resveratrol and BTP combination</title><p>The nature of the combined effects of resveratrol and BTP was determined using the method described by Zhou et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, based on the principles described by Chou and Talalay <xref rid="pone.0023395-Chou1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In brief, the expected value of combination effect between agent 1 and agent 2 is calculated as [(observed agent 1 value)/(control value)]×[(observed agent 2 value)/(control value)]×(control value); and the ratio is calculated as (expected value)/(observed value). A ratio of &gt;1 indicates a synergistic effect, and a ratio of &lt;1 indicates a less than additive effect.</p><p>Short term animal bioassay: Animals were divided into 6 groups of 5 in each and doses for selected treatments was same as detailed in long term study section for 2 weeks period. Briefly, groups and treatments are as below:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
<bold>Group I</bold>: Untreated control (No treatment).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group II</bold>: DMBA+TPA (single dose of DMBA was applied topically one week later followed by TPA application 4 times in a week).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group III</bold>: Acetone+resveratrol+BTP (animals were treated with acetone and 50 µM resveratrol topically, and 0.2% BTP as sole source of drinking fluid for 4 times in a week).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group IV</bold>: DMBA+TPA+resveratrol (DMBA and TPA application as in Gr. II and resveratrol treatment as in group III).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group V</bold>: DMBA+TPA+BTP (DMBA and TPA application as in Gr. II and BTP supplementation as in group III).</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Group VI</bold>: DMBA+TPA+resveratrol+BTP (DMBA and TPA application as in Gr. II and, resveratrol (25 µM/animal) and BTP (0.1%) treatment as in group III).</p></list-item></list><p>At the end of the experimental period all the animals were sacrificed and skin from the painted area was excised out, cleaned, snap frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at −80°C until further use.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Preparation of lysates</title><p>Whole skin tissue/tumor homogenates (10%) were made as described by Kataoka et al. <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kataoka1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, in both, the long term as well as the short term study. The supernatants were collected and stored at −80°C till use.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Western blotting</title><p>Western blotting was carried out as described earlier <xref rid="pone.0023395-Arora1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Protein concentration was measured following standard protocols <xref rid="pone.0023395-Lowry1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Proteins (60 µg) were resolved on 10–12% SDS PAGE and electroblotted on PVDF membrane. The blots were blocked overnight with 5% non-fat dry milk and probed with antibodies at dilutions recommended by the suppliers. Immunoblots were detected through chemiluminescence using kit of Millipore (Billerica, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Histopathological analysis</title><p>Paraffin sections (5 µm) of the skin tissues/tumors were stained with haematoxylin and eosin for histopathological analysis. Histopathological observations were made according to Bogovaski <xref rid="pone.0023395-Bogovaski1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Immunohistochemical (IHC) staining</title><p>Buffered formalin fixed and paraffin embedded skin/tumor tissues were cut into sections (5 µm thick), which were subsequently de-waxed and hydrated. Then endogenous peroxidase activity was quenched and epitope retrieval was performed. This was followed by blocking of non-specific binding of primary antibody to epitopes by a preincubation step with normal serum. Sections were then incubated overnight with the primary monoclonal anti-PCNA (1∶100) antibody. After incubation, the sections were again incubated with normal serum and then with HRP-conjugated secondary antibody. The colour was developed using substrate chromogen system diaminobenzidine (Dako, CA, USA). For the negative control, phosphate-buffered saline was used in place of the primary antibody. The immunostained slides were analyzed under microscope (Leica, Wetzler, Germany) attached with charge coupled device camera (JVC).</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Annexin-V and PI dual staining</title><p>Annexin-V and PI FITC detection Kit (BD, San Jose, CA, USA) was used for the differentiation between apoptotic and necrotic cell population. The single cell suspensions of treated and untreated skin tissues (from short term study) were prepared using Medimachine (Beckton Dickinson, San Jose, USA). For each sample, Annexin-V/PI fluorescence was analyzed, wherein fluorescence of cells was gated and counted using ‘Cell Quest 3.1 software’.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>DNA alkaline unwinding assay</title><p>Strand breaks in cellular DNA were quantitated by alkaline unwinding assay using hydroxyapatite batch procedure as described previously <xref rid="pone.0023395-Nigam1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. In brief, 100 µg of DNA from treated and untreated skin tissue samples (from short term study) was subjected to alkaline unwinding and the relative amount of duplex and single stranded DNA present at the end of the alkaline unwinding was quantified.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For the statistical analysis of skin tumor appearance dynamics, the Kaplan-Meier method of tumor-free survival estimation was applied. Statistically significant differences were determined between control and treatment groups using one-way ANOVA (GraphPad Prism software) followed by Dunnett post hoc test. Values with p&lt;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Effects of resveratrol and/or BTP on tumorigenicity rate</title><p>The b. wt. of each animal was recorded every week during the entire period of the experiment. Compared with the untreated control (group I), mice on DMBA and TPA treatment (group II) showed a significant reduction in b. wt. However, there was an increasing percentage of change in the b. wt. gain of the animal of the experimental treatments (groups III–VI) (data not shown). The first day of tumor incidence in the positive control (DMBA and TPA) group II was 48th day; however, it was 63th day in resveratrol treated group IV, 58th day in BTP treated group V and 84th day in the resveratrol and BTP treated group VI. There was no tumor induction in group III. The chemopreventive potential of resveratrol and BTP was also evident by significant (p&lt;0.01) increase in tumor free survival of animals. 36%, 48% and 72% of animals of group IV, V and VI, respectively, remained tumor-free till the termination of the experiment. However, in positive control group (II) 100% animals were observed with tumors by the end of 18th week (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The expected effect of the resveratrol/BTP combination on tumorigenicity rate (33%) was greater than the observed combination effect (28%) with a ratio of 1.17, suggesting that the resveratrol/BTP combination had a synergistic inhibitory effect on tumorigenicity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on DMBA and TPA-induced mouse skin tumors.</title><p>(A) Percentage of tumor-free survival, (B) cumulative number of tumors (CNT) per group, (C) reduction in average no. of tumors/mouse and (c) reduction in tumor volume/mouse (mm<sup>3</sup>). The data showed are of surviving animals upto 18<sup>th</sup> weeks in (A), (B) and (C) however, mean±SD of surviving animals from 18<sup>th</sup> to 26<sup>th</sup> weeks in (D). * indicates significant reduction over DMBA and TPA treated group II at 18<sup>th</sup> week (p&lt;0.01). ** indicates significant reduction over resveratrol and BTP alone treated groups at 18<sup>th</sup> week (p&lt;0.01). *** indicates significant reduction after 26<sup>th</sup> weeks (p&lt;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0023395-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Possible synergistic chemopreventive effect of the interaction between Res and BTP against DMBA and TPA-induced mouse skin tumorigenesis.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0023395-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (Groups)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Tumorigenicity (%)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">CNT (%)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">ANT (%)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">ATV (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Untreated control (I)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DMBA+TPA (II)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Acetone+Res+BTP (III)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DMBA+TPA+Res (IV)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DMBA+TPA+BTP (V)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DMBA+TPA+Res+BTP (VI)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>All the data are statistically significant, p&lt;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>Expected value of Res and BTP combination = [(observed value of Res)/(control value)]×[(observed value of BTP)/(control value)]×(control value).</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>Ratio = (expected value/observed value). A ratio of&gt;1 indicates a synergistic effect, and a ratio of &lt;1 indicates a less than additive effect.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>O, observed; E, expected; R, ratio; Res, resveratrol; CNT, cumulative number of tumors; ANT, average number of tumors/mouse; ATV, average tumor volume/tumor bearing mouse.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Protection was also seen in terms of reduction in tumor volume. The tumor volume was 130.0 mm3/mouse in DMBA and TPA group, which reduced to 52.6, 63.2 and 24.6 mm3/mouse in group IV, V and VI, respectively. The expected effect of the combined resveratrol and BTP on average tumor volume (19.7%) was higher than the observed combined effect (18.9%) with a ratio of 1.05, suggesting that resveratrol and BTP combination also had synergistic effect in reducing the tumor volume (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Protection afforded by resveratrol and BTP was also evident in terms of reduction in the cumulative number of tumors (CNT). While the positive control group showed 230 CNT, group IV, V and VI showed 71, 89, and 25 CNT, respectively, at 18th week (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). The observed effect (10.9%) in combination group VI was less than the expected value (11.9%), with ratio of 1.09, suggesting that resveratrol and BTP combination synergistically reduces CNT (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>When these tumor data were considered in terms of number of tumors per mice, at the termination of the experiment at 18 weeks on test, compared with 9.2 tumors per mouse in DMBA and TPA treated group, 4.4, 5.7 and only 2.5 tumors per mouse in group was recorded in group IV, V and VI, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Compared with the solitary resveratrol (75%) and BTP (67%) treated groups, decrease in the number of tumor per mouse in combination-treated group corresponded to 89% inhibition. The observed effect (27.2%) in combination group VI was less than the expected value (29.6%), with ratio of 1.08, suggesting that resveratrol and BTP combination also synergistically reduces CNT (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Effects of resveratrol and/or BTP on tumor growth and regression</title><p>We further extended the work to observe regression offered by combined doses of resveratrol and BTP in tumor volume and number if any. At 19th week, TPA treatment was ceased and morphological changes of the tumors were recorded in group IV B, IV C, V B, V C, VI B and VI C. Among these groups, in Gr. VI C, major commencement of regression was recorded from 22<sup>nd</sup> week onwards (p&lt;0.01). Apparently, group VI B from which resveratrol and BTP were withdrawn showed regression in terms of both tumor volume and number (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>). The tumor volume at 26th week reduced to 105.4 mm<sup>3</sup>/mouse in DMBA and TPA group II, 21.8 mm<sup>3</sup>/mouse in group VI B and 18.9 mm<sup>3</sup>/mouse in group VI C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). CNT reduced to 198, 10 and 6 in group II, VI B and VI C, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>). Changes in both tumor number and volume were also observed in solitary resveratrol and BTP treated groups (IV B, IV C, V B and V C) but the extent was lesser than combination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). Moreover, animals of group VI A did not show any morphological changes as well as development of tumors till the termination of the experiment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>). Thus, combined supplementation of resveratrol and BTP resulted in regression in both tumor volume and number and imparts better efficacy in terms of tumor regression then either of these agents alone.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0023395-t002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Combinatorial chemopreventive effect of Res and/or BTP on tumor regression.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0023395-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Number of animals with tumors</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">CNT</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">ANT(Mean ± SD)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">ATV(Mean ± SD)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18th</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26th</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>II</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBA+TPA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2±2.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.92±2.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.0±10.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.4±10.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IV A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)Res-Non-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IV B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)Res-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66±1.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66±2.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1±7.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8±6.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IV C</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)Res-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00±1.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71±2.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.1±6.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3±5.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>V A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)BTP-Non-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>V B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)BTP-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25±2.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5±2.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.3±6.2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.8±6.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>V C</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)BTP-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75±2.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2±2.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.1±5.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6±7.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>VI A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)Res+BTP-Non-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>VI B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(−)Res+BTP-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6±2.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0±2.0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2±5.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8±5.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>VI C</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)Res+BTP-tumor bearing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4±1.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0±1.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9±7.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9±8.6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">c</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p>significant reduction over DMBA and TPA treated group II at 18th week (p&lt;0.01).</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>b</label><p>significant reduction over BTP and Res alone treated groups IV B–C and V B–C at 18th week (p&lt;0.01).</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>c</label><p>significant reduction at 26th week (p&lt;0.01).</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>(−) indicates without treatment, (+) indicates with treatment.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label/><p>Res, resveratrol; CNT, cumulative number of tumors; ANT, average number of tumors/mouse; ATV, average tumor volume/tumor bearing mouse.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on phosphorylated MAPKs</title><p>It has been reported that topical application of TPA in mouse skin results in a marked increase in the phosphorylated form of MAPKs <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kundu2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, affecting fundamental cellular processes like proliferation, differentiation, and survival, thus we further evaluated the expression levels of MAPK family proteins <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kennedy1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In the present study, western blot analysis showed that the activation of MAPKs (ERK1/2 , JNK1/2 and p38) was gradually increased during progression of TPA-induced papillomagenesis in DMBA-initiated mouse skin over untreated control group (p&lt;0.05), in both long and short term studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g002">Figure 2A and B</xref>). However, supplementation of combined and solitary doses of resveratrol and BTP in DMBA and TPA treated animals, significantly (p&lt;0.05) down-regulated the expression levels of ERK1/2, JNK1/2 and p38 through inhibition of their phosphorylation as compared to animals of group II, in both experimental sets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g002">Figure 2A and B</xref>). There was no effect on the total amount of ERK1/2, JNK1/2 and p38 proteins after DMBA and TPA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g002">Figure 2A and B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Western blots showing the inhibitory effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on the expression levels of total and phospho-ERK1/2, JNK1/2 and p38 in mouse skin tumors.</title><p>(A) Long and (B) short term studies. Details for groups and treatments are described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and methods</xref> section. The bands shown here are from a representative experiment repeated three times with similar results. Equal loading was confirmed by stripping the immunoblot and reprobing it for β-actin. The pixel density of the specific immunoreactive bands was quantified by densitometry and expressed as a fold difference against β-actin. * more than corresponding value of untreated control group I (p&lt;0.05). **less than corresponding value of DMBA and TPA group II (p&lt;0.05). <sup>#</sup> less than corresponding value of BTP and Res alone treated groups IV and V (p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on histopathology of skin/tumor</title><p>Histologically skin tumor sections from DMBA and TPA applied group II exhibited varying degrees of structural and cytological changes as compared to untreated control group I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Tumors section of group II animals exhibit focal proliferation of squamous cells, presence of some necrotic cells and keratinization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). This clearly indicates the benign nature of tumors initiated and promoted by DMBA and TPA, respectively. However, skin sections from animals treated with resveratrol/BTP (group III), did not reveal any histopathological abnormalities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). The administration of both resveratrol and BTP led to suppression of DMBA and TPA induced skin tumorigenesis which was evident by skin/tumor sections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Skin tumor sections of group VI showed chances towards normalization of skin as compared to group II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Histological study of mouse skin/tumors.</title><p>(A) Long and (B) short term experimental groups. Details for groups and treatments are described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and methods</xref> section.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Similarly, in short term experimental groups' haematoxylin and eosin stained sections were showing pronounced preventive effects of resveratrol and BTP treatment when given in combination than alone over DMBA and TPA -induced changes in animals skin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). In group II, disorganization of epithelium, presence of necrotic cells and focal proliferative area were noticed as compared to group I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on proliferation marker</title><p>IHC analysis of PCNA was used to assess the proliferation activity during tumor promotion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). PCNA reactivity is associated with S phase of DNA replication <xref rid="pone.0023395-Mancini1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. It was observed that PCNA labelling indices were higher in animals treated with DMBA and TPA as compared to other groups. A characteristic intense staining and higher number of PCNA positive cells were observed as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4A</xref>. The representative untreated control group did not show significant positive staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). Further, treatment of resveratrol and BTP resulted in low expression levels of PCNA positive cells (p&lt;0.01) as compared to group II revealing that effects of combinational treatment of resveratrol and BTP were superior to single treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effects of resveratrol and BTP treatment on modulation of PCNA expression.</title><p>(A) Long and (B) short term experiments. Details are described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and methods</xref> section. The brown colour nuclei mark the reactivity with PCNA indicated by arrows. Bar diagram shows mean ± SD of three independent sets analysis. *significantly increased in comparison of group I (p&lt;0.01), **significantly decreased when compared with group II (p&lt;0.01). <sup>#</sup>significantly decreased when compared with groups IV and V (p&lt;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Similarly, PCNA staining were analyzed to determine the proliferative status of skin after treatment with DMBA and TPA and the respective preventive treatments in short term groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). It was observed that the number of PCNA positive cells were higher in animals of group II as compared to untreated animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). The skin sections from untreated animals did not show significant positive staining for PCNA (p&lt;0.01). Treatment with either resveratrol or BTP or both in combination in DMBA and TPA applied animals resulted in significantly low level of PCNA positive cells (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g004">Figure 4B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on phosphorylation and stabilization of tumor suppressor protein, p53</title><p>p53 in response to toxic insults to DNA, triggers a chain of cell cycle regulatory events to check the proliferation of altered cells to repair or minimize the damage <xref rid="pone.0023395-Mowat1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Meek1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and Ser 15 phosphorylation is essential for stabilization and activation of p53 <xref rid="pone.0023395-She1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. To determine whether p53 is phosphorylated at Ser15 in mouse skin tumors (long term study) treated with resveratrol, BTP or their combination, we used a phospho-specific antibody against p53 at Ser15 to do Western blot analysis. Our data showed that the level of p53 phosphorylation at Ser15 was increased in group IV and V upon treatment with resveratrol and BTP as compared with DMBA and TPA group II, however, significant increase in their expression was observed in combination group VI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Immunoblotting showed that the increased level of wild-type p53 protein corresponded well with the increased level of p53 phosphorylation at Ser15. These results are in agreement with earlier reports from our laboratory showing inhibitory effects of resveratrol and BTP individually in DMBA induced mouse skin tumors via enhancement of wild-type p53 <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kalra1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Roy2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. These results suggest that the combination of resveratrol and BTP more efficiently stabilized p53 and induced its phosphorylation at ser15 than either single agent.</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Effects of resveratrol and BTP treatment on modulation of p53 expression and p53 phosphorylation and stabilization.</title><p>Details for groups and treatments are described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and methods</xref> section. The bands shown here are from a representative experiment repeated three times with similar results. Equal loading was confirmed by stripping the immunoblot and reprobing it for β-actin. The pixel density of the specific immunoreactive bands was quantified by densitometry and expressed as a fold difference against β-actin. ** less than corresponding value of untreated control group I (p&lt;0.05). * more than corresponding value of DMBA and TPA group III (p&lt;0.05). <sup>#</sup> more than corresponding value of BTP and Res alone treated groups IV and V (p&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on apoptosis</title><p>Apoptosis is the most potent defence mechanism against cancer <xref rid="pone.0023395-Lowe1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. We next quantified the extent of apoptosis by flow cytometric analysis of the skin cells labelled with Annexin V/PI. Results showed significant (p&lt;0.05) percent increase in apoptotic population by either resveratrol/BTP or the two in combination (6.12±0.34, 5.23±0.52 and 14.00±0.20, respectively) over untreated (2.10±0.36) and DMBA and TPA group II which recorded 1.40±0.15 apoptotic populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g006">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0023395-g006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Representative figure of flow cytometric analysis of apoptosis in mouse skin on treatment with resveratrol and BTP.</title><p>The data is representative of three independent experiments (p&lt;0.05). Details are described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and methods</xref> section. Figure showing cells in the upper right (UR), upper left (UL) and lower right (LR) portions portion of the picture indicates late apoptotic cells, necrotic and pre-apoptotic cells, respectively whereas cells present in lower left (LL) portion of the picture indicate percentage of live cells.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3h"><title>Effect of resveratrol and/or BTP on DMBA and TPA-induced nick formation</title><p>Based on the amount of duplex DNA remaining after alkali treatment, the number of strand breaks generated per unit DNA was determined in mouse skin tissues obtained from short term study. DMBA and TPA caused a significant DNA damage (n = 1.50±0.17) over untreated (n = 0.007±0.001) in terms of strand breaks (p&lt;0.01). Inhibition of DMBA and TPA-induced DNA alkylation damage was recorded by either resveratrol or BTP or the two in combination and prevention percentage was found to be 45.79%, 40.52% and 60.53%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0023395-t003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023395.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Number of DNA strand breaks inhibited by resveratrol or/and BTP against DMBA and TPA- induced DNA alkylation damage.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0023395-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0023395.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of DNA strand breaks (n)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>II</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBA+TPA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50±0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IV</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBA+TPA+resveratrol</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81±0.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">a</xref> (45.79%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>V</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBA+TPA+BTP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90±0.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">a</xref> (40.52%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>VI</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBA+TPA+resveratrol+BTP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60±0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt112">b</xref> (60.53%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt110"><label/><p>Data are expressed as mean ± SD of five animals. ‘n’ represents number of strand breaks of duplex DNA over untreated control group.</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label>a</label><p>significant prevention over DMBA and TPA- induced DNA strand breaks (p&lt;0.01).</p></fn><fn id="nt112"><label>b</label><p>significant prevention over BTP and Res alone treated groups IV and V(p&lt;0.01).</p></fn><fn id="nt113"><label/><p>Values in parenthesis represents the percentage prevention offered by resveratrol or/and BTP against DMBA and TPA- induced DNA strand breaks.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Chemoprevention by using dietary agents in combination is gaining the attention of researchers and consumers as a plausible approach for the management of various neoplasia. In this study, employing two-stage mouse skin carcinogenesis protocol, we are able to show that combined treatment of resveratrol (25 µM/animal) and BTP (0.1%) synergistically suppressed the skin tumors more efficiently than either of these solitary agents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Administration of resveratrol and BTP in combination was found to be highly effective in decreasing the CNT and tumor volume (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0023395-t002">Table 2</xref>). Earlier studies from our laboratory have demonstrated the chemopreventive potential of both the agents against mouse skin carcinogenesis, respectively <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kalra1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Roy2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The central finding of the study is that combined doses of resveratrol and BTP also resulted in significant regression of tumors in regard to both tumor volume and number. Also, no increase in tumor volume or occurrence of tumors was observed in groups (tumor bearing and non tumor-bearing) after withdrawal of the combined treatment. Hence, we observed that resveratrol and BTP (in combination) had superior chemopreventive effects as compared to either resveratrol or BTP.</p><p>MAPKs, comprising a family of serine and threonine kinases of ERK, JNK, and p38, are important signaling components which convert external stimuli into a wide range of cellular responses, such as proliferation, survival, differentiation and migration <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kennedy1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. MAPK signalling cascades are highly relevant in the process of tumor promotion and progression induced by chemical carcinogens in mouse skin carcinogenesis, affecting not only cell proliferation, but also apoptosis by promoting the survival of the tumor cell <xref rid="pone.0023395-Afaq1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Singh1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Activation of the MAPKs pathway occurs in response to integrin-mediated cellular adhesion to the extracellular matrix, which plays a critical role in both tumor metastasis and angiogenesis <xref rid="pone.0023395-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Zhu1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. In the present study, we found that topical application of DMBA and TPA (Gr. II) resulted in a marked increase in the phosphorylated form of ERK1/2, JNK1/2 and p38 protein expression; however, resveratrol and/or BTP treatment inhibited this phosphorylation. Importantly, the combined administration of both resveratrol and BTP was found to be more potent in inhibiting phosphorylation of MAPKs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g002">Figure 2</xref>). These findings suggest a possibility that as an initial response resveratrol and BTP (in combination) modulate MAPKs activation further leads to inhibition of tumor growth and regression by apoptotic cell death.</p><p>In the present study, we further investigated the solitary and combined effect of resveratrol and BTP on expression of proliferation marker PCNA. Enhanced expression of PCNA, a 36 kDa co-factor of DNA polymerase δ, is one of the downstream effects of the activation of MAPK/ERK1/2 signalling and well correlated to the status of cellular proliferation <xref rid="pone.0023395-Singh2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Although single administration of resveratrol and BTP resulted in growth inhibition of DMBA and TPA-induced skin tumors, their combined treatment markedly inhibited the growth accompanying significant decrease in PCNA immunoexpression in tumor sections. Besides this, histologic analysis of the skin tissues of untreated animals displays major epithelial proliferation. In contrast the skin/tumor sections of mice given resveratrol and/or BTP display no indication of neoplasia. Therefore, inhibition of ERK1/2, JNK1/2 and p38 activation, suppression of PCNA upon resveratrol and BTP supplementation in combination, rather than alone treatments, suggest the superiority in synergistic effects of the two. This finding is quite intriguing, and it is tempting to speculate that a combination of resveratrol and BTP might have efficiently more influenced the cell death–related signaling pathways, ultimately leading to the suppression of well-established DMBA and TPA induced tumor in vivo, which might not possibly be achieved by a single administration of resveratrol or BTP.</p><p>To dissect the possible mechanisms in which the apoptotic and/or anti-proliferation signaling were triggered, we also examined the expression levels of the tumor suppressor p53 protein. p53 plays a crucial role in controlling the cell cycle, apoptosis, genomic integrity and DNA repair in response to various forms of stress <xref rid="pone.0023395-Meek1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. As aforementioned, post-translational modifications such as phosphorylation and acetylation are critical for stabilization and activation of p53 <xref rid="pone.0023395-She1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> our data showed that phosphorylation of p53 (Ser15) increased in mouse skin tumors treated with resveratrol and BTP, but the combination induced more efficient stabilization and phosphorylation of p53 protein at (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Consistent with the findings of our previous reports <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kalra1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Roy2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, wild-type p53 activity also increased more in these groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0023395-g005">Figure 5</xref>).Thus, indicate that in mouse skin tumors, growth inhibition induced by resveratrol and/or BTP is p53-dependent and induced p53 phosphorylation at Ser15 may be attributed to stabilization of p53.</p><p>Apoptosis is a selective process of physiological cell deletion that plays an important role in the balance between cellular replication and death. Furthermore, it has been suggested that some cancer chemotherapeutics and chemopreventives exert their effects by triggering either apoptotic cell death or cell cycle transition, and accordingly, the induction of tumor cell apoptosis is used to predict tumor treatment response <xref rid="pone.0023395-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Ahmad1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Therefore, we quantified the extent of apoptosis by flow-cytometric analysis of skin cells labelled with Annexin-V-PI. The results showed that combinatorial effect of resveratrol and BTP, leads to enhanced cell death than either of them alone. In addition, it is further noted that the administration of resveratrol and/or BTP inhibited the DMBA and TPA- induced DNA damage as revealed by the reduction in strand breaks. But combination doses exerted better effects than either of these two agents alone. This might be occurring because both of them are known to have ability to repair DNA damage <xref rid="pone.0023395-Parshad1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0023395-Sengottuvelan1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>.</p><p>In recent years, emerging evidence suggests that cancer-preventive agents might be combined for more effective treatment of cancer <xref rid="pone.0023395-deKok2" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. They can react together to give synergistic action to intervene cancer stages by different signaling pathways or to compensate for the opposite properties in cancer cell proliferation or apoptosis. Thus, we conclude that both resveratrol and BTP at low doses in combination synergistically inhibit established skin tumor growth than either of these agents alone accompanied by decrease in tumor volume and number. This is attributable to reduction in nick formation associated with a decrease in proliferation marker and tumor suppressor protein p53 together with an inhibition of MAPKs signaling and induction of apoptotic cell death in skin cells. Further pre-clinical and clinical trials are warranted to characterize the efficacy of dietary agents in combination with existing therapeutics for chemoprevention and chemotherapy of cancer.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank all their colleagues who were involved in the study for their excellent assistance. The authors are grateful to Director, Indian Institute of Toxicology Research (CSIR) Lucknow, India for his keen interest in the study. They are thankful to Neeraj Mathur, Scientist for statistical analysis of all the data. Authors are thankful to B. P. Chaudhari for all support of histopathological and IHC analysis. Authors also acknowledge Mr. SHN Naqvi for helping in animal experimentation.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by a research grant from Network Project (NWP-017), Council of Scientific &amp; Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi, India. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0023395-deKok1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Kok</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilms</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Breda</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Antioxidative and antigenotoxic properties of vegetables and dietary phytochemicals: the value of genomics biomarkers in molecular epidemiology.</article-title><source>Mol Nutr Food Res</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20024933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mnfr.200900288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Gromadzinska1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gromadzinska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reszka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasowicz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Anticarcinogenic activity of selenium—molecular mechanisms and epidemiological data.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akesson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Dietary vitamins, polyphenols, selenium and probiotics: biomarkers of exposure and mechanisms of anticarcinogenic action</source><publisher-loc>Lodz</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Nofer Institute of Occupational Medicine</publisher-name><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Akesson1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akesson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyrtopoulos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Compounds in food.</article-title><source>Eur J Nutr</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00394-008-2002-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18458830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Xu1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Combination of curcumin and green tea catechins prevents dimethylhydrazine-induced colon carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19861145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fct.2009.10.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-KumiDiaka1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumi-Diaka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haces</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hormann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Genistein-selenium combination induces growth arrest in prostate cancer cells.</article-title><source>J Med Food</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20553187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jmf.2009.0199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Zhou1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Soy phytochemicals and tea bioactive components synergistically inhibit androgen-sensitive human prostate tumors in mice.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jn/133.2.516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2683253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-George1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Synergistic growth inhibition of mouse skin tumors by pomegranate fruit extract and diallyl sulfide: Evidence for inhibition of activated MAPKs/NF-κB and reduced cell proliferation.</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><volume>49</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fct.2011.03.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Ndiaye1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ndiaye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The grape antioxidant Resveratrol for skin disorders: promise, prospects, and challenges.</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><volume>508</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21215251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.abb.2010.12.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3060966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Sil1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sil</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moulik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Black tea polyphenol (theaflavin) downregulates MMP-2 in human melanoma cell line A375 by involving multiple regulatory molecules.</article-title><source>J Environ Pathol Toxicol Oncol</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20528747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1615/jenvironpatholtoxicoloncol.v29.i1.80</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Jang1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udeani</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slowing</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Cancer chemopreventive activity of resveratrol, a natural product derived from grapes.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.275.5297.218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Hsieh1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Resveratrol: Biological and pharmaceutical properties as anticancer molecule.</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20623546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/biof.105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3655417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Bishayee1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishayee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Politis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darvesh</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Resveratrol in the chemoprevention and treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma.</article-title><source>Cancer Treat Rev</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctrv.2009.10.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Liu1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Resveratrol inhibits human lung adenocarcinoma cell metastasis by suppressing heme oxygenase 1-mediated nuclear factor-kappaB pathway and subsequently downregulating expression of matrix metalloproteinases.</article-title><source>Mol Nutr Food Res</source><volume>54</volume><issue>Suppl. 2</issue><fpage>S196</fpage><lpage>S204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20461740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mnfr.200900550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Roy1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Chemopreventive potential of resveratrol in mouse skin tumors through regulation of mitochondrial and PI3K/AKT signaling pathways.</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18791811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11095-008-9723-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Seeni1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Suppression of prostate cancer growth by resveratrol in the transgenic rat for adenocarcinoma of prostate (TRAP) model.</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18439064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kundu1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Resveratrol modulates phorbol ester-induced pro-inflammatory signal transduction pathways in mouse skin in vivo: NF-kappaB and AP-1 as prime targets.</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>1506</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16999939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bcp.2006.08.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kalra1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Resveratrol induces apoptosis involving mitochondrial pathways in mouse skin tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18201729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2007.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Weisburger1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisburger</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Mechanisms of action of antioxidants as exemplified in vegetables, tomatoes and tea.</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0278-6915(99)00086-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Lu1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Differential effects of theaflavin monogallates on cell growth, apoptosis, and Cox-2 gene expression in cancerous versus normal cells.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>6465</fpage><lpage>6471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11103814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Weisberger1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisberger</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivenson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliaga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Effect of black tea on azoxymethane-induced colon cancer.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9472717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/19.1.229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Roy2"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Induction of apoptosis by tea polyphenols mediated through mitochondrial cell death pathway in mouse skin tumors.</article-title><source>Cancer Biol Ther</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cbt.8.13.8728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19556852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Sun1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Green tea, black tea and breast cancer risk: a meta-analysis of epidemiological studies.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1310</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgi276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Baker1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beehler</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodabaugh</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Consumption of black tea or coffee and risk of ovarian cancer.</article-title><source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1525-1438.2006.00773.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kalra2"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Theaflavins induced apoptosis of LNCaP cells is mediated through induction of p53, down-regulation of NF-kappa B and mitogen-activated protein kinases pathways.</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>2137</fpage><lpage>2146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17499812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lfs.2007.04.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Chou1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talalay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Quantitative analysis of dose-effect relationships: the combined effects of multiple drugs or enzyme inhibitors.</article-title><source>Adv Enzyme Regul</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6382953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0065-2571(84)90007-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kataoka1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbajal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DiGiovanni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Stage-specific disruption of Stat3 demonstrates a direct requirement during both the initiation and promotion stages of mouse skin tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1108</fpage><lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgn061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2902397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18453544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Arora1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Modulation of p53 in 7,12-dimethylbenz[a] benzanthracene-induced skin tumors by diallyl sulphide in Swiss albino mice.</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15542785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Lowry1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbrough</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1951</year><article-title>Protein measurement with folin phenol reagent.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>193</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14907713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Bogovaski1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogovaski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year><article-title>Tumours of skin.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turusov</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pathology of tumours in laboratory animals</source><publisher-loc>Lyon</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IARC scientific publication no. 23</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Nigam1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Preventive effects of diallyl sulfide on 7, 12-dimethylbenz[a]anthracene induced DNA alkylation damage in mouse skin.</article-title><source>Mol Nutr Food Res</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>1328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17918166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mnfr.200700140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kundu2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Resveratrol inhibits phorbol ester-induced cyclooxygenase-2 expression in mouse skin: MAPKs and AP-1 as potential molecular targets.</article-title><source>Biofactors</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/biof.552210108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kennedy1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cellurale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A radical role for p38 MAPK in tumor initiation.</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2007.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Mancini1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jezequel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orlandi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of S-phase cells in normal human and rat liver by PC10 monoclonal antibody.</article-title><source>Liver</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-0676.1994.tb00048.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Mowat1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowat</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>p53 in tumor progression: life, death and everything.</article-title><source>Adv Cancer Res</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9561266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0065-230x(08)60764-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Meek1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The p53 response to DNA damage.</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15279792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dnarep.2004.03.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-She1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>She</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>ERKs and p38 kinase phosphorylate p53 protein at serine 15 in response to UV radiation.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>275</volume><fpage>20444</fpage><lpage>20449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10781582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M001020200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Lowe1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Apoptosis in cancer.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/21.3.485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Afaq1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afaq</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Suppression of UVB-induced phosphorylation of mitogen-activated protein kinases and nuclear factor kappa B by green tea polyphenol in SKH-1 hairless mice.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>9254</fpage><lpage>9264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1207035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Singh1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Silymarin inhibits growth and causes regression of established skin tumors in SENCAR mice via modulation of mitogen-activated protein kinases and induction of apoptosis.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11895866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/23.3.499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Chen1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borchers</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>UVB irradiation-induced activator protein-1 activation correlates with increased c-fos gene expression in a human keratinocyte cell line.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>32176</fpage><lpage>32181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9822695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.273.48.32176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Zhu1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacIntyre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Regulation of angiogenesis by vascular endothelial growth factor and angiopoietin-1 in the rat aorta model: distinct temporal patterns of intracellular signaling correlate with induction of angiogenic sprouting.</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><volume>161</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12213710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)64242-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1867259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Singh2"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Silymarin inhibits growth and causes regression of established skin tumors in SENCAR mice via modulation of mitogen-activated protein kinases and induction of apoptosis.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/23.3.499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11895866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Kim1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Ginsenoside Rh2 induces apoptosis independently of Bcl-2, Bcl-xL, or Bax in C6Bu-1 cells.</article-title><source>Arch Pharm Res</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10549570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF02979151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Ahmad1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feyes</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieminen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Green tea constituent epigallocatechin-3-gallate and induction of apoptosis and cell cycle arrest in human carcinoma cells.</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>1881</fpage><lpage>1886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9414176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/89.24.1881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Parshad1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parshad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarone</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Protective action of plant polyphenols on radiation-induced chromatid breaks in cultured human cells.</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>3263</fpage><lpage>3266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-Sengottuvelan1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sengottuvelan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deeptha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nalini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Res ameliorates DNA damage, prooxidant and antioxidant imbalance in 1,2-dimethylhydrazine induced rat colon carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Chem Biol Interact</source><volume>181</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cbi.2009.06.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0023395-deKok2"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Kok</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Breda</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Mechanisms of combined action of different chemopreventive dietary compounds: a review.</article-title><source>Eur J Nutr</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00394-008-2006-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18458834</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>