
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nature</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nature</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">358</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">wtpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0410462</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0028-0836</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-4687</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>UKPMC Funders Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3886898</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3886898.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3886898</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3886898</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">EMS55279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24305048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">EMS55279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">WTPA55279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">WTMS55279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">UKMS55279</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hmga2 functions as a competing endogenous RNA to promote lung cancer progression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names initials="MS">Madhu S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armenteros-Monterroso</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>East</surname><given-names initials="P">Philip</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravorty</surname><given-names initials="P">Probir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names initials="N">Nik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names initials="MM">Monte M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Downward</surname><given-names initials="J">Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Signal Transduction Laboratory, Cancer Research UK London Research Institute, 44 Lincoln’s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3LY, UK.
</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Bioinformatics and Biostatistics Group, Cancer Research UK London Research Institute, 44 Lincoln’s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3LY, UK.
</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Advanced Sequencing Facility, Cancer Research UK London Research Institute, 44 Lincoln’s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3LY, UK.
</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Genetics, Department of Pathology, the Stanford Cancer Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford CA 94305, USA.
</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Lung Cancer Group, Division of Cancer Biology, The Institute of Cancer Research, 237 Fulham Road, London SW3 6JB, UK.
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to J.D. (<email>julian.downward@cancer.org.uk</email>).</corresp><fn id="FN1"><p id="P1"><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> M.S.K. and J.D. designed the study. M.S.K. and E.A.M. performed the experiments described. M.S.K., P.E., and P.C. conducted bioinformatics analyses. N.M. performed the next-generation sequencing studies. M.M.W. provided necessary reagents and conceptual advice. M.S.K. and J.D. wrote the manuscript.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>505</volume><issue>7482</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">232028</issue-id><elocation-id>10.1038/nature12785</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>25</day><month>06</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-05 22:06:41.443"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, download and text and data- mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="emss-55279.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="other" vol="24" page="259" journal-id="Cell Res" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC3945890"><article-title>Aberrant ceRNA activity drives lung cancer</article-title><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><source>Cell Research</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3945890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24525785</pub-id></related-article><related-article related-article-type="commentary" vol="14" page="73"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="523" page="370" journal-id="Nature" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4527149"><article-title>Retraction: HMGA2 functions as a competing endogenous RNA to promote lung cancer progression</article-title><volume>523</volume><issue>7560</issue><date><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><source>Nature</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4527149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26061768</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p id="P2">Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is the most prevalent histological cancer subtype worldwide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. As the majority of patients present with invasive, metastatic disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>, it is vital to understand the basis for lung cancer progression. <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> is highly expressed in metastatic lung adenocarcinoma where it contributes to cancer progression and metastasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. Here we show that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> promotes lung cancer progression by operating as a competing endogenous RNA (ceRNA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> microRNA (miRNA) family. <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> can promote the transformation of lung cancer cells independent of protein-coding function but dependent upon the presence of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> sites; this occurs without changes in the levels of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> isoforms, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> affects <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> activity by altering miRNA targeting. These effects are further observed <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, where <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity drives lung cancer growth, invasion and dissemination. Integrated analysis of miRNA target prediction algorithms and metastatic lung cancer gene expression data reveals the TGF-β co-receptor <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> as a putative target of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function. <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> expression is regulated by the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA via differential recruitment to Argonaute-2 (Ago2), and TGF-β signalling driven by Tgfbr3 is largely necessary for <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> to promote lung cancer progression. Finally, analysis of NSCLC patient gene expression data reveals that <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> are co-ordinately regulated in NSCLC patient material, a vital corollary to ceRNA function. Taken together, these results suggest that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> promotes lung carcinogenesis as both a protein-coding gene and a non-coding RNA; such dual-function regulation of gene expression networks reflects a novel means by which oncogenes promote disease progression.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="United Kingdom">Cancer Research UK : </funding-source><award-id>A3570 || CRUK_</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="P3">The competing endogenous RNA hypothesis posits that specific RNAs can function as sinks for pools of active miRNAs, functionally liberating other transcripts targeted by that set of miRNAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Downregulation of the transcription factor Nkx2.1 promotes lung adenocarcinoma progression partially via derepression of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>, a non-histone chromosomal high mobility group protein. Intriguingly, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> has been described as a prototypic <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target transcript, with seven conserved sites in its 3′ untranslated region (3′ UTR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Reduction of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> by RNA interference, which would deplete both Hmga2 protein and transcript, greatly reduces metastatic ability. Thus, it is possible that the transcript could operate independent of the protein in lung cancer progression.</p><p id="P4">To determine if <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> can operate as a ceRNA for the <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> family, we generated an allelic series of Hmga2 expression constructs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). In this series, we expressed the wild-type full-length <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> cDNA (wt); <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> with mutation of all seven predicted <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> binding sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> (m7); <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> with mutation of the single in-frame start codon (ATG wt); or <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> with mutation of both the start codon and the <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> binding sites (ATG m7). We then examined these constructs in two lung cancer cell lines generated from the <italic toggle="yes">Kras<sup>LSL-G12D</sup>;Trp53<sup>flox/flox</sup></italic> mouse model: a cell line derived from a non-metastatic lung tumour which expresses very low levels of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> (368T1); and a cell line derived from a lymph node metastasis which expresses high levels of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> (482N1) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. Using two antibodies that recognize either the N-terminus or the second AT-hook of the protein (M. Narita, personal communication), we found that the Hmga2 wt and m7 constructs efficiently express full-length Hmga2 protein (m7 over-expresses Hmga2 due to loss of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> mediated suppression) while the Hmga2 ATG wt and ATG m7 constructs do not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). Importantly, we observe similar levels of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> transcript expressed in the allelic series (in the case of the 482N1 cell line, the allelic series was mutated to abrogate binding to a short hairpin RNA [shRNA] against <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). Moreover, expression of the allelic series has no effect on the expression of various <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> family members (Extended Data Fig. 1a). Taken together, this <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series allows us to compare specifically the roles of Hmga2 protein and transcript function on lung cell transformation.</p><p id="P5">We therefore compared the ability of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series to promote anchorage-independent growth of the lung cancer cell lines. We observed a striking promotion of soft agar growth by both Hmga2 wt and ATG wt in the 368T1 and 482N1 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1d and e</xref>); more modest growth was observed with Hmga2 m7, despite elevated protein expression relative to Hmga2 wt, and no growth was provided by Hmga2 ATG m7. This effect can be observed further in two additional human lung cancer cells (H1299 and SK-MES-1), as suppression of soft agar growth by <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> depletion can be rescued robustly by Hmga2 wt and ATG wt but more modestly by Hmga2 m7 (Extended Data Fig. 1b-e). Importantly, exogenous expression of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> reversed the ability of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA to promote anchorage-independent growth, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> regulates this effect (Extended Data Fig. 2b). To demonstrate that the effect of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA is driven by <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> sites in the 3′ untranslated region (3′UTR), we expressed only the wild type or <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> site mutated 3′UTRs in 368T1 cells and examined the consequences on anchorage-independent growth. Strikingly, expression of the wild type but not <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> mutant 3′UTR was sufficient to promote soft agar growth in 368T1 cells (Extended Data Fig. 2c).</p><p id="P6">Beyond direct <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> depletion, the Hmga2 wt and Hmga2 ATG wt constructs substantially rescued anchorage-independent growth in 482N1 cells stably over-expressing Nkx2.1, which we have previously shown to suppress lung cancer progression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> (Extended Data Fig. 2d). Notably, this effect is not due to a general proliferative benefit of Hmga2 wt and ATG wt cells, as BrdU incorporation in adherent conditions was comparable across the allelic series (Extended Data Fig. 3a). However, when lung cancer cells are placed in suspension, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> depletion suppressed proliferation and this proliferation was rescued substantially by Hmga2 wt and ATG wt and more marginally by Hmga2 m7 (Extended Data Fig. 3b); in contrast, the rate of apoptosis in the allelic series was not affected by growth in suspension (data not shown). Taken together, these results suggest that the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> transcript functions in a largely protein coding-independent but <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> site-dependent manner to promote lung cancer cell transformation <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</p><p id="P7">To examine the effect of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity on lung cancer cell dissemination <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, we intravenously transplanted 482N1 cells expressing either the control shRNA and expression construct or the shRNA targeting <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> plus the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series into syngeneic mice. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>, micro-CT analysis revealed a substantial rescue of lung tumour formation with expression of either the Hmga2 wt or ATG wt constructs (with more modest effects with the Hmga2 m7 construct). Histopathological analysis and quantification of surface lesions confirmed the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity on <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> lung tumourigenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2b and c</xref>). Moreover, the control shRNA, the shHmga2 plus Hmga2 wt and the shHmga2 plus Hmga2 ATG wt transplants generate a highly metastatic disease, with lesions disseminating to both local and distant lymph nodes, kidney, and the abdominal and thoracic cavities (data not shown). We also examined the effect of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function on survival in the transplant system. We observed a dramatic reduction in survival in animals transplanted with the Hmga2 wt and ATG wt cells, similar to that seen with transplant of the control shRNA cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>); we noted a more modest reduction in survival with transplant of the Hmga2 m7 cells. In total, these findings indicate that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> competing RNA activity dramatically promotes <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> lung cancer formation.</p><p id="P8">To elucidate the mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function on lung carcinogenesis, we analysed the set of genes differentially expressed between metastatic and non-metastatic <italic toggle="yes">Kras<sup>G12D</sup>;Trp53<sup><italic toggle="yes">flox</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">flox</italic></sup></italic>lung cancer cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> and compared them to the list of predicted <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target genes based upon the miRNA target prediction algorithm TargetScan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Kras</italic> was not a candidate in this analysis, in spite of previous description of <italic toggle="yes">Kras</italic> as an important <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Moreover, the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series had no impact on either expression of K-Ras protein or activity of downstream K-Ras signalling pathways (Extended Data Fig. 3c). In contrast, we observed several known Hmga2 transcriptional targets, including components of the Igf2bp family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>, validating this approach.</p><p id="P9">To elucidate more broadly which transcripts are <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets, we initially examined whether let-7 sites are enriched among transcripts induced by the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA through RNA-seq of the 482N1 allelic series combined with Sylamer analysis, which detects miRNA seed sites as nucleotide strings enriched within the 3′UTRs of transcripts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. We first compared control to <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> knockdown cells and observed a specific enrichment of let-7 sites lost with <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> depletion (Extended Data Fig. 4a). We then determined if this was specific to ceRNA activity by determining let-7 site enrichment upon re-expression of either the Hmga2 wt or ATG wt constructs in <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> knockdown cells. In both conditions, let-7 sites were enriched among the up-regulated transcripts (Extended Data Fig. 4b and c) Importantly, let-7 sites were not enriched with re-expression of either Hmga2 m7 or ATG m7 in the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>-depleted background (Extended Data Fig. 4d and e). Moreover, analysis of fragments per kilobase of exon per million fragments mapped (FPKM) in the RNA-seq results from control 482N1 cells showed <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> was among the most highly expressed predicted <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target transcripts, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> constitutes a physiologically germane fraction of the <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target milieu (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA broadly regulates let-7 targets.</p><p id="P10">To more specifically assess <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets, we examined which transcripts were suppressed in response to <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> depletion; 13 out of 34 predicted targets were suppressed by <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> knockdown (Extended Data Fig. 5a). To delineate which of these were Hmga2 transcriptional targets versus ceRNA targets, we re-expressed either Hmga2 wt or ATG wt in knockdown cells. As seen in Extended Data Figure 5b, 6 out of 13 transcripts were rescued by both Hmga2 wt and ATG wt, suggesting they are putative ceRNA targets; the remaining targets were rescued only by Hmga2 wt, suggesting they are targets of Hmga2 transcription factor function. These <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets were strikingly enriched in <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> regulated transcripts, as their repression by Hmga2 loss could be reversed with the use of a ‘tough decoy’ <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> sponge transcript, designed to be an efficient and long-term suppressor of miRNA function (Extended Data Fig. 5c)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. Conversely, over-expression of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> suppressed these transcripts, although Hmga2 transcriptional targets were also affected due to depletion of Hmga2 (Extended Data Fig. 5d). Taken together, these studies outline a collection of putative target transcripts regulated by <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function.</p><p id="P11">Among these six <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA target transcripts, we found the TGF-β co-receptor <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> to be both up-regulated in metastatic lung cancer cells and a putative <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> target. Furthermore, several <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets have been described as targets of TGF-β signalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Thus, we examined whether <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> exerts ceRNA function through enhanced TGF-β signalling via Tgfbr3. In line with this, we found that in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt promote the expression of Tgfbr3 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). This <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> up-regulation also occurs to a lesser degree at the mRNA level, as has been described previously for miRNA targets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Moreover, exogenous expression of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> reversed the ability of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA to up-regulate Tgfbr3, suggesting this effect is controlled by <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> (Extended Data Fig. 2a). An important consideration in ceRNA/target analysis is the absolute levels of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> transcripts in cells, so we determined the copies per cell of these factors (Extended Data Fig. 4f). We observed that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> had similar levels of transcript, as one might expect for two factors that can titrate expression of one another; similar results were observed in FPKM analysis of these transcripts in control 482N1 cells by RNA-seq (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Furthermore, total <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> family expression was within an order of magnitude of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>. As this pool of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> regulates the entire target set, one could expect miRNA occupancy to be a limiting factor, allowing for the contribution of a ceRNA-like <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>. Taken together, these results suggest that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> could regulate Tgfbr3 expression as a <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> ceRNA.</p><p id="P12">In line with these observations of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> promoting Tgfbr3 expression, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt activated TGF-β signalling via phosphorylation of Smad2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). This effect was <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> dependent, as exogenous <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> suppressed Smad2 phosphorylation (Extended Data Fig. 2a). That the TGF-β pathway is active in the absence of exogenous ligand is likely due to low but detectable levels of TGF-β in serum during cell culture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. We further examined whether <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function affects TGF-β pathway activation by two methods. First, we found that a TGF-β reporter (CAGA12)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> was potently induced by Hmga2 wt and ATG wt (Extended Data Fig. 5e). Second, analysis of TGF-β target transcript levels revealed specific expression of these genes with the Hmga2 wt and ATG wt constructs (Extended Data Fig. 5f). Notably, we observed little activation of the TGF-β pathway by Hmga2 m7, in spite of previous reports of Hmga2 functioning as a Smad2/3/4 co-activator in the epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>; this is likely due to the lack of upstream activation of the pathway. In line with this, the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA does not induce an EMT in either 368T1 or 482N1 cells (Extended Data Fig. 6a). Overall, these results indicate that the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA induces expression of Tgfbr3 and potentiates TGF-β signalling.</p><p id="P13">To determine whether the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> on <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> occur via <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> mediated de-repression, we first examined the effect of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function on a reporter containing the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> 3′ UTR. In both 368T1 and 482N1 cells, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt induced expression of luciferase under the control of the wild type <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> 3′ UTR, but not if the <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> site was mutated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). Furthermore, we found that the effect of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA was broadly miRNA dependent, as Hmga2 wt and ATG wt induced the reporter expression in <italic toggle="yes">Dicer1</italic>-intact sarcoma cells, but not in a <italic toggle="yes">Dicer1</italic>-null derivative cell line<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> (Extended Data Fig. 6b). To assess directly whether <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> induces <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> via competition away from Ago2, we performed RNA immunoprecipitation (RIP) on Ago2 in lung cancer cells expressing the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3d</xref>, we found that Hmga2 wt and ATG wt were as comparably recruited to Ago2 as endogenous Hmga2 while Hmga2 m7 and ATG m7 were not. Moreover, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt cells had a substantial decrease in <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> recruitment to Ago2. Of note, these effects on Ago2 occupancy by <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> are not caused by a change in <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> activity, as various <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> family members were comparably loaded on Ago2 across the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series (Extended Data Fig. 7). Thus, these results demonstrate <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>, via its <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> binding sites, displaces <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> from miRNA-mediated repression by RISC. In total, these results suggest the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA directly functions by blocking recruitment of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> to the Ago2-based miRNA repression complex.</p><p id="P14">To examine whether <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity through Tgfbr3 is functionally relevant, we used shRNAs to deplete <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> in 482N1 cells and 368T1 cells expressing either Hmga2 wt or ATG wt. At both the mRNA and protein level, multiple shRNAs reduced Tgfbr3 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3e and f</xref>). Moreover, knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> led to substantial suppression of TGF-β signalling, as evinced by loss of Smad2 phosphorylation, CAGA12 reporter activity and expression of TGF-β target genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 8a and b). We then assessed the functional effect of Tgfbr3 loss on <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA-driven soft agar colony formation. In all cells, <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> knockdown strikingly suppressed anchorage-independent growth, though not to the same extent as <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> depletion in 482N1 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>). This occurred without generally affecting proliferation, as measured by BrdU incorporation (Extended Data Fig. 8c). We further functionally analysed the broader set of six <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets by individually depleting them by siRNA (Extended Data Fig. 8d). When we compared their effects on anchorage-independent growth, both <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> loss strongly suppressed growth, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga1</italic> depletion modestly reduced colony formation, while the remaining targets had little effect (Extended Data Fig. 8e). It should be noted that these other targets include extracellular factors like Angptl2 and Col1a2 that might promote lung cancer progression <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> in a non-cell autonomous manner, and could thus still be relevant to <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity in lung cancer progression. This considered, these results still indicate that <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>, though certainly not the only relevant <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA target, is an important effector of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function in lung cancer cell transformation.</p><p id="P15">To determine if this effect of Tgfbr3 is driven through potentiation of TGF-β signalling, we inhibited the TGF-β pathway with the TGF-β receptor kinase inhibitor SB-431542 (SB)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. In 368T1 and 482N1 cells, SB treatment led to a substantial inhibition of Smad2 phosphorylation (Extended Data Fig. 9a). In addition, SB treatment of 482N1 and 368T1 Hmga2 wt and ATG wt cells markedly suppressed CAGA12 reporter activity and expression of TGF-β target genes (Extended Data Fig. 9b and c). We then examined whether SB could inhibit <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA driven soft agar colony formation and observed a striking reduction in anchorage-independent growth (Extended Data Fig. 9d). This impaired colony formation was not due to general proliferative arrest, as SB treated cells had a similar rate of BrdU incorporation (Extended Data Fig. 9e). Strikingly, many <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets are in fact TGF-β target genes, as their expression is suppressed by SB treatment and induced by exogenous addition of TGF-β (Extended Data Fig. 9f and g). Thus, it is possible that <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> could function in a feed forward loop in which it regulates TGF-β target genes directly through ceRNA function and indirectly through TGF-β signalling via Tgfbr3. In sum, these results indicate that TGF-β signalling via Tgfbr3 is an important pathway downstream of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA function.</p><p id="P16">Based upon the above findings, we wanted to explore if <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> functions as a ceRNA for <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> (the human orthologues of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>, respectively) in NSCLC patients. An important corollary of the ceRNA hypothesis is the coordinate regulation of a competing RNA and its targets, such that up-regulation of the ceRNA should lead to higher expression of the target RNA and vice versa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. To assess this, we used NSCLC gene expression data generated by the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) and sorted the patient cohort into the top and bottom quartiles of <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> expression (HMGA2 high and low, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>, we observed significantly higher levels of <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> transcript in <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> high versus low patient samples. To address the converse relationship, we sorted the TCGA data set into top and bottom quartiles of <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> expression (TGFBR3 high and low, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>). When we compared <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> transcript levels between the groups, we found <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> to be significantly over-expressed in <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> high versus low patient samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). To extend and validate these findings, we performed similar gene expression analyses of <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> in an independent lung adenocarcinoma patient gene expression cohort, the Director’s Challenge data set<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. Similar to the findings with the TCGA cohort, we observed <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> to be co-ordinately expressed in the Director’s Challenge data set (Extended Data Fig. 10a-d). While we focused specifically on high and low expressors of <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic>, where ceRNA activity is more likely to occur<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGBR3</italic> expression was broadly correlated across both data sets (Extended Data Fig. 10e and f). As these two data sets constitute two of the largest collections of NSCLC gene expression data available, we believe these findings are in line with <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> functioning as a ceRNA for <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> in NSCLC patients. It is possible that the co-expression of <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> could correspond to additional tumour characteristics these data sets do not include; future studies in independent data sets would be needed to assess this issue. In total, our results suggest a model by which <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> promotes lung cancer progression by competing for <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> occupancy with other targets, including <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>, leading to the up-regulation of those targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>). Importantly, this occurs without changes in the levels of <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> family microRNAs, reflecting specific competition for microRNA binding among targets.</p><p id="P17">Here we have outlined a novel gene expression pathway in which a protein-coding gene, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>, operates largely independently of its protein-coding function to promote lung cancer progression as a competing endogenous RNA. While much of this ceRNA activity is driven by over-expression of TGF-β signalling via Tgfbr3, there are likely additional <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA targets to be found in future studies. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> is over-expressed in many other cancer types<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, making it possible that <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> functions as a ceRNA in cancer sites beyond lung. Taken more broadly, these findings raise the possibility that many protein-coding genes differentially expressed in cancer might contribute to tumourigenesis through this distinct mode of regulatory gene expression. Moreover, these results raise issues with the validation of candidates in RNA interference screens. The “gold standard” assay for validating an siRNA target is expression of an siRNA-resistant form of the coding sequence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>; however, such an approach overlooks the possibility that depletion of both the full-length RNA and protein might contribute to a given phenotype, requiring complementation by the full-length transcript. Such dual-function ceRNA/protein activities necessitate a deeper exploration of the coding genome in biological systems.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="S6" specific-use="web-only"><title>Online-only Methods</title><sec id="S7"><title>Cell lines</title><p id="P23">368T1 and 482N1 cells were generated previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. KPD F/- and −/− sarcoma cells were a kind gift of Phillip A. Sharp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. Cancer Research UK Cell Services provided HEK293, Phoenix ampho, NCI-H1299, and SK-MES-1 cells. All cell lines were cultured in DMEM medium with 10% FBS, 10 mM glutamine and 1% penicillin and streptomycin at 37°C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/95% air incubator.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Drug and reagent treatment</title><p id="P24">For Western, luciferase, qRT-PCR, and BrdU analysis, 368T1 cells were co-treated with 2 ng/mL TGF-β and either DMSO or 2.5 μM SB-431542 (“SB”) and 482N1 cells were treated with either DMSO or 2.5 μM SB-431542 for 24 hours. For soft agar analysis, cells were fed with media containing either DMSO or SB.</p><p id="P25">For Western analyses, 368T1 and 482N1 cells were plated (2.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells) into 6-well plates overnight. Cells were then treated with DMSO, 1 μM AZD6244 or 1 μM PIK-75 for two hours and lysates were prepared.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Lentivirus and retrovirus production</title><p id="P26">Short hairpin RNA (shRNA) lentiviruses (which are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) were generated by co-transfection of HEK293 cells with shRNA vector and packaging vectors pCMV-VSVG and pCMV-8.2. MSCV-based retroviruses were generated by transfection of Phoenix ampho cells with retroviral vectors. 48 and 72 hours after transfection, virus particles in the medium were harvested, filtered, and transduced onto cells.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Stable cell line generation</title><p id="P27">Expression vectors were initially linearized overnight using BglII. Linearised DNA was then transfected into cells in 24-well plates, with media replaced six hours later. Cells were then replated into 6-well plates in the presence of 500 μg/mL G418 for selection over two weeks. For lentiviral and retroviral infection, cells were infected in 6-well plates and subsequently split into 10 cm dishes in the presence of 2.5 μg/mL puromycin for selection over 72 hours.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Western blotting</title><p id="P28">Western blotting was performed by standard methods. Antibody details are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="P29">RNA was isolated using RNA-Bee using manufacturers’ instructions. Both standard and miRNA-specific qRT-PCR was performed using QuantiTect SYBR Green primers as per manufacturers’ instructions (QIAGEN). Primer details are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Luciferase assays</title><sec id="S14"><title>CAGA12</title><p id="P30">Cells were seeded into 96-well plates in triplicate and co-transfected with pRL-TK (Promega) and either control pGL3 or the TGF-β reporter pCAGA12-GL3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. 24 hours later, luciferase activities were determined using the Dual-Luciferase Assay System as per manufacturers’ instructions (Promega).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title><italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> 3′ UTR</title><p id="P31">Cells were seeded into 96-well plates in triplicate and co-transfected with pGL3 (Promega) and either the control pRL-CXCR4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> or the wild type/mutant fragment of the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> 3′ UTR. Luciferase activities were determined as above.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><title>BrdU analysis</title><p id="P32">Cells were plated in triplicate into six-well plates overnight (2.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well). They were then treated with 10 μM BrdU for one hour, trypsinized, washed in PBS and stained for BrdU/DAPI analysis using standard methods by the Cancer Research UK Flow Cytometry Facility.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>siRNA/miRNA transfection</title><p id="P33">Cells were transfected with siRNA/miRNA as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Cells were subsequently plated into soft agar assays as above or harvested for RNA/protein as above.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>polyHEMA plating analysis</title><p id="P34">6-well plates were either mock coated or coated with (polyHEMA) as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. Cells were subsequently plated into these 6-wells overnight and BrdU analysis was performed as described above.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Histopathological analysis</title><p id="P35">After sacrifice by CO<sub>2</sub> asphyxiation, lungs were collected from animals and fixed overnight in 10% formalin. They were subsequently placed in 70% ethanol and submitted for embedding, sectioning, and hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> transcription</title><p id="P36">TOPO cloned fragments of <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> were <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> transcribed using the SP6 MAXIscript kit as per manufacturers’ instructions (Ambion). RNA was subsequently purified using the RNEasy cleanup kit as per manufacturers’ instructios (Qiagen).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Transcript copy number analysis</title><p id="P37">For determination of transcript copy number, RNA was prepared from 2 × 10<sup>6</sup> 482N1 cells using RNA Bee as described above. qRT-PCR was performed for <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">let-7a/c/e/f/i</italic> as described above. C<sub>T</sub> values were compared to a two-fold dilution series of either <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> transcribed <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> or synthetic <italic toggle="yes">let-7a/c/e/f/i</italic> miRNA mimics (Qiagen). Moles of transcript and copies of transcript per cell were then calculated using standard stoichiometric methods. Confidence intervals were calculated using a t-statistic.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>RNA library production and next-generation sequencing (RNA-seq)</title><p id="P38">Total RNA was generated from the 482N1 <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series (with biological triplicates) as described above. The Total RNA samples were initially quality controlled (QC) using the 6000 Nano RNA Chip on the BioAnalyser 2100 (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) to ensure RNA integrity and estimate concentration before starting the procedure. If the samples passed the initial QC the Total RNA samples were subjected to poly-A selection using Sera-Mag oligo (dT) beads (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.), and the bound poly-A RNA species utilized for downstream library prep using the Illumina mRNA kit RS-122-2101 (TruSeq Stranded mRNA Sample Prep. Illumina San Diego, CA, USA). The standard PCR cycles suggested in the protocol were also altered to match the concentration of the total RNA from the initial QC. After production of the mRNA libraries a final QC was performed on a DNA 1000 chip using the BioAnalyser 2100 (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA). If the mRNA libraries passed the QC they were ready for flow cell cluster formation on a cBot and then 100 b.p. Paired End (PE) sequencing by synthesis on the HiSeq 2500 was performed.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>RNA-seq data processing and analyses</title><p id="P39">We aligned 100 b.p. paired-end sequencing reads to the mouse genome (mm9, UCSC) using Tophat2/Bowtie2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> allowing for 5 mismatches, a mate-inner-distribution of −40 and a mate-standard-deviation of 50. These library fragment metrics were derived from an alignment of 5e5 sampled reads to the mouse transcriptome. We identified read-pair mappings to gene structures derived from RefSeq (RefGene table, UCSC) using the summarizeOverlaps function with mode IntersectStrict (GenomicRanges, Bioconductor). This generated a mean fragments per sample value of 33.5e6. Using these raw counts we identified genes expressed across the sample groups. We removed genes with a count &lt;= 10 across all samples prior to statistical analysis. The differential analysis was carried out using edgeR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> applying TMM library normalisation and a 0.0005 false discovery rate (fdr) to select expressed transcripts. In addition, we calculated gene level fragments per kilobase of exon per million fragments mapped (FPKM) values for the same gene set using Cufflinks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Sylamer analysis</title><p id="P40">A list of Ensembl gene IDs was generated from the set of transcripts expressed in the samples described above. This set of transcripts was then placed in rank order by their differential expression between two groups and analysed using the Sylamer algorithm via the SylArray platform<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. A Sylamer plot was then generated for all 8mer miRNA strings whose target sites were enriched significantly (p&lt;0.001 by hypergeometric testing).</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Statistical testing</title><p id="P41">Unless otherwise specified, statistical significance was assessed by the Student’s t-test.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Vector cloning</title><sec id="S27"><title>Hmga2</title><p id="P42">pCDNA3.1-Hmga2 wt and Hmga2 m7 (“wt” and “m7”) were acquired from Addgene (Plasmid nos. 14789 and 14792)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. In order to generate pCDNA3.1-Hmga2 ATG wt and pCDNA3.1-Hmga2 ATG m7 (“ATG wt” and “ATG m7”), the wt and m7 constructs were mutated by site-directed mutagenesis as per manufacturers’ instructions (Stratagene) using primers 5′-GGTAGCGGCGGCGGGAGGCAGGCTGAGCGCACGCGGTGAGG-3′ and 5′-CCTCACCGCGTGCGCTCAGCCTGCCTCCCGCCGCCGCTACC-3′. For generation of 482N1 shHmga2 stable cell lines, “wt”, “m7”, “ATG wt” and “ATG m7” the shRNA binding site was mutated using primers 5′-CCATTTCTGCAAGCTAAGTATGTTTGCAGGAGCCCCGGCTCCGGACGCGTAACTG CATCCAACTTTCTCC-3′ and 5′-GGAGAAAGTTGGATGCAGTTACGCGTCCGGAGCCGGGGCTCCTGCAAACATACT TAGCTTGCAGAAATGG-3′.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>pRL-Tgfbr3</title><p id="P43">A fragment containing the Tgfbr3 3′UTR was PCR amplified from 482N1 cDNA using primers 5′-TAAGAACTCGAGCTGCGTGTGTTCTCCGCAG-3′ and 5′-TAACAAGCGGCCGCCTGTCAGTTTAATGAACGAACC-3′. Both the PCR product and pRL-CXCR4 were digested with XhoI and NotI and ligated together to generate pRL-Tgfbr3. The let-7 mutant was generated by site-directed mutagenesis as above using primers 5′-GCAGGCGCGTGCCTGTCTTTTTGTACTGTAACGGGCTCATGGTTTGAATGATGAG CGTACTGCTGGTTG-3′ and 5′-CAACCAGCAGTACGCTCATCATTCAAACCATGAGCCCGTTACAGTACAAAAAGA CAGGCACGCGCCTGC-3′.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Hmga2-TOPO/Tgfbr3-TOPO</title><p id="P44">A fragment containing the Hmga2 cDNA sequence recognized by the respective qRT-PCR primers was PCR amplified from 482N1 cDNA using primers 5′-CTACATCCCGTCTCCCGAAAGGTGCTGG-3′ and 5′-GGATCCGGTAGAAATTGAATGTCGGCGCCCCCTAATC-3′. A fragment containing the Tgfbr3 cDNA sequence recognized by the respective qRT-PCR primers was PCR amplified from 482N1 cDNA using primers 5′-CTCGAGCAGAAGAAGTGCAAGGGGGCGTGAATATCG-3′ and 5′-CCATGTTGAAGGTAGCATTTCCATCGAGCTGGTCCTGGAAG-3′. PCR products were subsequently TOPO cloned as per manufacturers’ instructions (Invitrogen) and used as substrates for <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> transcription.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Hmga2 wt/m7 3′UTR</title><p id="P45">A fragment containing the Hmga2 3′UTR was PCR amplified from the Hmga2 wt or Hmga2 m7 pcDNA3.1 constructs used for transfection. Products were amplified using primers 5′-GCAGAATTCGGGGCGCCGACATTCAATTTC-3′ and 5′-TAAGCGGCCGCGCCCACAGAGGCTGTTATGTTTATTG-3′. PCR products were subsequently TOPO cloned as per manufacturers’ instructions (Invitrogen). TOPO clone inserts and pcDNA3.1-Hmga2 wt were EcoRI digested and ligated together to generate pcDNA3.1-Hmga2 wt 3′UTR and pcDNA3.1-Hmga2 m7 3′UTR.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Tables 1-6</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS55279-supplement-1.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="octet-stream" orientation="portrait" id="d36e1244" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S31"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the laboratory of T. Jacks for providing the 482N1 and 368T1 lung cancer cell lines and the laboratories of P.A. Sharp and P. Chambon for providing the KPD sarcoma cell lines. We thank the LRI FACS Facility for the BrdU analyses and the LRI Biological Resources Unit for assistance with the animal studies. We thank M.S. Ebert and E. De Bruin for critical review of the manuscript. M.S.K. is a Long-Term Fellow of the Human Frontier Science Program and the European Molecular Biology Organization. This work was funded by Cancer Research UK and by the European Commission’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under the grant agreement Lungtarget (project n° 259770).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2"><p id="P46"><bold>Author Information:</bold> Reprints and permissions information is available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/reprints">www.nature.com/reprints</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p id="P100">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimates of worldwide burden of cancer in 2008: GLOBOCAN 2008</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>2893</fpage><lpage>2917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21351269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.25516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heymach</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra0802714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10662965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Cello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HMGA2 participates in transformation in human lung cancer</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18505920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-07-0095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3086547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HMGA2 overexpression in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Mol Carcinog</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17477356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mc.20235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarhadi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased expression of high mobility group A proteins in lung cancer</article-title><source>J Pathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16521118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/path.1960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winslow</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Suppression of lung adenocarcinoma progression by Nkx2-1</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>473</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature09881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3088778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA sponges: competitive inhibitors of small RNAs in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17694064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth1079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3857099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karreth</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo identification of tumor-suppressive PTEN ceRNAs in an oncogenic BRAF-induced mouse model of melanoma</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22000016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2011.09.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3236086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poliseno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A coding-independent function of gene and pseudogene mRNAs regulates tumour biology</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>465</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20577206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature09144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3206313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poliseno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kats</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A ceRNA hypothesis: the Rosetta Stone of a hidden RNA language?</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21802130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2011.07.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3235919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coding-independent regulation of the tumor suppressor PTEN by competing endogenous mRNAs</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22000013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2011.09.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3235920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression cloning and characterization of the TGF-beta type III receptor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1657407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90074-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemann</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disrupting the pairing between let-7 and Hmga2 enhances oncogenic transformation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1137999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2556962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farh</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Most mammalian mRNAs are conserved targets of microRNAs</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.082701.108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2612969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RAS is regulated by the let-7 microRNA family</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2005.01.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brants</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of the insulin-like growth factor II mRNA-binding protein genes by architectural transcription factor HMGA2</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2004</year><volume>569</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2004.05.075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abreu-Goodger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting microRNA binding and siRNA off-target effects from expression data</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth.1267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2635553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term, efficient inhibition of microRNA function in mice using rAAV vectors</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth.1903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3420816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGFbeta signalling in context</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm3434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4027049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingolia</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian microRNAs predominantly act to decrease target mRNA levels</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>466</volume><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20703300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature09267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2990499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depletion of TGF-beta from fetal bovine serum</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20837018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jim.2010.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2989462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct binding of Smad3 and Smad4 to critical TGF beta-inducible elements in the promoter of human plasminogen activator inhibitor-type 1 gene</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3091</fpage><lpage>3100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9606191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/17.11.3091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1170648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thuault</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HMGA2 and Smads co-regulate SNAIL1 expression during induction of epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>33437</fpage><lpage>33446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18832382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M802016200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2662269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proliferation and tumorigenesis of a murine sarcoma cell line in the absence of DICER1</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>848</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22698408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2012.04.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3385871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SB-431542 is a potent and specific inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta superfamily type I activin receptor-like kinase (ALK) receptors ALK4, ALK5, and ALK7</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/mol.62.1.65</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shedden</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression-based survival prediction in lung adenocarcinoma: a multi-site, blinded validation study</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18641660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm.1790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2667337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Let-7 prevents early cancer progression by suppressing expression of the embryonic gene HMGA2</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2585</fpage><lpage>2590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17957144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.6.21.4845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaelin</surname><given-names>WG</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology. Use and abuse of RNAi to study mammalian gene function</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1225787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3705935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The GATA2 transcriptional network is requisite for RAS oncogene-driven non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22541434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2012.02.059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doench</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>siRNAs can function as miRNAs</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1064703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC195999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liau</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jazag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whang</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of HMGA1 promotes anoikis resistance and constitutive Akt activation in pancreatic adenocarcinoma cells</article-title><source>British journal of cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage><comment>doi:10.1038/sj.bjc.6603654</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17342093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bjc.6603654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2360112</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12152181"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</article-title><source>Genome biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>R36</fpage><comment>doi:10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4053844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><comment>doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2796818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</article-title><source>Nature biotechnology</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><comment>doi:10.1038/nbt.2450</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.2450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3869392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222703</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Hmga2 promotes lung cancer cell transformation in a protein-coding independent but <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> site dependent manner</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Diagram of Hmga2 allelic series: expression constructs containing the entire Hmga2 cDNA (“wt”); the cDNA with all seven <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> sites in the 3′ UTR mutated (“m7”); the cDNA with the start codon mutated (“ATG wt”); and the cDNA with both the start codon and <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> sites mutated (“ATG m7”). <bold>b</bold>, Hmga2 wt and m7 induce Hmga2 expression in non-metastatic lung cancer cells (368T1) and restores expression cells in metastatic lung cancer cells (482N1) depleted for endogenous Hmga2 (shHmga2). Two distinct HMGA2 antibodies are used: one recognizes the N-terminus of HMGA2 (HMGA2-CST) and the other recognizes the central AT-hook region of HMGA2 (HMGA2-Narita). <bold>c</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> RNA is comparably expressed by the wt, m7, ATG wt, and ATG m7 in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> expression is normalized to <italic toggle="yes">Gapdh</italic>. 368T1 values are normalized to empty and 482N1 values are normalized to shluc empty. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− standard deviation (s.d.) with propagated error. <bold>d</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt promote substantial anchorage-independent growth in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− s.d. <bold>e</bold>, Representative images of soft agar colonies. Magnification is 10X. ***: p&lt;0.0005; **: p&lt;0.005; *: p&lt;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emss-55279-f0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity enhances lung cancer progression <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p><bold>a</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt restore lung tumour growth in response to endogenous <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> knockdown. B6129SF1/Tac males were intravenously injected with 482N1 cells expressing either a control shRNA and empty vector (shluc empty) or shHmga2 with the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series. Three weeks afterwards, animals were scanned by micro-CT and representative transverse images are shown. The heart is demarcated (labelled ‘H’) and white arrows identify lung tumours. <bold>b</bold>, Representative histological images of lungs transplanted with 482N1 cells from the series described in a. Magnification is 1X. <bold>c</bold>, Lung surface tumour counts were taken from animals transplanted with 482N1 cells from the series described in a (n=3 animals per group). Values are technical triplicates represent mean +/− s.e.m. <bold>d</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt substantially reduce survival of animals transplanted with 482N1 cells expressing the shRNA targeting <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic>. Animals were intravenously transplanted with cells as in a. Animals were subsequently aged for survival and a Kaplan-Meier analysis was performed (n=9 animals per group). Median survival was 34 days for shluc empty/shHmga2 wt transplants; 37 days for shHmga2 ATG wt transplants; 43 days for shHmga2 m7 transplants; and 50 days for shHmga2 empty/ATG m7 transplants. Statistical significance was assessed by log-rank tests compared to shHmga2 empty. ****: p&lt;0.00005; ***: p&lt;0.0005; **: p&lt;0.005; *: p&lt;0.05; n.s.: not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emss-55279-f0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> ceRNA activity enhances TGF-β signalling through over-expression of Tgfbr3</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt substantially induce both Tgfbr3 protein expression and phosphorylation of Smad2 (pSmad2) in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. <bold>b</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt significantly promote expression of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> mRNA in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> expression is normalized to <italic toggle="yes">Gapdh</italic>. 368T1 values are normalized to empty and 482N1 values are normalized to shluc empty. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− s.d. with propagated error. <bold>c</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt specifically induce expression of a luciferase <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> 3′ UTR reporter in a <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> site-dependent manner in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. Cells were transfected with <italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> constructs of the control siCXCR4 multimer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> and either the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> wild type or <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> mutant 3′ UTR reporter. Values are normalized to co-transfected pGL3 plasmid. 368T1 values are normalized to empty and 482N1 values are normalized to shluc empty. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− s.d. with propagated error. <bold>d</bold>, Hmga2 wt and ATG wt displace <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> from Argonaute-2 (Ago2) based RNA-induced silencing complexes. Lysates from 368T1 and 482N1 cells of the <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> allelic series underwent either control immunoprecipitation (IgG) or immunoprecipitation for Ago2. RNA was purified and qRT-PCR was performed for <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> on both the immunoprecipitated and input RNAs. Values are depicted as the percentage of input RNA, are technical triplicates, have been performed independently twice, and represent mean +/− s.d. <bold>e</bold>, multiple shRNAs elicit substantial knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> mRNA in both 368T1 and 482N1 cells. 482N1 cells were infected with control shRNA (shluc) or a set of shRNAs targeting <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> (shTgfbr3.1-3.5), while 368T1 wt and ATG wt cells were infected with shluc or shTgfbr3.1, 3.2, 3.4, and 3.5. RNA was purified and qRT-PCR was performed. <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> expression is normalized to <italic toggle="yes">Gapdh</italic> and 368T1 wt and ATG wt and 482N1 values are normalized to shluc. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− s.d. with propagated error. <bold>f</bold>, multiple shRNAs induce knockdown of Tgbr3 and suppress TGF-β pathway activity in 368T1 and 482N1 cells. Cells were infected with shRNAs as in e and Western analysis was performed for Tgfbr3, pSmad2 and total Smad2 (Smad2). <bold>g</bold>, Tgfbr3 depletion reduces anchorage-independent growth of 368T1 wt and ATG wt and 482N1 cells. Cells were infected with the listed shRNAs and plated for anchorage-independent growth and colonies were counted as above. Values are technical triplicates, have been performed independently three times, and represent mean +/− s.d. ***: p&lt;0.0005; **: p&lt;0.005; *: p&lt;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emss-55279-f0003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> are reciprocally and co-ordinately upregulated in NSCLC patients</title><p><bold>a</bold>, The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) NSCLC gene expression data set was sorted on <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> expression. The top and bottom quartiles (HMGA2 low and high, respectively) were selected (45 patients per group) and <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> expression was compared by box and whisker plot. <bold>b</bold>, The TCGA data set was sorted into top and bottom quartiles of <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> expression as in a, and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> expression was compared by box and whisker plot. <bold>c</bold>, The TCGA data set was sorted into top and bottom quartiles of <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> expression (TGFBR3 low and high, respectively) as in a, and <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> expression was compared by box and whisker plot. <bold>d</bold>, The TCGA data set was sorted into top and bottom quartiles of <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR3</italic> expression as in c, and <italic toggle="yes">HMGA2</italic> expression was compared by box and whisker plot. In all box and whisker plots, values are presented on a log<sub>2</sub> scale. Significance was assessed by the Mann-Whitney test with a Bonferroni correction for multiple hypothesis testing. <bold>***</bold>: p&lt;0.0005. <bold>e,</bold> Model for <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> acting as a competing endogenous RNA for <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic>. In nonmetastatic NSCLC, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> expression is low, leading to suppressed <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> expression by <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic>. In metastatic NSCLC, <italic toggle="yes">Hmga2</italic> expression is elevated, titrating away <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> from <italic toggle="yes">Tgfbr3</italic> and allowing for its over-expression. This titration occurs without changes in <italic toggle="yes">let-7</italic> expression, reflecting competition for microRNA occupancy by target transcripts.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emss-55279-f0004.jpg"/></fig></floats-group></article>