
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Cell</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Cell</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101130617</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer cell</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1535-6108</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-3686</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3973134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3973134.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3973134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3973134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS407702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23079660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2012.09.003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS407702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA407702</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Coordinated Silencing of Myc-Mediated miR-29 by HDAC3 and EZH2 As a Therapeutic Target of Histone Modification in Aggressive B-Cell Lymphomas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaohong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiskus</surname><given-names initials="W">Warren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lwin</surname><given-names initials="T">Tint</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names initials="R">Rekha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yizhuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names initials="JC">John C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names initials="VE">Victor E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen-Kiang</surname><given-names initials="S">Selina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscinski</surname><given-names initials="LC">Lynn C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names initials="E">Edward</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names initials="WS">William S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names initials="KL">Kenneth L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotomayor</surname><given-names initials="E">Eduardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names initials="K">Kapil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Departments of Malignant Hematology and Experimental Therapeutics, H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute, Tampa, Florida 33613</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Immunology and Malignant Hematology, Tianjin Cancer Hospital, Tianjin, China</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Experimental Therapeutics, University of Kansas Cancer Center, Kansas City, Kansas 66160</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA 02115</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Pathology, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE 68198</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Chemical Biology Laboratory, Center for Cancer Research, National Cancer Institute, Frederick, MD 21702</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Pathology, Weill-Cornell Medical College, New York, NY 10065</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Jianguo Tao, MD, PhD, Department of Pathology and Experimental Therapeutics Program, Moffitt Cancer Center, 12902 Magnolia Dr, Tampa, FL 33613, USA. Phone: 813-979-3885; <email>Jianguo.Tao@moffitt.org</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">235865</issue-id><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>24</day><month>03</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-05 22:06:41.443"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-407702.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" vol="41" page="1198" journal-id="Cancer Cell" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="37311416"><article-title>Retraction Notice to: Coordinated Silencing of MYC-Mediated miR-29 by HDAC3 and EZH2 as a Therapeutic Target of Histone Modification in Aggressive B-Cell Lymphomas.</article-title><volume>41</volume><issue>6</issue><date><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><source>Cancer Cell</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37311416</pub-id></related-article><abstract><title>SUMMARY</title><p id="P1">We investigated the transcriptional and epigenetic repression of miR-29 by <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HDAC3</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic> in mantle cell lymphoma and other <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic>-associated lymphomas. We demonstrate that miR-29 is repressed by <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> through a co-repressor complex with <italic toggle="yes">HDAC3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> contributes to EZH2 upregulation via repression of the <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic> targeting miR-26a, and <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic> induces <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> via inhibition of the <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> targeting miR-494 to create positive feedback. Combined inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">HDAC3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic> cooperatively disrupted the <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">miR-29</italic> axis, resulting in restoration of miR-29 expression, down-regulation of miR-29 targeted genes, and lymphoma growth suppression <italic toggle="yes">in vitro and in vivo</italic>. These findings define a <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic>-mediated miRNA repression mechanism, shed light on <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> lymphomagenesis mechanisms and reveals promising therapeutic targets for aggressive B-cell malignancies.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P2">c-Myc (hereafter Myc) is a transcription factor that promotes oncogenesis by activating and repressing its target genes that control cell growth and proliferation (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Nilsson and Cleveland,2003</xref>). Myc is deregulated in a large proportion of aggressive B-cell lymphomas. Although Myc has been described as a defining feature and the driving oncogene for Burkitt lymphoma, the significance of Myc has also been recognized in other non-Hodgkin lymphomas (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Dave et al.,2006</xref>). Myc, which has been detected in 9-14% of diffuse large B-cell lymphomas, is associated with an adverse prognosis as a result of chemoresistance and with shortened survival. In mantle cell lymphoma (MCL), increased expression of Myc has been found to be associated with poor prognosis and MCL aggressiveness (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Hartmann et al.,2008</xref>). Myc overexpression has been implicated in high-grade large cell transformation in follicular and marginal zone cell lymphomas (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Slack and Gascoyne,2011</xref>), supporting the features of Myc in sustaining aggressive transformation of lymphomas. Despite current modes of intensive chemotherapy and radiation, survival in patients with high Myc activity is dismal. It is still unclear what direct Myc-induced transcriptional changes promote cell transformation, and the therapeutics against Myc has remained elusive.</p><p id="P3">Aberrant micro RNA (miRNA) expression and miRNA oncogenic and tumor suppressive functions have been extensively investigated in many tumors, including lymphomas (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Fabbri and Croce,2011</xref>). However, the molecular basis for miRNA dysregulation remains uncharacterized and emerging (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2010</xref>). Our work and others have indicated that the <italic toggle="yes">miR-29</italic> family might function as a tumor suppressor (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Fabbri et al.,2007</xref>; <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al.,2010</xref>). Expression of these miRNAs inhibits cell proliferation, promotes apoptosis of cancer cells, and suppresses tumorigenicity by targeting multiple oncogenes. Loss or downregulation of these miRNAs has been reported in a variety of hematopoietic and solid tumors and has been shown to be associated with high-risk chronic lymphocytic leukemia, lung cancer, invasive breast cancer, and cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Fabbri and Croce,2011</xref>). These observations are consistent with our recent study demonstrating that miR-29 is downregulated in aggressive MCL (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al.,2010</xref>).</p><p id="P4">Myc has been recently implicated in controlling the expression of a host of miRNAs (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al.,2008</xref>). The predominant consequence of activation of Myc is widespread repression of miRNA expression. Although the mechanisms by which Myc activates transcription have been extensively studied, less is known about how Myc represses transcription of target genes as well as miRNAs. It was reported that Myc repressed target genes <italic toggle="yes">Id2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Gadd153</italic> by recruitment of histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3; <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Kurland and Tansey,2008</xref>). More recently, our study demonstrated that Myc acts as a repressor of miRNA-15a/16 by recruiting HDAC3 (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al.,2012</xref>). These findings suggest that histone deacetylation may be involved in Myc-mediated transcriptional repression. Further evidence has shown that histone H3 lysine 27 trimethylation, which is mediated by enhancer of zeste homolog 2 (EZH2) at the promoter of the gene, leads to silencing of gene expression (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al.,2005</xref>). The polycomb-repressive complex 2 (PRC2) contains three core proteins (EZH2, SUZ12, and EED), and PRC2 is a transcriptional repressor that has a crucial function in maintaining the delicate homeostatic balance between gene expression and repression, the disruption of which may lead to oncogenesis (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Sparmann and van Lohuizen,2006</xref>). The roles of HDAC and PRC2 in miRNA regulation and dysregulation are largely unknown and have been so far poorly defined.</p><p id="P5">In this study, we explored the role of Myc, HDAC, and EZH2 in miR-29 repression and the contribution of miR-29 to cell survival and growth in Myc-associated lymphomas. We examined the regulation and functional roles of miRNAs, histone modifications and their interplay in Myc, EZH2 overexpression and tumorigenic potential of lymphoma cells. Furthermore, we tested molecular targeting strategies to restore miR-29 expression and examined whether combined inhibitors of HDAC and EZH2 cooperatively increase miR-29 expression and inhibit lymphoma growth and shorten <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> lymphoma survival.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="S3"><title>Myc Is Overexpressed in Aggressive MCL and Is Inversely Correlated with Expression of miR-29</title><p id="P6">We examined Myc and miR-29 expression and their correlation using purified lymphoma cells from MCL patients and normal donors. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>, compared with normal CD19<sup>+</sup> peripheral blood lymphocytes, miR-29a-c was significantly downregulated and Myc was significantly over-expressed in MCL samples. Furthermore, MCLs with higher Myc expression have significantly lower miR-29 expression. We used the P493-6 human B-cell line as a model to examine the role of Myc in miR-29 expression. P493-6 cells bear a tetracycline-repressible Myc construct, such that tetracycline withdrawal results in rapid induction of Myc followed by cell proliferation. We compared expression levels of Myc and miR-29 in tetracycline-treated (Mycoff) and untreated (Myc-on) cells and observed an inverse correlation between miR-29 and Myc expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B-D</xref>). Expression of primary miR-29 (pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c) and mature miR-29 was measured by quantitative reverse-transcribed polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) in P493-6 cells with and without Myc expression. We found both primary miR-29 and mature miR-29 to be remarkably lower in Myc-on B cells than in Myc-off cells. Whereas Myc repression after tetracycline treatment significantly upregulated, miR29a-c. In addition, MCL patient samples showed strong positive correlations between primary miRNAs of miR-29 and mature miR-29 expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1A-C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Myc, HDAC3, and PRC2 Are Tethered to the miR-29 Promoter Regions as a Co-repressor Complex to Downregulate miR-29 Expression Through Histone Deacetylation and Trimethylation</title><p id="P7">We next investigated the epigenetic regulation of Myc-induced miR-29 repression through histone acetylation and methylation. We first examined the effects of chromatin-modifying drugs on miR-29 expression in MCL and other Myc-expressing B-cell lymphomas. Using qRT-PCR, we evaluated the effects of a pan-HDAC inhibitor (vorinostat) on both pri- and mature miR-29 expression in MCL (Jeko-1) and Burkitt lymphoma cells (Ramos). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> shows that vorinostat caused a dose-dependent increase in miR-29a-c expression. miR-29 induction was also observed with another HDAC inhibitor, trichostatin A (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2A</xref>), suggesting an HDAC role in miR-29 gene expression and supporting that the miR-29 family members are subject to epigenetic control in lymphoma cells. We next studied the role of PRC2 in the downregulation of miR-29 since PRC2 has been shown to be recruited to gene promoters to induce histone trimethylation and gene repression. We evaluated the effects of the PRC2 inhibitor 3-deazaneplanocin A (DZNep) on miR-29 expression. Based on our previous study of using DZNep for leukemia cells(<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Fiskus et al.,2009</xref>), we chose the DZNep dosage range and revealed that DZNep resultes in a dose-dependent decrease in the protein expression of EZH2 and SUZ12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2B</xref>) and caused a dose-dependent increase in pri-miR-29a/b1, pri-miR-29b2/c, and mature miR-29 expression in these lymphoma cell lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2C</xref>). Overall, the above observations implied that both HDAC and PRC2 are involved in miR-29 expression.</p><p id="P8">We explored whether Myc, HDAC3, and/or EZH2 act together to be involved in miR-29 expression in Myc-expressing lymphoma cells. The role of Myc and HDAC3 in the transcriptional regulation of miR-29 gene expression was first examined by depleting the expression of Myc and HDAC3, respectively, with siRNA. Pri- and mature miR-29 expression levels were analyzed after Myc or HDAC3 was knocked down. In agreement with our earlier results with vorinostat, knockdown of HDAC3 significantly enhanced both pri- and mature miR-29 gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Moreover, knockdown of Myc also markedly increased miR-29 gene expression and decreased EZH2 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). When we assessed the role of PRC2 in Myc-mediated miR-29 repression, we found that depletion of EZH2 and/or SUZ12 using siRNAs also significantly increased miR-29 gene expression and decreased Myc expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>), further supporting the role of EZH2/PRC2 in miR-29 expression.</p><p id="P9">Next, we examined the miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c gene promoter regions for transcription factor binding sites and identified three highly conserved Myc binding sites (S1, S2, and S3) in a region ~5 kb upstream and in the first intron of both human miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). We investigated whether HDAC3 and EZH2/PRC2 could be recruited to the miR-29 promoters by Myc and whether HDAC3 and EZH2 mediated Myc-induced miR-29 repression using chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays. We used primers located within the miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c proximal promoter regions of Myc binding sites and revealed that antibodies against both Myc and HDAC3 efficiently immunoprecipitated the miR-29 promoter regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A-B</xref>). In addition, we found that site S3 of miR-29a/b1 and sites S2 and S3 of miR-29b2/c carry binding sites for both Myc and HDAC3, indicating that both Myc and HDAC3 can bind to the miR-29 promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3A</xref>). These bindings are specific and Myc dependent since no signal was detected at the miR-29 distal promoter (site S4) and no HDAC3 binding was detected when Myc was not bound at miR-29 promoters. These findings implicate the role of Myc in recruiting HDAC3 and suggest that HDAC3-mediated histone deacetylation might contribute to Myc-induced miR-29 gene repression. To confirm the requirement of Myc for HDAC3 binding, P493-6 cells were used to manipulate Myc expression levels. ChIP assays revealed HDAC3 binding in Myc-on and lack of binding in Myc-off P493-6 cells, supporting the recruitment role of Myc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). We further assessed the role of EZH2 in Myc-mediated miR-29 repression and investigated whether similar regulation patterns occur through recruitment of EZH2 and SUZ12 on miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c promoters. ChIP assay with anti-EZH2 and anti-SUZ12 antibody showed that both EZH2 and SUZ12 directly bound to the miR-29 promoters in Myc-on but not in Myc-off P493-6 lymphocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>) and was further validated in Burkitt and MCL cell lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3B</xref>). The loss of binding of these co-repressors detected by ChIP is not due to loss of the proteins from the cell but most likely due to absence of Myc since 24-hour tet treatment resulted in loss of Myc but no change in EZH2, SUZ12 or HDAC3 expression in P493 cells (insert of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Of note, the EZH2 and SUZ12 binding sites correspond to the Myc and HDAC3 binding sites, supporting the role of Myc in EZH2 and SUZ12 recruitment and the role of PRC2 in silencing miR-29 expression. The variation of degree and site of Myc binding on miR-29a/b1 (S3 only) and miR-29b2/c promoters (S2 and S3) likely contributes to different sensitivity of miR-29a/b1 and miR-b2/c to the treatment of HDAC and EZH2 inhibitors. Furthermore, inhibition of PRC2 with DZNep degraded EZH2 and SUZ12 and decreased EZH2 and SUZ12 binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). We next performed CHIP assay to validate the Myc, EZH2 and HDAC3 binding to miR-29 promoters in primary lymphoma samples. Four high Myc samples of two blastic MCLs, one Burkitt and one Burkitt-like (double-hit) lymphoma, and two low Myc indolent MCLs were chosen from our clinical samples and were used in this experiment. Myc expression levels in these samples were confirmed by FISH and immunohistochemical stains (not shown). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref> reveals consistent enrichment of Myc and to a lesser extent HDAC3 and EZH2 in miR-29 promoter regions in Myc-associated lymphomas and supports that these interactions are operative in primary lymphoma cells. Taken together, these results confirm that Myc is required and a significant mediator of EZH2-mediated miR-29 repression, suggesting that HDAC3 and EZH2 have coordinated effects on miRNAs such as miR-29 expression in Myc-associated lymphomas.</p><p id="P10">To test whether Myc binding is functional, we generated luciferase reporter constructs carrying the two alternative promoters of miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c at site S3 for miR29a/b1 and sites S2 and S3 for miR29b2/c and their mutated types (M2, M3). The mutants were constructed to harbor mutations in the Myc binding site (E-box). Both wild-type and mutant plasmids (E-boxes mutants) were then transfected into P493-6 and 293T cells, and luciferase activity was measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3C</xref>). We found luciferase activities of wild-type miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c promoters to be significantly repressed by Myc overexpression. Furthermore, knockdown of HDAC3 reversed Myc-mediated repression, supporting that HDAC3 is involved in Myc-driven miRNA repression. Compared with wild-type promoters, luciferase activity of mutated-type promoters was not significantly changed by Myc overexpression and HDAC3 knockdown. Similarly, knockdown of EZH2 reversed Myc-mediated repression in wild-type but not in mutant miR-29 promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>). Myc-mediated repression was not observed in M3 of the miR-29a/b1 promoter and M2 of the miR-29b2/c promoter. This is likely attributed to the dominant function of Myc binding in site S3 of miR-29a/b1 and site S2 of miR-29b2/c promoters. These results are in line with those of ChIP experiments showing strongest binding of Myc in S3 of miR-29a/b1 and in S2 of miR-b2/c promoters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Overall, these data show that both miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c loci contain Myc-binding regions that are under negative control by HDAC3 and EZH2 and that histone hypoacetylation and trimethylation contribute to Myc-induced miR-29 repression.</p><p id="P11">We further performed ChIP analysis to probe acetylated histone 4 (Ac-H4), trimethylated histone 3 (Me3-H3K27), and RNA polymerase II binding to miR-29 promoters. We first revealed that histone hypoacetylation and trimethylation are dependent on the presence of Myc since enrichment of Ac-H4 was significantly increased and Me3-H3K27 is significantly decreased in Myc-off P493-6 cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3D</xref>). This study also revealed that accumulation of RNA polymerase II, a hallmark of active transcription, is tightly controlled by Myc. In agreement with the epigenetic silencing effect of HDAC3 and EZH2, HDAC3 knockdown and EZH2 inhibition, respectively, increased Ac-H4 and decreased Me3-H3K27 at the miR-29 promoters (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3E-F</xref>). Of note, increased recruitment of RNA polymerase II was also observed. These results support the finding that depletion of Myc leads to reduced recruitment of HDAC3 and EZH2 and results in increased histone acetylation, decreased H3K27 trimethylation, and RNA polymerase II recruitment.</p><p id="P12">We further investigated whether PRC2 and HDAC3 form a co-repressor complex with Myc to repress miR-29 expression using co-immunoprecipitation assays. First, 293T cells were cotransfected with vectors expressing FLAG-tagged full-length specific HDAC3 and/or with full-length Myc. When Myc and HDAC3 were co-transfected in 293T cells, the existence of Myc, HDAC3, and SUZ12 but not EZH2 was detected in the immunoprecipitates obtained with an antibody against HDAC3 and the existence of Myc and HDAC3, but not SUZ12 and EZH2, was detected in immunoprecipitates obtained with an antibody against Myc. These results indicate that Myc co-immunoprecipitated with HDAC3 and that HDAC3 co-immunoprecipitated with Myc as well as SUZ12. Next, we asked whether endogenous Myc-HDAC3-PRC2 interaction also occurred in Myc-associated lymphoma cells. Having recently demonstrated that Myc and HDAC3 formed a co-immunoprecipitate complex to regulate the miRNA expression (Zhang et al.,2011), we further examined the interaction between HDAC3 and SUZ12 in P493-6 cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>, cell lysates immunoprecipitated with an HDAC3-specific antibody contained HDAC3 and SUZ12. The reverse endogenous co-immunoprecipitates of HDAC3 and SUZ12 with SUZ12 antibody was also demonstrated in Jeko-1 and P493-6 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B-C</xref>). Third, we further explored how Myc interacted with SUZ12 and EZH2 by using Myc-on and Myc-off P493-6 cells. In Myc-on P493-6 cells, strong HDAC3, weak SUZ12, and no EZH2 were coimmunoprecipitated with Myc antibody; strong SUZ12, moderate EZH2, and Myc were coimmunoprecipitated with HDAC3 antibody; strong EZH2, moderate HDAC3, and weak Myc were co-immunoprecipitated with SUZ12 antibody; and strong SUZ12, weak HDAC3, and no Myc were co-immunoprecipitated with EZH2 antibody. In contrast, in Myc-off P493-6 cells, there was no endogenous co-immunoprecipitation of HDAC3 and SUZ12 with Myc detected and relatively low levels of interaction of HDAC3 with SUZ12 and EZH2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Overall, these results suggest that SUZ12 and EZH2 interact with HDAC3 and Myc to form a multi-molecular complex. These components interact in a linear fashion, and HDAC3 bridges the interaction between Myc and SUZ12/EZH2. To prove this, we depleted HDAC3 and tested whether this would disrupt interaction between Myc and SUZ12/EZH2 in P493-6 cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>, SUZ12 was not detected in Myc-immunoprecipitate and Myc was not detected in SUZ12 immunoprecipitate, corroborating that HDAC3 bridges the interaction between Myc and SUZ12/EZH2. These data, in conjunction with results from luciferase reporter assay, support the cooperative function of HDAC3 and EZH2 as a co-repressor complex in repressing miR-29 expression.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>miR-29 Is Required for Myc-Mediated Oncogenic Activity by Targeting IGF-1R and CDK6 Pathways in MCL and Other Myc-Expressing B-cell Lymphomas</title><p id="P13">We investigated whether downregulation of miR-29 is necessary for cellular transformation induced by oncogenic Myc overexpression. In addition to CDK6, our bioinformatic analysis also revealed IGF-1R as a potential target of miR-29. Increased expression of miR-29 significantly downregulated IGR-1R (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4A</xref>). The relative luciferase activity of the wild-type construct of IGF-1R 3'-UTR was reduced by overexpression of miR-29c and was increased when miR-29c was knocked down, whereas such effects of miR29c on luciferase activity were not observed with the mutant construct of IGF-1R 3'-UTR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). These findings support a direct and specific interaction of miR29 on IGF-1R 3'-UTR. To confirm the relevance of the expression of IGF-1R and the relationship between miR-29 and IGF-1R, the expression of miR-29 and IGF-1R expression were assessed in a set of primary MCL tissues and normal B-lymphocytes. An inverse correlation of miR-29 and IGF-1R protein expression was observed in all MCL samples by using Pearson coefficient, and correlation coefficients were calculated identifying IGF-1R as a miR-29 target in addition to the previously demonstrated CDK6 in MCL (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4B-C</xref>).</p><p id="P14">Given the oncogenic feature of Myc and regulatory role of Myc in miR-29 expression, we postulated that Myc-mediated miR-29 repression and subsequent miR-29 target changes contribute to Myc-driven lymphoma cell growth and proliferation. We, therefore, tested whether Myc upregulates miR-29 targets (CDK6 and IGF-1R expression) in Myc-on and Myc-off P493-6 cells. With Myc turn-on, protein levels of CDK6 and IGF-1R were significantly increased, whereas they were significantly downregulated with Myc turn-off (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). In contrast, mRNA levels of CDK6 and IGF-1R were not significantly influenced by Myc (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4D</xref>). These data suggest a post-transcriptional mechanism of CDK6 and IGF-1R expression and are in line with Myc-driven miR-29-mediated regulation of CDK6 and IGF-1R expression. Of note, when Myc is turned off (Myc-off cells), IGF-1R declines at a faster rate than CDK6. This may be related to differences in the mRNA and/or protein half-life of these two proteins. We further assessed whether miR-29 mediated Myc-driven CDK6 and IGF-1R induction and cell growth in Myc-expressing lymphoma cells. In P493-6 cells, the ectopic forced expression of miR-29 abolished Myc-induced CDK6 and IGF-1R expression, and miR-29 knockdown blocked Myc-off-mediated CDK6 and IGF-1R repression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4A</xref>). Furthermore, knockdown of CDK6 and IGF-1R induced significant inhibition of cell growth and colony formation, and the combined inhibition of CDK6 and IGF-1R resulted in a more marked inhibition of cell growth and colony formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4E</xref>). Accordingly, miR-29 overexpression as well as Myc knockdown significantly abrogated lymphoma colony formation capacity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5F</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4F-G</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Myc-miR-26a-EZH2-miR-494 Positive Feedback Loop Sustains Myc Activity and miR-29 Repression in MCL and Other Aggressive B-cell Lymphomas</title><p id="P15">Accumulating evidence has indicated Myc-dependent regulation of EZH2, with further evidence revealing the ability of EZH2 to induce Myc expression (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Sander et al.,2008</xref>; <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al.,2011</xref>). We speculated that a feedback loop existed between Myc and EZH2, thereby maintaining Myc overexpression and miR-29 repression in Myc-associated lymphomas. We thus explored the interaction between Myc and EZH2 and examined the role of this circuitry in sustaining miR-29 repression. First, we tested whether Myc stimulates EZH2 expression by repression of its negative regulator miRNAs. Since EZH2 was identified by TargetScan as a potential miR-26a target and was recently experimentally validated (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Sander et al.,2008</xref>), we examined the effects of miR-26a on EZH2 expression. Overexpression of miR-26a reduced EZH2 and Myc protein abundance in Jeko-1 and Mino cells, and ectopic expression of miR-26a inhibited EZH2 3’-UTR luciferase reporter activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>), confirming that miR-26a regulates EZH2. Given that miR-26a is a reported Myc-regulated miRNA, we next used the P493-6 cells to confirm and explore the mechanism by which Myc induces EZH2 expression. Expression of miR-26a in Myc-on P493-6 cells was significantly lower than that shown in Myc-off cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Furthermore, the effects of Myc on EZH2 expression were examined, revealing that mRNA levels of EZH2 and SUZ12 were not changed, whereas protein levels were significantly increased in Myc-on cells and decreased in Myc-off cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S5A</xref>). This result implies that Myc regulated EZH2 via post-transcriptional regulation. Moreover, ectopic expression of miR-26a blocked Myc-induced EZH2 expression in Myc-on P493-6 cells. To substantiate that miR-26a expression is responsible for Myc-induced EZH2 change, we inhibited miR-26a by using Anti-miR-26a and revealed increased EZH2 expression in Myc-off P493-6 cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>), further supporting the role of miR-26a in Myc-regulated EZH2 expression. We next tested whether EZH2 stimulates Myc expression. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6D</xref> shows that inhibition of EZH2 by using DZNep and shRNA against EZH2 significantly decreased Myc expression, substantiating the regulatory role of EZH2 in Myc expression and implying a positive feedback loop of Myc and EZH2. We reasoned that EZH2 induces Myc expression through repression of Myc-repressing miRNAs. Thus, we next explored the EZH2-regulated miRNAs by examining the effects of EZH2 inhibition on the expression of miRNAs. miRNA microarray was performed and the expression profile from Jeko-1 cells after 72-hour DZNep (2 μM) treatment was determined (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5B</xref>). We identified a set of miRNAs that were upregulated by DZNep, downregulated by PRC2, and are predicted to target Myc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E-F</xref>). To further test whether these miRNAs target the Myc 3′-UTR directly, we cloned the full length of <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> 3′-UTR and constructed a luciferase reporter plasmid (p-miR-MYC-3’-UTR-WT). The plasmid was co-transfected into 293T cells, with each of the above-identified pre-miRNAs and luciferase activity measured. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5C</xref> shows that the luciferase activity of wild-type Myc reporter were reduced by overexpression of miR-135, miR-200, and miR-374, as well as most noticeably decreased by miR-494 overexpression. With TargetScan predicting that Myc 3’-UTR contains two miR-494-binding sites, we subsequently mutated the miR-494 binding sites in Myc-3′-UTR to test whether miR-494 specifically targets Myc 3’-UTR. As revealed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6F</xref>, the mutation abolished the suppressive effect of miR-494 on the luciferase reporter activity. These results demonstrated that the miR-494 specifically and directly targeted the Myc gene. To determine whether miR-494 is required and a significant mediator for EZH2-mediated Myc induction, we performed qRT-PCR and validated that miR-494 was upregulated by EZH2 inhibition through DZNep treatment and shEZH2 or siEZH2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5D-E</xref>). To further confirm that miR-494 is directly regulated by EZH2, Chip assay was performed and showed the direct EZH2 binding to miR-494 promoter regions. Furthermore, this binding is inhibited by the depletion of EZH2 through DZNep treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig S5F</xref>). We next showed that overexpression of miR-494 downregulated Myc protein level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6G</xref>). Accordingly, downregulation of EZH2 was also observed, supporting the presence of a Myc-miR-26a-EZH2-miR-494 feed-forward circuit sustaining Myc activity and miR-29 repression.</p><p id="P16">To address whether the above observations in MCL and Ramos cell lines are relevant to other aggressive cell lines and primary lymphoma cells, we examined the relationship between Myc, EZH2, and miR-26a as well as miR-29 expression levels in Myc-expressing lymphoma cell lines and primary Myc-expressing lymphomas. The cell lines included two transformed large B-lymphoma cell lines (SUDHL4, SUDHL10); the EBV-associated lymphoma line SKW6.4; aggressive MCL lines Jeko-1, Mino-1, HBL-2, NCEB-1, Rec-1 and Z138c; and Burkitt lymphoma cell lines Raji and Ramos. The primary lymphomas included Burkitt lymphomas, high-grade transformed diffuse large cell lymphomas, and MCLs. For comparison, we also included normal control B lymphocytes as control, with Myc-on and Myc-off P493-6 cells as positive and negative cell lines. In line with our hypothesis, low expression levels of miR-29 family and miR-26a were correlated with high expression of Myc and EZH2 and correlation coefficients were calculated in these cell lines and primary samples by using Pearson coefficient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A-D</xref>). When compared with normal control B-lymphocytes, Myc expression was positively correlated with EZH2 expression in these primary samples. Collectively, these observations provide EZH2 and HDAC3 as potential therapeutic targets for aggressive B-cell lymphomas.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Combined Inhibitors of HDAC and EZH2 Cooperatively De-repressed miR-29 and Suppressed Tumor Growth <italic toggle="yes">in vitro and in vivo</italic> in MCL and Other Aggressive B-Cell Lymphomas</title><p id="P17">In light of the importance of low or absent expression of miR-29 in MCL aggressive progression and the ability of miR-29 expression to inhibit tumor cell growth, reactivation of miR-29 represents a promising therapeutic approach for this tumor type. Given that HDAC3 and EZH2 converged at miR-29 promoters to repress miR-29 expression and suppression of CDK6 and IGF-1R pathways by miR-29, we next tested whether inhibition of HDAC and EZH2 cooperatively restored miR-29 expression and subsequently inhibited CDK6 and IGF-1R to block the clonenogenic growth in soft agar and lymphoma growth in vivo. We also asked whether combined inhibitors of HDAC and PRC2 are more effective in induction of miR-29 expression, suppression of CDK6 and IGF-1R, and tumorigenicity in vivo. Compared with each agent alone, co-treatment with vorinostat and DZNep induced significantly higher expression of pri-miR-29a/b1, pri-miR-29b2/c, and mature miR-29 than each agent alone in HBL2, Ramos, Mino as well as Z138c MCL cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6A-D</xref>). Both DZNep and vorinostat resulted in enhanced inhibition of colony formation with corresponding downregulation of CDK6 and IGF-1R in HBL2 and Z138c cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B-C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6B</xref>). Next, we compared the effects of DZNep and/or vorinostat on the viability of transformed and non-transformed lymphocytes by using P493-6 cells. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref> demonstrates that exposure to DZNep or vorinostat induced more loss of viability in Myc-on than in Myc-off P493-6 cells. Finally, we determined whether the combination of DZNep and vorinostat would also exert increased in vivo anti-lymphoma activity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E</xref> shows that co-treatment with DZNep and vorinostat inhibits tumor growth and significantly improves survival of NOD/SCID mice bearing lymphoma xenografts. Lymphoma size was remarkably reduced and survival of NOD/SCID mice with lymphoma due to MCL lymphoma cells was significantly higher when they were treated with DZNep plus vorinostat than when treated with vorinostat, DZNep, or vehicle alone. Furthermore, to confirm that the in vivo targets of these inhibitors were inhibited, Western blot was performed and revealed that vorinostat and/or DZNep treatment resulted in significant down-regulation of EZH2, SUZ12 and down-stream target, IGF-1R as well as Myc from harvested lymphoma tissues (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6E</xref>). In addition, to validate the direct role of co-repressors EZH2 and HDAC3 in lymphoma formation in vivo, two independent genetic approaches were used. HBL2 cells were first transfected with siRNAs or shRNAs against EZH2 or HDAC3 to deplete their expression and subsequently these cells were applied to an in vivo lymphoma formation experiment as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E</xref>. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6F-G</xref> confirmed that HDAC3 or EZH2 siRNA or shRNA knocked down EZH2 or HDAC3 respectively and significantly abolished lymphoma growth in vivo supporting the role of EZH2 and HDAC3 in lymphoma formation. To support that the tumor inhibition is due to decreased proliferation, the proliferation status of the tumor cells in shEZH2 and shHDAC3 treated HBL2 xenografts was measured by using proliferation marker genes Ki-67 and PCNA. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig S6H</xref> shows that the Ki-67 and PCNA genes were indeed significantly decreased in shEZH2 and shHDAC3 groups when compared to shCtrl group, indicating that the tumor suppression by shEZH2/HDAC3 is at least partially through proliferation inhibition.Taken together, c-Myc-mediated miR-29 repression through coordinated epigenetic silencing of HDAC3 and EZH2 is a important therapeutic target of histone modifications in aggressive B-cell lymphomas.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S8"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p id="P18">This study was undertaken to investigate 1) the potential interplay between Myc and histone modifiers HDAC3 and EZH2 and their role in miR-29 gene repression, 2) the role of the miR-29 family and their downstream targets in Myc-driven oncogenesis, 3) the underlying mechanism of persistent Myc activation in these aggressive lymphomas through a Myc-miRNA-EZH2 positive feedback loop, and 4) whether HDAC3 and EZH2 cooperatively regulate miR-29 expression and accordingly whether inhibitors of HDAC and EZH2 restore expression of miR-29 in Myc-transformed B lymphoma cells to significantly inhibit tumorigenesis ex vivo and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Our findings indicate that miR-29 repression is a result of Myc/HDAC3 and EZH2 interaction and contributes to aggressive clinical outcome of Myc-associated lymphomas. Results of this study led to the identification of a model for interplay between Myc, HDAC3, PRC2, and miRNAs and their contribution to Myc-associated lymphomagenesis and HDAC3/EZH2/miR-29 as significant therapeutic targets for aggressive lymphomas. We showed that Myc, HDAC3, and PRC2 form a repressive complex tethered to miR-29 promoter elements to epigenetically repress miR-29 transcription in Myc-expressing lymphoma cells. Subsequent miR-29 downregulation resulted in induction of CDK6 and IGF-1R and mediated Myc-driven lymphomagenesis shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8G</xref>, Furthermore, we demonstrated that Myc contributed to the upregulation of EZH2 via repressing EZH2-targeting miR-26a and that EZH2 in turn induced Myc expression via Myc-targeting miR-494, thereby generating <italic toggle="yes">a positive feedback loop</italic> to ensure persistent high protein levels of Myc and EZH2 and further repression of miR-29, which could be involved in maintaining the malignant phenotype. In addition to miR-494 other miRNAs such as miR-135a, miR-186, and miR-200c are also regulated by EZH2 and in turn may cooperatively regulate Myc expression. Treatment with pan-HDAC inhibitor vorinostat, EZH2 inhibitor DZNep, and their specific siRNAs disrupt the Myc-miRNA-EZH2 regulatory circuitry, resulting in enhanced restoration of miR-29ac expression, downregulation of miR-29 target genes CDK6 and IGF-1R, and suppression of lymphoma cell growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6D-F</xref>). Moreover, several other tumor suppressor and oncogene such as TCL-1, MCL1 (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Pekarsky et al.,2006</xref>; <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Mott et al.,2007</xref>) are also regulated by miR-29 and may contribute to miR-29-medaited oncogenesis. On the other hand, a recent study implicated that miR-29 can function as an oncogene in indolent chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), suggesting that miR-29 can function as both tumor suppressor or oncogene depending on the cellular context (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Pekarsky et al.,2006</xref>).Our findings indicated miR-29 is a tumor suppressor in aggressive MCL and revealed critical mechanisms for Myc-driven miRNA suppression and rational therapeutic targets of histone modifications in aggressive B-cell malignancies. These data also indicate that c-Myc-driven miR-29 repression through recruitment of HDAC3 and/or EZH2 could be a generic mechanism for miRNA silencing in aggressive B-cell lymphomas. The c-Myc driven miRNA repression may underlie the molecular mechanism for lymphoma aggressive transformation and can be epigenetically targeted through manipulation of histone modifications.</p><p id="P19">We identified a regulatory element (site S3) located ~5 kb upstream from the miR-29a/b1 and two regulatory elements (sites S2 and S3) located ~5 kb upstream from miR-29b-c cluster. These elements contain Myc binding site(s) that also associate with the transcriptional repressor factors EZH2 and HDAC3. Co-immunoprecipitation assays revealed that Myc coimmunoprecipitates with HDAC3 and HDAC3 with EZH2, likely through SUZ12 to form a Myc-HDAC3-PRC2 complex. These findings support the notion that Myc repressed miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c through recruitment and interaction with HDAC3 and PRC2 as a co-repressor complex. Given that miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c are located in the different chromosomes, have different promoter regions and Myc-binding sites, miR-29 transcripts indeed respond differently to the presence or absence of Myc, EZH2 and HDAC3 as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Furthermore, ChIP analysis demonstrated that Myc, HDAC3, and PRC2 co-localize to the promoters of the miR-29 cluster genes and that HDAC3 and EZH2/PRC2 binding to miR-29 promoters was Myc dependent, supporting the role of Myc in the recruitment of HDAC3 and PRC2 to the miR-29 promoters. Finally, luciferase reporter assays demonstrated that miR-29 is repressed by Myc acting through HDAC3 and EZH2-mediated histone deacetylation and trimethylation. Recent work has shown that Myc is involved in miR-29 gene expression regulation and that HDAC with Myc is responsible for the silencing of miR-29b in acute myeloid leukemia cells (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al.,2010</xref>). Our current findings suggest that PRC2 is an additional factor ensuring miR-29 downregulation through working in concert with HDAC3. Thus, these findings define a key mechanism of miRNA transcriptional repression by Myc and shed light on the poorly understood mechanisms involved in miRNA suppression in B-cell lymphomas.</p><p id="P20">The Myc-miR-26a-EZH2-miR-494 positive feedback loop was observed in Myc-expressing lymphoma cell lines and primary lymphoma cells examined. We conclude that miR-26a can function as a tumor suppressor miRNA in Myc-associated lymphomas. Once Myc is activated, miR-26a is repressed; the more miR-26a is decreased, the more its target gene (such as EZH2) is activated. Inverse correlations between miR-26a, miR-29 and Myc, EZH2 expression were detected in both cell lines and primary samples supporting the presence of Myc-miRNA-EZH2 positive feedback loop. The decrease in miR-26a expression and consequent increase in EZH2 expression have been reported in a variety of aggressive tumors such as hepatocellular carcinoma, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, and Burkett lymphoma (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Sander et al.,2008</xref>). The frequent EZH2 overexpression found in human cancers is associated with more aggressive cancer phenotypes with poor prognosis (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">So et al.,2011</xref>). This was further supported by findings in a larger cohort of hepatocellular carcinoma patients, where low miR-26a expression was associated with shorter overall survival (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Kota et al.,2009</xref>). In addition, EZH2 was detected in the neoplastic large cells in intermediate- and high-grade B-cell lymphomas, and its expression was correlated with clinical grade and the presence of Ki-67 expression (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">van Kemenade et al.,2001</xref>). In MCL, EZH2 is upregulated in proliferating MCL cells, with expression levels of Myc and EZH2 being the strongest prognostic factors independent of tumor proliferation and clinical factors of MCL (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Visser et al.,2001</xref>). These reports concur with our previous and current findings that miR-29 expression is reversely correlated, controlled with Myc and EZH2, and associated with MCL aggressive progression (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al.,2010</xref>). Our significant finding of the Myc-EZH2-miR-29 axis provides insight into how EZH2 is activated and contributes to tumor aggressive transformation, thus revealing mechanistic links between EZH2 and its upstream and downstream signaling in Myc-associated lymphomas.</p><p id="P21">The results on EZH2 regulation of Myc are in agreement with previous studies showing that EZH2 induced Myc expression and provide insight into the mechanisms of Myc activation and EZH2-driven cell proliferation. Recent studies have revealed recurrent somatic mutations of <italic toggle="yes">EZH2</italic> in lymphomas and the inactivating somatic mutations of the H3K27 demethylase, <italic toggle="yes">UTX</italic>, in multiple cancers (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">van Haaften et al.,2009</xref>). These findings suggest that deregulation of H3K27 methylation may also contribute to constitutive Myc activation in these lymphomas and EZH2 trimethylase as an ideal therapeutic target for lymphoma therapy. Here, we reveal that dynamic forces act through a feedback circuit to modulate oncogenic expression of proteins, Myc and EZH2, at the post-transcriptional level via miRNAs. This reverberating relationship ensures the signal transduction of the upstream triggering events, leading to the sustained induction of Myc and EZH2 as well as the suppression of the downstream miR-29 family. Given the role of EZH2 in Myc activation and miR-29 repression, inhibition of EZH2 will target both upstream (Myc) and downstream (miR-29, CDK6, IGF-1R) signaling event of aggressive lymphomas.</p><p id="P22">The transcriptional and posttranscriptional repression of miRNAs through Myc-mediated HDAC3 and PRC2 could be a common feature of many tumor suppressor miRNAs. Thus, our findings provide rational to redirect therapeutic effort by reactivating these tumor suppressor miRNAs through combined inhibition of HDAC and PRC2. Convincingly, we demonstrated that the combination of HDAC and EZH2 inhibitors (vorinostat and DZNep) or their siRNAs induced more miR-29a/b1 and miR-29b2/c gene expression, resulting in the synergistic reduction of protein levels of CDK6 and IGF-1R and subsequent inhibition of cell survival and colony formation in vitro. Of note, HDAC3 and EZH2 overexpression was detected in essentially all of the lymphoma cell lines and primary samples that we tested but not in normal B-lymphocytes and nontransformed B-lymphocytes. This provides a strong rationale that targeting HDAC3 and EZH2 may be more effective in lymphoma cells than in normal B lymphocytes. Indeed, our study showed that vorinostat and DZNep dramatically inhibited cell growth of transformed P493-6 cells and had no or minimal effect on non-transformed P493-6 cells. Finally, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies presented in this work illustrated that, compared with treatment with each agent alone, combined treatment with DZNep and vorinostat inhibits tumor growth and significantly improves survival of NOD/SCID mice bearing MCL xenografts. These results strongly support further development and testing of a combination of anti-EZH2 and a specific HDAC3 inhibitor against aggressive lymphomas.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S9"><title>EXPERIMENT PROCEDURES</title><sec id="S10"><title>Cell Lines, Cell Proliferation, Colony Formation Assay and Patient Samples</title><p id="P23">Cell lines and patients samples information are detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Information (SI)</xref>. All patient tissue specimens were from fresh biopsy-derived lymphoma tissues (lymph nodes) after informed consent was obtained, in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, and after approval by the institutional review board of the University of South Florida. Details of cell proliferation and colony formation assays are also described in SI.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Co-Immunoprecipitation (co-IP) and Chromatin Immunoprecipitation (CHIP)</title><p id="P24">For co-IP in 293T, cells were transfected with plasmids using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Cells were harvested 36 hrs after transfection. 200 g protein was immunoprecipitated with the primary antibody (2 g) overnight at 4°C, and the immunocomplexes were r esolved by SDS-PAGE followed by immunoblot analysis.</p><p id="P25">For endogenous protein interaction in Jeko-1, immunoprecipitation was performed using the Pierce co-IP Kit (Thermo Scientific). 6 g anti-HDAC3 antibody, anti-SUZ12 antibody or Normal Rabbit IgG was coupled to AminoLink Plus Coupling Resin according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Immune complexes were eluted from the resin, and analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by immunoblot analysis.</p><p id="P26">For P493-6 cell line, cells were lysed in NP-40 lysis buffer. 1000 g protein was immunoprecipitated with the primary antibody (2 g) overnight at 4°C. HDAC3 was detected using GenScript One-Hour IP-Western Kits.</p><p id="P27">For Chip assay, 2×10<sup>6</sup> cells and 3 g of antibody was used per immunoprecipitation. The immunoprecipitated DNA was treated with RNase (Ambion) for 30 minutes at 37°C and proteinase K (Roche) for an hour at 45°C.The DNA wa s purified with Qiagen PCR Spin columns. Purified DNA was analyzed by real-time PCR using specific primers. Primer sequences used in ChIP assay are listed in the SI.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Luciferase Assays</title><p id="P28">Cells transfected with indicated plasmid were harvested and subjected to luciferase reporter assay using the luciferase assay system according to the manufacture’s instruction (Promega). Details of this analysis and procedure are described in SI.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>siRNA Knockdown and Short-Hairpin RNA-Mediated Gene Knockdown</title><p id="P29">For transient trasfection of siRNA, 5×10<sup>6</sup> cells were transfected by electroporation using Nucleofector (Amaxa, Gaithersburg, MD) according to the manufacture’s instruction.</p><p id="P30">For short-hairpin RNA-mediated gene knockdown, cells were transduced with indicated lentivirus particles followed with puromycin selection. And the knock-down efficiency was confirmed by WB.</p><p id="P31">The details of these analysis and procedures are described in SI.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR Analysis and miRNA Microarray Analysis</title><p id="P32">For Quantitative RT-PCR Analysis, total RNA was isolated from cells with Trizol reagent (invitrogen). Quantitative reverse-transcribed polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions (Applied Biosystems).</p><p id="P33">Jeko-1 cells were treated with DZNep for 72 hours. Total RNA was extracted and reverse transcribed into cDNA using the Megaplex™ Primer Pools by TaqMan® miRNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems). The cDNAs were used to perform the microarray analysis using TaqMan® Array miRNA Cards according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Array data were analyzed using DataAssist™ Software V3.0 (Applied Biosystems).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Tumorigenesis Assays</title><p id="P34">5×10<sup>6</sup> Z138c cells were injected into flanks of NOD/SCID mice (n = 6 mice per condition). Treatment was initiated when mean tumor volume was approximately 200 mm<sup>3</sup>. Mice were treated intraperitoneally with DMSO (vehicle), 1 mg/kg of DZNep twice per week, and/or 30 mg/kg of Vorinostat daily for 2 weeks. Tumor growth was measured by calipers every three days. Survival of the mice in all groups is represented by Kaplan-Meier plot. All animal studies were performed in accordance with Kansas University Cancer Center Institutional Guidelines and Regulations for animal care and under protocols approved by the Kansas University Medical Center Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P35">All of the analyses were completed by SPSS 11.0 software, with p&lt; 0.05 considered statistically significant. Statistical analysis for Cell proliferation and Tumor growth curve was carried out by ANOVA. Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) Test was used to test the Kaplan-Meier plot. 
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>01</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS407702-supplement-01.doc" orientation="portrait" id="d36e817" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S17"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We are grateful to the Tissue Procurement and Molecular Core Laboratory at Moffitt Cancer Center for providing specimens and molecular analysis. We thank Rasa Hamilton for editorial assistance. This work was supported by grants from the National Cancer Institutes (R01 CA137123, to JT), Maher Fund (to JT), Susan and John Sykes Lymphoma Research Fund (to JT) and Lymphoma Research Foundation (to JT).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p content-type="publisher-disclaimer" id="P36">This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain.</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p id="P37">ACCESSION NUMBER</p><p id="P38">The GEO database accession number for the microarray data is <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE40019">GSE40019</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p id="P39">SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</p><p id="P40">Supplemental information includes six Fig. (Fig. S1 to S6) and Supplemental Experimental Procedures.</p></fn><fn id="FN4"><p id="P41">CONFLICT-OF-INTEREST DISCLOSURE</p><p id="P42">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arking</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas-Tikhonenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread microRNA repression by Myc contributes to tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18066065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.2007.30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2628762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of human DAB2IP gene expression mediated by polycomb Ezh2 complex and histone deacetylase in prostate cancer.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>22437</fpage><lpage>22444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M501379200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dave</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kluin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boerma</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisenburger</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenwald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular diagnosis of Burkitt's lymphoma.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>354</volume><fpage>2431</fpage><lpage>2442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa055759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of microRNAs in lymphoid biology and disease.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Hematol</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21519241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MOH.0b013e3283476012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3400499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garzon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimmino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanesi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callegari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costinean</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Cymering</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-29 family reverts aberrant methylation in lung cancer by targeting DNA methyltransferases 3A and 3B.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>15805</fpage><lpage>15810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17890317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0707628104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2000384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiskus</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sreekumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jillella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combined epigenetic therapy with the histone methyltransferase EZH2 inhibitor 3-deazaneplanocin A and the histone deacetylase inhibitor panobinostat against human AML cells.</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2009</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>2733</fpage><lpage>2743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19638619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2009-03-213496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2756128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrisqueta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klapper</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Five-gene model to predict survival in mantle-cell lymphoma using frozen or formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>4966</fpage><lpage>4972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2007.12.0410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chivukula</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wentzel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vivekanandan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torbenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic microRNA delivery suppresses tumorigenesis in a murine liver cancer model.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19524505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2009.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2722880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myc-mediated transcriptional repression by recruitment of histone deacetylase.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>3624</fpage><lpage>3629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18483244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-6552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santhanam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwind</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maharry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sp1/NFkappaB/HDAC/miR-29b regulatory network in KIT-driven myeloid leukemia.</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20385359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2010.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2917066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MiR-26a inhibits cell growth and tumorigenesis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma through repression of EZH2.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21199804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-10-1850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronk</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gores</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mir-29 regulates Mcl-1 protein expression and apoptosis.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>6133</fpage><lpage>6140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17404574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1210436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2432524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myc pathways provoking cell suicide and cancer.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>9007</fpage><lpage>9021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1207261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pekarsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santanam</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimmino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palamarchuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Efanov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maximov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rassenti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tcl1 expression in chronic lymphocytic leukemia is regulated by miR-29 and miR-181.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>11590</fpage><lpage>11593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17178851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-3613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klapproth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kestler</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stilgenbauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MYC stimulates EZH2 expression by repression of its negative regulator miR-26a.</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>4202</fpage><lpage>4212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18713946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2008-03-147645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascoyne</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MYC and aggressive B-cell lymphomas.</article-title><source>Adv Anat Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21490439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/PAP.0b013e3182169948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>So</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA Methyltransferase Controls Stem Cell Aging by Regulating BMI1 and EZH2 through MicroRNAs.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e19503</fpage><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0019503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3091856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sparmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Lohuizen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycomb silencers control cell fate, development and cancer.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Haaften</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalgliesh</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bignell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edkins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Meara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Somatic mutations of the histone H3K27 demethylase gene UTX in human cancer.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2873835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Kemenade</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raaphorst</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blokzijl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fieret</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satijn</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coexpression of BMI-1 and EZH2 polycomb-group proteins is associated with cycling cells and degree of malignancy in B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma.</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2001</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>3896</fpage><lpage>3901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood.v97.12.3896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunster</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kluin-Nelemans</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manders</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raaphorst</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willemze</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Polycomb group protein EZH2 is upregulated in proliferating, cultured human mantle cell lymphoma.</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><year>2001</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>950</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2141.2001.02641.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lwin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscinski</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sotomayor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Myc represses miR-15a/miR-16-1 expression through recruitment of HDAC3 in mantle cell and other non-Hodgkin B-cell lymphomas.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3002</fpage><lpage>3008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2011.470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3982396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lwin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dessureault</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscinski</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezania</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>microRNA expression profile and identification of miR-29 as a prognostic marker and pathogenetic factor by targeting CDK6 in mantle cell lymphoma.</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2010</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>2630</fpage><lpage>2639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20086245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2009-09-243147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852365</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text position="float" id="BX1" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlights</title></caption><p>Interplay between Myc, HDAC3 and EZH2 defines a mechanism of miRNA repression</p><p>Myc-miRNA-EZH2 positive feedback loop underlies Myc activity and tumor aggressiveness</p><p>miR-29 is required for Myc oncogenesis and cooperatively regulated by HDAC3 and EZH2</p><p>Targeting HDAC and EZH2 inhibits aggressive lymphomagenicity in vitro and in vivo</p></boxed-text><boxed-text position="float" id="BX2" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Significance</title></caption><p>Aberrant miRNA expression and miRNA oncogenic and tumor suppressive functions have been extensively investigated in many tumors, including lymphoma; however, the molecular basis for miRNA dysregulation remains unknown and emerging. Our findings of miRNA regulation by c-Myc (hereafter Myc) and epigenetic deacetylation by HDAC3 and trimethylation by EZH2 present a common mechanism for repression of many other tumor suppressor miRNAs. We demonstrated a Myc-miRNA-EZH2 feed-forward pathway that leads to persistent Myc and EZH2 overexpression and miR-29 repression, thus maintaining tumorigenic potential of lymphoma cells. Restoration of miR-29 expression through epigenetic drug co-treatment resulted in enhanced inhibition of oncogenic signaling pathways, lymphoma growth in vivo, and is a therapeutic target of histone modifications in aggressive B-cell lymphomas.</p></boxed-text><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Myc is overexpressed in aggressive MCLs and is inversely correlated with expression of miR-29</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) miR-29a-c expression inversely correlated with Myc expression in primary MCL cells. Expression levels of miR-29a-c and Myc in normal B lymphocytes and primary MCL samples were measured by qRT-PCR. The High Myc group is defined as those samples in the upper quartile (25%) of Myc expression while all others are placed in the Low Myc group for the patient samples. <bold>(B-D)</bold> Expression of Myc and miR29a-c in tetracycline (Tet)-treated (Myc turn-off or Myc-off) and untreated (Myc turn-on or Myc-on) P493-6 cells. <bold>B,</bold> Western Blot shows Myc expression levels in Myc-off P493-6 cells treated with Tet and in Mycon P493-6 cells after removal of Tet for indicated times. <bold>C,</bold> Pri-miR-29 expression levels in Mycoff P493-6 cells treated with Tet and in Myc-on P493-6 cells after removal of Tet for indicated times. <bold>D,</bold> Mature miR-29 and Myc expression levels in Myc-off P493-6 cells treated with Tet and in Myc-on P493-6 cells after removal of Tet for indicated times. Pri-miR-29 level was normalized to GAPDH, and mature miR-29 expression was normalized to RNU44. Results in B are representative of 3 independent experiments. Results in C and D are means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figgure 2</label><caption><title>MiR-29 family is co-regulated by HDAC3 and PRC2</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Vorinostat treatment for 48 hours dose-dependently increased primary and mature miR-29 expression levels in Jeko-1 and Ramos cells. <bold>(B)</bold> DZNep treatment for 48 hours downregulated EZH2 and SUZ12 in Jeko-1, Ramos and HBL2 Cells. <bold>(C)</bold> DZNep treatment for 48 hours dose-dependently increased primary and mature miR-29 expression in Jeko-1, Ramos and HBL2 Cells. <bold>(D)</bold> Knockdown of Myc or HDAC3 by siRNAs increased pri- and mature miR-29 expression levels in Mino, Jeko-1 and Ramos cells. mRNA and miRNA expression levels of cells treated with siCtrl were arbitrarily set as 1. <bold>(E)</bold> Knockdown of EZH2 and SUZ12 by their siRNAs increased miR-29a-c gene expression in Mino and Ramos cells. Results in A-E are means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Myc recruits HDAC3 and PRC2 to miR-29 promoters to repress the miR-29 transcription through histone deacetylation and trimethylation</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Schematic diagram showing location of Myc-binding sites of pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c regulatory region. S1, S2, and S3 represent Myc-binding site, which has E-box sequence. S4 was used as negative control and is located in the intron 4 of pri-miR-29b2/c and without E-box in this region. Both pri-miR-29s are highly conserved in their putative promoter region and in the pre-miR-29 stem sequences, encoded in the last intron (pre-miR-29a/b1) on chr.7q32.3 and the last exon (pre-miR-29b2/c) on chr.1q32.2 respectively. <bold>(B)</bold> ChIP assay showing Myc and HDAC3 enrichment on pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c promoters. ChIP assay was performed using Myc or HDAC3 antibody to detect binding on pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c promoters, S1-S3 regions and S4 was used as a negative control. % Input was calculated with 2<sup>(Ct [1% of input]-Ct[ChIP])</sup>. <bold>(C)</bold> ChIP assay showing Myc, HDAC3, EZH2 and SUZ12 enrichment on pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c promoters and dependence of HDAC3, EZH2/SUZ12 binding on Myc in P493-6 cells with or without 24 hours Tet treatment, Inserts, Western blots showing protein level of Myc, HDAC3 and EZH2/SUZ12 in Myc-on and Myc-off (24 hours Tet treatment) P493-6 cells. <bold>(D)</bold> ChIP assay showing EZH2 and SUZ12 enrichment on pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c with or without DZNep treatment. <bold>(E)</bold> ChIP assay showing Myc, HDAC3, EZH2 and SUZ12 enrichment on pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c promoters in primary lymphoma samples with high Myc expression (blastic MCLs, Burkitt or Burkitt like lymphomas) and no enrichment in primary samples with low myc expression (indolent MCLs). <bold>(F)</bold> Schematic diagram of pri-miR-29a/b1 and pri-miR-29b2/c promoter luciferase reporter. Solid boxes represent point mutation of E-Box. P493-6 cells were transfected with either wild-type or mutants (M) of pri-miR-29a/b1 or pri-miR-29b2/c promoter luciferase reporter, together with siHDAC3, siEZH2, or non-targeting siRNA. The luciferase activity is normalized to β-galactosidase. Results are means ± SD from 3 biological replicates. For ChIP assays, IgG was used as negative control. In B-F, results are means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. Inserts, Western blots showing protein level. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>HDAC3 bridges the interaction between Myc and PRC2 to form a co-repressor complex</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> 293T cells were transfected with Myc plasmid or FLAG-HDAC3 plasmid or cotransfected with Myc plasmid and FLAG-HDAC3 plasmid. The whole cell lysates were immunoprecipitated using an antibody against Myc, HDAC3, and control IgG, followed by Western blot with an antibody against Myc, FLAG, SUZ12, and EZH2. <bold>(B)</bold> Reciprocal Co<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>IP showing endogenous Co-IP of HDAC3 and SUZ12. Whole cell extracts of Jeko-1 cells were subjected to IP with anti-HDAC3 antibody followed by Western blotting for SUZ12, and similar whole cells extracts were subjected to IP with anti-SUZ12, followed by Western blotting with anti-HDAC3. <bold>(C)</bold> Co-IP of Myc, HDAC3, and SUZ12/EZH2 in Myc-on and Myc-off P493-6 cells. Cell lysates of P493-6 with and without Tet treatment were immunoprecipitated with Myc, HDAC3, SUZ12, EZH2, and control IgG, respectively, followed by Western blotting with an antibody against Myc, HDAC3, SUZ12, and EZH2. <bold>(D)</bold> HDAC3-mediated interaction between Myc and SUZ12/EZH2. P493-6 (Myc-on) cells were transfected with HDAC3 siRNA or non-targeting siRNA to knock down HDAC3, and Co-IP experiments were performed to evaluate interaction between Myc and SUZ12/EZH2. A-D, Input is equivalent to 10% of the lysate used for the Co-IP. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>miR-29 is required for Myc-mediated oncogenic activity by targeting IGF-1R and CDK6 pathways</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> IGF-1R is a direct target of miR-29. Overexpression of miR-29a-c downregulates IGF-1R expression and reduces luciferase activity of wild-type IGF-1R 3′ UTR reporter (IGF-1R-WT) but not mutated IGF-1R 3′UTR reporter (IGF-1R-M). <bold>(B)</bold> miR-29 level is reversely correlated with IGF-1R protein expression of MCL patient samples. <bold>(C)</bold> IGF-1R and CDK6 expression in Myc-on and Myc-off P493-6 cells. <bold>(D)</bold> 48hrs after pre-miR-29a-c transfection abolished Myc-induced CDK6 and IGF-1R expression and knockdown of miR-29 by anti-miR-29 blocked “Myc-off”-induced CDK6 and IGF-1R repression, and anti-miR-29s (pool of anti-miR-29a-c) is used to knockdown miR-29 expression. <bold>(E)</bold> Knockdown of IGF1R and CDK6 by their siRNAs inhibits lymphoma cell survival measured by MTT and colony formation assay in HBL2 cells after transfection with siIGF-1R and siCDK6 or control siRNA. Micrographs show the appearance of colonies in methycellulose gels at low power. <bold>(F)</bold> Over-expression of miR-29 decreases the colony formation. The numbers of tumor colonies were enumerated microscopically after an incubation of 2 weeks. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments or means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Myc-miR-26a-EZH2-miR-494 positive feedback loop sustains Myc activity and miR-29 repression</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> EZH2 is a direct target of miR-26a. Overexpression of miR-26a downregulates EZH2 and Myc expression and suppresses EZH2 3’-UTR luciferase activity in 293T cells. <bold>(B)</bold> miR-26a expression is regulated by Myc. miR-26a, EZH2, SUZ12, and c-Myc protein expression levels in Myc turn-on and Myc turn-off P493-6 cells. <bold>(C)</bold> Overexpression of miR-26a by Pre-miR-26a suppresses Myc-induced EZH2 expression in Myc-on P493-6 cells, while suppression of miR-26a by Anti-miR-26a increases EZH2 expression in Myc-off P493-6 cells. <bold>(D)</bold> Inhibition of EZH2 with DZNep or shRNA decreases Myc protein expression. <bold>(E)</bold> Putative Myc 3’-UTR targeting miRNAs are upregulated by EZH2 inhibition. <bold>(F)</bold> TargetScan and microCosm depicting potential binding sites for the DZNep upregulated miRNAs in Myc-3’-UTR and Myc is a direct target of miR-494. 293T cells are co-transfected with luciferase reporters, which contain the wild-type or mutant of Myc 3’-UTR, and overexpression of miR-494 inhibits Myc-3’-UTR but not mutant 3’-UTR luciferase activities. <bold>(G)</bold> Overexpression of miR-494 suppresses Myc and EZH2 expression. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments or means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0006.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>miR-26a and miR-29 downregulation are reversely correlated with upregulation of Myc and EZH2 in MCL and other aggressive Myc-expressing lymphomas</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> miR-26a and miR-29 expression levels and Myc and EZH2 protein levels in MCL and other aggressive B-cell lymphoma cell lines. Cell lines were as follows: Jeko-1, Mino, HBL-2, NCEB-1, REC-1, Z138c (MCL); Raji and Ramos (Burkitt lymphoma)’ SUDHL-4 (Su-4), SUDHL-10 (Su10) (transformed large B-cell lymphoma); and SKW6.2 (EBV-associated lymphoma). <bold>(B)</bold> miR-26a and miR-29 expression levels and Myc and EZH2 protein levels in primary MCL samples and other aggressive B-cell lymphoma samples. Samples were as follows: P1 and P5 (aggressive MCL); P31-35 and P13 (Burkitt lymphoma); P36, P14, and P24-P25 (high grade transformed diffuse large B-cell lymphomas). N1-N3, CD19 sorted normal B lymphocytes. miR-29 and miR-26a expression levels were measured by qRT-PCR and normalized to RNU44. Myc and EZH2 expression levels were evaluated by Western blot, A-B, the relative level of Myc and EZH2 protein was measured by quantitative densitometry and is indicated below each lane. Insert, correlation between Myc and EZH2 protein. r, correlation coefficient.<bold>(C)</bold> Correlation between Myc/EZH2 protein expressions with miR-26a/miR-29a-c level in MCL and other aggressive B-cell lymphoma cell lines. r, correlation coefficient. <bold>(D)</bold> Correlation between Myc/EZH2 protein expressions with miR-26a/miR-29a-c level in primary MCL and other aggressive B-cell lymphoma samples. r, correlation coefficient. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments or means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0007.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Combined inhibition of HDAC and PRC2 cooperatively reactivates miR-29 level and suppresses tumor cell growth in vitro and in vivo</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Combined treatment with vorinostat and DZNep induces higher expression of primary miR-29a/b1, primary miR-29b2/c, and mature miR-29a-c than each agent alone in HBL-2 cells. <bold>(B-C)</bold> Combined treatment with vorinostat and DZNep induced higher downregulation of IGF-1R and CDK6 protein (B) and inhibition of clonogenic growth (C) than each agent alone in HBL-2 cells. <bold>(D)</bold> Cell proliferation assay (CCK8) showing that Myc-on P493-6 cells are more sensitive than Myc-off P496-3 cells to DZNep and vorinostat treatment. <bold>(E-F)</bold> Co-treatment with DZNep and vorinostat inhibits tumor growth and significantly improves survival of NOD/SCID mice bearing MCL xenografts. Tumor growth was measured by calipers. Results are mean tumor volume ± SEM, (treatment vs. vehicle control, * p&lt;0.001; combination vs. single agent, ** p=0.0002, # p=0.0004). Survival of mice in all groups is represented by a Kaplan-Meier plot and Log-rank test was used. (n = 6 mice per condition) <bold>(G)</bold> Model of feed-forward regulatory circuit in which Myc contributes to the upregulation of EZH2 via repressing EZH2-targeting miR-26a and that EZH2 in turn relieves <italic toggle="yes">Myc</italic> negative regulation via Myc-targeting miR-494, thereby generating <italic toggle="yes">a positive feedback loop</italic> to ensure persistently high protein levels of Myc and EZH2 and further repression of miR-29. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments or means ± SD from at least 3 biological replicates. (See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-407702-f0008.jpg"/></fig></floats-group></article>