
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Skelet Muscle</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Skelet Muscle</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1569</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">skelmuscle</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101561193</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Skeletal Muscle</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-5040</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3356597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3356597.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3356597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3356597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22541644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2044-5040-2-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2044-5040-2-6</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MyoD-dependent regulation of NF-κB activity couples cell-cycle withdrawal to myogenic differentiation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names initials="MH">Maura H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>mparker@fhcrc.org</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Maltzahn</surname><given-names initials="J">Julia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>jvonmaltzahn@ohri.ca</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkar</surname><given-names initials="N">Nadine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>Nadine.Bakkar@osumc.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Joubori</surname><given-names initials="B">Ban</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ban.aljoubori@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jeff</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ishibashij@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names initials="D">Denis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>denis.guttridge@osumc.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names initials="MA">Michael A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>mrudnicki@ohri.ca</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Health Sciences Graduate Programme, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Molecular Medicine Program, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Current address: Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Clinical Research Division, Seattle, WA, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>The Ohio State University College of Medicine, Columbus, Ohio, USA</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, 501 Smyth Rd, Ottawa, ON, K1H 8L6, Canada</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">205880</issue-id><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>05</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-12 13:25:15.480"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright ©2012 Parker et al; licensee BioMed Central. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Parker et al; licensee BioMed Central. </copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.skeletalmusclejournal.com/2/1/6"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Skelet Muscle" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC3717048"><article-title>Retraction: MyoD-dependent regulation of NF-κB activity couples cell-cycle withdrawal to myogenic differentiation</article-title><volume>3</volume><date><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><source>Skeletal Muscle</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2044-5040-3-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3717048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23870549</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Mice lacking MyoD exhibit delayed skeletal muscle regeneration and markedly enhanced numbers of satellite cells. Myoblasts isolated from <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts proliferate more rapidly than wild type myoblasts, display a dramatic delay in differentiation, and continue to incorporate BrdU after serum withdrawal.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Primary myoblasts isolated from wild type and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mutant mice were examined by microarray analysis and further characterized by cell and molecular experiments in cell culture.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We found that NF-κB, a key regulator of cell-cycle withdrawal and differentiation, aberrantly maintains nuclear localization and transcriptional activity in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. As a result, expression of cyclin D is maintained during serum withdrawal, inhibiting expression of muscle-specific genes and progression through the differentiation program. Sustained nuclear localization of cyclin E, and a concomitant increase in cdk2 activity maintains S-phase entry in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts even in the absence of mitogens. Importantly, this deficit was rescued by forced expression of IκBαSR, a non-degradable mutant of IκBα, indicating that inhibition of NF-κB is sufficient to induce terminal myogenic differentiation in the absence of MyoD.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>MyoD-induced cytoplasmic relocalization of NF-κB is an essential step in linking cell-cycle withdrawal to the terminal differentiation of skeletal myoblasts. These results provide important insight into the unique functions of MyoD in regulating the switch from progenitor proliferation to terminal differentiation.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Skeletal muscle</kwd><kwd>Myoblasts</kwd><kwd>MyoD</kwd><kwd>NF-κB</kwd><kwd>IKK</kwd><kwd>IκB</kwd><kwd>Differentiation</kwd><kwd>Myogenesis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Cell survival and differentiation is regulated by NF-κB, a family of ubiquitously expressed transcription factors comprising RelA/p65, c-Rel, RelB, p50 (processed form of p105), and p52 (processed form of p100) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. NF-κB proteins function as homo- or heterodimers, the most common of which is the p50/p65 heterodimer. All family members contain a DNA-binding domain, a protein-protein dimerization domain, and a nuclear localization sequence (NLS). However, only RelA/p65, c-Rel, and RelB have a transactivation domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>Sub-cellular localization of NF-κB is regulated by ‘inhibitor of κB’ proteins: IκBα, IκBβ, and IκBϵ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. IκB proteins bind NF-κB, mask the nuclear localization signal, and sequester NF-κB in the cytoplasm as an inactive protein. Upon induction, IκB kinases (IKKs) phosphorylate IκB, releasing NF-κB and targeting IκB for degradation. The released NF-κB enters the nucleus, binds DNA, and regulates gene transcription. This process is normally activated by molecules such as cytokines, growth factors, and bacterial products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>Myogenic specification and differentiation requires the myogenic regulatory factors (MRFs), namely MyoD, Myf5, myogenin, and MRF4/Myf6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The MRFs share a highly homologous basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) domain, which is required for DNA binding and dimerization with the E-protein family of transcription factors. MRF-E-protein heterodimers bind to the consensus E-box sequence, CANNTG, in gene promoters and regulate transcriptional activation.</p><p>In particular, MyoD and Myf5 are essential for murine skeletal muscle development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, mice lacking MyoD are viable and fertile, and display no overt phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. This indicates that myogenic specification and differentiation during embryonic and fetal development occurs in the absence of MyoD, due to the presence of other myogenic regulatory factors, such as Myf5. Analysis of regeneration in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> muscle established an essential role for MyoD in regulating adult myogenesis. In particular, increased numbers of satellite cells and a deficient muscle regenerative process in mice lacking <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup>), or <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic> and dystrophin (<italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup><italic toggle="yes">:mdx</italic>), suggests that in the absence of MyoD, satellite cells have an increased propensity for self-renewal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Analysis of the differentiation kinetics of cultured <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> satellite cell derived myoblasts revealed a marked delay in differentiation, characterized by reduced expression of differentiation specific markers such as myosin heavy chain, <italic toggle="yes">myogenin</italic><italic toggle="yes">MRF4</italic><italic toggle="yes">α-actins</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">acetylcholine receptor-δ</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Although a portion of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> cells express myosin heavy chain (MyHC), these myocytes fail to fuse and remain primarily mononuclear. Moreover, the majority of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts display continued incorporation of bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) into DNA after serum withdrawal, indicating DNA synthesis is maintained in the absence of mitogen stimulation.</p><p>In this study, we examined the role MyoD plays in regulating cell-cycle withdrawal during terminal differentiation in adult myogenesis by undertaking a closer investigation of the molecular phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. We observed that <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts maintained nuclear localization of NF-κB after serum withdrawal, and displayed altered expression of NF-κB target genes. In particular, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts failed to down-regulate <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic>, an NF-κB target gene and key mediator of cell-cycle withdrawal and differentiation in myoblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Importantly, inhibition of NF-κB activity, through expression of a mutant form of IκBα (IκB-SR), rescued the differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. Therefore, we conclude that MyoD controls cell-cycle withdrawal by regulating the subcellular localization of the NF-κB family of transcription factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Myoblast isolation and cell culture</title><p>Myoblasts were isolated from 6 to 8 week old <italic toggle="yes">wild type (WT)</italic> Balb/C mice and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mice and cultured as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. To induce differentiation, the cells were washed once with PBS and transferred to differentiation medium (DMEM supplemented with 5% horse serum (Invitrogen), and 2X penicillin/streptomycin). C2C12 murine myoblasts were cultured and differentiated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Transfections and luciferase assay</title><p>C2C12 and MyoD-/- myoblasts were transfected in low serum Opti-MEM using Lipofectamine (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer. Reporter and expression plasmids were previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], and all transfections were normalized to CMV-βGAL expression. For luciferase assays, cells were lysed in MPER (Pierce) and assays were performed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. MyoD siRNA was obtained from SantaCruz and transfections were performed using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA isolation and RNase protection assay</title><p>RNA was isolated using TriZol Reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The RNase protection assay was performed using the RiboQuant kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions (BD Bioscience, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). The relative amount of radioactivity present in each band was quantitated using a Phosphorimager (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, England), and the values obtained for each cyclin were normalized to the value for the GAPDH control.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblotting and antibodies</title><p>Proteins were separated on 10% or 12% SDS-polyacrylamide gel, and transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride membrane (Immobilon-P; Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) according to established protocols. The antibodies used were all from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz. CA, USA): anti-cyclin D1 (C-20), anti-cyclin D2 (H-289), anti-cyclin D3 (C-16), anti-cdk4 (C-22), anti-cyclin A1 (C-19), anti-cyclin E (C-19), anti-cdk2 (H-298), anti-cyclin H (C-18), anti-cdk7 (C-19), anti-NF-κB p65 (C-20), anti-Myf5 (C-19), anti-MyoD (C-20), and anti-IKKγ (FL-419). For immunoblotting, all antibodies were used according to the manufacturer’s instructions, normally at a dilution of 1:500 or 1:1,000. Goat anti-mouse and goat anti-rabbit secondary antibodies were used at 1:2,000 (BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA). Antibody-bound proteins were detected using enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL; GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, England) and X-OMAT 5 X-ray film.</p></sec><sec><title>Kinase assays</title><p>Each 10-cm plate from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts were lysed with 300 μL of NP-40 Lysis/IP buffer (50 mM Tris–HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 2.5 mM EGTA, 1 mM DTT, 10% glycerol, 0.1 mM Na<sub>2</sub>VO<sub>3</sub>, 50 mM NaF, 20 mM β-glycerophosphate, 50 μg/mL PMSF, 2 μg/mL leupeptin, 1 μg/mL aprotinin, 10 μg/mL pepstatin). Immunoprecipitated cdk2 was incubated with 1 μg of histone H1 (Invitrogen) and 5 μCi of γ-<sup>32</sup>P-ATP (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, England) in kinase buffer, and incubating at 30°C for 20 min. IKK kinase assays were performed as previously described using a GST-IκBα substrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>Mouse U74Av2 GeneChip microarrays (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) were used to analyse gene expression in wild type and MyoD-/- primary myoblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. A list of genes related to the NF-κB pathway was defined with reference to commercial microarrays (Panomics; Superarray Bioscience, Frederick, MD, USA) and the literature. Microarray data is available from StemBase (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scgp.ca:8080/StemBase/">http://www.scgp.ca:8080/StemBase/</ext-link>) under experiment number E223 (samples S361-4) and E59 (S78-9) and from the National Center for Biotechnology Information’s Gene Expression Omnibus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) under series accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE3245">GSE3245</ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSM73053">GSM73053</ext-link>…64) and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE3244">GSE3244</ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSM73026">GSM73026</ext-link>, -29, -32, -35, -38, and -41).</p></sec><sec><title>Virus production and transduction</title><p>To generate ecotrophic retroviral supernatant, Phoenix-eco packaging cell lines were obtained from ATCC, cultured in DMEM with 4.5 g/L glucose (Invitrogen Life Technologies), supplemented with 100 U/mL penicillin and 100 μg/mL streptomycin, and 10% FBS (Hyclone, Logan, UT, USA), and transfected either with pBabe/Iκ (expressing IKBα-SR) or pBabe (empty vector) using lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen Life Technologies). Retroviral supernatant was harvested 48 h after transfection and filtered through a 0.45 μm syringe filter (Millipore). Primary proliferating <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> cells were infected with diluted viral supernatant plus 8 μg/mL polybrene (hexadimetherine bromide, Sigma Aldrich, ST. Louis, MO, USA). Drug selection was conducted using 2 μg/mL Puromycin (Sigma Aldrich) for 7 days; uninfected controls were obliterated after 4 days of selection. Differentiation was induced by replacing growth medium with DMEM + 5% horse serum (Hyclone).</p></sec><sec><title>Animals</title><p>All animal procedures conform with the Canadian Council on Animal Care’s Guide to the Care and Use of Experimental Animals, the Animals for Research Act, and were approved by the Animal Care Committee at University of Ottawa.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Sustained activation of NF-κB during differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts</title><p><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts express myosin heavy chain upon serum withdrawal, yet fail to fuse into multinucleated myotubes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. This phenotype is recapitulated in MyoD-expressing <italic toggle="yes">IκBα-/-</italic> fibroblasts, in which NF-κB is persistently nuclear localized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Given that NF-κB is normally relocalized to the cytoplasm during myogenic differentiation, we sought to determine if NF-κB remains in the nucleus during induction of differentiation in myoblasts lacking MyoD. Nuclear and cytoplasmic protein extracts from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts were subjected to western blot analysis using an antibody specific for p65/RelA. Strikingly, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts displayed continued nuclear localization of NF-κB (RelA/p65) after mitogen withdrawal, whereas RelA/p65 was appropriately relocated to the cytoplasm in <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Furthermore we conducted immunofluorescence analyses of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> cells under growth and differentiation conditions. We observed continued nuclear localization of NF-κB (RelA/p65) in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> cells during differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) while <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> cells displayed the expected shift in localization of NF-κB (RelA/p65) during differentiation. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> myoblasts appear to have less cytoplasmic NF-kB than WT myoblasts in growth conditions, suggesting that NF-κB signalling is aberrant in the absence of MyoD in proliferation as well as differentiation.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>NF-κB remains localized to the nucleus after serum withdrawal in</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts.</bold><bold>(A)</bold> Protein was isolated from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts and a western blot using the nuclear (N) and cytoplasmic (C) fractions was performed with an antibody specific for the p65 subunit of NF-κB. A western blot with an antibody specific for α-tubulin was performed using the cytoplasmic fractions. <bold>(B)</bold> Immunofluorescence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> myoblasts and myotubes demonstrate that NF-κB remains localized in the nucleus in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> myoblasts even after differentiation. Staining for NF-κB in red, nuclei are counterstained with DAPI (in blue). Scale bar: 20 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-1.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine if continued nuclear localization of p65 correlates with increased transcriptional activity, an NF-κB specific luciferase reporter (3xκB-Luc) was transfected into C2C12 cells lacking MyoD expression. C2C12 myoblasts transfected with <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-specific siRNA (siMyoD-C2C12) exhibited a significant decrease in MyoD expression, and resembled <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, data not shown). Luciferase activity in 3xκB-Luc-transfected siMyoD-C2C12 myoblasts was increased relative to control cells, indicating that in the absence of MyoD, RelA/p65 continued to be transcriptionally active after induction of differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Co-transfection with exogenous p65 enhanced activation of the 3xκB-Luc reporter, yet siMyoD cells continued to exhibit elevated NF-κB activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Loss of MyoD activates NF-κB.</bold><bold>(A)</bold> Protein isolated from C2C12 myoblasts transfected with control siRNA or siRNA specific for MyoD were analyzed by western blot using antibodies specific to MyoD and α-tubulin. <bold>(B)</bold> C2C12 cells transfected with control siRNA (siCont) or MyoD siRNA (siMyoD) were co-transfected with an NF-kB reporter vector (3xκB-Luc). Bars represent average luciferase activity (relative light units (RLUs)) (n = 3). Error bars represent standard deviation. <bold>(C)</bold> Same as B, with the addition of a p65 (NF-κB) expression vector.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-2.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine if expression of NF-κB target genes, or genes that participate in the NF-κB signalling pathway, were altered in the absence of MyoD, the expression profiles of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts and <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts were compared using an Affymetrix microarray (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Known NF-κB target genes were selected from genes displaying differences in expression (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bu.edu/nf-kb/gene-resources/target-genes/">http://www.bu.edu/nf-kb/gene-resources/target-genes/</ext-link> for an overview). Genes that were specifically up-regulated in myoblasts lacking MyoD are tabulated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, whereas genes that were down-regulated are documented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. NF-κB target genes such as <italic toggle="yes">MCP-1/CCL2/GRO-α</italic><italic toggle="yes">MIP-2/CXCL1</italic>, matrix metalloproteinases (<italic toggle="yes">MMP3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MMP13</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">VCAM1</italic><italic toggle="yes">IL-6</italic><italic toggle="yes">BCL-2</italic><italic toggle="yes">IL-11</italic><italic toggle="yes">IGFBP-2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">JunB</italic> are represented in both Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, indicating that nuclear localized NF-κB was transcriptionally active in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. Furthermore we investigated genes involved in myogenesis. We found the following genes to be down-regulated in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts compared to <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts: myogenin, Myf5, Mef2C, embryonic myosin heavy chain, MRF4/Myf6, as well as Six1.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>NF-κB-related genes up-regulated in</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>RefSeq</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Fold</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gene name</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ccl2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011333">NM_011333</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">166.7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bgn<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_007542">NM_007542</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biglycan<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mmp3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_010809">NM_010809</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matrix metallopeptidase 3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cxcl1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_008176">NM_008176</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thbs2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011581">NM_011581</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.9<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thrombospondin 2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mmp13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_008607">NM_008607</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matrix metallopeptidase 13<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vcam1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011693">NM_011693</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vascular cell adhesion molecule 1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Il6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_031168">NM_031168</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interleukin 6<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ier3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_133662">NM_133662</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Immediate early response 3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Penk1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_001002927">NM_001002927</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Preproenkephalin 1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pcaf<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_020005">NM_020005</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p300/CBP-associated factor<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H2-T23<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_010398">NM_010398</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Histocompatibility 2, T region locus 23<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stat6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_009284">NM_009284</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Signal transducer and activator of transcription 6<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ptgs2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011198">NM_011198</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prostaglandin-endoperoxide synthase 2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abcb1b<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011075">NM_011075</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATP-binding cassette, sub-family B (MDR/TAP), 1B<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gja1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_010288">NM_010288</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gap junction membrane channel protein alpha 1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tnfaip3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_009397">NM_009397</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor necrosis factor, alpha-induced protein 3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bcl2</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_009741">NM_009741</ext-link></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-cell leukemia/lymphoma 2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>NF-κB-related genes down-regulated in</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>RefSeq</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Fold</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gene name</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Il11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_008350">NM_008350</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-23.2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interleukin 11<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Igfbp2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_008342">NM_008342</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-9.1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Insulin-like growth factor binding protein 2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tlr6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011604">NM_011604</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toll-like receptor 6<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fos<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_010234">NM_010234</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3.1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FBJ osteosarcoma oncogene<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ccnd3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_007632">NM_007632</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2.7<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cyclin D3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cd80<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_009855">NM_009855</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD80 antigen<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Junb<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_008416">NM_008416</ext-link><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2.3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jun-B oncogene<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Selp</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_011347">NM_011347</ext-link></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Selectin, platelet</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts maintain expression of cyclin D1 and D2 after serum withdrawal</title><p><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts continue to proliferate in the absence of mitogens, indicating that cell-cycle modulators, such as cyclins, may be aberrantly expressed and/or regulated. Given that RelA/p65 specifically regulates expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic> in myoblasts we hypothesized that persistent activation of RelA/p65 would result in continued expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts, even after serum withdrawal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>In order to investigate changes in important cell-cycle genes in the absence of MyoD, RNA was isolated from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> primary myoblasts, and the relative expression level of a variety of cyclins was determined using an RNase protection assay. The relative amount of mRNA present for each cyclin was quantitated using a phosphorimager, and normalized to a <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> control. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref> show resulting autoradiographs of polyacrylamide gels, and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref> graphically depicts quantitation of the results. <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts exhibited a higher level of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D2</italic> mRNA, and a lower level of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cyclin G1</italic> mRNA when compared to WT myoblasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>). However, neither <italic toggle="yes">cyclin E</italic> nor <italic toggle="yes">cyclin H</italic> mRNA was affected by the absence of MyoD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts maintain cyclin D expression after serum withdrawal.</bold><bold>(A, C)</bold> RNA was isolated from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts and an RNase protection assay was performed with the indicated probes. The protected <sup>32</sup>P-labeled fragments were separated on a polyacrylamide gel, the gel dried and exposed to X-ray film. <bold>(B, D)</bold> The amount of each protected fragment was quantitated using a phosphorimager. The values obtained were normalized relative to the GAPDH control and the L32 control, and graphed as a function of the number of days in differentiation medium (DM), n = 3. <bold>(E)</bold> Nuclear protein was isolated from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts and a western blot was performed with the indicated antibodies. <bold>(F)</bold> Quantitative real-time PCR for Cyclin D3 of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> myoblasts, n = 3.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-3.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine if changes in mRNA expression are translated into changes in protein levels, nuclear protein extracts were isolated from a similar differentiation time course and analyzed by western blot analysis. In accord with RNase protection assay results, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts displayed a higher level of cyclin D1 and D2 protein in the nucleus, and continued expression of both cyclins after mitogen withdrawal (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>). Expression of cyclin D3 protein, on the other hand, was not altered in the absence of MyoD. Taken together, these data imply that persistent activation of RelA/p65 is responsible for expression of cyclin D1 in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts after serum withdrawal.</p><p>pRb is also phosphorylated by cyclin E-cdk2, and this phosphorylation is required for S-phase entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Moreover, forced expression of cyclin E bypasses the need for cyclin D/cdk4 activity in cell-cycle progression from G1 to S phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin E</italic> mRNA was not altered in the absence of MyoD, indicating that the increase in cyclin D1 expression is not inducing cell-cycle progression through stimulation of E2F activity on the <italic toggle="yes">cyclin E</italic> promoter (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C and D</xref>).</p><p>However, overexpression of cyclin D1 may also inhibit MRF activity and myogenic differentiation through a mechanism independent of pRb or MyoD phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Indeed, a hypophosphorylated mutant of pRb (pRbΔp35; EF), which induces cell-cycle withdrawal, is unable to rescue cyclin D-dependent inhibition of muscle-specific gene expression (MH Parker, MA Rudnicki, unpublished observations).</p></sec><sec><title>Loss of MyoD stimulates S-phase entry</title><p>Although expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin E</italic> mRNA was not altered (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>), western blot analysis of protein extracts from a differentiation time course of wild type and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/</italic></sup>-myoblasts displayed an increased level of cyclin E protein in the nucleus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). This may be the result of increased stability of cyclin E protein, or of prolonged nuclear localization after mitogen withdrawal. The level of nuclear cdk2 protein was also elevated, and more importantly, appeared to be the slower migrating, activated form. In order to determine if cdk2 activity was maintained after mitogen withdrawal, a kinase assay was employed using protein extracts from the same differentiation time course of wild type and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. As expected, elevated levels of cdk2 correlated with increased cdk2 kinase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts enter S-phase more readily than WT myoblasts.</bold><bold>(A)</bold> Western blot was performed using the indicated antibodies and nuclear protein isolated from a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts. <bold>(B)</bold> Cdk2 was immunoprecipitated from protein extracts of a differentiation time course of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts, and assayed for kinase activity using histone H1 and γ-<sup>32</sup>P-ATP as substrate. <bold>(C)</bold> Proliferating <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts were fixed in ethanol and DNA stained with propidium iodide (PI). Cells were analyzed for DNA content by FACS analysis. The percentage of cells in each phase of the cell cycle is indicated.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-4.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine if increased cdk2 kinase activity forced cells to enter S-phase more readily, proliferating <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts were fixed and analyzed for DNA content using fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS). As expected, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts displayed a two-fold increase in the number of cells in S-phase (23% of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts compared to 12% of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). This increase in the proportion of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts in S-phase was accompanied by a decrease in the proportion of cells in the G1 phase of the cell cycle (68% of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> cells compared to 84% of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> cells). Therefore, in the absence of MyoD, myoblasts enter into S-phase more readily, likely as a result of increased cyclin E-cdk2 activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of NF-κB restores differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts</title><p>Skeletal muscle differentiation requires both cell-cycle withdrawal and muscle-specific gene expression. <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts fail to withdraw from the cell cycle, as evidenced by continued DNA synthesis after induction of differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Given that <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts aberrantly maintain transcriptionally active RelA/p65 after serum withdrawal, we hypothesize that persistent activation of RelA/p65 is responsible for the failure to exit the cell cycle. Moreover, we propose that the inability to induce cell-cycle withdrawal is directly responsible for the delay in differentiation in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts.</p><p>IκB kinases (IKKs) phosphorylate IκB, resulting in degradation of IκB and nuclear localization of RelA/p65 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. To determine if IKK activity is aberrantly maintained in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts after induction of differentiation, IKK was immunoprecipitated from <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> and wild type myoblast protein extracts and kinase activity assayed using GST-IκBα and γ-<sup>32</sup>P-ATP as substrate. <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts displayed approximately 2-fold greater IKK activity, as compared to WT myoblasts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Elevated IKK activity in</bold><bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></bold></sup><bold>myoblasts is responsible for increased NF-κB activity.</bold><bold>(A)</bold> Kinase assay (KA): IKK was immunoprecipitated from protein extracts of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> (MyoD<sup>+/+</sup>) and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts, and assayed for kinase activity using GST-IκBα and γ-<sup>32</sup>P-ATP as substrate. Immunoblot (IB): IKK was immunoprecipitated from protein extracts of <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> (MyoD<sup>+/+</sup>) and <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> primary myoblasts, and assayed by western blot using an antibody specific for IKKγ. <bold>(B)</bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts were transfected with vector control, vector expressing a dominant negative mutant IKKβ (IKKβ DN) or a non-phosphorylatable mutant of IkBα (IκB-SR), in addition to an NF-κB reporter (3xκB-Luc). Bars represent average luciferase activity (relative light units (RLUs)) (n = 3). Error bars represent standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-5.jpg"/></fig><p>If increased IKK activity results in RelA/p65 activation, then inhibiting IKK should inhibit NF-κB transcriptional activity. Treating <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts with a chemical inhibitor of IKK (data not shown), or expressing a dominant negative mutant of IKKβ (IKKβ DN), resulted in decreased activity of 3xκB-Luc, indicating that elevated IKK activity is in part responsible for persistent NF-κB transcriptional activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Therefore, to target RelA/p65 directly, a non-phosphorylatable mutant form of IκBα (IκBα-SR) was expressed, which is resistant to targeted degradation and prevents nuclear localization of NF-κB. Indeed, expression of IkBα-SR in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts inhibited 3xκB-Luc activity, indicating that NF-κB was directly repressed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Moreover, expression of IκBα-SR in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts down-regulated expression of cyclin D1 and cdk2 upon initiation of differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>). This strongly suggests that sustained nuclear localization of RelA/p65 in the <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts is responsible for cellular proliferation after serum withdrawal.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Nuclear localization of NF-κB inhibits terminal differentiation.</bold><bold>(A)</bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup>-/-</sup> myoblasts were infected with empty capsid (pBABE) or virus expressing IκBα-SR (pBABE-IkB). Protein extracts from proliferating infected cells and uninfected cells (control) were analyzed by western blot analysis using an antibody specific to IκBα. <bold>(B)</bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts were infected with empty capsid (pBABE) or virus expressing IκBα-SR (pBABE-IkB). Proliferating cells (GM), or cells induced to differentiate for 5 days, were fixed and assessed for myosin heavy chain (MyHC) expression (in green). Nuclei were visualized using DAPI (in blue). <bold>(C)</bold> Fusion index of myotubes from <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> cells either infected with a control (pBABE) or an IκBα-SR (pBABE-IkB) expressing virus, n = 5, ** = <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** = <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001. <bold>(D)</bold><italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts were infected with empty capsid (pBABE) or virus expressing IκBα-SR (pBABE-IkB). Protein extracts from a differentiation time course of infected and uninfected cells were analyzed by western blot analysis using the antibodies indicated</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="2044-5040-2-6-6.jpg"/></fig><p>Importantly, inhibition of NF-κB activity also induced expression of myogenin and myosin heavy chain one day after serum withdrawal, and resulted in the formation of multinucleated myotubes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>). This is in contrast to <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts infected with control virus, which up-regulated myogenin and myosin heavy chain to a much lower extent, even 5 days after serum withdrawal (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>, DM5). Additionally we examined the fusion index of myotubes of control and IκBα-SR expressing <italic toggle="yes">MyoD-/-</italic> cells at days 3 and 5 after serum withdrawal. Overexpression of IκBα-SR led to a significantly increased fusion index as well as to more differentiation in general (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>).</p><p>It is interesting to note that IκBαSR-expressing <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> cells up-regulate expression of Myf5 during proliferation and early differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>). Increased expression of Myf5 may compensate for the lack of MyoD, and may be responsible for the induction of differentiation specific genes, such as myogenin and myosin heavy chain, after cell-cycle withdrawal. This is consistent with the fact that embryonic and fetal skeletal muscle development is able to occur in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Finding the specific MyoD-regulated gene product that links cell-cycle withdrawal and terminal myogenic differentiation has been hitherto elusive. In this study, we demonstrate that continued proliferation and inhibition of differentiation in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts is due to persistent nuclear localization of RelA/p65. Expression of a non-phosphorylatable mutant of IκBα (IκBα-SR), which induces cytoplasmic retention of RelA/p65, down-regulated expression of cyclin D1 in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts, and resulted in the formation of multinucleated myotubes. Therefore, inhibition of RelA/p65 activation was able to substitute for MyoD expression during myogenic differentiation. Taken together, this indicates that RelA/p65 provides the link between MyoD-induced cell-cycle withdrawal and differentiation.</p><p>MyoD is postulated to initiate expression of p21 and p57, inhibitors of cdk2 and cdk1 kinase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Moreover, mice lacking <italic toggle="yes">p21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">p57</italic> are phenotypically similar to <italic toggle="yes">myogenin</italic> knockout mice, in that they lack differentiated myofibers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. These data suggest that myogenic cell-cycle withdrawal and differentiation requires MyoD-dependent induction of cdk inhibitor expression. However, <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts have a similar level of <italic toggle="yes">p21</italic> mRNA as compared to <italic toggle="yes">WT</italic> myoblasts, and mice lacking <italic toggle="yes">p21</italic> display no apparent muscle abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Therefore, we propose that adult satellite cells utilize an alternate or additional mechanism for inducing cell-cycle withdrawal during terminal differentiation: down-regulation of RelA/p65 activity.</p><p>Notably, <italic toggle="yes">MIP-2/CXCL1/GRO-α</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IL-6</italic>, which were upregulated 33-fold and 8-fold, respectively, in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts, are associated with constitutive activation of NF-κB, and promote tumor growth and progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Importantly, <italic toggle="yes">IGFBP-2</italic>, which binds IGFs and specifically inhibits IGF-dependent myogenic cell proliferation, was down-regulated 9.1-fold in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Therefore, in the absence of MyoD, myoblasts are programmed to proliferate as a result of maintaining growth factor signaling. This is consistent with data demonstrating that <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts have an increased propensity for proliferation and self-renewal.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Biglycan</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">thrombospondin 2</italic>, two genes that were up-regulated in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts (73.5-fold and 16.9-fold, respectively), are extracellular matrix components that play important roles in scaffolding and signal transduction during myogenic regeneration. In particular, biglycan binds TGF-β, and plays an important role in mediating TGF-β signaling in responding cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. This is important given that TGF-β inhibits myogenic differentiation and induces expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Taken together, these data strongly suggest that NF-κB regulates expression of genes important for inducing cell proliferation.</p><p>During normal differentiation of myoblasts, NF-κB is relocalized to the cytoplasm and DNA-binding activity decreases within 24 h of serum withdrawal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Differentiation is accelerated in myoblasts expressing a non-phosphorylatable form of IκBα (IκBαSR), which is unable to be degraded, thus inhibiting NF-κB (p65) nuclear localization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Furthermore, these IκBαSR-expressing myoblasts proliferate less rapidly and down-regulate expression of <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D1</italic>. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">IκBα</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) infected with a MyoD-expressing retrovirus maintain NF-κB nuclear localization, resulting in the formation of fewer myotubes that are smaller and incorporate fewer nuclei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Our experiments explain mechanistically why <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic>-null myoblasts display a phenotype similar to that of MyoD-infected <italic toggle="yes">IκBα</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> MEFs.</p><p>During myogenic regeneration, satellite cells are activated and proliferate prior to initiating differentiation. Increased numbers of satellite cells and a deficient muscle regenerative process in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mice suggest that in the absence of MyoD, satellite cells have an increased propensity for self-renewal rather than differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. In light of the data presented here, we conclude that RelA/p65 plays an important role during the myoblast to myotube transition during adult myogenesis. Indeed, treatment of <italic toggle="yes">mdx</italic> mice with a cell permeable peptide inhibitor of IKK, which specifically inhibits NF-κB activity, restores regeneration, as evidenced by a greater number of newly formed myofibers, and increased muscle tetanic force [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>].</p><p>Failure to induce myogenic differentiation is also illustrated in rhabdomyosarcoma (RDS), one the most common childhood solid tumors. RDS is characterized by inhibition of MyoD activity and concomitant failure to withdraw from the cell cycle and differentiate. This study suggests that loss of MyoD activity in RDS cells may cause aberrant nuclear localization of NF-κB, resulting in sustained cyclin D1 expression. As such, inhibiting IKK and stabilizing IκBα may play a valuable role in inhibiting proliferation and inducing differentiation in RDS cells.</p><p>During myogenesis, cytoplasmic re-localization of RelA/p65 after mitogen withdrawal plays a key role for down-regulating <italic toggle="yes">cyclin D</italic> expression, inducing cell-cycle withdrawal and activating differentiation-specific gene expression. Therefore, the regulation of NF-κB is essential in the induction of myogenic differentiation. Our experiments define the mechanistic link between MyoD and NF-κB that acts to couple cell-cycle withdrawal to terminal differentiation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We have demonstrated that NF-κB, a key regulator of cell-cycle withdrawal and differentiation, aberrantly maintains nuclear localization and transcriptional activity in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts. Cyclin D is consequently maintained during serum withdrawal, inhibiting progression through myogenic differentiation. Sustained nuclear localization of cyclin E, and a concomitant increase in cdk2 activity maintains S-phase entry in <italic toggle="yes">MyoD</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> myoblasts even in the absence of mitogens. Forced expression of IκBαSR, a non-degradable mutant of IκBα, rescued the deficit indicating that inhibition of NF-κB is sufficient to induce terminal myogenic differentiation. Therefore, MyoD-induced cytoplasmic relocalization of NF-κB is an essential step in linking cell-cycle withdrawal to terminal differentiation.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>bHLH, Basic helix-loop-helix; BrdU, Bromodeoxyuridine; FACS, Fluorescence activated cell sorting; IKK, IκB kinase; MEF, Mouse embryonic fibroblast; MRF, Myogenic regulatory factors; MyHC, Myosin heavy chain; NLS, Nuclear localization sequence; WT, Wild type; siRNA, Small interfering RNA.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>MHP and NB carried out the experiments and drafted the manuscript. BAJ and JM carried out the rescue experiments. JI performed the microarray experiment. DG provided essential reagents and participated in the design and coordination of the study. MAR conceived of the study, and participated in its design and coordination and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Mark Gillespie for critical reading of the manuscript. MAR holds the Canada Research Chair in Molecular Genetics and is an International Research Scholar of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. This work was supported by grants to MAR from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Muscular Dystrophy Association, the National Institutes of Health, and the Canada Research Chair Program, and by grants to DG from the National Institutes of Health.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Shared principles in NF-kappaB signalling</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18267068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2008.01.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>The NF-kappaB and I kappa B proteins: new discoveries and insights</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8717528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.14.1.649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Neriah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Phosphorylation meets ubiquitination: the control of NF-[kappa]B activity</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10837071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.18.1.621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skaug</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><article-title>The role of ubiquitin in NF-kappaB regulatory pathways</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2009</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.biochem.78.070907.102750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Looking back to the embryo: defining transcriptional networks in adult myogenesis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12838342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrg1109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnegelsberg</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>MyoD or Myf-5 is required for the formation of skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8269513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(93)90621-v</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Targeted inactivation of the muscle regulatory gene Myf-5 results in abnormal rib development and perinatal death</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1423602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90507-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asakura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Muscle satellite cells are multipotential stem cells that exhibit myogenic, osteogenic, and adipogenic differentiation</article-title><source>Differentiation</source><year>2001</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11776477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1432-0436.2001.680412.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabourin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girgis-Gabardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asakura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Reduced differentiation potential of primary MyoD-/- myogenic cells derived from adult skeletal muscle</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10037786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.144.4.631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2132931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yablonka-Reuveni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Primig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natanson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The transition from proliferation to differentiation is delayed in satellite cells from mice lacking MyoD</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/dbio.1999.9284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5027208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelison</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olwin</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><article-title>MyoD(-/-) satellite cells in single-fiber culture are differentiation defective and MRF4 deficient</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10926754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/dbio.2000.9682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albanese</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reuther</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestell</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>NF-kappaB controls cell growth and differentiation through transcriptional regulation of cyclin D1</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5785</fpage><lpage>5799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10409765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.19.8.5785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC84428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>NF-kappaB signalling: a tale of two pathways in skeletal myogenesis</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20393192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/physrev.00040.2009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><article-title>NF-kappaB-induced loss of MyoD messenger RNA: possible role in muscle decay and cachexia [see comments]</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>2363</fpage><lpage>2366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11009425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.289.5488.2363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Didonato</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>Assaying for I kappa B kinase activity</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2000</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10914035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0076-6879(00)22038-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asakura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>MyoD induces myogenic differentiation through cooperation of its NH2- and COOH-terminal regions</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16275751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.200502101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2171269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladner</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caligiuri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>Tumor necrosis factor-regulated biphasic activation of NF-kappa B is required for cytokine-induced loss of skeletal muscle gene products</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>2294</fpage><lpage>2303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12431991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M207129200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladner</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carathers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollenbach</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttridge</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>IKK/NF-kappaB regulates skeletal myogenesis via a signalling switch to inhibit differentiation and promote mitochondrial biogenesis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18299349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.200707179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2265568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harbour</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dei Santi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Postigo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><article-title>Cdk phosphorylation triggers sequential intramolecular interactions that progressively block Rb functions as cells move through G1</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81519-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sardet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of cyclin E transcription by E2Fs and retinoblastoma protein</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8649818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whoriskey</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicinski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Rescue of cyclin D1 deficiency by knockin cyclin E</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10380928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)80788-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohtz</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><article-title>Positive and negative regulation of D-type cyclin expression in skeletal myoblasts by basic fibroblast growth factor and transforming growth factor beta. A role for cyclin D1 in control of myoblast differentiation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>4093</fpage><lpage>4100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7876159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.270.8.4093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skapek</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><article-title>Inhibition of myogenic differentiation in proliferating myoblasts by cyclin D1-dependent kinase [see comments]</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7863328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.7863328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skapek</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novitch</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><article-title>Cyclin-mediated inhibition of muscle gene expression via a mechanism that is independent of pRB hyperphosphorylation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>7043</fpage><lpage>7053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8943359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.16.12.7043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC231707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halevy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novitch</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skapek</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><article-title>Correlation of terminal cell cycle arrest of skeletal muscle with induction of p21 by MyoD</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>1018</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7863327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.7863327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rawls</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sands</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><article-title>p53-independent expression of p21Cip1 in muscle and other terminally differentiating cells [see comments]</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7863329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.7863329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Figliola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maione</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>MyoD induces the expression of p57Kip2 in cells lacking p21Cip1/Waf1: overlapping and distinct functions of the two cdk inhibitors</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15254975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcp.20044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><article-title>p21(CIP1) and p57(KIP2) control muscle differentiation at the myogenin step</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9925645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.13.2.213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC316389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Mice lacking p21CIP1/WAF1 undergo normal development, but are defective in G1 checkpoint control</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7664346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90039-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><article-title>Skeletal muscle cytokines: regulation by pathogen-associated molecules and catabolic hormones</article-title><source>Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.mco.0000165003.16578.2d</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busby</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemmons</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotwein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>A highly conserved insulin-like growth factor-binding protein (IGFBP-5) is expressed during myoblast differentiation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>22305</fpage><lpage>22312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7693664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewton</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coolican</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chernausek</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Florini</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>Modulation of insulin-like growth factor actions in L6A1 myoblasts by insulin-like growth factor binding protein (IGFBP)-4 and IGFBP-5: a dual role for IGFBP-5</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4652(199810)177:1&lt;47::AID-JCP5&gt;3.0.CO;2-E</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewton</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Florini</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><article-title>IGF binding proteins-4, -5 and −6 may play specialized roles during L6 myoblast proliferation and differentiation</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>1995</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7537792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1677/joe.0.1440539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotwein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Rapid activation of insulin-like growth factor binding protein-5 gene transcription during myoblast differentiation</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7476973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/mend.9.7.7476973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Florini</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewton</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magri</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangiacapra</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><article-title>IGFs and muscle differentiation</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8184742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-4615-2988-0_31</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Droguett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabello-Verrugio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riquelme</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Extracellular proteoglycans modify TGF-beta bio-availability attenuating its signalling during skeletal muscle differentiation</article-title><source>Matrix Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16766169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.matbio.2006.04.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jester</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funderburgh</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saika</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roughley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><article-title>Excess biglycan causes eyelid malformation by perturbing muscle development and TGF-alpha signalling</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2876305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Megeney</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kablar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>MyoD is required for myogenic stem cell function in adult skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8675005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.10.10.1173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalta</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bupha-Intr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carathers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahenk</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>IKK/NF-kB signalling interplay in macrophages and myofibers promotes muscle degeneration in Duchenne muscular dystrophy</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2007</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17380205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI30556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1821069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>