
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">7804127</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International journal of pharmaceutics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0378-5173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1873-3476</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3573139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3573139.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3573139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3573139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS388646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22633904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2012.05.025</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS388646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA388646</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of Choroidal Neovascularization and Biodegradable Polymeric Particle Size on Transscleral Sustained Delivery of Triamcinolone Acetonide</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names initials="RS">Rajendra S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">¶</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names initials="P">Puneet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN2" ref-type="author-notes">¶</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelhauser</surname><given-names initials="HF">Henry F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names initials="UB">Uday B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Departments of Pharmaceutical Sciences and Ophthalmology University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Emory Eye Center, Emory University, Atlanta, GA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Uday B. Kompella, Ph.D., Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, 12850 E. Montview Blvd., Aurora, CO 80045, Phone: (303) 724 4028, Fax: (303) 724-4666, <email>uday.kompella@ucdenver.edu</email></corresp><fn id="FN2" fn-type="equal"><label>¶</label><p>Rajendra S Kadam and Puneet Tyagi contributed equally to the work presented here and should therefore be regarded as equivalent authors</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>434</volume><issue>1-2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">219594</issue-id><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>13</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>09</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-19 20:25:42.303"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms388646.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="Fed Regist" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6283784"><article-title>Findings of Research Misconduct</article-title><volume>83</volume><issue>234</issue><date><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><fpage>62875</fpage><lpage>62875</lpage><source>Federal Register</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6283784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30556543</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Purpose</title><p id="P2">One objective of this study was to determine whether polymeric nanoparticles and/or microparticles sustain transscleral choroidal and retinal delivery of triamcinolone acetonide (TA) for two months in therapeutically effective concentrations after single periocular administration. Another objective of this study was to assess the influence of choroidal neovascularization on transscleral delivery of TA.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Methods</title><p id="P3">Polymeric nano- and micro-particles of TA were prepared by o/w emulsion- solvent evaporation method using poly-L-lactide (PLA). Particles were characterized for drug loading, size, surface morphology, and the in vitro drug release profile. Choroidal neovascularization (CNV) was induced in brown Norway (BN) rats using a 532 nm diode argon laser and the CNV induction was assessed using fluorescein angiography. In vivo delivery was assessed in control and CNV induced rats at 2 months after periocular injection of TA loaded nano- or micro-particle suspension, or plain TA suspension in PBS (pH7.4). Ocular tissue levels of TA were estimated using LC-MS/MS following liquid-liquid extraction of drug from tissue samples. Nile red loaded microparticles entrapped in periocular tissue at the end of the study were visualized using scanning electron microscopy and confocal microscopy. Inhibitory effect of TA on VEGF secretion was evaluated in ARPE-19 cells.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P4">Triamcinolone acetonide-PLA nano- (551 nm) and micro-particles (2090 nm), with 14.7 and 29.5 % drug loading, respectively, sustained in vitro TA release for about 45 and 120 days. After subconjunctival injection, microparticles were able to sustain the delivery in all intraocular tissues for 2 months; whereas no drug levels were detected for TA loaded nanoparticles and plain suspension of TA. Intraocular delivery of TA from microparticles was higher in CNV induced rats when compared to control rats. Significant amount of microparticles remained in periocular tissue at 2 months after injection, and maintained spherical shape. TA decreased VEGF secretion by 50 % at 0.07μM. At the end of the in vivo study, choroid-RPE and retina TA levels in CNV induced rats were 16- and 5-fold higher than the IC<sub>50</sub> for VEGF secretion.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P5">Single periocular injection of polymeric microparticles but not nanoparticles sustained effective levels of TA in choroid-RPE and retina for 2 months, with the TA delivery being greater in CNV induced rats than the control rats.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Microparticles</kwd><kwd>Nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>Triamcinolone Acetonide</kwd><kwd>Choroidal Neovascularization</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="United States">National Eye Institute : NEI</funding-source><award-id>R01 EY018940 || EY</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="United States">National Eye Institute : NEI</funding-source><award-id>R01 EY017533 || EY</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S5"><title>1.0 INTRODUCTION</title><p id="P6">Age related macular degeneration (AMD) is a leading cause of blindness amongst the elderly population. In the United States alone, more than 8 million people suffer from the AMD and this number is expected to increase by 50% by 2020(<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">Jager et al., 2008</xref>). AMD is a chronic, multifactorial, life-long ocular disease. Available medical treatment helps to avoid further progression of the disease, but cannot cure the disease and hence, chronic administration of pharmaceutical therapy is necessary(<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">Nowak, 2006</xref>). Current gold standard for the treatment of the wet or neovascular form of AMD is ranibizumab, an antibody fragment that binds vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF). Further, bevacizumab, a full length VEGF antibody and triamcinolone acetonide (TA), a corticosteroid, are being used off-label to treat wet AMD (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">Nowak and Bienias, 2007</xref>).</p><p id="P7">In AMD, therapeutic agents need to reach the retina and choroid-retinal pigmented epithelium (RPE) to exert their action. Drug delivery to the posterior ocular tissues by conventional topical or systemic routes is limited by extraocular epithelial barriers (conjunctival and corneal epithelium) and the blood-tissue barriers (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">Sunkara G and Kompella UB, 2003</xref>). Drug delivery to the posterior segment of the eye is most efficiently achieved by local, ocular routes of administration including intravitreal, subretinal, suprachoroidal, and periocular injections(<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Raghava et al., 2004</xref>). However, intravitreal and subretinal routes are highly invasive to the retina and repeated injections have a high risk of serious complications including retinal detachment and endophthalmitis(<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">Shah et al., 2011</xref>). On the other hand, periocular injections, which include subconjunctival, subtenon, peribulbar, retrobulbar, and posterior juxtascleral injections, are generally considered safer, as these are more peripheral to the eye(<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">Raghava et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Triamcinolone acetonide is the most commonly used off-label steroid treatment for AMD and vitreoretinal disorders(<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">Jonas et al., 2002</xref>). Vitreal half-life of TA after intravitreal injection of 0.3 mg drug suspension in a vitrectomized and nonvitrectomized rabbits is 1.57 days and 2.89 days respectively (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Chin et al., 2005</xref>). In order to maintain the effective concentration of TA in the target tissue for prolonged periods, the patient must be administered a high initial dose or receive frequent injections. Higher intravitreal concentration of TA is associated with various side effects including blurred vision, cataract, elevated intraocular pressure, and retinal cell damage (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">Ozkiris and Erkilic, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">Schlichtenbrede et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, the most common approach for achieving therapeutic levels of TA in the target tissue is to administer frequent intravitreal injections, which as described above increases the risk for injection-related complications. An alternative to intravitreal injection is periocular injection of TA, which is a less invasive and a safer option for delivery of TA to the choroid-RPE and retina at effective concentrations. The major problem with periocular injection of TA suspension is the very short half-life of TA in the periocular space because of conjunctival lymphatic and blood clearance(<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2006</xref>). Cheruvu et al. showed that the choroid-RPE half-life of celecoxib, a drug that is less soluble than TA, is 3.7 hr after subconjunctival injection of celecoxib suspension in Brown Norway rats (BN)(<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Cheruvu et al., 2008</xref>). Similar to intravitreal injection, patients treated with periocular injections must be administered multiple injections in order to maintain effective concentrations, which is inconvenient and costly. Development of sustained delivery systems can maintain the effective drug levels for prolonged period of time to effectively reduce the dosing frequency(<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">Kompella et al., 2010</xref>). Drug encapsulated in biodegradable polymeric nano- and micro-particles with properly designed vehicles are clinically viable options for the sustained delivery of drug molecules administered by periocular injection. A previous report from our laboratory showed the effectiveness of subconjunctivally injected celecoxib-PLGA microparticles for two months in a diabetic retinopathy model(<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Amrite et al., 2006</xref>). Further, the transccleral delivery of therapeutic agents to the posterior ocular tissues can be higher in AMD patients due to compromised ocular barriers and altered clearance. Significant reduction in choroidal blood flow in AMD patients has been previously reported(<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Grunwald et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Grunwald et al., 2005</xref>). Additionally, growth of new choroidal vessels into and through the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) or subretinal space can result in loss of the RPE barrier integrity (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">Dobi et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2011</xref>), which can lead to enhanced transscleral delivery of therapeutic agents. Previously we observed enhanced delivery of celecoxib to the choroid and retina in a diabetic rat as compared to control rats(<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Cheruvu et al., 2009</xref>). No reports are currently available regarding delivery of therapeutic agents in choroidal neovascularization.</p><p id="P9">Based on all the above reasoning, the main objective of this study was to determine the influence of choroidal neovascularization (CNV) on transscleral delivery of TA. Another objective of this study was to develop polymeric, biodegradable nano- and micro-particles and assess their ability to sustain TA delivery to choroid-RPE and retina in therapeutically effective concentrations for at least two months</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>2.0 MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="S7"><title>2.1 Materials</title><p id="P10">Poly (L-lactide) (PLA), with inherent viscosity of 0.95–1.20 dL/gm, (product No. B6002-2P) was purchased from Birmingham Polymers (Pelham, AL). Triamcinolone acetonide was purchased from Spectrum Chemical Mfg. Corp (New Brunswick, NJ). Dichloromethane, poly (vinyl alcohol) of Mw 30000 – 70000, acetonitrile, and sodium azide were purchased from Sigma Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). All other chemicals and reagents used in this study were of analytical reagent grade.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>2.2 Preparation of triamcinolone acetonide loaded nanoparticles and microparticles</title><p id="P11">Nanoparticles were prepared by an o/w emulsion-solvent evaporation method. PLA polymer (200 mg) was dissolved in 5 ml dichloromethane and mixed with 1 ml dichloromethane containing TA (100 mg) and Nile red (0.5 mg). The drug polymer solution was transferred to 30 ml of cold 2% w/v aqueous polyvinyl alcohol solution in an ice bath under sonication (Misonix Sonicator 3000, Farmingdale, NY) at 3 W for 2 minutes to prepare an o/w emulsion. The o/w emulsion was transferred to 100 ml chilled 2% w/v aqueous polyvinyl alcohol solution in an ice bath under sonication at 12–15 W for 2 minutes to stabilize the emulsion. The emulsion was stirred for 3 hours at room temperature using a magnetic stirrer to harden the nanoparticles. The hardened nanoparticles were then centrifuged for 20 min at 27000 g using an ultracentrifuge. The nanoparticle pellet was washed twice with 150 ml distilled water. The final pellet was dispersed in 10 ml double distilled water and lyophilized in a Labconco freeze dryer (Labconco Corporation, Kansas City, MO) over 24 hours.</p><p id="P12">TA loaded microparticles were also prepared by o/w emulsion-solvent evaporation method. PLA polymer (200 mg) was dissolved in 5 ml of dichloromethane. TA (100 mg) and 1 ml of Nile red solution (0.5 mg/ml solution in dichloromethane) were dissolved in the above polymer solution. The drug polymer dispersion was transferred to 30 ml of 2% w/v aqueous polyvinyl alcohol solution under homogenization at 10,000 rpm for 2 minutes using a Virtishear Cyclone® Homogenizer. The above o/w emulsion was further transferred to 100 ml of 2% w/v aqueous polyvinyl alcohol solution under homogenization at 10,000 rpm for 5 minutes using a Virtishear Cyclone® Homogenizer. The final emulsion was stirred for 3 hours using a magnetic stirrer. The microparticles thus formed were centrifuged at 10,000 g for 20 minutes. The microparticle pellet obtained after centrifugation was washed twice with 150 ml distilled water. The final microparticle pellet was redispersed in 10 ml double distilled water and lyophilized in a Labconco freeze dryer (Labconco Corporation, Kansas City, MO) over 24 hours.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>2.3 Characterization of nanoparticles and microparticles</title><p id="P13">Lyophilized particles (1 mg) were resuspended in 5 ml of filtered deionized water to measure particle size and size distribution. Nanosizer (Malvern Inc., Westborough, MA) was used to evaluate particle size and size distribution. Surface morphology was studied with a scanning electron microscope (JSM-6510, Jeol USA, Inc., CA) after mounting particles on aluminum stubs and coating with a layer of gold using a sputter Coater (Anatech USA, CA). TA and Nile red content in the particles was measured by dissolving 1 mg of lyophilized TA loaded particles in 2 ml chloroform, followed by vortexing (Vortex Genie, Scientific Industries, Bohemia, NY) for 1 hour at room temperature. TA and Nile red content was measured in chloroform using UV spectrophotometry (238 nm and 520 nm for TA and Nile red, respectively). Separate standard curves for TA and Nile red were prepared by dissolving a known amount of TA or Nile red in chloroform, followed by serial dilutions. All measurements were done in triplicates. The % drug loading and entrapment efficiency in particles were determined using following formulas.</p><disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>Drug</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mtext>Loading</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">mass</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">drug</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">nanoparticles</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">mass</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">nanoparticles</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>Encapsulation</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mtext>Efficiency</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Experimental</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">drug</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">loading</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Theoretical</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">drug</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">loading</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></sec><sec id="S10"><title>2.4 In vitro drug release study</title><p id="P14">Two milligrams of drug loaded particles were dispersed in 1 ml of pH 7.4 phosphate buffered saline (PBS). The particle dispersion was transferred into a dialysis membrane bag (7Spectra/por<sup>®</sup>, Spectrum Laboratories, CA) with a molecular weight cut off of 10000 Da. The dialysis bag was suspended in 10 ml pH 7.4 PBS containing 0.05 % w/v sodium azide, maintained at 37 °C in a shaker incubator (Max Q 4000 Shaker, Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA). Two ml of dissolution medium was withdrawn at various intervals and replaced with drug-free dissolution medium maintained at 37 °C. The amount of drug released in the dissolution medium at each time interval was analyzed by UV spectrophotometer at 238 nm. All incubations were done in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>2.5 Animals</title><p id="P15">Animal studies were conducted in accordance with ARVO Statement for the Use of Animals in Ophthalmic and Vision Research and guidelines by animal care committee of University of Colorado Denver. Adult male Brown Norway rats (150–180 g) were purchased from Harlan Sprague Dawley Inc. (Indianapolis, IN, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>2.6 Induction and assessment of CNV</title><p id="P16">Rats were anesthetized using an intraperitoneal injection of 50 mg/kg ketamine and 10 mg/kg xylazine mixture. Pupils were dilated by topical administration of 1% tropicamide solution. A glass cover slip with a drop of 2.5% hypromellose solution was used to visualize the fundus of the rat. Eight laser spots (100 μm, 150 mW, 100 ms) concentric with the optic nerve were placed in the right eye of each rat using a 532 nm diode laser (Oculight Glx; Iridex Inc., Mountain View, CA, USA) and a slit lamp (Zeiss slit lamp 30SL; Carl Zeiss Meditec Inc., Dublin, CA, USA). Left eye was used as a control for each animal. Rats showing hemorrhage upon laser administration were excluded from the study. The Bruch’s membrane breakage was confirmed using bubble formation as the end point. CNV lesions were allowed to develop for 14 days after induction of laser burns for tissue distribution studies. Development of CNV was studied using a Fundus camera (Genesis Df, Kowa Optimed, CA) after intravenous injection of 1% sodium fluorescein solution (250 μl)in PBS pH 7.4.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>2.7 In vivo tissue distribution</title><p id="P17">In vivo tissue distribution of TA loaded polymeric nano- or micro-particle dispersions and TA suspension was carried out in normal and CNV induced BN rats. Rats were anesthetized with intraperitoneal injection of 50 mg/kg ketamine and 10 mg/kg xylazine. TA loaded nanoparticle or microparticle dispersion or TA suspension (25 μl containing 150 μg of TA) was administered into the posterior subconjunctival space of right eye (ipsilateral) using a 30-gauge needle (n =4). The left eye was untreated. The animals were allowed to recover from anesthesia, and water and food were provided ad libitum and kept for 2 months. At the end of 2 months, the animals were euthanized by intraperitoneal injection of sodium pentobarbital (250 mg/kg). Eyes and periocular tissues were collected and immediately frozen using a mixture of isopentane and dry ice. Tissues were stored at −80 °C until analysis. Ocular tissues were separated by dissection of the eye in frozen condition on a ceramic tile placed above dry ice isopentane bath. Drug levels were measured in sclera, choroid-RPE, retina, vitreous, lens, cornea, iris-ciliary body, and periocular tissue by an LC-MS/MS method.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>2.8 Assessment of nanoparticles and microparticles entrapped in rat periocular tissue</title><p id="P18">Microparticles entrapped in periocular tissues were visualized using confocal microscopy. For confocal microscopy, tissues were placed on a glass slide and a drop of Supermount mounting medium was added. A cover slip was placed on the tissue and air dried for 2 hours before assessment using Nikon C1si® confocal microscope. Confocal microscopy indicated the presence of Nile red dye in periocular tissues. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) was used to further confirm that particles were present in the tissue. For SEM, tissues were mounted on aluminum stubs and coated with a layer of gold using a sputter Coater (Anatech USA, CA). The morphology was observed with JSM-6510 scanning electron microscope (Jeol USA, Inc., CA) at an accelerating voltage of 5.0 kV.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>2.9 VEGF Secretion Assay</title><p id="P19">Inhibitory effect of TA on VEGF secretion in ARPE-19 cells was evaluated as per previously described methods (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Kompella et al., 2003</xref>). Briefly, 4000 cells were seeded per well in a 96-well plate and cultured for 24 hours until 70 to 80 % confluency. After 24 hours, the culture medium was replaced with serum free medium and cells were allowed to remain in quiescence for 12 hours before drug treatment. Cells were treated with 50 nM to 50 μM of TA for 12 hours. At the end of 12 hours, the medium was collected and the secreted VEGF was quantified using an ELISA kit capable of detecting VEGF<sub>165</sub> and VEGF<sub>121</sub> isoforms (Research Diagnostic, Inc., Flanders, NJ).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>2.10 Tissue sample processing</title><p id="P20">TA content in rat ocular tissues was measured after extraction of drugs from tissues by liquid-liquid extraction. Briefly, the weighed amount of ocular tissues were mixed with 500 μl of PBS (pH 7.4) containing and 250 ng/mL budesonide (internal standard) in 2 ml microcentrifuge tube, vortexed for 10 minutes, and then homogenized using a hand homogenizer in an ice bath. Dichloromethane (1.5 ml) was added to this homogenate and vortexed for 10 minutes using a multitube vortexer (VWR LabShop, Batavia, IL). The organic layer was separated by centrifugation at 10,000 g for 10 minutes. Separated organic layer was transferred into clean glass tubes and evaporated under nitrogen stream (Multi-Evap; Organomation, Berlin, MA) at 40 °C. The residue after evaporation was reconstituted with 250 μl of acetonitrile: water (75: 25 v/v) and subjected to LC-MS/MS analysis. The liquid-liquid extraction method for extraction of TA from rat ocular tissues was validated to determine the extraction recovery using three different concentrations (low, medium and high) to cover the entire range of expected concentrations of TA in various tissues.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>2.11 LC-MS/MS analysis</title><p id="P21">Ocular tissue levels of TA were measured by means of LC-MS/MS. An API-3000 triple quadrupole mass spectrometer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) coupled with a PerkinElmer series-200 liquid chromatography (Perkin Elmer, Walthm, Massachusetts, USA) system was used for analysis. Analytes were separated on a Sunfire C18 column (2.1 × 50 mm, 5 μm) using 5 mM ammonium formate in water (A) and acetonitrile (B) as mobile phase. A linear gradient elution at a flow rate of 0.25 ml/minute with total run time of 4 minutes was as follows: 60% A (0 – 0.8 minute), 10% A (2.0 – 4.0 minute), and 60% A (5.0–6.0 minute). TA and budesonide (internal standard) were analyzed in positive ionization mode with following multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) transitions: 435 → 415 (TA); 431 → 413 (budesonide).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>2.12 Data Analysis</title><p id="P22">The data obtained for VEGF secretion were fit to sigmoidal inhibitory models with a baseline effect using WinNonlin software (version 1.5; Scientific Consulting, Inc., Cary, NC). Statistical comparisons between two experimental groups were performed using independent samples Student’s t-test. The results were considered statistically significant at P&lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S19"><title>3.0 RESULTS</title><sec id="S20"><title>3.1 Preparation and characterization of nanoparticles and microparticles</title><p id="P23">Triamcinolone acetonide loading was 29.5 and 14.7 % for microparticles and nanoparticles, respectively. Nile red content was 0.33 and 0.41% and for microparticles and nanoparticles, respectively. The particle size for nanoparticles and microparticles was 551 and 2090 nm, respectively. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) was used to study surface morphology. SEM images showed that the particles were spherical in shape with small pores on the surface (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>3.2 In vitro drug release</title><p id="P24">Release of TA from nanoparticles and microparticles was monitored using UV spectrophotometer. The time for complete release of TA from nanoparticles and microparticles was about 45 and 120 days, respectively. Burst release of 6.31 and 4.97 % was observed from nanoparticles and microparticles, respectively (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>3.3 Assessment of CNV</title><p id="P25">CNV development was monitored before laser treatment and 7 days and 14 days after laser treatment with a fundus camera (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Sodium fluorescein leakage was seen to increase with time. In comparison to day 7, fluorescein leakage was more at day 14.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>3.4 In vivo drug delivery</title><p id="P26">In vivo delivery of TA was assessed in control and CNV induced BN rats after subconjunctival injection of nanoparticle or microparticle dispersion in PBS (pH 7.5) and plain TA suspension in PBS. At the end of 2 months post injection, no drug levels were detected in any ocular tissues for nanoparticles or the plain suspension group. TA microparticles sustained the delivery of TA for 2 months post injection in both control and CNV induced rats. As shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, TA levels were highest in periocular tissue (site of injection). For posterior ocular tissue the rank order of drug distribution was in order of; choroid-RPE ≥ sclera&gt; retina &gt; vitreous. TA levels in CNV induced rats were 3.6-, 2.3-, 2.4-, 2.9-, and 1.3- folds higher in sclera, choroid-RPE, retina, vitreous, and periocular tissue respectively than control rats. Differences were statistically significant only for sclera, lens, and iris-ciliary body. Although the TA delivery to choroid-RPE, retina, and vitreous in CNV induced rats not different statistically significant from control rats, the P values were less than 0.12.</p><p id="P27">Significant amount of entrapped microparticles were observed in the periocular tissues of both control and CNV induced rats at the end of 2 months post injection. Microscopic visualization of periocular tissues using scanning electron microscope (SEM) and confocal microscope showed the presence of microparticles in periocular tissues (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Microparticles were loaded with Nile red as a tracer dye, visible in red color in confocal microscopy images (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>3.5 Inhibition of VEGF secretion</title><p id="P28">Triamcinolone acetonide inhibited VEGF secretion from ARPE-19 cells with an IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.07 ± 0.01 μM. Drug effects were evident at concentrations as low as 0.05 μM (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>), with the reduction in VEGF secretion being 33%.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S25"><title>4.0 DISCUSSION</title><p id="P29">This study for the first time shows that the transscleral delivery of TA to the intraocular tissues was higher in CNV induced rats when compared to control animals. Further, we have successfully developed biodegradable polymeric microparticles of TA, which sustained choroidal and retinal delivery for 2 months in therapeutically effective concentration after a single periocular injection. Further, we showed that significant amount of microparticles remain in the periocular space at the end of two months and maintain their spherical shape.</p><p id="P30">To sustain the long term delivery of TA, polymeric nano- and micro-particles were prepared using poly(L-lactide). Pure poly(L-lactide), has degradation half-life of 12 to 16 months(<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Yeo and Park, 2004</xref>). Further, TA is a lipophilic drug molecule and entrapment efficiency of lipophilic drugs is much better in a hydrophobic homopolymer such as PLA than a more hydrophilic copolymer such as PLGA. Herein, we demonstrated that particles made with PLA have 14.7 % drug loading in nanoparticles and 29.5 % drug loading in microparticles (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Microparticles have better drug loading and entrapment efficiency than nanoparticles since they have lower surface-to-volume ratio, which minimizes surface drug that is removed during particle washes(<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">Lecaroz et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Mohanraj VJ and Chen Y, 2006</xref>). For microparticles, entrapment efficiency was 88.5 %, whereas for nanoparticles the entrapment efficiency was 44.1 %, which is significantly lower than microparticles (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Surface morphology of particles showed uniform spherical shapes with small pores on the particle surface. Removal of organic solvent from the particle core results in the formation of honey comb like internal structure and pores on the surface of particles (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">Yeo and Park, 2004</xref>). In vitro release profile showed that microparticles sustained the drug release for longer duration than nanoparticles (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Since nanoparticles are smaller in diameter, their surface area is larger than their volume and hence, the large amount of drug closer to the particle surface results in rapid drug release(<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">Mohanraj VJ and Chen Y, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">Redhead et al., 2001</xref>). Previously, we have also shown that in vitro release of budesonide was faster form PLA nanoparticles than microparticles(<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Kompella et al., 2003</xref>). Although we did not measure the residual dichloromethane content in this study, an earlier study of ours employing similar methods indicated that PLA microparticles have a dichloromethane content of about 1 ppb (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Shelke et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p id="P31">Long term sustained in vivo delivery of TA form polymeric particles was evaluated in BN rats after periocular injection. Previously, we showed that budesonide loaded microparticles sustain the choroidal and retinal delivery for 2 weeks whereas, nanoparticles exhibited detectable drug levels for only 7 days after periocular injections in rats(<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Kompella et al., 2003</xref>). The objective of the current study was to sustain TA delivery for at least 2 months after periocular injection. Herein, we demonstrated that single periocular injection of TA microparticles sustained the posterior segment drug delivery for at least 2 months (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), whereas no drug levels were detected for plain drug suspension and nanoparticles. Our in vivo results were in agreement with the in vitro release profile of TA form nano- and micro-particles, where nearly 100 % of the drug was released within 45 days for nanoparticles and 120 days for microparticles (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Further, a significant amount of microparticles remained at the site of injection even after 2 months, which is expected to sustain the TA delivery for longer periods. Microscopic examination of periocular tissue showed that particles still maintained their spherical shape and were entrapped in the tissue matrix (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref> and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Previously we have shown that PLA microparticles remain in the rabbit vitreous for 3 months after intravitreal injection and maintain its spherical shape and sustain the delivery of hydrophilic drug molecule (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">Shelke et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p id="P32">After subconjunctival injection of TA microparticles, significant amount of drug remained at the site of injection (periocular tissue). Delivery of TA to posterior ocular tissues was in order of choroid-RPE ≥ sclera &gt; retina &gt; vitreous (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). TA levels in choroid-RPE were slightly higher than sclera; even though choroid-RPE comes after sclera for subconjunctival delivery. TA is a lipophilic corticosteroid; significant amount of lipophilic drug molecules preferentially accumulate in choroid-RPE due to melanin binding (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Thakur et al., 2010</xref>). Previously, with subconjunctival injection of corticosteroids and beta-blockers, we observed similar trends of drug distribution to the posterior ocular tissues, with drug levels being higher in choroid-RPE than sclera, retina, and vitreous for lipophilic drugs such as TA (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">Kadam and Kompella, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Thakur et al., 2010</xref>). Significant amount of TA levels were detected in the anterior segment ocular tissues including cornea, aqueous humor and iris-ciliary body. Delivery of drug to the anterior tissue after periocular injection can be partially explained by leak-back of drug through the needle track as well as diffusion across conjunctiva into the tear film (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">Cheruvu et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p id="P33">Another objective of the current study was to evaluate the effect of disease state on intraocular delivery of TA after periocular injection. Previously with a diabetic retinopathy model, we showed that the retinal delivery of celecoxib was 2.0-fold higher in diabetic rats than in control rats(<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Cheruvu et al., 2009</xref>). In the current study, there was more TA delivered to all ocular tissues in the CNV induced rats compared to control rats (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Further, the drug levels in the CNV group at the dosing site were 1.3-fold higher but not significantly different from the control group. One possible reason for the increase in TA delivery in CNV induced rats may be due to compromised ocular barriers and altered delivery or clearance in the choroid-RPE and retina. Various literature reports showed that there is a significant reduction in choroidal blood flow in AMD patients compared to normal healthy subjects(<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">Grunwald et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">Grunwald et al., 2005</xref>). Further, during CNV progression, migration of choroidal endothelial cells in RPE results in disruption of the RPE barrier(<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">Hartnett et al., 2003</xref>), which might increase retinal drug delivery from the periocular site. The combination of reduced blood flow and disruption of ocular barriers may result in higher intraocular delivery of TA in CNV induced rats compared to control rats. Although the TA delivery was higher in CNV induced rats than the control rats, significant differences were only observed with sclera, lens, and iris-ciliary body.</p><p id="P34">To develop the exposure-response relationship between TA delivery to the choroid-RPE and an efficacy parameter related to CNV, we measured the inhibitory effect of TA on VEGF secretion. An elevation in VEGF levels is a key contributor for the development of ocular neovascular diseases such as CNV and diabetic retinopathy (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">Miller, 1997</xref>). Various studies indicated a central role for elevated VEGF in the pathogenesis of CNV ((<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">Spilsbury et al., 2000</xref>) (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">Kwak et al., 2000</xref>)), and it was previously shown that inhibitory effect of TA on choroidal neovascularization can be explained in part by a reduction in VEGF secretion ((<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Tong et al., 2006</xref>)). Our in vitro VEGF secretion assay in ARPE-19 cells showed a very potent inhibitory effect of TA with an IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.07 ± 0.01 μM. This effect is in good agreement with previous published reports. Budesonide and fluocinolone acetonide, other potent corticosteroids showed 43 and 37 % inhibition of VEGF secretion, respectively, in ARPE-19 cells at 0.1 μM (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Ayalasomayajula et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">Kompella et al., 2003</xref>). In our in vivo delivery study, at the end of 2 months, drug levels in the choroid-RPE were 1.14 and 0.48 μM and 0.36 and 0.14 μM in the retina, in CNV and normal rats, respectively. Compared to the IC<sub>50</sub> for VEGF inhibition, these levels were 16- and 7-fold higher in choroid-RPE and 5- and 2-fold higher in retina of CNV and normal rats, respectively, Thus, single periocular injection of TA microparticles can sustain choroid-RPE and retinal drug levels for at least 2 months at therapeutically effective concentrations.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>5.0 CONCLUSION</title><p id="P35">In summary, PLA microparticles are better than nanoparticles in sustaining posterior segment delivery of TA after periocular injection. Spherical microparticles remained entrapped in the tissue matrix at the site of injection after 2 months. Delivery of TA is significantly higher in CNV induced rats than control rats, and polymeric microparticles maintain therapeutic concentrations of TA in choroid-RPE and retina for at least 2 months after a single periocular injection.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S27"><p>This work was supported by NIH grants EY017045 (through Emory University), EY018940, and EY017533.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN3"><p content-type="publisher-disclaimer">This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amrite</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayalasomayajula</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheruvu</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Single periocular injection of celecoxib-PLGA microparticles inhibits diabetes-induced elevations in retinal PGE2, VEGF, and vascular leakage</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.05-0531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3324981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayalasomayajula</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Fluocinolone inhibits VEGF expression via glucocorticoid receptor in human retinal pigment epithelial (ARPE-19) cells and TNF-alpha-induced angiogenesis in chick chorioallantoic membrane (CAM)</article-title><source>J Ocul Pharmacol Ther</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19284324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/jop.2008.0090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheruvu</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amrite</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Effect of eye pigmentation on transscleral drug delivery</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18172110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.07-0214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3324932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheruvu</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amrite</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Effect of diabetes on transscleral delivery of celecoxib</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11095-008-9757-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Difference in clearance of intravitreal triamcinolone acetonide between vitrectomized and nonvitrectomized eyes</article-title><source>Retina</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00006982-200507000-00002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobi</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puliafito</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Destro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>A new model of experimental choroidal neovascularization in the rat</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2464985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archopht.1989.01070010270035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Influence of Dll4 via HIF-1alpha-VEGF signaling on the angiogenesis of choroidal neovascularization under hypoxic conditions</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>e18481</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21526177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0018481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3079714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hariprasad</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DuPont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brucker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Foveolar choroidal blood flow in age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9477998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metelitsina</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Reduced foveolar choroidal blood flow in eyes with increasing AMD severity</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.04-1050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartnett</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McColm</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovejoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Amore</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Retinal pigment epithelium and endothelial cell interaction causes retinal pigment epithelial barrier dysfunction via a soluble VEGF-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>Exp Eye Res</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14550401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0014-4835(03)00189-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mieler</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>358</volume><fpage>2606</fpage><lpage>2617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMra0801537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreissig</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degenring</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Repeated intravitreal injections of triamcinolone acetonide as treatment of progressive exudative age-related macular degeneration</article-title><source>Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source><volume>240</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12530461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00417-002-0547-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Influence of lipophilicity on drug partitioning into sclera, choroid-retinal pigment epithelium, retina, trabecular meshwork, and optic nerve</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><volume>332</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/jpet.109.161570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2835449</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4293444"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6283784"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayalasomayajula</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Subconjunctival nano- and microparticles sustain retinal delivery of budesonide, a corticosteroid capable of inhibiting VEGF expression</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>1192</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12601049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.02-0791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Recent advances in ophthalmic drug delivery</article-title><source>Ther Deliv</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21399724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4155/TDE.10.40</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3051398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campochiaro</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>VEGF is major stimulator in model of choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>3158</fpage><lpage>3164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecaroz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamazo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renedo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco-Prieto</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Biodegradable micro- and nanoparticles as long-term delivery vehicles for gentamicin</article-title><source>J Microencapsul</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17123922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/02652040600946886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor and ocular neovascularization</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><volume>151</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9212726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1857918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohanraj</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Nanoparticles – A Review</article-title><source>Tropical Journal of Pharmaceutical Research</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>573</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD): pathogenesis and therapy</article-title><source>Pharmacol Rep</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bienias</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD): etiopathogenesis and therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>Postepy Hig Med Dosw (Online)</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozkiris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erkilic</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Complications of intravitreal injection of triamcinolone acetonide</article-title><source>Can J Ophthalmol</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15825532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0008-4182(05)80119-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Periocular routes for retinal drug delivery</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Deliv</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16296723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1517/17425247.1.1.99</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11864216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Redhead</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Illum</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Drug delivery in poly(lactide-co-glycolide) nanoparticles surface modified with poloxamer 407 and poloxamine 908: in vitro characterisation and in vivo evaluation</article-title><source>J Control Release</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11182205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0168-3659(00)00367-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galban</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bungay</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Csaky</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>A rabbit model for assessing the ocular barriers to the transscleral delivery of triamcinolone acetonide</article-title><source>Exp Eye Res</source><volume>82</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.exer.2005.08.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlichtenbrede</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rensch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vom Hagen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Toxicity assessment of intravitreal triamcinolone and bevacizumab in a retinal explant mouse model using two-photon microscopy</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>5880</fpage><lpage>5887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19578025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1167/iovs.08-3078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vander</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Outcomes and risk factors associated with endophthalmitis after intravitreal injection of anti-vascular endothelial growth factor agents</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>2028</fpage><lpage>2034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ophtha.2011.02.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Intravitreal poly(L-lactide) microparticles sustain retinal and choroidal delivery of TG-0054, a hydrophilic drug intended for neovascular diseases</article-title><source>Drug Deliv and Transl Res</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22888471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13346-010-0009-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3416885</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5590050"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spilsbury</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakoczy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Overexpression of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in the retinal pigment epithelium leads to the development of choroidal neovascularization</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10880384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)64525-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1850220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunkara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Membrane transport processes in the eye</article-title><source>Ophthalmic drug Delivery Systems</source><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kompella</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Influence of drug solubility and lipophilicity on transscleral retinal delivery of six corticosteroids</article-title><source>Drug Metab Dispos</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21346004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/dmd.110.037408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3082374</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4293399"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Effects of triamcinolone on the expression of VEGF and PEDF in human retinal pigment epithelial and human umbilical vein endothelial cells</article-title><source>Mol Vis</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Control of encapsulation efficiency and initial burst in polymeric microparticle systems</article-title><source>Arch Pharm Res</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14969330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF02980037</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Size, surface morphology, and in vitro release profile of triamcinolone acetonide loaded poly-L-lactide nanoparticles and microparticles. Triamcinolone acetonide microparticles sustained in vitro release for more than 120 days whereas nanoparticles released the entire drug within 45 days.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Development of CNV lesions occurred within 14 days after laser burn in BN rats. Representative fluorescein angiography images assessing CNV induction in Brown Norway rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Single periocular injection of triamcinolone acetonide microparticles sustain the intraocular delivery of TA for 2 months. Tissue distribution of TA in BN rat ocular tissues at the end of 2 months after periocular injection of TA microparticles at a dose equivalent to 150 μg of TA/animal. TA levels in ocular tissues were below the limit of detection (2.5 ng/ml) for the nanoparticle and plain drug suspension groups. Data represents mean ± SD for N=4. * Significantly different from control at P ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Assessment of entrapped microparticles in periocular tissues (site of injection) in BN rats 2 months post injection. Pictures were obtained using a scanning electron microscope (JEOL) at 5,000X magnifications. Arrowhead shows the entrapped microparticles in periocular tissue of BN rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f4.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Confocal microscopy images of periocular tissue were obtained from control and microparticles injected rats. Pictures were obtained using confocal microscope (Nikon C1 si®) set at 20X magnification. Nile red was added as tracer dye in microparticles, which appears red under the microscope.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Triamcinolone acetonide inhibits the VEGF secretion in ARPE-19 cells. Data represents mean ± SD for N= 6. The IC<sub>50</sub> values were calculated using the inhibitory sigmoid <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>max model with baseline effects.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms388646f6.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Physicochemical characterization of triamcinolone acetonide loaded poly-L-lactide nanoparticles and microparticles.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Batch</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Particle size (nm)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polydispersity index</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nile red loading (% w/w)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triamcinolone acetonide loading (% w/w)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triamcinolone acetonide encapsulation efficiency (%w/w)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microparticles</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2090 ± 302.7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043 ± 0.030</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 ± 0.027</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 ± 2.82</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.5 ± 6.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nanoparticles</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">551.4 ± 80.8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146 ± 0.013</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 ± 0.038</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 ± 1.95</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1 ± 5.70</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>