
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3894187</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3894187.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3894187</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3894187</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-38596</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Glycobiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject><subj-group><subject>Akt Signaling Cascade</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematology</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematologic Cancers and Related Disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Leukemias</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancers and Neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematologic Cancers and Related Disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Leukemias</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Basic Cancer Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reversal Effect of ST6GAL 1 on Multidrug Resistance in Human Leukemia by Regulating the PI3K/Akt Pathway and the Expression of P-gp and MRP1</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Reversal Effect of ST6GAL 1 on MDR in Leukemia</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongye</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names initials="L">Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names initials="K">Keji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaobo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="H">Huimin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>College of Laboratory Medicine, Medical University, Dalian, Liaoning Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Laparoscopic Surgery, the First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian, Liaoning Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Nuclear Medicine, People's Hospital of Peking University, Beijing, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Medical Biology, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Tromsø, Tromsø, Norway</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Microbiology, Dalian Medical University, Dalian, Liaoning Province, China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rishi</surname><given-names initials="A">Arun</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Wayne State University, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jiali@dlmedu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LJ HM LC. Performed the experiments: HM LC KH. Analyzed the data: HM LC YL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KH HZ. Wrote the paper: LJ HM LC. Revised the language: XS.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">231665</issue-id><elocation-id>e85113</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 01:25:11.020"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Ma et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ma et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0085113.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6797186"><article-title>Retraction: Reversal Effect of ST6GAL 1 on Multidrug Resistance in Human Leukemia by Regulating the PI3K/Akt Pathway and the Expression of P-gp and MRP1</article-title><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><date><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><elocation-id>e0224304</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6797186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31622433</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>β-galactoside α2, 6-sialyltransferse gene (ST6GAL) family has two members, which encode corresponding enzymes ST6Gal I and ST6Gal II. The present atudy was to investigate whether and how ST6GAL family involved in multidrug resistance (MDR) in human leukemia cell lines and bone marrow mononuclear cells (BMMC) of leukemia patients. Real-time PCR showed a high expression level of ST6GAL1 gene in both MDR cells and BMMCs (*P&lt;0.05). Alternation of ST6GAL1 levels had a significant impact on drug-resistant phenotype changing of K562 and K562/ADR cells both in vitro and in vivo. However, no significant changes were observed of ST6GAL2 gene. Further data revealed that manipulation of ST6GAL1 modulated the activity of phosphoinositide 3 kinase (PI3K)/Akt signaling and consequently regulated the expression of P-glycoprotein (P-gp, *P&lt;0.05) and multidrug resistance related protein 1 (MRP1, *P&lt;0.05), which are both known to be associated with MDR. Therefore we postulate that ST6GAL1 is responsible for the development of MDR in human leukemia cells probably through medicating the activity of PI3K/Akt signaling and the expression of P-gp and MRP1.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grants from the National Key Basic Research and Development Program (973 program) of China (no. 2012CB822100), and supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (81071415, 81271910). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>MDR and disease relapse are often regarded as the causes of the failure of chemotherapeutic drug treatments in patients diagnosed with malignant neoplasm including leukemia <xref rid="pone.0085113-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Numerous reports have focused on the mechanisms of MDR of tumor cells, for example the expression of drug transporting pumps, changes in the targets of anticancer drugs, decrease of drug activity, as well as changes in apoptosis regulatory pathways that contribute to MDR <xref rid="pone.0085113-Leslie1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-Gergely1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. MDR is conventionally regarded as the consequence of overexpression of transporter proteins belonging to the ATP binding cassette (ABC) family such as P-gp and MRP1, which lead to lower intracellular drug accumulation and hence reduce cellular toxicity of chemotherapeutic agents <xref rid="pone.0085113-Kourti1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Recently, researchers pay more attention to the relationship between glycan alterations and resistance to chemotherapy of neoplastic cells. Although structure modifications of glycans have been observed in drug-resistance leukemia cells, little is known about the effects of glycosyltransferases or relevant glycogenes on the development of leukemia drug-resistance <xref rid="pone.0085113-Nakano1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Sialic acids, which are terminal monosaccharide attached to glycan chains of cell surface, are commonly found in glycoconjugates. Various sialic acid decorations on the cell surface are shown to be involved in many biological processes, such as cell recognition, cell adhesion, receptor activation, cancer progression, metastatic spread and signal transduction <xref rid="pone.0085113-Varki1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-Hedlund1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. ST6GalI is a sialyltransferase that links the sialic acid residues to terminal galactose of glycan chains by α- 2, 6-linkage <xref rid="pone.0085113-MilfloresFlores1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. It distributes widespread tissue-specific distribution in mammals, and the aberrant expression of ST6GalI is often related to poor prognoses in colon, epithelial tumors, gastric cancers and acute myeloid leukemia <xref rid="pone.0085113-Nakano1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Swindall1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-Gretschel1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Overexpression of ST6GalI was involved in chemotherapy resistance in ovarian tumor cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Schultz1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The altered levels of ST6GalI were also found in Hca-F and Hca-P murine hepatocarcinoma cells with differed invasive properties both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0085113-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. In contrast to ST6GalI, ST6GalII, a recently identified additional sialyltransferase, confines to human intestine, colon and brain <xref rid="pone.0085113-Dalziel1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Petit1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. It exhibits relatively low and no activities toward some glycoproteins and glycolipids respectively and seems to recognize oligosaccharides to glycoproteins as acceptor substrates <xref rid="pone.0085113-Takashima1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Takashima2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Tremendous studies have focused on the involvement of sialylation in tumorigenesis, but the relationship between ST6GalI or ST6GalII and MDR remains unclear.</p><p>PI3K/Akt signaling activation might be implicated in the progression of a wide variety of neoplasias <xref rid="pone.0085113-Bellacosa1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Recent research illustrated that aberrant activation of PI3K/Akt pathway contributed to the survival and drug resistance of different types of human neoplasm cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Garcia1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Cordo1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Activation of Akt was associated with poor prognosis and chemotherapeutic resistance in pediatric B-precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia <xref rid="pone.0085113-Morishita1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. In leukemic cells, chemoresistance was shown to be maintained by PI3K/Akt signaling activation, and could be reversed by LY294002, a known PI3K/Akt antagonist <xref rid="pone.0085113-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. PI3K/Akt kinase pathway also modulated P-gp-mediated multidrug resistance in L1210/VCR mouse leukemic cell line <xref rid="pone.0085113-Barancik1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. But Tazzari showed that that in human acute myelogenous Leukemia (AML) blasts a strong correlation exists between upregulation of the PI3K/Akt survival pathway and MRP1 expression, whereas such a relationship was not found for the P-gp <xref rid="pone.0085113-Tazzari1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. However, little is known regarding the effect of the signaling pathways on ST6GalI, ST6GalII-mediated leukemia MDR.</p><p>The aims of the present study were to determine sialylated oligosaccharide alterations and the expression level of ST6GAL family among the four pairs of parental and chemoresistant human leukemia cell lines. In addition, we examined the regulation of ST6Gal I or ST6Gal II in leukemia MDR via PI3K/Akt pathway and the possible mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Differential expression of ST6GAL1, ST6GAL2 in four pairs of leukemia cell lines</title><p>To analyze the expression profiles of ST6GAL family in drug sensitive and MDR cells, a real-time RT-PCR analysis was performed. ST6GAL1 was significantly expressed at an elevated level in four MDR cell lines compared with those of four drug-sensitive parental cell lines. By contrast, no significant change of ST6GAL2 was observed. Western blotting analysis further confirmed the enzyme expression in drug sensitive and MDR cells at protein level. These data indicated that differential ST6GAL1 expression might be associated with MDR of leukemia, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g001">Fig. 1A and B</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0085113-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Differential expression of ST6GAL1 and ST6GAL2 in four pairs of leukemia cell lines.</title><p>(A) The mRNA levels of ST6GAL1 and ST6GAL2 analyzed by real-time PCR. Four ADR cells expressed higher levels of ST6GAL1 mRNA than their parental cell types (*P&lt;0.05). No significant changes of ST6GAL2 were observed. (B) Western blotting analysis of ST6GalI and ST6GalII at protein levels. GAPDH served as a control. Data are the means ± SD of triplicate determinants.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Suppression of ST6GAL1 gene enhances chemosensitivity of K562/ADR cells in vitro and in vivo</title><p>Due to the significant increase of ST6GAL1 mRNA and protein expression in K562/ADR cells, we silenced, by shRNA, ST6GAL1 to elucidate the direct implication of ST6GAL1 in the chemosensitivity of K562/ADR cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2A and B</xref>, the expression of ST6GAL1 was significantly reduced in K562/ADR-shRNA transfectants compared with control transfectants both at transcription and protein level. K562/ADR-shRNA-1 transfectant was chosen for the following experiments.</p><fig id="pone-0085113-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Silence of ST6GAL1 gene enhances the chemosensitivity of K562/ADR cell both in vitro and in vivo.</title><p>(A) ST6GAL1 transcript was decreased apparently in K562/ADR cells by shRNA treatment. (B) After shRNA transfection, distinct reduction of ST6Gal 1 was observed at protein levels by western blotting analysis. (C) Cell chemosensitivity was assessed by cytotoxicity assays. The reported values are the IC<sub>50</sub> (Mean ± SD) of three independent experiments. IC<sub>50</sub> represents the drug concentration producing 50% decrease of cell growth. *P&lt;0.05 vs K562/ADR-control shRNA cells. (D) When exposed to adriamycin, the tumor volume of nude mice bearing K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 xenograft was significantly diminished (*P&lt;0.05). (E) Down-regulation of ST6GAL1 was also shown by IHC staining in xenograft tumors derived from K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 cells (400×). (F) Flow cytometry analysis showed a lower expression of ST6GAL1 in K562/ADR cells with ST6GAL1 transfection. The data are means ± SD of 3 independent assays (*P&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>After ST6GAL1 shRNA transfection, the ability of adriamycin, paclitaxel and vincristine to inhibit the growth of K562/ADR was evaluated by MTT assay. The results showed that IC<sub>50</sub> values were significantly decreased in K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA group compared to the control, suggesting that cell proliferation was inhibited by therapeutic drug and chemosensitivity was remarkably restored when ST6GAL1 gene was suppressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p><p>To investigate how knockdown of ST6Gal1 gene impacted on chemosensitivity of leukemia cells, we used nude mice bearing K562/ADR and K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 xenografts to analyze the differences of tumor volumes when therapeutic drugs were administrated. A significant reduction of mean tumor volume of K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 tumor was observed, as compared with K562/ADR-control shRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). After the measurement of tumor volume, tumors were sectioned for IHC staining analysis of ST6GalI expression pattern, the expression of it was reduced in the mice group with shRNA treatment compared to untreated group or control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2E</xref>).</p><p>In addition, α-2, 6 sialylation level at the cell surface, detected by FITC-conjugated SNA, was also decreased by treatment with shRNA in K562/ADR cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2F</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Overexpression of ST6GAL1 gene mediates MDR in K562 cells in vitro and in vivo</title><p>To explore the effect of ST6GAL1 on chemosensitivity, a K562 cell line stably expressing ST6GAL1 was established. It was found that the levels of ST6GAL1 mRNA, protein and α2, 6-linked sialic acid were increased notably in ST6GAL1 transfectants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g003">Fig. 3A.B.F</xref>). The IC<sub>50</sub> values for the drugs were significantly increased in the K562/ST6GAL1 group than those in the K562/mock group. Thus, the overexpression of ST6GAL1 in K562 cells resulted in decreased chemosensitivity to antitumor drugs in vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0085113-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Overexpression of ST6GAL1 gene enhances the chemoresistance of K562 cells both in vitro and in vivo.</title><p>After transfection, ST6GAL1 mRNA (A) and protein (B) were increased notably in K562 cells by real time PCR and western blot. (C) Cell chemosensitivity was assessed by cytotoxicity assays. The reported values are the IC<sub>50</sub> (Mean ± SD) of three independent experiments. IC<sub>50</sub> represents the drug concentration producing 50% decrease of cell growth. *P&lt;0.05 vs K562/mock cells. (D) An increase of mean tumor in mice group with K562/ST6GAL1 was observed, as compared with that in K562 group and K562/mock group. Within K562/ST6GAL1 group, an increase of tumor growth was found in group without ADR, compared with that with ADR (*P&lt;0.05). (E) Up-regulation of ST6GAL1 was also shown by IHC staining in xenograft tumors derived from K562/ST6GAL1 cells (400×). (F) Increased expression of ST6GAL1 was detected by flow cytometry analysis in K562/ST6GAL1 cells. The data are means ± SD of 3 independent assays (*P&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Nude mice were inoculated with tumor cells K562, K562/mock and K562/ST6GAL1. Tumor volumes were measured and compared between the groups with or without adriamycin treatment. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g003">Fig. 3D</xref> showed that in the group of mice bearing K562 tumors, tumor volumes with adriamycin treatment were lower than those without. But in the group of mice bearing K562/ST6GAL1 tumors, tumor volumes increased significantly even after adriamycin treatment. High expression level of ST6GalI in tumor cells of K562/ST6GAL1 was also validated by IHC staining, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g003">Fig. 3E</xref>. Thus, overexpression of ST6GAL1 gene in K562 cells led to raised resistance to chemotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Effect of ST6GAL1-activated PI3K/Akt signaling pathway on the expression of P-gp and MRP1 expression</title><p>It has been reported that the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway is activated in K562 cell line <xref rid="pone.0085113-Conde1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Here, we assessed the activity of the PI3K/Akt signaling by ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 treatment in K562/ADR cells. Western blotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>) showed that the levels of P110α (the catalytic subunit of PI3K), phosphorylation of Akt at Ser473 and Thr308, and NF-κB were significantly reduced with shRNA transfection. However, there was no change in the total amount of Akt protein. Conversely, over-expression of ST6GAL1 in K562 cells enhanced proteins expression of P110α, Akt Ser473, Akt Thr308, and NF-κB, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0085113-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effect of ST6GAL1-activated PI3K/Akt signaling pathway on the expression of P-gp and MRP1.</title><p>(A) The main molecules of PI3K/Akt pathway were repressed at protein levels with ST6GAL1 shRNA transfection in K562/ADR cells. (B) The increased protein levels of PI3K/Akt signaling molecules were determined by western blot in K562/ST6GAL1 cells. (C) Decreased expression of P-gp and MRP1 were examined by flow cytometry analysis in K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA cells. (D) Flow cytometry analysis revealed a higher co-expression of P-gp and MRP1 in K562 cells with ST6GAL1 transfection. The data are means ± SD of 3 independent assays (*P&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>P-gp and MRP1 are the recognized molecules which contributed to the development of MDR <xref rid="pone.0085113-Kourti1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Hence, we investigated whether ST6GAL1 could influence the expression of P-gp and MRP1. Interestingly, flow-cytometric analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g004">Fig. 4C and 4D</xref>) illustrated that elevated expression levels of P-gp and MRP1 were detected in K562/ST6GAL1 cells compared to those of control cell groups. In addition, K562/ADR cells expressed lower levels of P-gp and MRP1 with ST6GAL1 supression. Therefore, the data might indicate an additional mechanism of ST6GAL1 in MDR of leukemia cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Inhibition of PI3K/Akt pathway increases the chemosensitivity of K562/ADR cells both in vitro and in vivo</title><p>In order to explore the activity of PI3K/Akt signaling pathway on chemoresistance of K562/ADR cells, PI3K/Akt pathway was pharmacologically inhibited. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>, K562/ADR cells with LY294002 treatment or Akt siRNA showed obviously decreased protein levels of the main signal molecules of PI3K/Akt pathway. By MTT assay <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, we observed the inhibition of PI3K/Akt pathway sensitized K562/ADR cells to chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>), the similar results were also observed by <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> chemosensitivity analysis, reduced tumor volumes were detected in mice group bearing K562/ADR tumors with impaired PI3K/Akt signaling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). Altered expression levels of the main signal molecules of PI3K/Akt pathway in mice group bearing K562/ADR tumors with LY294002 or Akt siRNA treatment were also validated by IHC staining, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>
</p><fig id="pone-0085113-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>PI3K/Akt inhibition changes the chemosensitivity of K562/ADR cells both in vitro and in vivo.</title><p>(A) The K562/ADR cells were pretreated LY294002 or Akt siRNA. Expressions of PI3K/Akt signaling molecules were then examined by western blot analysis. LY294002 or Akt siRNA treatment also alleviated chemoresistance of K562/ADR cells, revealed by <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (B) and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (C). (D) Down-regulation of PI3K/Akt signaling molecules was also shown by IHC staining in xenograft tumors derived from LY294002 or Akt siRNA treatment cells (400×). (E) Flow cytometry analysis showed that inhibition of PI3K/Akt pathway resulted in reduced levels of P-gp and MRP1. The data are means ± SD of 3 independent assays. <sup>*</sup>P&lt;0.05 vs DMSO treatment cells; <sup>#</sup>P&lt;0.05 vs control siRNA treatment cells.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Moreover, to investigate whether suppression of PI3K/Akt signaling activity could influence the expression of P-gp and MRP1, a flow-cytometric analysis was carried out. Lower levels of P-gp and MRP1 were present in K562/ADR cells with LY294002 or Akt siRNA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5E</xref>). The results implicated a role for PI3K/Akt signaling in regulating P-gp and MRP1 expression and modulating the chemoresistance of K562/ADR cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Overexpression of ST6GAL1 is detected in patients' AML and CML cases with chemoresistance</title><p>Expression of MDR-related marker, ST6GAL1 and ST6GAL2 in leukemia patients is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085113-t001">Table 1</xref>. The frequency of P-gp positivity was 92.1% (70 of 76) in AML patients and 86.2% (25 of 29) in CML patients. Then patients were divided into four groups: AML without MDR, AML/MDR, CML without MDR and CML/MDR. As was shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085113-t002">Table 2</xref>, there was a significant difference in the expression of ST6GAL1 between AML/MDR patients (91.4%, 64 of 70) and those without MDR (16.6%, 1 of 6). Accordingly, the proportion of ST6GAL1 positive CML/MDR samples was 90.9% (20 of 22), this was found to be significantly higher than the chemosensitive CML group (28.5%, 2 of 7). However, expression of ST6GAL2 showed no difference between drug resistant groups and chemosensitive groups. According to these results, it was further confirmed the role of ST6GAL1 over-expressions in drug resistance of leukemia cells.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0085113-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinicopathologic characteristics of the leukemia patients.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0085113-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients Demographics</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subcategory</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AML(n = 76)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CML(n = 29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age(years)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17–76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Splenic enlargement</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin&lt;110.0 g/L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC count (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet count (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;300</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;300</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-gp (+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRP1 (+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST6GAL1(+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST6GAL2(+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0085113-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085113.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>The differential expression of ST6GAL1 and ST6GAL2 between MDR and chemosensitive patients.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0085113-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0085113.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">AML(n = 76)</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">CML(n = 29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemosensitivity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemosensitivity</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST6GAL1(+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (91.4%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (90.9%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (28.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST6GAL2(+)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (18.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (14.3%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>P&lt;0.05 vs. patients without MDR.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Clinically chemotherapy resistance is the result of interaction of numerous biological variables <xref rid="pone.0085113-Kars1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. MDR, as an issue with increasing concern, contributes to the chemotherapy failure in leukemia. Recently, some progresses have been gained in revealing the mechanism of MDR <xref rid="pone.0085113-Daiane1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Our study continued to investigate the role of ST6GalI in mediating MDR in human leukemia cells and its possible mechanisms.</p><p>Aberrant expression of sialylated glycans has been detected in carcinomas of pancreas, gastric, breast, bladder, brain and colon <xref rid="pone.0085113-PrezGaray1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-Inagaki1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. In this study, we found the expression profiles of ST6GAL1 in four pairs of human leukemia cell lines and in the tumor cells of leukemia patients by using a real-time PCR analysis. All the leukemia cells with MDR were characterized with higher expression levels of ST6GAL1 compared to the cells without MDR. ST6GAL1 is known to be involved in the process of proliferation, invasion, and apoptosis of cancer cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Schultz2" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-Dalziel2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. From our results we postulate that abnormal expression of ST6GAL1 also involves in the development of MDR possibly, another malignant behavior of tumor cells. There was not a significant difference of ST6GAL2 expression between the cell groups with or without MDR.</p><p>As up-stream regulators of glycoproteins, glycosyltransferases catalyzed the biosynthesis of glycans. They often exhibit abnormal activity in tumors and participate in the process of drug-resistance development <xref rid="pone.0085113-Baran1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Zhang et al have observed an elevated level of ST6GAL1 in drug resistance cell line K562/ADR <xref rid="pone.0085113-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. However, a comprehensive understanding of how ST6GAL1 correlated with the MDR of human leukemia cells was not currently available. In this study, we targeted ST6GAL1, which was over-expressed in K562/ADR cells, and altered the expression levels of the glycogene. A link was found between differential expression levels of ST6GAL1 and changed drug-resistant phenotypes of K562 and K562/ADR cells both in vitro and in vivo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g003">3</xref>). Thus, based on this insight we hypothesized that ST6GAL1 might function as a critical factor involved in MDR.</p><p>The PI3K/Akt signal transduction pathway plays a pivotal role in controlling neoplastic cell growth, survival, motility, invasion and drug resistance <xref rid="pone.0085113-Pandurangan1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-AbdulGhani1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Recent data has confirmed the correlation of the ST6GAL1-mediated PI3K/Akt signaling pathway with multidrug resistance <xref rid="pone.0085113-Dalziel2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0085113-AbdulGhani1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Increasing evidences showed that PI3K/Akt signaling was frequently activated in AML cell lines and patient blasts and strongly contributed to proliferation, survival, and drug resistance of these cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0085113-Matkovic1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Akt1 activity/phosphorylation was also up-regulated in MDR human T-lymphoblastic leukemic CEM cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Maraldi1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Here, we demonstrated that the K562/ADR cell line presented higher PI3K/Akt activity than the sensitive one, which was in accordance with the MDR phenotype. Altered expression of ST6GAL1 remarkably modulated the activity of PI3K/Akt pathway in human leukemia cell lines. Furthermore, blockage of PI3K/Akt pathway by Akt-specific inhibitor, LY294002, or Akt siRNA reversed ADR cells to chemosensitivity, indicating that ST6GAL1 might promote the development of MDR probably through activating the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085113-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Thus, consistent with already reported results, LY294002 can antagonize P-gp-mediated multidrug resistance <xref rid="pone.0085113-Barancik1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>It has been reported that the PI3K/Akt signaling enhances drug efflux by ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters in order to maintain MDR of tumor cells <xref rid="pone.0085113-Tazzari2" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. ABC transporters are a superfamily of transmembrane proteins that transports a wide variety of substrates across cell membranes. They are found on the surface of normal cells and various cancer cells, where they play significant roles in the development of MDR <xref rid="pone.0085113-Higgins1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. As two main members of ABC transporters, P-gp and MRP1 are frequently used as markers to screen MDR patients clinically. MRP1 expression is also under the control of the PI3K/Akt signal transduction network in human acute myelogenous leukemia blasts <xref rid="pone.0085113-Tazzari1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. We found a positive relationship between the levels of P-gp and MRP1 and the expression level of ST6GAL1, as well as the activity of PI3K/Akt signaling in K562 and K562/ADR cell lines. Since ST6GAL1 was observed as regulatory gene on the activity of PI3K/Akt signaling, we assumed that ST6GAL1 might increase the expression of P-gp and MRP1 through PI3K/Akt pathway, thereby mediating MDR of leukemia cells.</p><p>In summary, our results demonstrate an association between differential expression of ST6GAL1 and changed MDR phenotypes of leukemia cells. The possible mechanism is ST6GAL1 activating the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway that results in the expression of P-gp and MRP1. However, drug resistance is multifactorial event, and multiple glycomic alterations could also be responsible for these phenotypes. Therefore, the molecular machanism of tumor MDR remains to be further investigated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Cells</title><p>Four human leukemia cell lines, including a chronic myelogenous leukemia cell line (K562), an acute myelogenous leukemia cell line (HL60), an acute promyelocytic leukaemia cell line (NB4), and a leukemic monocytic cell line (U937) were obtained from the KeyGEN Company (China). All cell lines were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) supplemented with 10% heat inactivated fetal bovine serum (Gibco) and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco) at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO2. Adriamycin (Sigma) was added to parental cell cultures in stepwise increasing concentrations from 0.1 µg/ml to 5 µg/ml for 2 months to develop an adriamycin-resistant (ADR) subline, namely K562/ADR, HL60/ADR, NB4/ADR and U937/ADR, correspondingly. To maintain the MDR phenotype, the complete medium of the resistant cell clones were supplemented with 1.0 mg/L adriamycin. ADR cells were maintained in complete medium without adriamycin for one week and cells with &gt;90% viability prior to subsequent treatments.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Samples from leukemia patients</title><p>The study cohort was made up of 105 previously untreated leukemia patients, including 76 cases of acute myeloid leukemia (AML) and 29 cases of chronic myeloid leukemia (CML). All patients were obtained in the First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University between April 2010 and July 2012, and they provided written informed consent, and the institutional ethics committees of the First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University approved the study as well as contents of the written consent. The leukemic subtypes of AML were determined according to the French-American-British classification as follows: 35, 27 and 14 cases of M2, M3 and M5, respectively. Patients' clinical characteristics were given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0085113-t001">Table 1</xref>. The diagnosis of AML and CML was based on cytomorphology, cytochemistry, multiparameter flow cytometry, immunology, molecular genetics and cytogenetics.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Separation of leukemic blast cell</title><p>BMMC were separated by Ficoll-Hypaque density gradient centrifugation from bone marrow or peripheral blood taken at the initial diagnosis and were cultured in plastic dishes to remove adherent cells at 37°C for 24 h. Freshly separated non-adherent cells were maintained in modified Dulbecco's medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum, 10 mM β-mercaptoethanol, 2 mM L-glutamine, 50 ng/mL human stem cell factor, 10 ng/mL human interleukin-3, and 10 ng/mL human interleukin-6. The expressions of P-gp and MRP1 were measured by flow cytometric assays to determine the resistant phenotype of patients. ST6GAL1 and ST6GAL2 levels of all patients were determined by real time PCR.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Real Time PCR analysis</title><p>Total RNA was isolated with Trizol reagents (Gibco BRL, Rockville, MD, USA) and cDNA was synthesized using QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit (QIAGEN, valencia, CA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Real time PCR was carried out on a Roche LightCycler480 real time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) using QuantiTect SYBR Green PCR Kit (QIAGEN, valencia, CA). After a denaturation and polymerase activation step (15 min at 95°C), 40 cycles of denaturation (15 s at 94°C), annealing (30 s at 58°C) and extension (30 s at 72°C) were run. The sequences of the primers used for the real-time PCR assays were as follows: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CTTGTTTTCCTGCTCAGA-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GCAAACAGAAGAAAGACCA- 3′</named-content> for ST6GAL1, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-ACGCTGCTGATTGACTCTTCT-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CACATACTGGCA CTCATCTAA-3′</named-content> for ST6GAL2; <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CTCCTCCACCTTTGACG-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CACCACC CTGTTGCTGTA-3′</named-content> for GAPDH, the expression of target gene was determined relative to GAPDH and calculated as 2<sup>−(Ct</sup>
<sub>Target gene</sub>
<sup>−Ct</sup>
<sub>GAPDH</sub>
<sup>)</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Total cell protein were electrophoresed in 10% SDS-PAGE gel and blotted onto a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane. After being blocked with 5% powdered skim milk for 2 h in phosphate-buffered saline containing 0.1% Tween 20 (PBST), the membranes were incubated with antibody (1∶500 diluted, Abcam, Cambridge, UK), overnight at 4°C, and then incubated with secondary antibody anti-rabbit/mouse-HRP (1∶2000 diluted, Santa Cruz Biotech, Santa Cruz, CA). GAPDH antibody (1∶200 diluted, Santa Cruz Biotech, Santa Cruz, CA) was used as a control. All bands were detected using ECL Western blotting kit (Amersham Biosciences, UK), according to the manufacturer's instruction.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Deregulation of ST6GAL1 in K562/ADR cells by RNAi</title><p>K562/ADR cells were transferred to a 6 well plate which was seeded 5×10<sup>5</sup> cells in 1 ml of growth medium in each well and incubated at 37°C in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. The cell cultures were transfected with ST6GAL1 shRNA-1, ST6GAL1 shRNA-2 and ST6GAL1 shRNA-3 (Thermo Fisher, Inc, 178042). Scrambled shRNA was used as the negative control. ST6GAL1 shRNAs were mixed with Lipofectamine™ 2000 (Invitrogen). Transfer cells were cultured and incubated at 37°C for 6 h, followed by incubation with complete medium for additional 24 h. Then cells were harvested for further study. The cell transfection efficiency was 85% by fluorescent microscope and the cell viability was 90% by trypan blue dye exclusion assay.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Over-expression of ST6GAL1 in K562 cells</title><p>The human ST6GAL1 coding region were obtained from TaKaRa company (Dalian, China) and were inserted into the pEGFP-N1 vector (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) respectively using EcoRI, XhoI sites. Cells were transfected with 5 µg of target gene expression vector or empty vector (EV) in 100-mm dishes using TurboFect Transfection Reagent (QIAGEN, valencia, CA) according to the manufacturer's instruction. After 60 days of screening, the cell lines stably expressing ST6GAL1 (K562/ST6GAL1), and empty vector (K562/mock) were established. Then cells were collected for further explorations.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>In vitro drug cytotoxic assay</title><p>MTT assay was used to measure the drug resistance. 1×10<sup>4</sup> cells per well were plated in 96-well plate and incubated with different anticancer drugs paclitaxel, vincristine, and adriamycin (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) for 48 h, respectively. Then cells were treated with 100 µl MTT (0.5 mg/ml, Sigma). After 4 h incubation at 37°C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, 100 µl DMSO (Gibco) was pipetted to solubilize the formazan product for 30 min at room temperature. The spectrometric absorbance was measured at 490 nm by microplate reader (Model 680; Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). Each test was repeated three times. The drug resistance was estimated by comparing the IC<sub>50</sub> values (drug concentration that inhibits cell growth by 50%) from growth inhibition curves.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>In vivo chemosensitivity assay</title><p>Five-week-old nude mice were obtained from Animal Facility of Dalian Medical University and were provided with sterilized food and water. Approximately, 1×10<sup>7</sup> K562 and 1×10<sup>7</sup> K562/ADR viable cells were injected subcutaneously into the right flank of each nude mouse. When mice bearing palpable tumors (about 1 week after tumor cell inoculation), K562, K562/ST6GAL1, K562/mock, K562/ADR, K562/ADR-control shRNA, K562/ADR-ST6GAL1 shRNA-1 tumor-bearing mice were randomly divided into control and treatment groups (n = 6 animals per group). The treatment groups received 7 mg/kg adriamycin i.p. three times a week for 3 weeks, and the control groups received physiological saline alone. Mice were sacrificed and their tumors were isolated, weighed, and photographed. The tumor volume was calculated by the following formula: Tumor volume = 1/2(length×width<sup>2</sup>). Experiments were approved by the Committee on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of the Dalian Medical University, China (Permit Number: 12-896).</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Immunohistochemical (IHC) staining analysis</title><p>Visible tumors were removed from the mice and immunohistochemistry was performed on paraffin embedded sections. The slides were dried, deparaffinized, rehydrated. After deparaffinization and blocking of endogenous peroxidase, the slides were labeled overnight at 4°C with antibodies (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) at a dilution of 1∶200. The following staining was performed at room temperature for 60 min with secondary streptavidin-HRP-conjugated antibody (Santa Cruz Biotech, Santa Cruz, CA). Finally, the sections were counterstained with hematoxylin and cover-slipped. The Image-Pro Plus4.5 Software (Media Cybernetics, USA) was used to analyze the expression of proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Inhibition of the PI3K/Akt signaling</title><p>LY294002 (Sigma) or Akt siRNA was used to suppress the activity of the PI3K/Akt signaling in K562/ADR cells. Briefly, cells (1×10<sup>4</sup> cells per well) were incubated with dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), the PI3K inhibitor LY294002 (10 µM) dissolved in DMSO, Akt control siRNA and Akt siRNA. Cells were collected after 24 h. Changes in chemosensitivity and gene expression were measured by MTT assay and western blot analysis, respectively. Each experiment was run in triplicate to determine means and SDs.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Flow cytometry analysis</title><p>Tumor cells were washed with 1×phosphate buffered saline (PBS) buffer containing 20 g/L bovine serum, and then were preincubated with 5% powdered skim milk for 30 min to block nonspecific binding. For surface staining of P-gp and MRP1, aliquots of cells were incubated with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-anti human P-gp, MRP1 (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) or an isotype control antibody (Santa Cruz Biotech, Santa Cruz, CA) for 40 min at 4°C at the recommended dilutions. For detection of α-2, 6 sialylation, cell lysates were incubated with FITC-Sambucus nigra (SNA) lectin (Vector Laboratories, Inc). After repeated centrifugation at 1000 r/min, labeled cells were resuspended in 0.2 ml PBS and were analyzed with FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA). Fluorescence intensity was measured by Cell Quest software.</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>SPSS17.0 software was used, and each assay was performed at least three times. The data were expressed as mean±SD and Student's t-test was used to determine the significance of differences in multiple comparisons. *P&lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0085113-Wang1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The proteasome inhibitor bortezomib reverses P-glycoprotein-mediated leukemia multi-drug resistance through the NF-kappaB pathway</article-title>. <source>Pharmazie</source>
<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22512091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Leslie1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deeley</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SPC</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Multidrug resistance proteins: role of P-glycoprotein MRP1, MRP2, and BCRP (ABCG2) in tissue defense</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source>
<volume>204</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.taap.2004.10.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Bosch1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pharmacogenomics of drug-metabolizing enzymes and drug transporters in chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>448</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18370231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-59745-205-2_5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Gergely1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gergely</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genthem</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Targeting multidrug resistance in cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16518375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrd1984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Kourti1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kourti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vavatsi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gombakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzimagiorgis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Expression of multidrug resistance 1 (mdr1), multidrug resistance-related protein 1 (mrp1), lung resistance protein (lrp), and breast cancer resistance protein (bcrp) genes and clinical outcome in childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Hematol</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17875533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1532/IJH97.E0624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Nakano1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Göbel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavallaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identification of glycan structure alterations on cell membrane proteins in desoxyepothilone B resistant leukemia cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>M111.009001</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/mcp.M111.009001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3226403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Zhang1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Glycomic alterations are associated with multidrug resistance in human leukemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1244</fpage>–<lpage>1253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2012.04.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Varki1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Diversity in cell surface sialic acid presentations: implications for biology and disease</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source>
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17632542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/labinvest.3700656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7100186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Hedlund1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>α2, 6–linked sialic acids on N-Glycans modulate carcinoma differentiation in vivo</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18199532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-1340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-MilfloresFlores1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Milflores-Flores</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millán-Pérez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-López</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes-Leyva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallejo-Ruiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of P1 promoter activity of the beta-galactoside alpha2,6-sialyltransferase I gene (siat 1) in cervical and hepatic cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source>J Biosci</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12038-012-9194-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Swindall1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swindall</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellis</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Sialylation of the fas death receptor by ST6Gal-I provides protection against fas-mediated apoptosis in colon carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>22982</fpage>–<lpage>22990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21550977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M110.211375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3123066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Swindall2"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swindall</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Londono-Joshi</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fineberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ST6Gal-I protein expression is upregulated in human epithelial tumors and correlates with stem cell markers in normal tissues and colon cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>2368</fpage>–<lpage>2378</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23358684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-3424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4038408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Gretschel1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gretschel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haensch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlag</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemmner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Clinical relevance of sialyltransferases ST6GAL-I and ST3GAL-III in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncology</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12931020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000072339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Schultz1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swindall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sztul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ST6Gal-I sialyltransferase confers cisplatin resistance in ovarian tumor cells</article-title>. <source>J Ovarian Res</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1757-2215-6-25">10.1186/1757-2215-6-25</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23578204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1757-2215-6-25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3637436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Zhang2"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Modification of glycosylation mediates the invasive properties of murine hepatocarcinoma cell lines to lymph nodes</article-title>. <source>Plos one</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e65218</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0065218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3688732</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6730859"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Dalziel1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dalziel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dall'Olio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>TaylorPapadimitriou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mouse ST6Gal sialyltransferase gene expression during mammary gland lactation</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/glycob/11.5.407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Petit1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thisse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delannoy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular phylogeny and functional genomics of β-Galactoside α2, 6-Sialyltransferases that explain ubiquitous expression of ST6GAL1 gene in amniotes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>38399</fpage>–<lpage>38414</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20855889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M110.163931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2992273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Takashima1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparison of the enzymatic properties of mouse beta-galactoside alpha2, 6-sialyltransferases, ST6GalI and II</article-title>. <source>J Biochem (Tokyo)</source>
<volume>134</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12966079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jb/mvg142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Takashima2"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsujimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the second type of human β-galactoside α 2,6-sialyltransferase(ST6Gal II), which sialylates Gal β 1,4GlcNAc structures on oligosaccharides preferentially. Genomic analysis of human sialyltransferase genes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>45719</fpage>–<lpage>45728</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12235148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M206808200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Bellacosa1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bellacosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Activation of AKT kinases in cancer: implications for therapeutic targeting</article-title>. <source>Adv Cancer Res</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16095999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0065-230X(05)94002-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Garcia1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alaniz</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>RIC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hajos</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>PI3K/Akt inhibition modulates multidrug resistance and activates NF-kappaB in murine lymphoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Leukemia Research</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18640717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.leukres.2008.06.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Cordo1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cordo</surname><given-names>RRI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alaniz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hyaluronan oligosaccharides sensitize lymphoma resistant cell lines to vincristine by modulating P-glycoprotein activity and PI3K/Akt pathway</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>1012</fpage>–<lpage>1018</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17985348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.23122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Morishita1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsukahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Washio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Activation of Akt is associated with poor prognosis and chemotherapeutic resistance in pediatric B-pecursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pbc.24034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Wu1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>LY294002 inhibits K562 leukemic cells by regulating PI3k/Akt channel <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Journal of Huazhong Univercity of Science and Technology</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11596-009-0412-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19662361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Barancik1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barancik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohacova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sedlak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sulova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>LY294,002, a specific inhibitor of PI3K/Akt kinase pathway, antagonizes P-glycoprotein-mediated multidrug resistance</article-title>. <source>European journal of pharmaceutical sciences</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17010577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejps.2006.08.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Tazzari1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tazzari</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cappellini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelisti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Multidrug resistance-associated protein 1 expression is under the control of the phosphoinositide 3 kinase/Akt signal transduction network in human acute myelogenous leukemia blasts</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17215852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2404523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Conde1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pabón</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jayo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lastres</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>González-Manchón</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Involvement of ERK1/2, p38 and PI3K in megakaryocytic differentiation of K562 cells</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Haematology</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20070854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-0609.2010.01416.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Kars1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kars</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iseri</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ural</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>In vitro evaluation of zoledronic acid resistance developed in MCF-7 cells</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Reasearch</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>4031</fpage>–<lpage>4038</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18225567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Daiane1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daiane</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juliana</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilma</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Relationships between multidrug resistance (MDR) and stem cell markers in human chronic myeloid leukemia cell lines</article-title>. <source>Leukemia Research</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.leukres.2009.11.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-PrezGaray1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Garay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arteta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Llop</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cobler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagès</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>α2,3-sialyltransferase ST3Gal IV promotes migration and metastasis in pancreatic adenocarcinoma cells and tends to be highly expressed in pancreatic adenocarcinoma tissues</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> pii: S1357-2725(13)00152-0.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2013.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23726834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Li1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Altered mRNA expressions of sialyltransferases in human gastric cancer tissues</article-title>. <source>Med Oncol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21140242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12032-010-9771-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Bos1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomis</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genes that mediate breast cancer metastasis to the brain</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>459</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>1009</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19421193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature08021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2698953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Correia1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malagolini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ligeiro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calais</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ST3Gal.I sialyltransferase relevance in bladder cancer tissues and cell lines</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19811634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2407-9-357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2763879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Inagaki1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokudo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sialoglycoconjugate expression in primary colorectal cancer and metastatic lymph node tissues</article-title>. <source>Hepatogastroenterology</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17419230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Schultz2"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swindall</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellis</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the metastatic cell phenotype by sialylated glycans</article-title>. <source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22699311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10555-012-9359-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4079276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Dalziel2"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dalziel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dall'Olio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mungul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ras oncogene induces β -galactoside α 2, 6-sialyltransferase (ST6Gal I) via a RalGEF-mediated signal to its housekeeping promoter</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>3623</fpage>–<lpage>3634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1432-1033.2004.04284.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Baran1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baran</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bielawski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunduz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogretmen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Targeting glucosylceramide synthase sensitizes imatinib-resistant chronic myeloid leukemia cells via endogenous ceramide accumulation</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source>
<volume>137</volume>: <fpage>1535</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00432-011-1016-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11827825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Pandurangan1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pandurangan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Potential Targets for Prevention of Colorectal Cancer: a Focus on PI3K/Akt/mTOR and Wnt Pathways</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2201</fpage>–<lpage>2205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23725112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7314/apjcp.2013.14.4.2201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Dobbin1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbin</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The importance of the PI3K/AKT/MTOR pathway in the progression of ovarian cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>8213</fpage>–<lpage>8227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23591839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms14048213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3645739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-AbdulGhani1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Ghani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gyorffy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurchott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The PI3K inhibitor LY294002 blocks drug export from resistant colon carcinoma cells overexpressing MRP1</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1743</fpage>–<lpage>1752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1209201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Xu1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scialla</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bagg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Survival of acute myeloid leukemia cells requires PI3 kinase activation</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2002-11-3429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Zhao1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konopleva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabreira-Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase dephosphorylates BAD and promotes apoptosis in myeloid leukemias</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14628071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2403220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Grandage1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grandage</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linch</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khwaja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>PI3-kinase/Akt is constitutively active in primary acute myeloid leukaemia cells and regulates survival and chemoresistance via NF-kappaB, Mapkinase and p53 pathways</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2403653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Karajannis1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karajannis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Direnzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shmelkov</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Activation of FGFR1b signaling pathway promotes survival, migration and resistance to chemotherapy in acute myeloid leukemia cells</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16598308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2404203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Matkovic1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matkovic</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brugnoli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertagnolo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banfic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visnjic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The role of the nuclear Akt activation and Akt inhibitors in all-trans-retinoic acid-differentiated HL-60 cells</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>941</fpage>–<lpage>951</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16617325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2404204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Maraldi1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maraldi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertacchini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benincasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Pol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Reverse-phase protein microarrays (RPPA) as a diagnostic and therapeutic guide in multidrug resistant leukemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Oncol</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21132263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2010.850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Tazzari2"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tazzari</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cappellini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelisti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Multidrug resistance-associated protein 1 expression is under the control of the phosphoinositide 3 kinase/Akt signal transduction network in human acute myelogenous leukemia blasts</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17215852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.leu.2404523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0085113-Higgins1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Multiple molecular mechanisms for multidrug resistance transporters</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>446</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>757</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17429392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature05630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>