
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3655947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3655947.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3655947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3655947</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23696862</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-36753</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Mouse</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject><subj-group><subject>Apoptotic Signaling Cascade</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Signaling in Cellular Processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Apoptotic Signaling</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell Death</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Obstetrics and Gynecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Gynecologic Cancers</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Basic Cancer Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Tumor Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancers and Neoplasms</subject><subj-group><subject>Gynecological Tumors</subject><subj-group><subject>Ovarian Cancer</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Novel Insights into the Synergistic Interaction of a Thioredoxin Reductase Inhibitor and TRAIL: The Activation of the ASK1-ERK-Sp1 Pathway</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">DTCD Sensitizes TRAIL-Induced Apoptosis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="G">Guimin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="J">Junqiu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiacong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>College of Instrumentation and Electrical Engineering, Jilin University, Changchun, P.R. China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>College of Life Science, Jilin University, Changchun, P.R. China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Jilin University, Changchun, P.R. China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Supramolecular Structure and Materials, Jilin University, Changchun, P.R. China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider-Stock</surname><given-names initials="R">Regine</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Institute of Pathology, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>ttlin@jlu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TL JL. Performed the experiments: TL YC ZD. Analyzed the data: TL JS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GL JL. Wrote the paper: TL YC. Software used and operation: GL JL. Breeding nude mice: ZD JL. Cell cultural supervision: GL.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">222430</issue-id><elocation-id>e63966</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Lin et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lin et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0063966.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7094841"><article-title>Retraction: Novel Insights into the Synergistic Interaction of a Thioredoxin Reductase Inhibitor and TRAIL: The Activation of the ASK1-ERK-Sp1 Pathway</article-title><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>e0231103</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0231103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32210462</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (TRAIL) induces cell death in various types of cancer cells but has little or no effects on normal cells. Unfortunately, not all cancer cells respond to TRAIL; therefore, TRAIL sensitizing agents are currently being explored. Here, we reported that 6-(4-<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Dimethylaminophenyltelluro)-6-deoxy-β-cyclodextrin (DTCD), a cyclodextrin-derived diorganyl telluride which has been identified as an excellent inhibitor of thioredoxin reductase (TrxR), could sensitize TRAIL resistant human ovarian cancer cells to undergo apoptosis. <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic>, DTCD enhanced TRAIL-induced cytotoxicity in human ovarian cancer cells through up-regulation of DR5. Luciferase analysis and CHIP assays showed that DTCD increased DR5 promoter activity via Sp1 activation. Additionally, DTCD stimulated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) activation, while the ERK inhibitor PD98059 blocked DTCD-induced DR5 expression and suppressed binding of Sp1 to the DR5 promoter. We further demonstrated that DTCD could induce the release of ASK1 from its complex with Trx-1, and recovered its kinase activity. Meanwhile, suppression of ASK1 by RNA interference led to decreased ERK phosphorylation induced by DTCD. The underlying mechanisms reveal that Trx-1 is heavily oxidized in response to DTCD treatment, in accordance with the fact that DTCD could inhibit the activity of TrxR that reduces oxidized Trx-1. Moreover, using an A2780 xenograft model, DTCD plus TRAIL significantly inhibited the growth of tumor <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Our results suggest that Trx/TrxR system inhibition may play a critical role in apoptosis by combined treatment with DTCD and TRAIL, and raise the possibility that their combination may be a promising strategy for ovarian carcinoma treatment.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Young Scientists Fund of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 21101071); Project supported by the China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (Grant No. 2012T50306; 20110491303); Outstanding Youth Foundation of Jilin Province, China (Grant No. 3D511B190537); Fundamental Research Funds for Jilin University (Grant No. 450060441140, 450060445216). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Ovarian carcinoma is the fifth most common cause of cancer deaths in women and accounts for the highest tumor-related mortality of gynecologic malignancies <xref rid="pone.0063966-Jemal1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. While the majority of ovarian cancer patients experience a clinical remission following surgical cytoreduction and adjuvant platinum/taxane-based chemotherapy, up to 80% of these patients’ cancers will recur within 18–24 months and only 20% of the people will survive 5 years from diagnosis <xref rid="pone.0063966-Herzog1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. As with other solid tumors, the focus of therapeutic research in ovarian cancer has shifted from more traditional cytotoxic drugs to biologic agents targeting specific cellular mechanisms.</p><p>TNF-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (TRAIL) is a member of the tumor necrosis factor (TNF) family of cytokines. TRAIL exerts cytotoxic effects on malignant cells without any harm to normal cells <xref rid="pone.0063966-Walczak1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. TRAIL can bind to two death receptors (DR), DR4 and DR5, which contain a cytoplasmic functional death domain <xref rid="pone.0063966-LeBlanc1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Following the engagement with DR, TRAIL triggers cell death through at least two fundamental apoptotic pathways, referred to as the extrinsic pathway and the intrinsic pathway <xref rid="pone.0063966-Almasan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The apoptosis initiated by the extrinsic pathway involves DR engagement, death-inducing signaling complex formation, and proteolytic caspase-8 activation <xref rid="pone.0063966-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Caspase-8 further activates Bid, which, in turn, translocates to the mitochondria and activates the intrinsic pathway <xref rid="pone.0063966-Srivastava1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Meanwhile, activated caspase-8 is also released into the cytoplasm and induces a protease cascade that stimulates effector caspases such as caspase-3 and caspase-7, which ultimately cut vital cellular substrates resulting in apoptosis <xref rid="pone.0063966-Kischkel1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. DR not only give the apoptosis signal but also activate NF-κB, which regulates the expression of survival factors such as members of the inhibitor of apoptosis (IAP) family and Bcl-xL <xref rid="pone.0063966-Schneider1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>However, despite its promise, TRAIL resistance is well established and limits efficacy in many preclinical models, including ovarian cancers <xref rid="pone.0063966-Kendrick1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-Bevis1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The mechanism of the resistance has been attributed to dysfunction of different steps in the apoptosis pathways, as well as elevation of survival signals. The former include suppressed expression of the DRs or caspases by mutation or imprinting <xref rid="pone.0063966-Lane1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The survival signals consist of over expression of Bcl-2 and IAPs family <xref rid="pone.0063966-Woods1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Therefore, modulation of these points with a chemotherapeutic agent would sensitize TRAIL-induced apoptosis in ovarian cancer cells <xref rid="pone.0063966-Mao1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-GoncharenkoKhaider1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p>6-(4-N,N-<underline>D</underline>imethylaminophenyl<underline>t</underline>elluro)-6-deoxy-β-<underline>c</underline>yclo<underline>d</underline>extrin (DTCD; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Figure 1A</xref>), a synthetic cyclodextrin-derived diorganyl telluride, has exhibited marked anti-inflammatory activity with very low toxicity <xref rid="pone.0063966-McNaughton1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Recent studies reveal that DTCD also possesses anti-cancer activities against malignant cancer cells <xref rid="pone.0063966-Engman1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-Huang1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The chemopreventive activity has been attributed to its ability to inhibit thioredoxin reductase (TrxR), which is overexpressed in primary tumors and becoming an attractive target for cancer therapy <xref rid="pone.0063966-Nogueira1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0063966-Pennington1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. However, the anticancer mechanism of DTCD in TRAIL-mediated apoptosis has not yet been characterized.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>DTCD sensitizes human ovarian cancer cells to TRAIL-induced cytotoxicity <bold><italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></bold>
<bold>.</bold>
</title><p>(A) The structural formula of DTCD. (B) Cytotoxic effects of TRAIL or DTCD on human ovarian carcinoma cells. Cells were treated with different concentrations of TRAIL (0–500 ng/mL, <italic toggle="yes">left</italic>) or DTCD (0–10 µM, <italic toggle="yes">right</italic>) for 24 h. Then cell viability was determined by MTT assay. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 versus vehicle control. (C) DTCD sensitize resistant ovarian cancer cells, but not HOSE cells to TRAIL induced cytotoxicity. Ovarian cancer cells and HEMC cells were treated simultaneously with DTCD (10 µM) and/or TRAIL (200 ng/mL) for 24 h. (D) Synergistic induction of cell death by DTCD and TRAIL. For combination experiments, five doses of DTCD and TRAIL were used from serial dilutions covering the IC<sub>50</sub> (fractional affected 0.5) values. The combination index (CI) analysis was conducted according to the median-effect plot analysis of Chou and Talalay. CI &lt;1, CI = 1, and CI &gt;1 represent synergism, additivity, and antagonism of the two agents, respectively. (E) Effects of combined treatment with DTCD and TRAIL on cell apoptosis. Cells were treated with DTCD (10 µM) and/or TRAIL (200 ng/mL) for 24 h after 30 min pretreatment with (+)/without (−) z-VAD-fmk (25 µM), then assayed by AnnexinV/PI staining. (F) Representative images of DNA fragmentation and nuclear condensation in response to DTCD and/or TRAIL treatment as detected by TUNEL and DAPI staining assay (magnification, 200×).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>In this study, we have examined whether DTCD and TRAIL interact to enhance their cytotoxicity towards ovarian carcinoma cells. Our results show that DTCD potentiates TRAIL-triggered apoptosis through DR5 up-regulation which is dependent on the activation of ASK1-ERK-Sp1 signaling pathway. Using the A2780 xenograft model, we further demonstrated that this combination significantly reduced tumor burden <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Taken together, our findings suggest that DTCD is an ideal candidate for TRAIL-induced apoptosis in human ovarian carcinoma.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Cells and Materials</title><p>Human ovarian cell lines A2780, SKOV3, OVCAR3, CAOV3, PA-1, OV-4 and ES-2 cells obtained from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) were grown in DMEM (Gibco) supplemented with 4.5 g/L of glucose, 4 mmol/L of L-glutamine, 100 units/mL of penicillin/streptomycin and 10% FCS (Invitrogen). DTCD was prepared as previously described <xref rid="pone.0063966-McNaughton1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Human ovarian surface epithelial cells (HOSEs, Cambres) were grown as described in the manufacturer’s instructions. Soluble Recombinant Human TRAIL was purchased from R&amp;D Systems. 3,3-dihexyloxacarbocyanine iodide (DiOC<sub>6</sub>) and 4,6-diami-dino-2-phenyindole (DAPI) were obtained from Sigma. PD98059, SP600125, SB203580, z-VAD-fmk, and Z-IETD-fmk were purchased from Calbiochem.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Cell Viability and Apoptosis Assay</title><p>Cell viability was assessed using the 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2-5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT, Chemicon) colorimetric method. Annexin V assays were done using the Annexin V-FITC apoptosis detection kit (Clontech). For TUNEL &amp; DAPI staining, apoptotic DNA fragmentation was examined by using an in situ cell death detection kit (Roche) following the manufacturer’s recommendations.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Cellular Fractionation</title><p>Cells were collected after 24 h of treatment and pretreated with a 25-µL protease inhibitor cocktail (Pierce). An NE-PER Nuclear and Cytoplasmic Extraction kit (Pierce) was used to extract nuclear and cytoplasmic contents. Samples were concentrated with PEG 8000, and protein concentrations were estimated using a Micro BCA kit (Pierce). To separate cytosolic proteins from mitochondria, cells (10<sup>6</sup>) were lysed in 30 µL ice-cold lysis buffer (80 mM KCl, 250 mM sucrose, 500 µg/mL digitonin and proteases inhibitors in PBS). Then, cell lysates were centrifuged for 5 min at 10000×g. Proteins from the supernatant (cytosolic fraction) and pellet (mitochondria fraction) were mixed with Laemmli buffer.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p>Samples (30 µg protein) were separated by SDS-PAGE and then transferred to nitrocellulose paper (Immobilon-NC, Millipore) soaked in a Tris (20 mM), glycine (150 mM) and methanol (20%) buffer at 55 V for 4 h. After washing, the blots were incubated overnight at 4°C with the following primary antibodies: mouse monoclonal anti-poly ADP ribosyl polymerase (PARP), anti-Sp1 (diluted 1∶1000 v/v, Santa Cruz); anti-caspase-3, anti-caspase-8, anti-caspase-9, anti-Cytochrome c, anti-Smac/DIABLO, anti-TRAIL-R2, anti-TRAIL-R1, anti-cIAP1, anti-cIAP2, anti-XIAP, anti-Bcl-xL, anti-Bid, anti-t-Bid, anti-Bax, anti-Bad (1∶2000 v/v, Stressgen) and mouse monoclonal anti-nucleolin, anti-β-actin, anti α-tubulin and anti-COX IV (1∶2000 v/v, Sigma). Antibodies against JNK, ERK, p38, ASK-1 and their phosphorylated products were purchased from Cell Signalling Technology. Following incubation, the secondary antibodies (diluted 1∶2000 v/v, Sigma) were added for 1 h at room temperature. Proteins were visualized using an enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL) system (Santa Cruz) and captured on X-ray films.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Flow Cytometry of Death Receptors</title><p>Following 24 h-incubation with DTCD or DTCD+TRAIL, adherent cells (1 ×10<sup>6</sup>) were stained with 200 µL PBS containing saturating amounts of anti-DR4 or anti-DR5 antibody (R&amp;D Systems) on ice for 30 min. Then, cells were reacted with FITC-conjugated rabbit anti-goat IgG (Sigma) on ice for 30 min. After washing with PBS, the expressions of these death receptors were analyzed by FACS Calibur (Becton Dickinson).</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Real-time PCR</title><p>For quantitative PCR, 1 µL of gene primers with SYBR Green (Applied Biosystems) in 20 µL of reaction volume was applied. Primer sequences for each of the genes analyzed are as follows: DR4 forward primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GCTCAGGTTGTTTGTTGCATCGGC-3′</named-content>, reverse primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GCCAGTTTTGTTGGAGGCGTTCCG-3′</named-content>; DR5 forward primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GAGACAACAAAACGGCGCCGAGGT-3′</named-content>, reverse primer: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CAGCAACTGTGAGACTACGGCTAC-3′</named-content> and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) primers, all purchased from Clontech. Temperature cycling and real-time fluorescence measurement were done using an ABI prism 7300 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems).The relative expression level for each target gene mRNA was calculated using the following formula: [2∧-(CT <sub>target</sub> - CT <sub>GAPDH</sub>)] × 100%, where CT is the threshold cycle.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Luciferase Assays</title><p>The pDR5/−605 plasmid was prepared according to our previous work (Lin et al., 2011). For luciferase assay, A2780 cells were co-transfected with 1 µg of pDR5/605 plasmid construct and 0.2 µg of the pCMV-β-galactosidase plasmid by the Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen), in accordance with the manufacturer’s instructions. Luciferase activity was normalized by β-galactosidase activity in cell lysates and expressed as an average of three independent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Assay</title><p>The chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assay was done using the EZ-Chip assay kit according to the manufacturer’s protocol (Upstate Biotechnology). The primers used for the amplification of the Sp1-binding site of DR5 promoter region were 5′-GCCAGGGCGAAGGTTA-3′(sense) and 5′-GGGCATCGTCGGTGTAT-3′(antisense; 276-bp DNA product).</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay</title><p>DNA-protein binding assays were carried out with a nuclear extract. Synthetic complementary Sp1 (<named-content content-type="gene">5′-ATTCGATCGGGGCGGGGCGAGC-3′</named-content>) binding oligonucleotides (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) were 3′-biotinylated using the biotin 3′-end DNA labeling kit (Pierce) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Small Interfering RNA</title><p>DR5, ASK1 siRNA, and control siRNA were purchased from Dharmacon, Inc. (Lafayette,CO). Cells were transfected with Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer’s recommendations in the presence of siRNAs. For siRNA-mediated silencing of JNK, p38 and ERK, transient transfections were performed using JNK, p38, ERK1 or ERK2 SMARTpool siRNA (Dharmacon RNA Technologies).</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>ASK1 <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> Kinase Assay</title><p>Cell lysates were prepared under non-denaturing conditions as described previously <xref rid="pone.0063966-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, and 150 µg of protein was used for each kinase assay. The kinase in cell lysates was captured using the anti-ASK1 antibody and then incubated with MKK4 (Upstate Biotechnologies) in the presence of [γ- <sup>32</sup>P] ATP, and MKK4 phosphorylation was detected using autoradiogram.</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>Assay for ASK1-Trx-1 Complex Formation</title><p>Immunoprecipitation of ASK1-Trx-1 complexes was performed using Protein A/G PLUS-Agarose beads as per the instructions of the manufacturer (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Briefly, cells were lysed in IP assay buffer, and half of each cell lysate was incubated with 1 mmol/L DTT for 30 min. The lysate was then precleared by adding 40 µL Protein A/G PLUS-Agarose beads and incubating for 30 min at 4 °C. Cell lysates were then incubated with 6 µg anti-Trx-1 and 40 µL Protein A/G PLUS-Agarose beads for 4 h at 4 °C. The immunopercipitates were boiled in 1×electrophoresis sample buffer, and samples were subjected to SDS-PAGE analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title>Trx Redox Status Assay</title><p>A2780 cells (10<sup>6</sup>) were lysed in 6 mol/L guanidinium chloride, 50 mmol/L Tris/HCl (pH 8.3), 3 mmol/L EDTA, and 0.5% Triton-X-100 containing 50 mmol/L iodoacetic acid. After 30 min at 37 °C, the excess iodoacetic acid was removed using Microspin G-25 columns (GE Healthcare Life Sciences). Oxidized and reduced Trx-1 were separated by native PAGE. The gel was electroblotted onto a nitrocellulose membrane and probed with a Trx-1 antibody, followed by HRP-conjugated secondary antibody. Bands corresponding to Trx-1 were visualized by ECL.</p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The authors confirm that all animal studies were conducted according to the experimental practices and standards specifically approved by the Animal Welfare and Research Ethics Committee at Jilin University. Nude female mice were bred in rodent facility. The animals were kept in a specific pathogen-free environment, in positive pressure rooms with filtered and humidified air. The animals were kept under standard conditions, and food and water were supplied ad libitum.</p></sec><sec id="s2o"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> Tumor Growth Model</title><p>A2780 cells (5×10<sup>6</sup>) resuspended in 0.1 mL serum-free DMEM were subcutaneously (s.c.) injected into the right axilla of 6-week-old female Balb/c nu/nu mice (National Academy of Medical Sciences). When the tumor volume (TV) reached 150 mm<sup>3</sup>, mice were randomly divided into four groups (n = 8/group) to receive treatment of an intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of vehicle control (100 µL of 0.9% NaCl), DTCD (60 mg/kg/2d – dose of 0.05LD<sub>50</sub>, based on preliminary experiments, 1.2 mg/2 d for a 20-g mouse in a maximal volume of 100 µL 0.9% NaCl), TRAIL (10 mg/kg/2d) and the combination of DTCD plus TRAIL (6 h after DTCD treatment). The volume of the tumors and the weight of the mice were measured every 2–3 days. Tumor volume was measured with a caliper and calculated by the following formula: (long axis×short axis<sup>2</sup>)/2.</p><p>The mice were treated for a period of 20 days. At the end of <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments, the animals were sacrificed under anesthesia using avertin, approximately 24 hours following TRAIL and/or DTCD treatment. Tumor tissues were then immediately removed, fixed in paraformaldehyde at room temperature and then embedded in paraffin for the further immunohistochemistry, which is beyond the scope of the present study.</p></sec><sec id="s2p"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The mean and standard deviation (SD) were calculated for each experimental group. Differences between groups were analyzed by one-or two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni’s multiple comparison tests using PRISM statistical analysis software (GraphPad Software version 5.0). Significant differences among groups were calculated at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>DTCD Sensitizes TRAIL-induced Apoptosis Regardless of Cell type Specificity through Activation of Caspase</title><p>We first examined the cytotoxic effects of TRAIL sensitivity on a panel of human ovarian cancer cells using a standard MTT cell survival assay. Different concentrations (50,100,200, and 500 ng/mL) of recombinant human soluble TRAIL were used. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, only two (OVCAR3, CAOV3) out of seven ovarian cancer cell lines were efficiently killed by TRAIL in a dose-dependent manner. In contrast, the remaining cell lines were either partially resistant (40–80% cell death; ES-2, PA-1) or resistant (&lt;20% cell death; SKOV3, A2780, OV-4) to TRAIL at concentrations up to 500 ng/mL. Hence, we choose 200 ng/mL of TRAIL for the experiment further on.</p><p>To investigate whether DTCD could exhibit anti-proliferative effects, TRAIL-resistant cell lines SKOV3 and A2780 were incubated with the increasing concentrations of DTCD (1.25, 2.5, 5.0, 10.0 µM) for 24 h and then also subjected to the MTT assay. DTCD alone induced a limited cell death (&lt;10%) at concentrations up to 10 µM. We thus choose 10.0 µM dose of DTCD for the following characterization of cell death.</p><p>We next evaluated whether DTCD could cooperate with TRAIL to induce growth suppression of ovarian cancer cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>, approximately 70% decrease of cell viability in A2780 and SKOV3 cells was observed. In contrast, the combination treatment induced minimal cytotoxic effects in normal human ovarian surface epithelial cells (HOSEs), indicating DTCD did not abrogate the potential tumor selectivity of TRAIL. Notably, exposure to the combination of DTCD and TRAIL exerts synergistic effects in A2780 and SKOV3 cells (CI&lt;1), as determined by the median dose-effect isobologram analysis <xref rid="pone.0063966-Chou1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>).</p><p>We then investigated whether the combination treatment is dependent on apoptosis. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Fig. 1E</xref>, the treatment of A2780 cells with a combination of DTCD and TRAIL for 24 h significantly increased the accumulation of apoptotic cells (AnnexinV–positive/propidium iodide–negative), whereas DTCD or TRAIL alone slightly induced apoptosis. Cell apoptosis induced by the combined treatment were further confirmed by TUNEL and DAPI staining assay which can detect early stage of DNA fragmentation in apoptotic cells prior to morphology changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g001">Fig. 1F</xref>). Finally, the apoptosis induced by DTCD in combination with TRAIL were significantly diminished when cells were pre-incubated for 1 h with 100 µM z-VAD-fmk, a broad-spectrum caspase inhibitor, indicating a caspase-dependent mechanism. Taken together, these results suggest that DTCD synergistically sensitize resistant breast cancer cells, not untransformed ovarian cells, to TRAIL-induced apoptosis <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Treatment with a Combination of DTCD and TRAIL Activates Extrinsic and Intrinsic Apoptosis Pathways</title><p>When using DiOC<sub>6</sub>, we found that marked reduction in the mitochondrial membrane potential had occurred in cells treated with DTCD plus TRAIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>), indicating that the combinational treatment could suppress the inhibitory factors in mitochondria. While pretreatment with caspase-8 inhibitor z-IETD-fmk normalized mitochondrial membrane potential, confirming the involvement of caspase-8 activity in the DTCD-enhanced sensitization. It is known that TRAIL-induced caspase-8 activation can lead, via tBid and Bax, to cytochrome c and Smac/DIABLO release from mitochondria. Cytosolic cytochrome c enables apoptosome formation, which leads to caspase-9 activation that in turn processes and activates the executioner caspases. We then evaluated these proximal events in TRAIL-induced apoptotic pathways. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>, treatment with TRAIL in combination with DTCD promoted robust caspase-8 processing, whereas, little or no change was observed in cells treated with a single agent. Moreover, the combinatorial group caused a time-dependent cleavage of BID protein and the formation of its truncated form of BID (tBID). As expected, during DTCD and TRAIL treatment, Bax levels were high in the cytosol at 6 h when co-incubated with TRAIL and DTCD, and then they declined thereafter. Meanwhile, Bax levels in the mitochondrial fraction were increased at 6 h post-drug exposure, and this process was accompanied by the release of cytochrome c and Smac/DIABLO, from the mitochondria into the cytosol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). Similar to caspase-8 cleavage, caspase-3, caspase-9, and PARP were also activated after the combined treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). Collectively, these results indicated that treatment with a combination of DTCD and TRAIL reduces the expression of multiple proteins associated with cell survival through the extrinsic and intrinsic apoptotic signal pathway.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Treatment with a combination of DTCD and TRAIL activates apoptotic signal via the extrinsic and intrinsic pathways.</title><p>(A) Effects of DTCD plus TRAIL on mitochondrial membrane potential. A2780 cells were pretreated with(+)/without (-) z-IETD-fmk, and then were treated with DTCD (10 µM) and/or TRAIL (100 ng/mL). Mitochondrial membrane potential was measured by flow cytometry using DiOC<sub>6</sub> dye. (B) Effects of TRAIL combined with DTCD on Caspase-8 and Bid cleavage. A2780 and SKOV3 cells were treated with DTCD (10 µM) and/or TRAIL (200 ng/mL) for the indicated time points, then subjected to Western blotting. (C) Levels of cytochrome c, Smac/DIABLO and Bax in cytosolic and pellet fractions were determined by Western blot. Following treatment, A2780 cells were lysed and cytosolic proteins were separated from mitochondria as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>. COX IV and β-actin levels were used as internal controls for mitochondrial and cytosol specimen, respectively. (D) Effects of TRAIL combined with DTCD on levels of proapoptotic proteins. (E) DTCD combined with TRAIL regulates the expression of Bcl-2 and IAPs families.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>DR5 Upregulation is important for DTCD Stimulated TRAIL-induced Apoptosis</title><p>Since TRAIL is known to trigger apoptotic signals via DR4 and DR5, we next examined whether the modulation of DR4 and/or DR5 protein levels by DTCD might be involved in its sensitizing effect on TRAIL-induced apoptosis. We found that treatment of A2780 cells with DTCD induces a time-dependent (<italic toggle="yes">left</italic>) and dose-dependent (<italic toggle="yes">right</italic>) increase in the protein levels of DR5 but did not affect the levels of DR4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Flow cytometric analysis, considered as a more sensitive method, also showed that surface expression of DR5 but not DR4 was also notably increased by DTCD treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Consistent with this result, the expression of DR5 was significantly up-regulated not only in ovarian carcinoma cells <xref rid="pone.0063966-Yaginuma1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> with wild-type p53 (A2780), but also in those with mutant p53 (OVCAR3 and ES2) and p53 null type (SKOV3), indicating that DTCD-induced DR5 up-regulation is not p53-dependent in ovarian cancer cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Furthermore, suppression of DR5 expression by transfection of A2780 cells with DR5 siRNA also effectively inhibited DTCD stimulated TRAIL-induced growth inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>), confirming the idea that DTCD-induced upregulation of DR5 is critical for the enhancement of TRAIL sensitivity in A2780 cells.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>DTCD increases DR5 but not DR4 levels in ovarian cancer cell lines.</title><p>(A) DTCD-induced DR5 upregulation in A2780 cells. Cells were treated with 10 µM DTCD for the indicated time or treated with indicated amount of DTCD for 24 h and then subjected to Western blot analysis. (B) Effects of DTCD on the surface expression levels of DR5. Cells were incubated with or without 10 µM DTCD for 24 h, then subjected to flow cytometry analysis. (C) DTCD-induced DR5 upregulation in other types of ovarian cancer cells. (D) Effect of DR5 siRNA on DTCD/TRAIL-induced cell death. A2780 cells were transfected with control siRNA or DR5 siRNA. 24 h after the transfection, cells were treated with 10 µM DTCD and 200 ng/mL TRAIL for another 24 h. Cellular viability was determined by MTT assay (<italic toggle="yes">left</italic>). The levels of DR5 were analyzed by Western Blotting (<italic toggle="yes">right</italic>). *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus vehicle control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>DTCD Activates DR5 Transcription through the Activation of Sp1 in the DR5 Promoter Regions</title><p>To assess whether DTCD–induced DR5 up-regulation is tightly controlled at transcriptional level, we analyzed expression of DR5 mRNA by RT-PCR. We found that DTCD treatment increases DR5 mRNA expression in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>), but not DR4 mRNA (data not shown). Next, the effects of DTCD on the promoter activities of reporter constructs containing 605-bp fragments of the DR5 gene promoter region (pDR5/−605) in A2780 cells were examined by luciferase assays. Results indicated that DTCD significantly increases the promoter activities of pDR5/605 in time- and dose-dependent manners (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). In particular, 10 µM DTCD enhanced the DR5 promoter activity approximately four fold greater than control values at 24 h, supporting the idea that DTCD-induced DR5 up-regulation is controlled at the transcriptional level. To further demonstrate the precise mechanism by which DTCD regulates DR5 expression, western blot and ChIP analysis were performed to quantify Sp1 activity on the DR5 promoter regions. As expected, treatment with 10 µM DTCD time dependently increased Sp1 nucleus translocation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). Additionally, DTCD also increased Sp1 binding to the promoter regions of DR5 and significant Sp1 binding levels were observed at 6 h after DTCD treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). These results show that DTCD up-regulates DR5 expression via Sp1 binding and activation on the DR5 promoter region.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>DTCD mediates transcription of DR5 through Sp1 activation.</title><p>(A) DTCD treatment increases the DR5 mRNA levels. Real-time PCR was used to quantify the DR5 mRNA levels following 24 h of DTCD treatment. (B) Effects of DTCD on DR5 promoter activity. pDR5/−605 plasmid was transfected into A2780 cells, which were then treated with DTCD (10 µM) for the indicated time points or indicated amounts of DTCD, lysed and assayed for luciferase activity. (C) DTCD activates Sp1 translocation to the nucleus. (D) <italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> binding of Sp1 on DR5 promoter regions by DTCD. ChIP assay was done using antibodies against Sp1 in both cells. Negative controls were done using antibody against rabbit IgG.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Transactivation of the DR5 Promoter Requires Activation of Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase by DTCD</title><p>The phosphorylation of Sp1 has been widely studied, with results showing that certain kinases that phosphorylate Sp1. Some of them affect its transactivation activity, while others, regulate its DNA binding affinity <xref rid="pone.0063966-Chu1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Serine or threonine residues could be phosphorylated by kinases, we then investigated whether DTCD-mediated Sp1 DNA binding is mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) dependent. The results revealed that three major MAPKs, JNK, p38, and ERK, were activated by the treatment with 10 µM of DTCD, following a time-dependent pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). In particular, JNK-MAPK activation displayed a rapid on set within 30 min of treatment, followed by a progressive decline, returning to basal levels after 3 h. Activation of p38 by DTCD was marginal, reaching maximum values within 30 min of treatment, decreasing thereafter and reaching control levels at 6 h. Activation of ERK1/2 was also observed at 30 min of DTCD treatment, followed by a consistently strong activated form within 24 h. The above results indicate that DTCD induces a differential activation of the three well-established MAPK subfamilies, in relation to time of exposure. These MAPKs were also activated by DTCD in a dose-dependent manner (5–50 µM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). Although phosphorylation of JNK and p38 slightly occurred at 50 µM of DTCD treatment, treatment with 5 µM of DTCD for 1 h was enough to activate ERK with a fixed concentration of TRAIL. The above results indicate that activation of ERK could play an essential role in DTCD-mediated potentiation of TRAIL-induced apoptosis.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>DTCD affects the levels of MAPK phosphorylation.</title><p>A2780 cells were incubated with 10 µM of DTCD for indicated times (A) or with indicated amounts of DTCD+TRAIL for 1 h (B) and the levels of -ERK, -JNK, - p38 and their phosphorylated forms were determined by western blotting. (C) MAPKs are involved in DTCD-mediated upregulation of Sp1 DNA binding activity. A2780 cells were stimulated with 10 µM DTCD for 24 h after pretreatment with 20 µmol/L PD98059, 20 µmol/L SP600125, and 10 µmol/L SB203580 for 1 h. Then, Sp1 DNA binding activity and nuclear translocation were analyzed by EMSA (<italic toggle="yes">left</italic>) and Western blotting (<italic toggle="yes">right</italic>), respectively. (D) Effects of PD98059 on DR5 promoter activity and expression assay. PD98059 inhibits DR5 luciferase activity induced by DTCD. pDR5/605 plasmid was transfected into A2780 cells, which were then pretreated with 20 µmol/L PD98059 for 1 h and further treated with 10 µM DTCD for 24 h, lysed and assayed for luciferase activity and Western blot assay, respectively. (E) Effects of PD98059 on the cytotoxicity induced by DTCD and TRAIL.A2780 cells were treated with DTCD (10 µM) and TRAIL (200 ng/mL) in the presence of indicated amount of PD98059 for 24 h. Cell viability was determined by MTT assay. (F) Cells were transfected with ERK1 siRNA, ERK 2 siRNA or control siRNA, respectively. 24 h after the transfection, cells were treated with 10 µM DTCD for another 24 h, and cell extracts were subjected to Western blotting. (G) Cells were transfected with JNK1/2 siRNA or p38 siRNA, then treated with 10 µM DTCD for 24 h. Western blotting was then used to analyze the extracts for JNK, and p38 MAPK expression.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>To date, there is no evidence indicating how DTCD stress-induced MAPK activation affects Sp1 gene expression in cancer cells, therefore pharmacological inhibitors of various kinases were used to study these pathways. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>, only inhibition of ERK by PD98059 significantly blocked DTCD-induced Sp1-binding activity and translocation of Sp1 to the nucleus. But SB203580 (a specific inhibitor of p38 kinases) and SP600125 (a specific inhibitor of JNK kinases) have no significant effect on Sp1 expression level. Meanwhile, pretreatment with PD98059 dose dependently attenuated the DTCD-mediated upregulation of both promoter activity and protein levels of DR5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>). Cell viability assay further confirmed that inhibition of ERK by PD98059 reduced the cytotoxic effects of combined treatment with DTCD and TRAIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5E</xref>).</p><p>As inhibition of protein expression using RNA interference is often more specific than functional inhibition using small molecules. We then transfected A2780 cells with control siRNA and specific siRNA against ERK1 and ERK2. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5F</xref>, the reduction in ERK1/2 expression by the siRNA correlated with suppression of DTCD induced up-regulation of DR5 and Sp1. However, the JNK and p38 siRNA had minimal effects on DTCD-induced DR5 and Sp1 up-regulation, which further confirmed that ERK is required for death receptor induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g005">Fig. 5G</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>DTCD-mediated ASK1 Induction Contributes to ERK Activation and Cell Apoptosis Induced by TRAIL</title><p>ASK1, also known as MAPK kinase kinase 5 (abbreviated as MAP3K5), is part of the MAPK cascade <xref rid="pone.0063966-Takeda1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. We, therefore, examined the effects of DTCD on TRAIL-induced activation of ASK1. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>, DTCD could increase the phosphorylated levels of ASK1 (p-ASK1) and the kinase activity of ASK1. This observation raised the possibility that ASK1 induction by DTCD might lead to enhancement of ERK activity. We then determined whether ASK1 knockdown by siRNA could impair the activation of ERK targets. We found that depletion of ASK1 by siRNA not only prevented its own induction by DTCD but also substantially impair the induction of ERK and its down stream targets, Sp1 and DR5. These results confirm that DTCD-mediated rapid ASK1 phophorylation (within 1 h) could be responsible for ERK activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>). To this end, we used ASK1 siRNA to reduce ASK1 expression in A2780 cells and observed a marked reduction in the level of apoptosis following DTCD treatment or both (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>). The above observations suggest that the active engagement of ASK1-ERK is necessary in response to potentiation of TRAIL-induced apoptosis by DTCD. Reduced Trx is known to inhibit activation of ASK1, whereas when Trx is oxidized, it releases ASK1, permitting ASK1 to be phosphorylated and becoming an active MAPKKK. We, therefore, explored the status of the ASK-Trx-1 complex in A2780 cells in response to DTCD. As expected, DTCD dose-dependently decreased the amount of ASK1 associated with Trx-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>), indicating that Trx-1 might be one of the key players in regulating DTCD-mediated promotion of TRAIL-induced apoptosis. Incubation of the cell lysate with the reducing agent DTT can restore the integrity of the ASK-Trx-1 complex, suggesting that their dissociation could be resulted from DTCD-induced oxidation of Trx-1. We therefore determined whether DTCD could influence the cellular levels and the redox status of Trx-1. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g006">Fig. 6E</xref>, DTCD did not change the total protein level of Trx-1, however, a significant change in the oxidation status of Trx-1 in response to treatment with DTCD was observed. Furthermore, the redox status of Trx-1 changed in a concentration-dependent manner. At low concentrations, we observed both reduced and oxidized forms of Trx-1, whereas, at high concentrations, the reduced band was undetectable, and only two oxidized forms were present. Meanwhile, oxidation status of Trx-1 was also increased when cells were co-treated with DTCD plus TRAIL.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>DTCD synergizes with TRAIL in activation of ASK1/ERK pathway.</title><p>(A) Cells were treated with DTCD (10 µM) at indicated time points and the expression of ASK1 and p-ASK1 was determined by immunoblotting. For <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> kinase activity assay, the ASK1 in the lysates was immunoprecipitated (IP) with the anti-ASK1 antibody and then incubated with MKK4 in the presence of [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP, and MKK4 phosphorylation was detected via autoradiogram. (B) Suppression of ASK1 expression by RNA interference inhibits DTCD and/or TRAIL-induced apoptosis upon ERK activation. A2780 cells were transfected with ASK1 siRNA and treated with DTCD in the presence or absence of TRAIL. The levels of p-ASK1, ASK1, p-ERK, ERK, Sp1 and DR5 were analyzed by Western Blotting. Cell apoptosis were assayed by AnnexinV/PI staining (C). (D) Oxidation of Trx will bring on dissociation of the complex Trx-1-ASK1 and activation of MAPK system. A2780 cells were treated with DTCD for 1 h. Cell protein lysates were treated with or without DTT (1 mmol/L) for 30 min and then subjected to immunoprecipitation (IP) using an anti-Trx-1 antibody and the precipitates were immunoblotted for ASK1. (E) The level of Trx-1 was detected by Western blot in whole-cell lysates from A2780 cells treated with DTCD for 1 h in the absence or presence of TRAIL (200 ng/mL). Cell lysates were processed to identify Trx-1 redox forms denoted as follows: <italic toggle="yes">red</italic>, reduced form; <italic toggle="yes">ox</italic>, oxidized form, the topmost <italic toggle="yes">ox</italic> band is the one most oxidized.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>The Combination of DTCD and TRAIL Inhibits Tumor Growth in Nude Mice Implanted with Human A2780 Xenografts</title><p>Based on the above findings, we next sought to evaluate whether the effect of DTCD alone and in combination with TRAIL could inhibit tumor growth <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. As expected, the combination therapy of TRAIL and DTCD notably inhibited the tumor growth of the A2780 xenografts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>), with T/C value 27.5% and inhibition rate 70.5%, which was prominently stronger than TRAIL-administrated group (T/C value: 83.3%, inhibition rate: 10.2%), and DTCD-treated group (T/C value: 61.7.6%, inhibition rate: 31.9%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>). The relative tumor volume (RTV) of combination group was remarkably decreased from that of vehicle group (p&lt;0.001); and more importantly, comparing with TRAIL-alone group or DTCD- alone group, combination group exerted significantly more potent activities. Thus the simultaneous administration of TRAIL and DTCD more distinctly arrested the growth of A2780 xenograft tumors, compared to either agent alone or vehicle control groups. Finally, the tumor growth suppression that was observed in the A2780 xenograft tumor model was also observed in all other xenograft (OVCAR3, ES2, and SKOV3) models tested (data not shown).</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> efficacy of TRAIL in combination with DTCD.</title><p>(A) The tumor growth inhibitory effect of DTCD and TRAIL on A2780 human xenograft models. The relative tumor volume (RTV) on day n was calculated using RTV = TVn/TV<sub>0</sub>, where TVn is the TV on day n and TV0 is the TV on day 0. (B) Therapeutic effect of treatment was expressed in terms of T/C. The calculation formula is T/C (%) = mean RTV of the treated group/mean RTV of the control group×100%.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Earlier, we reported that 2-Tellurium-bridged b-cyclodextrin (2-TeCD), one of TrxR inhibitors, could sensitize TRAIL-resistant human breast cancer cells and xenograft tumors to undergo apoptosis via Sp1-mediated DR5 up-regulation. However, we do not provide mechanistic evidence that how this effect achieved and how this effect could be correlated with the TrxR inhibitory activity <xref rid="pone.0063966-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In this study, we have examined whether DTCD (a novel synthetic TrxR inhibitor) and TRAIL interact to enhance their cytotoxicity towards ovarian carcinoma cells with the previous results, the present study show that DTCD could also potentiate TRAIL-triggered apoptosis through DR5 up-regulation. Additionally, we provided evidences to demonstrate the fact that the sensitization effects is heavily dependent on the activation of ASK1-ERK-Sp1 signaling pathway. These findings are accordance with the underlying mechanism that DTCD could inhibit activity of TrxR that reduces oxidized Trx-1.</p><p>Sp1 is well known to bind to G-rich elements such as GC-box (GGGGCGGGG) and GT-box (GGTGTGGGG) <xref rid="pone.0063966-Black1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Recently, it has been evidenced that binding of Sp1 in the promoter regions tightly regulates DR5 transcription in a variety of cancer cells, and the required specific Sp1 site was mainly found at -605 to +3 to the transcription start site <xref rid="pone.0063966-Yoshida1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. In the present study, we found that treatment with DTCD significantly induced expression of Sp1 in A2780 and SKOV3 cells that was correlated to the induction of DR5. Furthermore, the ChIP assay showed that Sp1 can directly bind to the DR5 promoter regions and regulated transcriptional expression.</p><p>Moreover, we explored the novel mechanism that ERK activation was involved in the DTCD-mediated Sp1 activation and cell death, which can be blocked significantly by PD98059, the inhibitor for ERK. According to our knowledge, the TrxR inhibitory activity of DTCD would be possible explanation for the observed results. Mammalian TrxR is a key enzyme for maintenance of intracellular reduced environment since it acts as a direct antioxidant of Trx-1. Impairment of TrxR will lead to increased levels of oxidized Trx-1. In the reduced form, Trx-1 associates with ASK-1, therefore, oxidation of Trx-1 results in ASK-1 dissociation and consequent activation of the MAPK/ERK pathway <xref rid="pone.0063966-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. This hypothesis is consistent with our results: (a) the oxidation of Trx-1 seemed complete at the highest DTCD concentrations; (b) ASK1 is phosphorylated (within 1 h) before long-lasting ERK activation and cell death; (c) In the case of ERK activation, the release of ASK1 from its complex with Trx-1. Our findings are also consistent with recent publications indicating that in TrxR inhibitor-induced apoptosis, ERK phosphorlylation was activated by the ASK1-p38 MAPK pathway <xref rid="pone.0063966-Yamagishi1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-Saggioro1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Our results represent a convincing mechanistic link between Trx/TrxR system and ERK pathways. The mechanisms by which ERK induces apoptosis are not completely clarified yet, but it is believed that might occur at many different levels involving both the extrinsic and intrinsic apoptotic pathways <xref rid="pone.0063966-Zhuang1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. For instance, inhibition of ERK phosphorylation decreases Bax expression <xref rid="pone.0063966-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and in addition, ERK activation has been shown to be crucial in the regulation of Sp1 phosphorylation and consequently Sp1 dependent proapoptosis gene transcription <xref rid="pone.0063966-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0063966-Liao1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. These facts rationalize the present observations indicating that DTCD could upregulate both of ERK and Sp1 phosphorylation and then potentiate cell death.</p><p>Based on these results, we proposed a working model for the mechanism of action of DTCD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063966-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). As already reported for some organotellurium compounds, DTCD can inhibit TrxR by irreversible covalent binding to its catalytic site <xref rid="pone.0063966-Engman2" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. This hampers the function of both mitochondrial and cytosolic TrxR that act as mediators of electron flow from NADPH to peroxiredoxins through Trx, and lead to an increase in the oxidized form of Trx and to the accumulation of hydrogen peroxide. Both of the events can improve the levels of phospho-ERK. Indeed, it has been reported that hydrogen peroxide accumulation can trigger ERK1/2 phosphorylation <xref rid="pone.0063966-Hsieh1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. On the other hand, oxidation of Trx will bring on dissociation of the complex Trx-1-ASK1 and activation of MAPK system observed as subsequent ERK1/2 phosphorylation and Sp1 activation. These events are critical in DTCD-induced DR5 expression, and renders cells more sensitive to the cytotoxic activities of TRAIL.</p><fig id="pone-0063966-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063966.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Proposed model for the molecular mechanisms underlying TRAIL and DTCD-induced apoptotic pathways.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0063966.g008.jpg"/></fig><p>In summary, here we have highlighted a novel function of DTCD: sensitizing human ovarian cancer cells to TRAIL-induced apoptosis via upregulation of DR5 which is dependent on activation of the ASK1-ERK-Sp1 signaling pathway. It deserves further assessment as a candidate mechanism for the pharmacologic control of cancer. Moreover, it is more reasonable to consider that the mechanism presented here may be shared by more compounds, and provide strong evidences that TrxR inhibitors in combination of TRAIL can be a promising strategy for cancer therapy.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0063966-Jemal1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2009</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.20006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Herzog1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Recurrent ovarian cancer: how important is it to treat to disease progression?</article-title>
<source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>7439</fpage>–<lpage>7449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15569973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-04-0683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Walczak1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walczak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ariail</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gliniak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Tumoricidal activity of tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand in vivo</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9930862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/5517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-LeBlanc1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashkenazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Apo2L/TRAIL and its death and decoy receptors</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12655296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.cdd.4401187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Almasan1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashkenazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Apo2L/TRAIL: apoptosis signaling, biology, and potential for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12787570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1359-6101(03)00029-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Li1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cleavage of BID by caspase 8 mediates the mitochondrial damage in the Fas pathway of apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9727492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81590-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Srivastava1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>TRAIL/Apo-2L: mechanisms and clinical applications in cancer</article-title>. <source>Neoplasia</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11774036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.neo.7900203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1506567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Kischkel1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kischkel</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuntharapai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Apo2L/TRAIL-dependent recruitment of endogenous FADD and caspase-8 to death receptors 4 and 5</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10894161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1074-7613(00)80212-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Schneider1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thome</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bodmer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>TRAIL receptors 1 (DR4) and 2 (DR5) signal FADD-dependent apoptosis and activate NF-kappaB</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>836</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9430228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1074-7613(00)80401-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Kendrick1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Straughn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (TRAIL) and its therapeutic potential in breast and gynecologic cancers</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17602728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2007.05.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Bevis1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bevis</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Straughn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Overcoming TRAIL resistance in ovarian carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>
<volume>119</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20638107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2010.05.034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Lane1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Côté</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grondin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couture</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piché</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Acquired resistance to TRAIL-induced apoptosis in human ovarian cancer cells is conferred by increased turnover of mature caspase-3</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16546965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-05-0362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Woods1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Woods DC, White YA, Dau C, Johnson AL (2011) TLR4 activates NF-κB in human ovarian.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2011.05.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3118942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Mao1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transfection of Smac/DIABLO sensitizes drug-resistant tumor cells to TRAIL or paclitaxel-induced apoptosis in vitro</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol res</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18029193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2007.09.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-GoncharenkoKhaider1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goncharenko-Khaider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matte</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rancourt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piché</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The inhibition of Bid expression by Akt leads to resistance to TRAIL-induced apoptosis in ovarian cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>5523</fpage>–<lpage>5536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20661217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2010.288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3007125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-McNaughton1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birmingham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cotgreave</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cyclodextrin-derived diorganyl tellurides as glutathione peroxidase mimics and inhibitors of thioredoxin reductase and cancer cell growth</article-title>. <source>J Med Chem</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14695837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/jm030916r</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Wang1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect of 2-TeCD on the expression of adhesion molecules in human umbilical vein endothelial cells under the stimulation of tumor necrosis factor-alpha. Int Immunopharmacol 9: 1087–1091.granulosa tumor cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>409</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2009.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Engman1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallegos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Water-soluble organotellurium compounds inhibit thioredoxin reductase and the growth of human cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Drug Des</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11354308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Huang1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Artificial selenoenzymes: designed and redesigned</article-title>. <source>Chem Soc Rev</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1171</fpage>–<lpage>1184</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21125082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c0cs00046a</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Nogueira1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Organoselenium and organotellurium compounds: toxicology and pharmacology</article-title>. <source>Chem Rev</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>6255</fpage>–<lpage>6285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15584701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/cr0406559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Urig1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Urig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>On the potential of thioredoxin reductase inhibitors for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Semin Cancer Biol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.semcancer.2006.09.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Pennington1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Sela</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Thioredoxin and thioredoxin reductase as redox-sensitive molecular targets for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharm Des</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3368</fpage>–<lpage>3377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18045191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Gao1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Signore</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotection against focal ischemic brain injury by inhibition of c-Jun N-terminal kinase and attenuation of the mitochondrial apoptosis-signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>694</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.jcbfm.9600062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Chou1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talalay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Quantitative analysis of dose-effect relationships: the combined effects of multiple drugs or enzyme inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Adv Enzyme Regul</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6382953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0065-2571(84)90007-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Yaginuma1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yaginuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Abnormal structure and expression of the p53 gene in human ovarian carcinoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>4196</fpage>–<lpage>4199</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1638534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Chu1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Sp1, regulation of gene expression by phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>348</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15777659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gene.2005.01.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Takeda1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naguro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ichijo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Apoptosis signal-regulating kinase 1 in stress and immune response</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source>
<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17883330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.48.113006.094606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Lin1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>2-Tellurium-bridged β-cyclodextrin, a thioredoxin reductase inhibitor, sensitizes human breast cancer cells to TRAIL-induced apoptosis through DR5 induction and NF-κB suppression</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21081474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgq234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Black1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azizkhan-Clifford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sp1 and krüppel-like factor family of transcription factors in cell growth regulation and cancer</article-title>. <source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>188</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11424081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcp.1111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Yoshida1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Promoter structure and transcription initiation sites of the human death receptor 5/TRAIL-R2 gene</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>507</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>385</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0014-5793(01)02947-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Zhang1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Lamki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Streb</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Thioredoxin-2 inhibits mitochondria-located ASK1-mediated apoptosis in a JNK-independent manner</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>
<volume>94</volume>: <fpage>1483</fpage>–<lpage>1491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.RES.0000130525.37646.a7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15117824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Yamagishi1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Numakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokomaku</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ERK1/2 are involved in low potassium-induced apoptotic signaling downstream of ASK1-p38 MAPK pathway in cultured cerebellar granule neurons</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>
<volume>1038</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15757638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.brainres.2005.01.041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Saggioro1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saggioro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rigobello</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paloschi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Folda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moggach</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Gold(III)-dithiocarbamato complexes induce cancer cell death triggered by thioredoxin redox system inhibition and activation of ERK pathway</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1128</fpage>–<lpage>1139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17961825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chembiol.2007.08.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Zhuang1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schnellmann</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A death-promoting role for extracellular signal-regulated kinase</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
<volume>319</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/jpet.106.107367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Pan1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs inhibit matrix metalloproteinase-2 via suppression of the ERK/Sp1-mediated transcription</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>32775</fpage>–<lpage>32780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M202334200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Park1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Role of mitogen-activated protein kinases in hydrogen peroxide-induced cell death in osteoblastic cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicology</source>
<volume>215</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16125295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tox.2005.07.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Liao1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufau</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase Calpha-induced derepression of the human luteinizing hormone receptor gene transcription through ERK-mediated release of HDAC1/Sin3A repressor complex from Sp1 sites</article-title>. <source>Mol Endocrinol</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1449</fpage>–<lpage>1463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18372343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/me.2008-0035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2422830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Engman2"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Engman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Maharik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birmingham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Thioredoxin reductase and cancer cell growth inhibition by organotellurium compounds that could be selectively incorporated into tumor cells</article-title>. <source>Bioorg Med Chem</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>5091</fpage>–<lpage>5100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14604673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bmc.2003.08.021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0063966-Hsieh1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papaconstantinou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Thioredoxin-ASK1 complex levels regulate ROS-mediated p38 MAPK pathway activity in livers of aged and long-lived Snell dwarf mice</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16449798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1096/fj.05-4376com</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1479092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>