
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">750</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">9882906</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3245465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3245465.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3245465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3245465</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21976771</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err271</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The roles of the cation transporters CHX21 and CHX23 in the development of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names initials="AR">A. R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names initials="D">D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names initials="J">J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names initials="HJ">H. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>School of Biosciences, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Institute of Science and the Environment, University of Worcester, Henwick Grove, Worcester WR2 6AJ, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>j.newbury@worc.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">203826</issue-id><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2011 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p><license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="err271.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="72" page="775" journal-id="J Exp Bot" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8243603"><article-title>RETRACTION: The roles of the cation transporters CHX21 and CHX23 in the development of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><volume>72</volume><issue>2</issue><date><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8243603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33428752</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genome encodes a family of 28 proteins whose members have been associated with the transport of monovalent cations across membranes. Experiments have been performed to elucidate the biochemical function and the role in plant development of two closely related members of this <italic toggle="yes">CHX</italic> family. A genotype carrying a knockout of the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> gene (At1g05580) showed no phenotype when grown in glasshouse conditions. In particular, it did not exhibit the reduced root growth phenotype observed for a knockout of its homologue <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> when exposed to elevated sodium concentration. However, it was not possible to produce plants that were homozygous knockout for both <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic>. Reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) experiments revealed that both genes are highly expressed in flower buds, flowers, and pollen. However, examination of pollen grain viability and pollen tube growth through excised styles did not reveal a phenotypic difference between the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> condition and other haplotypes. Crosses between selected mutants and wild-type plants in which the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> haplotype was produced by either the male or female parent demonstrated unequivocally that the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> haplotype could not pass through the female line. This suggests that the genes share a critical function in the development and/or function of the female gametophyte and that this function cannot be provided by other members of the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> gene family. Experiments were carried out using the heterologous expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> genotypes carrying combinations of deletions of genes involved in the transport of sodium or potassium across membranes. The results show that <italic toggle="yes">CHX23</italic> would only complement the poor colony growth phenotype associated with the deletion of the yeast gene <italic toggle="yes">kha1</italic>. The conclusion is that both <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> act in potassium homeostasis within the female gametophyte and this is discussed in terms of the diversification of gene sequence and function within the <italic toggle="yes">CHX</italic> gene family.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cation transport</kwd><kwd>CHX</kwd><kwd>female gametophyte</kwd><kwd>gene knockout</kwd><kwd>yeast</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The sequencing of the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Arabidopsis Genome Initiative, 2000</xref>) allowed the identification of large numbers of genes encoding putative membrane-bound transporters (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Mäser <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). These include members of the CPA (cation proton antiporter) superfamily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>) which are considered to be involved in monovalent cation exchange in plants, animals, fungi, and bacteria. In <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic>, the CPA1 group of transporters includes eight NHX (sodium/hydrogen exchanger) proteins. The two most highly characterized are AtNHX1, which is localized in the vacuolar membrane and enables sodium compartmentalization in the vacuole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Apse <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>) and AtNHX7 (SOS1) which is localized in the plasma membrane and is thought to be involved in sodium efflux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Wu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Shi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). The CPA2 family consists of two cation transporter families: the KEA (potassium exchange antiporters) and CHX (cation hydrogen exchangers) families. There are six members of the KEA family in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> which are thought to function as K<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporters, given their homology to proteins with this function in bacteria. The <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> CHX family comprises 28 members and these are thought to be involved in cation/H<sup>+</sup> transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).</p><p>The CHX group represents an interesting model for the study of the diversification of protein sequence and function. Many of the CHX proteins exist as pairs of close homologues, such as AtCHX13 and AtCHX14, and AtCHX21 and AtCHX23 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Such relationships clearly suggest that members of each pair possessed a relatively recent common ancestor. <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX13</italic> lie close together on chromosome 2. Their nearest homologues are <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX14</italic>, respectively and these two genes lie close together on chromosome 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online), suggesting that the current situation is a result of the duplication of part of an ancestral chromosome. This proposition is strengthened by the observation that <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX8</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX7</italic> lie next to each other further along chromosome 2 and the closest homologues to these genes are <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX6a</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX5</italic> which again lie next to one another on chromosome 1.</p><p>To date, only a few of the AtCHX transporters have been characterized in yeast and/or <italic toggle="yes">in planta</italic>. AtCHX17 is an endomembrane transporter which was shown to transport potassium in yeast and is therefore thought to have a role in potassium homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Cellier <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Maresova and Sychrova, 2006</xref>). Similarly, CHX20 has been shown to transport potassium in yeast, but only under alkaline conditions. This transporter is located in the guard cells and is thought to function in osmoregulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Padmanaban <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX13</italic> restored the growth of yeast lines mutant at both <italic toggle="yes">trk1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">trk2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Zhao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The conclusion of the authors was that AtCHX13 has a role in K<sup>+</sup> acquisition and that it is involved in high-affinity potassium uptake. The gene is expressed in roots under conditions of potassium deficiency and, using <sup>86</sup>Rb as a tracer, the protein has been shown to mediate high-affinity K<sup>+</sup> uptake in both <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> and yeast. Green fluorescent protein (GFP)-tagged versions of the protein were localized within the plasma membrane in both yeast and plant.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Cellier <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> reported that expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX17</italic> could be detected, using northern analysis, in anthers and also in roots that had been subjected to Na<sup>+</sup> stress, K<sup>+</sup> starvation, abscisic acid treatment, or low external pH. Using <italic toggle="yes">GUS</italic> constructs and <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR), they showed that the gene is expressed in the epidermal and cortical cells of mature roots in response to these stresses. Gene knockouts in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> accumulated less K<sup>+</sup> in their roots compared with the wild type in response to Na<sup>+</sup> stress and K<sup>+</sup> starvation. Their conclusion was that AtCHX17 is involved in K<sup>+</sup> acquisition and homeostasis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Maresova and Sychrova (2006)</xref> were subsequently able to demonstrate that <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX17</italic> cDNA complements a growth defect at increased pH phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">Δkha1</italic> in yeast. They showed that a GFP-tagged AtCHX17 protein had a punctuate distribution resembling that of the Golgi apparatus. They speculated that AtCHX17 and Sckha1p may both function in pH and K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis in Golgi cisternae.</p><p>AtCHX21 has been shown to be localized on the plasma membrane of root endodermal cells and has been shown to play a role in the transport of sodium into the stele. Genotypes homozygous for a knockout allele of the gene exhibited lower root growth rates in the presence of elevated sodium or potassium ions. When exposed to elevated sodium concentrations around their roots, these genotypes were shown to contain lower levels of sodium within their transpiration stream and lower amounts of sodium accumulated in their leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> reported <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> expression to be widespread around the plant following experiments employing RT-PCR and a <italic toggle="yes">CHX23</italic> promoter–<italic toggle="yes">GUS</italic> fusion. Work with a GFP fusion protein showed that AtCHX23 is located in the chloroplast envelope. They employed two types of mutant to affect the expression of this gene: an RNA interference (RNAi) line and a mutant produced using ethylmethane sulphonate (EMS) that resulted in a product with a point mutation (Phe761 to lysine). Both mutants displayed a striking phenotype in homozygous lines. Under ‘ideal conditions’ they exhibited a reduced growth rate and had yellower leaves (possessing less chlorophyll) than the wild type, and possessed smaller siliques with fewer seeds. The chloroplasts in the mutants lacked granal stacks and must have been severely compromised with regard to their photosynthetic capacity. Growth of seedlings on MS medium supplemented with 30 mM KCl increased the growth rate of the mutants and led to higher chlorophyll accumulation. On the basis of this observation, the authors suggested that CHX23 might function in K transport. However, they also reported that <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> mutants displayed a high sensitivity to NaCl, with seed germination being reduced in elevated salt conditions.</p><p>In contrast to the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> reported that <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> is preferentially expressed in pollen. This conclusion was based on the use of microarray data, RT-PCR experimentation, and the examination of transgenic plants bearing a <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> promoter–<italic toggle="yes">GUS</italic> fusion. They were unable to explain the discrepancy between their results and those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> concluded that 18 of the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> genes are specifically or preferentially expressed in the male gametophyte and speculated that some CHX proteins may play a role in osmotic adjustment and K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis as mature pollen desiccates and then rehydrates.</p><p>In this study, the role of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> in root growth was assessed to determine whether knocking out this gene results in a phenotype similar to that of plants with a mutant allele of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> (its closest homologue). Next, crosses were carried out between genotypes bearing mutant alleles of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> in an attempt to determine the phenotypic characteristics of a double mutant. Since the results indicate that the genes have an overlapping function in reproduction, experiments were carried out to discover which part of this process is blocked when the genes are mutant. Finally, heterologous expression experiments were performed in yeast to determine the ionic specificity of AtCHX23. The experimental approaches used here exploit the gene knockout resources available for two model organisms: <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. The results provide information about the function of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> but also afford an opportunity to consider the processes by which two similar genes (<italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic>) have diverged from one another in recent evolutionary history.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Genetic resources and plant growth</title><p>A seed stock from the SAIL collection (Code 899 G8), carrying a putative T-DNA insert in gene <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> (At1g05580), was obtained from the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre. Genotypes homozygous for a knockout mutant allele of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> (SLAT 01_19_03b) had already been produced (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Seedling growth, DNA extraction, general PCR methodology, and DNA sequencing were as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> using the gene- and T-DNA specific primers shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p></sec><sec><title>RT-PCR</title><p>RNA was initially extracted using a Trizol™-based method from pollen and flowers of the SAIL line (see above) and a (negative segregant) wild type in order to test whether the putative mutant produced <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> transcript. The RNA was DNase treated and used to produce cDNA by reverse transcription; primers 05580Fseq (TAATCACCACCGCAATCTTCG) and 05580R3 (ATCGTTTAAACCGGCAGTC ACCGG) were used to amplify <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> cDNA using PCR, and the products of the reaction were examined using agarose gel electrophoresis.</p><p>In order to determine the tissues in which <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> is expressed, RNA was then extracted from 100 mg of root, stem, leaf, bud, flower, and silique tissue (using Trizol extraction except for root and silique where the Qiagen RNAeasy minikit was employed). RNA was then DNase treated, reverse transcribed, and the same primers were used to amplify <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> cDNA.</p><p>To test <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> expression further, a sample of mature pollen cDNA was kindly provided by Berger's group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Pina <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). As the average length of the transcript was 600 bp, primers were designed in this region at the 3′ end of the gene and using 2.5/5 ng of pollen cDNA.</p></sec><sec><title>Complentation assays in yeast</title><p>A full length cDNA clone of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> (clone RAFL09-91-J02) was obtained from the Riken collection. This clone was transformed into <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and the insert amplified using primers containing <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>I restriction sites, with the forward primer also containing a Kozak translation initiation sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Kozak, 1991</xref>). The PCR product was cloned into pGEM-T, transformed into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, and the construct sequenced. The construct was then excised using <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>I and cloned into pYES2 which is a yeast/<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> shuttle vector with a galactose-inducible promoter upstream of the insert position. This recombinant plasmid was introduced into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> to facilitate further checking of the sequence. Along with the empty vector (pYES2) it was then transformed into the yeast strain, W303a, which is W303-1A <italic toggle="yes">MATa leu2-3/112 ura3-1 trp1<sup>−1</sup>his3-11/15 ade2-1 can1-100 GAL SUC2 mal10</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Wallis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>). Derivatives that were subsequently used were: AB11c, which is <italic toggle="yes">Δena1-4 Δnha1 Δnhx1</italic>; KTA40-2, which is <italic toggle="yes">Δena1-4 Δnha1 Δnhx1 Δkha1</italic>; LMM03, which is <italic toggle="yes">Δtrk1 Δtrk2</italic>; and LMM04, which is <italic toggle="yes">Δtrk1 Δtrk2 Δtok1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Maresova and Sychrova, 2005</xref>).</p><p>For complementation testing using the conventional colony growth assay, yeast strains were grown in liquid culture to 1.0 <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub>600</sub>, 10-fold serially diluted to 1/1000, and then 3 μl aliquots were plated onto selective medium; 10-fold serial dilutions of these initial samples were then applied. Arginine phosphate (SDAP) selective medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Rodriguez Navarro and Ramos, 1984</xref>) was used because of its low potassium level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Padmanaban <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Plates were incubated at 30 °C for assessment of colony growth. Each complementation assay was repeated on five different occasions using independent colonies, and the results shown were consistently obtained in all five tests.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout alleles</title><p>DNA was extracted from individual plants carrying a putative T-DNA insertion in gene <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> (At1g05580). Primers were designed to regions of the gene and the T-DNA insert and PCR products were sequenced. These demonstrated that the T-DNA was inserted in the predicted exon 5 of the gene (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). Since the seed stock received contained heterozygous lines with respect to the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> allele, it was also possible, by genetic segregation, to obtain lines homozygous for either the wild type or the mutant <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> allele for use in comparisons in subsequent phenotypic tests.</p><p>RT-PCR was carried out to ensure that no transcript was produced in the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> insertional mutant. As <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> had been reported to be preferentially expressed in pollen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), whole flower cDNA was used to test for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> expression from wild-type and insertional mutant lines. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> shows that the putative mutant form of <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> is a knockout since the 1.5 kb cDNA amplified from wild-type flowers is absent. Additional characterization was also carried out on the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> insertional mutant previously described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> also shows that the cDNA produced using template RNA from root tissue of wild-type plants was absent when RNA from the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> insertional mutant was used.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>RT-PCR analysis of <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> insertional mutants showing the absence of transcripts (compared with the wild type). Col(0) (wild type) root cDNA, <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic> mutant root cDNA, and genomic DNA (G) were used as substrates in PCR amplifications using the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic>-specific primers NaT<sub>1</sub>F<sub>5</sub> and NaT<sub>1</sub>R<sub>5</sub>, and then re-amplified using nested primers NaT<sub>1</sub>F<sub>6</sub> and NaT<sub>1</sub>R<sub>6</sub> (A). Actin was amplified using primers ActF and ActR. Flower cDNA samples from Col(0) (wild type) and the <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> mutant were used as substrates in PCR amplifications using primers 05580Fseq and 05580R3 (B).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f01_ht.jpg"/></fig><p>The copy numbers of the T-DNA insertions in the genotypes bearing the knockout <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> alleles were assessed. The use of a T-DNA-specific probe revealed a single T-DNA insert in the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> knockout line using Southern analysis (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). In addition, the use of an appropriate restriction enzyme showed that there is only one T-DNA insertion within the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> locus (rather than a tandem insertion). Copy number in the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> mutant line was assessed using fluorescent <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH). Chromosomal spreads from flower buds from both wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout plants were probed with a T-DNA sequence. No hybridization was detected in wild-type cells but hybridization was evident at a single locus in <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Fluorescent <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) to identify the number of T-DNA insertions in the mutant <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic>. Cells undergoing prophase I were isolated from Col(0) and <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> flower buds. FISH was carried out using a digoxigenin (DIG) nick-translated pBluescript T-DNA-specific probe followed by anti-DIG–rhodamine (red label) and viewed using a fluorescence microscope. No hybridization to chromosomes was apparent in Col(0) chromosomes. Hybridization to a single locus is apparent for <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> chromosomes, and for some cells it is clear that the <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> genotype is homozygous for the T-DNA insertion since there is hybridization to the same region of sister chromosomes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f02_3c.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Phenotypic analysis of plants containing combinations of knockout alleles</title><p>During detailed analyses of the growth of sets of <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout and wild-type plants grown under ideal conditions in a glasshouse, no observations of differential chlorophyll content of the two genotypes were made (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Evans, 2008</xref>). While roots of seedlings carrying a knockout of <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic> had been shown to grow more slowly in the presence of 50 mM and 100 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), roots homozygous for the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout grew at the same rate as the wild type (not shown).</p><p>In order to determine whether the close structural homologues AtCHX23 and AtCHX21 possessed overlapping functions, attempts were made to produce homozygous double mutant lines for study. Crosses were made between lines homozygous for the knockout allele at either the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> (unlinked) loci. The genotypes of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrids (<italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>) were confirmed using PCR with four pairs of allele-specific primers. The plants were allowed to self-pollinate and the F<sub>2</sub> population was screened. Of the 76 individuals examined, 1/16 would be expected to be homozygous knockout for both <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic>; however, no such double mutants were observed. In a further test, 40 progeny of the F<sub>2</sub>s with the genotype <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> and 40 with the genotype <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> were allowed to self-fertilize and their progeny characterized using PCR. In both cases, one would expect 1/4 of the progeny to have the genotype <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup>. However, once again all other possible genotypes were observed except for the homozygous double mutant. The probability that a double knockout did not exist in the sample is <italic toggle="yes">&gt;</italic>99.999%.</p><p>Since 100% germination was obtained in these experiments (data not shown), the reason for the absence of double mutants from the progeny populations appeared to lie at an earlier stage of development. To help establish the stage at which lethality is expressed, the expression of the genes was assessed in different tissues. RNA was extracted from root, stem, leaf, flower bud, flower, and silique tissue, and locus-specific primers were designed to amplify the <italic toggle="yes">CHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CHX23</italic> transcripts using RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> transcript was present in the root, leaf, and flower, and very low levels were present in the stem and flower bud. <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> transcript was detected only in flower buds and flowers. Hence, <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> has wider expression within the plant but both genes are expressed in flower buds and flowers. RT-PCR was next carried out on pollen cDNA. Using a cDNA library produced from the RNA of mature pollen, it was shown that both genes are expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). Hence, it appeared possible that the lethality observed in the absence of a functional copy of one of the genes may be due a lesion in pollen development.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>RT-PCR analysis showing the expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic>, and an actin control in different tissues. Amplification was for 45 cycles for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> but 30 cycles for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> and the actin control. R, root; St, stem, L, leaf; B, bud; F, flower; Sil, silique.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f03_ht.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>RT-PCR analysis of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> using mature pollen cDNA. <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> cDNA was initially amplified for 30 cycles using NaT<sub>1</sub>F<sub>7</sub> and NaT<sub>1</sub>R<sub>7</sub>, and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> cDNA using 05580F6 and 05580R<sub>3</sub>. PCR products were then amplified for a further 30 cycles using the same primers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f04_ht.jpg"/></fig><p>Tests were carried out on pollen viability using the Alexander vital stain. Pollen was collected from plants that were wild type, were homozygous mutants for either <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic>, or were homo-insufficient mutants recovered from the double knockout cross (<italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>). Half of the pollen produced by the latter mutants will be <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup>. However, non-viability of a proportion of the pollen was not detected from any of the parental genotypes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S4</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online).</p><p>To assess pollen tube growth in a ‘semi-<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>’ manner, wild-type pistils were removed from flower buds at anthesis, pollinated with wild-type or mutant pollen (homozygous knockout mutants or <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>), and examined microscopically over time. Wild-type pollen reached the base of the pistil 24 h after pollination. Indistinguishable results were obtained even though half of the pollen from some genotypes was <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>‘Semi-<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>’ pollen tube growth. Emasculated buds from Col(0) (wild-type) plants were pollinated with pollen from Col(0) or a mutant (<italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup>) genotype. Twenty-four hours later the stigmas were fixed, stained with aniline blue, and viewed under a UV microscope using a DAPI (4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole) filter. No differences in pollen tube growth were observed for this mutant or when pollen from a <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> mutant was used (not shown).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f05_ht.jpg"/></fig><p>One method for testing for reduced transmission of genetic material through either gametophyte is to make reciprocal backcrosses of selected genotypes to the wild type. For example, half of the gametes produced by a <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> parent will be <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup>. If this is used as the male parent in a backcross to the wild type, and the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic> function is required for pollen production, then one would observe a clear shift from the expected ratio of genotypes in the progeny produced; none of the progeny would carry the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> allele. This test was used with four classes of backcrosses, each involving 25 pairs of plants. The results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) demonstrate that where the male parent was <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>, the ratio of genotypes in the progeny population was as expected, with normal transmission of the mutant through the male gamete. However, the data show that there was no transmission of the mutant alleles through the female line. This is clear evidence that the <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–</sup> condition is lethal at some stage in the development or function of the female gametophyte.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The expected and actual ratios of genotypes obtained following reciprocal crosses between the wild type (Col-0) and <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> or <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crosses (male×female)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expected ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed ratio</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Col-0 × <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1 (<italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/+</sup>:<italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup>)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25:0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Col-0 × <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1 (<italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/+</sup>:<italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25:0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> × Col-0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1 (<italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/+</sup>:<italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13:12</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>For each cross, the male parent is given first.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>If female gametophyte function is compromised where both AtCHX21 and AtCHX23 are absent, one would expect this to be reflected in the number of developing seeds in the siliques of specific genotypes. This prediction was confirmed when seed number was found to be lower in siliques of the self-pollinated genotypes <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> than in the wild type (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). As a consequence, the former genotypes also have shorter siliques (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.001). Examination of siliques revealed undeveloped ovules/aborted seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>) which failed to mature along with the other seeds.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Testing for transmission of double mutant haplotypes through male and female gametophytes. Self-pollination was allowed for a range of genotypes, and the effect on seed number and silique length was assessed. (A) Mean seed number per silique. (B) Mean silique length. Col(0), wild type; 21ko, <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/+</sup>; 23ko, <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/+</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup>; AaBB, <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/+</sup>; aaBb, <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup>. (This figure is available in colour at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f06_3c.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Seed development was monitored in self-pollinated Col(0) (wild type) and <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>–/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>+/–</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">chx21</italic><sup>+/–</sup><italic toggle="yes">chx23</italic><sup>–/–</sup> plants. Unfertilized ovules/aborted seeds were observed in the mutants compared with normal seed development in Col(0) siliques. (This figure is available in colour at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f07_3c.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Heterologous expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> in yeast</title><p>The results obtained using gene knockouts <italic toggle="yes">in planta</italic> suggest that <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> have overlapping functions that are required for the development of female gametes when the plant is grown under ‘ideal conditions’. Sequence homology strongly suggests that these genes encode monovalent cation transporters and there is experimental evidence, using heterologous expression, that some members of the AtCHX family act to transport potassium. In order to test whether AtCHX23 functions to move potassium across a membrane, a full-length cDNA derived from the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> gene was incorporated into the vector pYES2 and transformed into yeast cells. This vector has a galactose-inducible promoter upstream of the introduced sequence so that expression can be induced as desired. Initially, the transgenes were expressed in yeast strain W303a; the cells were homogenized and protein samples subjected to western analysis. The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>) showed that the transgene was expressed following induction using galactose.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Demonstration that a transgenic yeast line produces AtCHX23. Yeast transformants containing the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> construct in pYES2 within yeast strain W303a were grown in liquid YNB in glucose followed by (inductive) galactose until stationary phase. P100 protein fractions were extracted, resolved using 8% SDS–PAGE, and subjected to western analysis. The filter was probed with anti-CHX23 (diluted 1/1000), followed by goat anti-rat secondary antibody conjugated to horseradish peroxidase. AtCHX23 is absent from the lane containing protein extracted from transformed yeast cells growing in glucose (lane 1) but occurs in cells transferred to galactose (lane 2: galactose induces transgene expression in the construct used). Further details of the primary antiserum production are available in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f08_ht.jpg"/></fig><p>Colony growth tests were then carried out using strains of yeast that are deficient in several monovalent cation transporter functions. Since AtCHX21 has been shown to export sodium <italic toggle="yes">in planta</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) a test for sodium tolerance in yeast was performed using the triple mutant AB11c; this strain lacks both the sodium-extruding ATPase genes (<italic toggle="yes">ena1-4</italic>) and sodium/proton antiporters (<italic toggle="yes">nha1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">nhx1</italic>). The expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> within AB11c did not rescue colony growth under sodium stress (not shown).</p><p>There is evidence to suggest that the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> gene family may have a role in potassium homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). To test a potential role for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> in high affinity potassium uptake, the gene was transferred to LMM03, a yeast strain lacking the high affinity potassium transporters <italic toggle="yes">trk1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">trk2</italic>. Mutants lacking these two genes were unable to sustain colony growth below 10 mM KCl at pH 5.7; the addition of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> failed to restore growth under these conditions. As the yeast gene <italic toggle="yes">tok1</italic> also contributes to some potassium uptake when this cation is at low concentrations, the assays were repeated using strain LMM04 which is <italic toggle="yes">Δtrk1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Δtrk2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Δtok1</italic>. However, no restoration of colony growth below 10 mM KCl was observed (not shown).</p><p>kha1p is the closest yeast protein homologue to the plant AtCHX family and is also a member of the CPA2 superfamily. A phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">Δkha1</italic> is reduced yeast colony growth at alkaline pH which disappears with increasing potassium concentration. Strain KTA 40-2 is <italic toggle="yes">Δena1-4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Δnha1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Δnhx1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Δkha1</italic>, and colonies of this genotype did not grow well on medium adjusted to pH 7.5 containing 1, 5, or 25 mM KCl. However, the addition of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> complemented this mutation at 1 mM and 5 mM KCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Also, at pH 4.5 and 5.5, strains containing <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> were more tolerant to 800 mM KCl compared with those bearing the empty vector (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). To confirm that the results were due to the expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> under the control of the galactose-inducible promoter, the same tests were performed on cultures grown in glucose rather than galactose. No complementation was observed in strain KTA 40-2 under these conditions.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><p>Colony growth test, in SDAP medium, of yeast strain KTA 40-2 (<italic toggle="yes">Δena1-4 Δnha1 Δnhx1 Δkha1</italic>) containing: 1, pYES2 (‘empty vector’); 2, pYES2-<italic toggle="yes">CHX23</italic> (A) in the presence of 800 mM KCl at pH 4.5 and (B) in the presence of 1 mM KCl at pH 7.5. The inoculated samples were serially diluted (10-fold) from left to right.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jexboterr271f09_ht.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The examination of the growth and development of a <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout mutant has not revealed a phenotype. The plants grew and flowered at the same rate as the wild type in a glasshouse. As in the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>, the striking phenotype with reduced growth and less chlorophyll reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> was not observed. These authors were working with two genotypes exhibiting lowered expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic>. It was not possible to explain this difference. The lack of phenotype of the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout in the present study extends to the absence of an effect on root growth rate in the presence of elevated sodium concentrations which had previously been reported for a knockout of the close homologue <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This result for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> was accompanied by the demonstration of its role in the endodermis loading sodium ions into the transpiration stream when that cation is present in high concentrations around the roots.</p><p>In spite of the lack of a mutant phenotype for the <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> knockout, it was demonstrated that it is not possible to produce progeny plants that are homozygous knockout for both <italic toggle="yes">Atchx23</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Atchx21</italic>. This must mean that there is functional redundancy and that both genes can play a role that is required at some point in the reproductive process. This function appears to be absolutely required since when no functional copy of either gene is present, progeny plants are not produced. Hence, the sequence homology of these recently diverged genes is matched by the conservation of a critical shared function. It also means that the function is required when monovalent cation levels are not elevated since the attempts to produce the double mutants were carried out under ideal glasshouse conditions. Further, it means that the essential function performed by <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> is not provided by any of the many other <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> genes within the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> genome.</p><p>Following this discovery, the effect of the removal of this function on pollen development was tested. Although both genes are expressed in pollen [according to the present RT-PCR results and the reports of both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (2004)</xref>], it was not possible to detect an altered phenotype in either pollen grains or pollen tube growth within excised styles. Indeed, a critical experiment designed to determine the location of the lesion in reproductive development using mutant genotypes as either male or female parents in crosses with wild-type plants revealed unequivocally that homozygous double knockouts cannot be obtained because the <italic toggle="yes">chx21<sup>–</sup>chx23<sup>–</sup></italic> genotype is not transmitted through the female line. This finding is consistent with the observation of undeveloped ovules/aborted seeds in the shorter siliques that have arisen from the self-pollination of plants that will produce some <italic toggle="yes">chx21<sup>–</sup>chx23<sup>–</sup></italic> gametes. These results mean that experimentation should now be carried out to determine the precise female gametophyte tissue in which <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> share their essential function; an interesting question is whether the genes act before or after fertilization.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sze <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> concluded that 18 of the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> genes are specifically or preferentially expressed in the male gametophyte and speculated that some CHX proteins may play a role in osmotic adjustment and K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis as mature pollen desiccates and then rehydrates. The present results do not preclude a key role for <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> and/or <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> in pollen development and function. The removal of their function might pass unobserved if there is sufficient functional redundancy and their specific function is shared by other <italic toggle="yes">CHX</italic> genes. If these genes do play a role in pollen biology then one would assume that the molecular function, cation specificity, and membrane location would be the same in both male and female gametophytes.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> reported that AtCHX23 is located in the chloroplast envelope following an experiment with a CHX23–GFP fusion protein. Furthermore, they reported that the chloroplasts in the mutants lacked granal stacks. As in most plants, plastids are maternally inherited and it is interesting to speculate that a lesion in a plastid function is responsible for the breakdown of the female gametophyte in these mutants. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Song <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (2004)</xref> point out, conditions that impair various metabolic functions of the plastid (which include, for example, the synthesis of amino acid-specific lipids, carotenoids, purines, and pyrimidines) will inevitably lead to wider disturbances in the biochemistry and physiology of the plant.</p><p>The experiments involving the heterologous expression of <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> made use of a range of yeast genotypes bearing combinations of gene deletions. The results of the complementation assays suggest that AtCHX21 and AtCHX23 are involved in potassium tolerance. Tolerance levels varied with pH, with complementation occurring at high (800 mM) potassium concentrations at pH 4.5 and low levels (1–25 mM) at pH 7.5. As 800 mM potassium is a much higher concentration than naturally occurring levels, the most probable function of these CHXs appears to be in potassium homeostasis. The ability to rescue yeast colony growth at alkaline pH at low potassium concentrations has similarities to the <italic toggle="yes">Δkha1</italic> phenotype. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Maresova and Sychrova (2005)</xref> showed that the reduced growth rate of the <italic toggle="yes">Δkha1</italic> strain at alkaline pH could be overcome by the addition of potassium. <italic toggle="yes">kha1</italic> is the closest yeast homologue to the CHXs, being a member of the CPA2 gene family. The present experiments demonstrating complementation of the yeast <italic toggle="yes">kha1</italic> gene by <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> follow those of Maresova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2006) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Padmanaban <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> who reported complementation of this yeast gene by <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX17</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX20</italic>, respectively. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Zhao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> showed that <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX13</italic> complements mutations at the <italic toggle="yes">trk1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">trk2</italic> loci that are involved in high-affinity potassium uptake.</p><p>How do the current results relate to the previously reported role of AtCHX21 in endodermal sodium transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Hall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>)? It has been confirmed that both <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX21</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX23</italic> are expressed in root and flowers. It is proposed that the observed action of AtCHX21 in loading Na into the transpiration stream when the roots are exposed to high sodium levels is not of adaptive value to the plant. Most <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> genotypes (including Col-0, the genetic background of the genotypes used in these studies) are not adapted to saline conditions, and the phenotype observed appears to occur when the plants are exposed to high salinity conditions that they cannot survive in nature. The loading of sodium ions into the transpiration stream appears physiologically perverse and, in the light of the current results, it is proposed that the adaptive role played by the AtCHX21 protein within the endodermal cells is actually the control of potassium levels in the stele. Because of the demonstration that AtCHX21 (or AtCHX23) is required for the normal function of the female gametophyte, it is now apparent that AtCHX21 can play a role in more than one tissue. It may also play a role in pollen development, although if so the present results suggest that this function can also be covered by the products of other CHX genes. This represents an interesting model for the study of the diversification of sequence and function within a gene family.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1"><bold>Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> The relative positions of nine members of the <italic toggle="yes">AtCHX</italic> gene family. The arrows show the closest homologues between pairs of genes; the numbers indicate the percentage identity at the amino avid level.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1"><bold>Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Diagram representing the knockout mutant of gene At1g05580, showing primer positions relative to base 1 of the At1g05580 coding region (arrows) and the regions they amplify.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1"><bold>Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Southern analysis.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err271/DC1"><bold>Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Pollen viability testing.</p><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_63_1_59__index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_err271_00060665_file001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apse</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aharon</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snedden</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumwald</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salt tolerance conferred by over-expression of a vacuolar Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>1256</fpage><lpage>1258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10455050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.285.5431.1256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Arabidopsis Genome Initiative</collab><article-title>Analysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35048692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cellier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conejero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepetit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casse</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of AtCHX17, a member of the cation/H+ exchangers, CHX family, from <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> suggests a role in K+ homeostasis</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2004</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15341627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02177.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Studley</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny as a guide to structure and function of membrane transport proteins</article-title><source>Molecular Membrane Biology</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15204625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09687680410001720830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> cation transporters <italic toggle="yes">in planta</italic> and through expression in yeast (<italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>)</article-title><year>2008</year><comment>PhD thesis, University of Birmingham, UK</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newbury</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of CHX21: a putative sodium transporter in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16513816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jxb/erj092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of vertebrate messenger RNA sequences—intimations of translational Control</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><year>1991</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1955461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1083/jcb.115.4.887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2289952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maresova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sychrova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> kha1 deletion mutants</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04410.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maresova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sychrova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> CHX17 gene complements the kha1 deletion phenotypes in</article-title><source>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/yea.1424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17133624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mäser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic relationships within cation transporter families of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>1646</fpage><lpage>1667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11500563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.126.4.1646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC117164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanaban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanroj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Participation of endomembrane cation/H<sup>+</sup> exchanger AtCHX20 in osmoregulation of guard cells</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2007</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17337534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.106.092155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1913804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feijo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene family analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> pollen transcriptome reveals biological implications for cell growth, divisions control and gene expression regulation</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15908605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.104.057935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1150393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez Navarro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual system for potassium transport in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Journal of Bacteriology</source><year>1984</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6384187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.159.3.940-945.1984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC215750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishitani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> salt tolerance gene SOS1 encodes a putative Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+</sup> antiporter</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>6896</fpage><lpage>6901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.120170197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC18772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jagendorf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A probable Na<sup>+</sup> (K<sup>+</sup>)/H<sup>+</sup> exchanger on the chloroplast envelope functions in pH homeostasis and choloroplast development in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source> Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>10211</fpage><lpage>10216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0403709101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC454189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15220473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanaban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cellier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression patterns of a novel AtCHX gene family highlight potential roles in osmotic adjustment and K<sup>+</sup> homeostasis in pollen development</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2532</fpage><lpage>2547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.104.046003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC523320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrebet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombination mutation in <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> identifies a novel eukaryotic topoisomerase</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2546682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(89)90855-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SOS1, a genetic locus essential for salt tolerance and potassium acquisition</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.8.4.617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC161124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>N-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanaban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschi</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AtCHX13 is a plasma membrane K<sup>+</sup> transporter</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1104/pp.108.124248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2556814</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>