
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">349</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plospath</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101238921</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3111544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3111544.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3111544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3111544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21695245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-10-00233</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bacteria-Induced Dscam Isoforms of the Crustacean, <italic toggle="yes">Pacifastacus leniusculus</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam Isoforms Induced by Bacteria</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watthanasurorot</surname><given-names initials="A">Apiruck</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiravanichpaisal</surname><given-names initials="P">Pikul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="H">Haipeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names initials="I">Irene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names initials="K">Kenneth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Comparative Physiology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>National Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology, National Science and Technology Development Agency, Pathumthani, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Marine Environmental Science, College of Oceanography and Environmental Science, Xiamen University, Xiamen, Fujian, People's Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names initials="DS">David S.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Stanford University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Kenneth.Soderhall@ebc.uu.se</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AW PJ IS KS. Performed the experiments: AW HL. Wrote the paper: AW PJ IS KS.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">197212</issue-id><elocation-id>e1002062</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>06</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-24 12:25:24.787"><day>24</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Watthanasurorot et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS Pathog" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4856373"><article-title>Retraction: Bacteria-Induced Dscam Isoforms of the Crustacean, <italic toggle="yes">Pacifastacus leniusculus</italic>
</article-title><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>4</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><elocation-id>e1005630</elocation-id><source>PLoS Pathogens</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4856373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27144534</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The Down syndrome cell adhesion molecule, also known as Dscam, is a member of the immunoglobulin super family. Dscam plays an essential function in neuronal wiring and appears to be involved in innate immune reactions in insects. The deduced amino acid sequence of Dscam in the crustacean <italic toggle="yes">Pacifastacus leniusculus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam), encodes 9(Ig)-4(FNIII)-(Ig)-2(FNIII)-TM and it has variable regions in the N-terminal half of Ig2 and Ig3 and the complete Ig7 and in the transmembrane domain. The cytoplasmic tail can generate multiple isoforms. <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam can generate more than 22,000 different unique isoforms. Bacteria and LPS injection enhanced the expression of PlDscam, but no response in expression occurred after a white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) infection or injection with peptidoglycans. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam silencing did not have any effect on the replication of the WSSV. Bacterial specific isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were shown to have a specific binding property to each tested bacteria, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. The bacteria specific isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were shown to be associated with bacterial clearance and phagocytosis in crayfish.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Invertebrate animals lack an adaptive immune system and have no antibodies. Vertebrate antibodies belong to the immunoglobulin super family of proteins, and one other member of this large family is the Down syndrome cell adhesion molecule or <italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic>. Of specific interest is that Dscam proteins in invertebrates show a great diversity of isoforms, and its gene structure in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and other insect species allow for more than 30,000 different isoforms. Dscam proteins are important for the interaction between neurons in insects, but recently a role for this hypervariable protein in immune defense has been shown. Here, we show that Dscam proteins with similar highly variable structures are present in a crustacean, the freshwater crayfish <italic toggle="yes">Pacifastacus leniusculus</italic>. We also found that specific isoforms could be induced in the animal after injection of different bacteria. The Dscam isoforms induced by <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> were found to cluster together in a phylogenetic analysis. Furthermore we produced recombinant proteins of the different isoforms that were induced by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and we could demonstrate that these proteins can bind specifically to their corresponding bacteria. The bacteria specific isoforms of Dscam were also shown to be associated with bacterial clearance and phagocytosis in crayfish. Our study therefore provides new insights into the function of invertebrate Dscams in immunity.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The immunoglobulin super family (IgSF) is composed of proteins that contain at least one immunoglobulin domain <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Garver1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Several members of IgSF are expressed on the cell surface and there serve as receptors for diverse ligands, and contribute to a variety of cellular activities <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dermody1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In vertebrates, many IgSF members play essential roles as immune molecules (also known as antibodies) by recognizing non-self entities and then promoting their elimination <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Hutter1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Although it appears as if all invertebrates lack true antibodies, diversified IgSF molecules have been shown to be involved in immune defense of several invertebrates <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watson1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. However, this does not imply that the diversification of IgSF in invertebrates have any relation to the antibody diversification in vertebrates <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Recently, one IgSF member, the Down syndrome cell adhesion molecule gene or <italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic>, that can generate hypervariable isoforms through alternative splicing was shown to act as an opsonin and to enhance phagocytosis in insects <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watson1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic> was first detected on the human chromosome 21q22, a region associated with Down Syndrome <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Yamakawa1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Then, orthologues of Dscam were identified in various species and the typical domain structure of the <italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic> gene is highly conserved. The Dscam molecules are widely expressed in the nervous system and play an essential role in neural circuit formation <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Agarwala1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Hattori1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Moreover, transcripts of fly Dscam was detected in fat body cells and hemocytes, which both are important components of the insect immune system <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watson1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Boehm1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. The Dscam in hemocytes of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Anopheles gambiae</italic> can bind to <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and potentially acts as both a phagocytic receptor and as an opsonin. In the mosquito, <italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic> can generate pathogen-specific spliced forms upon immune challenge <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. These findings provide some evidences that Dscam may have functions not only in neuronal wiring, but also in innate immunity in insects.</p><p>In the present study, the full-length cDNA and variable regions of <italic toggle="yes">P. leniusculus</italic> Dscam (<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam) were identified and characterized. We also present results showing that different isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam can be induced by immune challenge, that they can bind bacteria and that they are important in bacterial clearance.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Isolation and characterization of the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam</title><p>A large open reading frame of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam (6,009 bp) was identified that encodes a polypeptide of 2,002 aa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The closest sequence matching that of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was Dscam of <italic toggle="yes">L. vannamei</italic> (identity <italic toggle="yes"> = </italic>85%). Domain homology analysis using SMART showed that the deduced amino acid sequence contains a signal peptide at amino acids 1–24, ten tandem repeated immunoglobulin domains (Ig), six fibronectin type III domains (FNIII) and a transmembrane domain (TM). The domain organization of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam is 9(Ig)-4(FNIII)-(Ig)-2(FNIII)-TM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). It also has a conserved cell attachment sequence (Arg-Gly-Asp: RGD motif) between Ig6 and Ig7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The sequence in the 3′ UTR contains a polyadenylation signal (AATAA) and is located at 55 bp upstream of the poly A tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g001">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Identification and characterization of Dscam in <italic toggle="yes">P. leniusculus</italic>.</title><p>A) Amino acid sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam; double underlining represents signal peptide, while the Immunoglobulin (Ig) and Fibronectin type III (FNIII) domains are indicated by light and dark gray shading, respectively. A conserved RGD motif between Ig6 and Ig7 is indicated by single underlining. In addition, the single transmembrane domain is shown in a box. B) Schematic diagram showing the domain organization of the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam protein. C) 3′ UTR containing the polyadenylation signal (AATAA) is indicated by double underlining and a stop codon is bold and underlined.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Expression of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam transcript diversity</title><p>To identify the variable regions of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam, several regions of the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were amplified using different primer pairs and the location of each pair of primers is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s001">Figure S1</xref>. Fifty clones of each of the six amplified regions were selected and sequenced, translated and aligned using ClustalW. Alternatively spliced mRNA segments of the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were detected in the N-terminal of Ig2 and Ig3, in the entire length of the Ig7 domain, in the transmembrane domain and in the cytoplasmic tail (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g002">Figure 2B–E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). In total 12, 29, 32 and 2 alternative spliced forms of the exons encoding Ig2, Ig3, Ig7 and the transmembrane domains, respectively were detected and therefore at least 22,000 different unique isoforms could in theory be generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g002">Figure 2A–2E</xref>). The other domains were highly conserved, especially Ig8-FNIII4. The cytoplasmic tail of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam contains some highly conserved motifs similar to the corresponding area in Dscams of other species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s001">Figure S1B</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>High diversity regions of Dscam in freshwater crayfish.</title><p>A) Diagram showing the locations of putative alternatively spliced exons of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. The variable regions are indicated at the N-terminal parts of Ig2 (red) and Ig3 (pink) and complete Ig7 (blue) and transmembrane (green) domains in crayfish. The number of alternative exons is presented by bars under the diagram. B–E) Multiple amino acid sequence alignment of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam variable regions of Ig2(B), Ig3(C), Ig7(D) and transmembrane domain (E) aligned by ClustalW, Dark shading indicates the boundary of each domain.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Tissue expression and phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam</title><p>In crayfish, <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was abundantly expressed in the heart, moderately expressed in the testis, the hematopoietic tissue (HPT), brain and nerve, whereas low expression was detected in the stomach, gill, muscle and hemocytes. The <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was not detected in hepatopancreas or in intestine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g003">Figure 3A</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Tissue distribution and phylogenetic analysis.</title><p>A) The expression of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was studied in various tissues, such as HP  =  Hepatopancreas, ST =  Stomach, IN =  Intestine, G =  Gill, TT =  Testis, H =  Heart, M =  Muscle, B =  Brain, HC =  Hemocyte and N =  abdominal nerve. A 40S ribosomal gene was used as an internal control. B) A phylogram based on multiple alignments between <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic> and other Dscam proteins; <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAF71926">AAF71926</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Apis mellifera</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAT96374">AAT96374</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Homo sapiens</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AF217525">AF217525</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Mus musculus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="NP_112451">NP_112451</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Danio rerio</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAT36313">AAT36313</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Daphnia pulex</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ACC65888">ACC65888</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Xenopus tropicalis</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="NP_001136135">NP_001136135</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_416734">XP_416734</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Bos taurus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_002693048">XP_002693048</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Canis familiaris</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_546506">XP_546506</ext-link>) <italic toggle="yes">Rattus norvegicus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAL57167">AAL57167</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Macaca mulatta</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_002803170">XP_002803170</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Callithrix jacchus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_002761477">XP_002761477</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Tribolium castaneum</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="NP_001107841">NP_001107841</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Nasonia vitripennis</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_001599258">XP_001599258</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_001949262">XP_001949262</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Equus caballus</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="XP_001491675">XP_001491675</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Aedes aegypti</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="EAT37388">EAT37388</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Aplysia californica</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ABS30432">ABS30432</ext-link>) and <italic toggle="yes">Litopenaeus vannamei</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ACZ26466">ACZ26466</ext-link>). A human junctional adhesion molecule A or JAMA was used as outgroup (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="NP_058642">NP_058642</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>A phylogenetic analysis clearly separated the Dscam proteins of vertebrates and invertebrates in two different groups and <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam clustered with other members of invertebrate Dscams (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>LPS and bacteria injection induce <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam transcription</title><p>To investigate whether immune challenge induces higher expression of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam in crayfish hemocytes, LPS, peptidoglycan (PG), <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> or WSSV was used as immune elicitors. The results of quantitative RT-PCR revealed that the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam mRNA expression was significantly induced by LPS-, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli-</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> at 6 h to 24 h post injection compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g004">Figure 4A, 4C, 4D</xref>). In contrast, the expression profile of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam in PG- and WSSV- injected animals was not changed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g004">Figure 4B and 4E</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Expression profiles of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam in response to immune challenge.</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam expression was significantly higher than the control from 6 h post-injection with LPS (A), <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (C) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (D). In contrast, PG (B) and WSSV (E)-injection did not have any effect on the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam expression level. The asterisk indicates that the expression levels are significantly different (*<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;0.05</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">**P&lt;0.01</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Clustering of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms in hemocytes during a bacterial infection</title><p>In order to characterize the major isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic> in hemocytes of normal and bacteria injected crayfish, <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam cDNA fragments encompassing the signal peptide to Ig3 from each group were amplified and cloned (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). A total of 50 clones of each cDNA fragment were sequenced. Ten isoforms were detected in all groups, i.e. normal, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> injected and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> injected crayfish. These isoforms were named as Normal isoform (N) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s005">Table S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s006">Table S3</xref>). Furthermore ten abundant isoforms were found only in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> injected group and were named <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> induced isoform (E) or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> induced isoform (S), respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s005">Table S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s006">Table S3</xref>). All isoforms were subjected to multiple sequence alignment using clustalW. The similarity of each <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoform was then clustered by the maximum likelihood (ML) and Bayesian inference (BI) methods. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g005">Figure 5B</xref>, the clustering tree contained two major branches. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> induced isoforms were separated into one branch, whereas the other branch consisted of two sub-branches of normal isoform and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> induced isoform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g005">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Bacteria-induced <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms.</title><p>A) Different isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were amplified from hemocyte cDNA of normal crayfish, at 12 h post injection with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. The PCR products were detected on 1.2% agarose gel. The PCR-products from normal crayfish (N) are shown in lanes 1–3, while PCR-products from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (E) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (S) injected animals are shown in lanes 4–6 and 7–9 respectively. B) Clustering of all <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms is based on the similarity of their amino acid sequence. The gray shaded boxes represent the chosen isoforms. C) Multiple amino acid sequence alignment of the isoforms E2, N6 and S9 aligned by ClustalW. Dark shading indicates the boundary of each domain.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>The E isoforms of PlDscam isoforms had a VNKEYIIRGDSA(F/I)LKCSIPSFVA(D/N) motif and a EIGSPATFTCRAQAHPVPQY motif present at the N-terminal of the Ig2 and Ig3 domains, respectively. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g005">Figure 5B and 5C</xref> the isoforms N6, E2 and S9 are different, and therefore we used these isoforms as representative alternative spliced forms of normal, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>-induced isoforms for a bacterial binding assay.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Binding of r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>
</title><p>Recombinant proteins covering the Ig1-Ig3 domains of the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>lDscam isoforms of N6, E2 and S9 were produced and tested whether these domains have any putative function in binding to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli or S. aureus</italic>. These proteins were expressed in bacterial systems and the size of all soluble recombinant proteins was ∼67 kDa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). All recombinant proteins were fused with GST at the N-terminus and contained the Ig1-Ig3 domains. We used these r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscams in bacterial binding assays to reveal whether different isoforms are capable of direct binding to bacteria. The GST protein was used as a non-specific binding control in these experiments. The <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> bacterial binding assays showed that all isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam had different binding ability to the two tested bacteria. The r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam of isoform E2 clearly bound to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and had significantly higher binding than the N6 and S9 isoforms. In contrast, binding of r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam S9 to <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was significantly higher (P&lt;0.05) than that of N6 and E2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g006">Figure 6B</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Bacteria-induced <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms have different binding ability to bacteria.</title><p>A) Different <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms were amplified from N6, E2 and S9 subclones and recombinant proteins were produced. The recombinant isoforms were subjected to 12% SDS and were confirmed by western blotting. Isoforms from non-injected animals in lanes 1 and 4; <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>- induced isoform in lanes 2 and 5; and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>-induced isoform in lanes 3 and 6. B) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> binding assays of r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (left) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (right), respectively. Binding of bacteria to different r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms, consisting of N6 = isoforms from non-induced animal, E2 =  <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> induced isoforms, S9 =  <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> induced isoforms or GST =  control recombinant protein was determined using ELISA by measuring the absorbance of samples at 450 nm (OD450). C and D) The effect of bacteria induced isoforms on the clearance process <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> was tested by pre-incubation of the bacteria <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (C) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (D) with each recombinant isoform prior to injection into crayfish. The bacterial numbers in crayfish were determined as CFU/ml of crayfish in the hemolymph at 40 min (black) and 3 h (grey) after the bacterial challenge. This experiment was repeated three times and data represent means of these experiments. E) Phagocytosis and nodule formation of FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria by crayfish hemocytes. Black arrows show nodule formation under normal light microscopy. White arrows show the ingested FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria by crayfish hemocytes under UV light microscope. Red arrows show nodules that contain several ingested bacterial particles under UV light microscope. F) The percentage of crayfish hemocytes ingesting FITC-conjugated heat-killed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (left) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (right) that had been pre-incubated with each isoform of the recombinant proteins and the phagocytic hemocytes was determined at 1.5 h after challenge. Significant difference compared to control is marked by *<italic toggle="yes"> = P&lt;0.05</italic> and **  = <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;0.01</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>The effect of specific bacteria induced isoforms on bacterial clearance and phagocytosis</title><p>Recombinant proteins of isoforms E2 and S9 that specifically interacted with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, respectively, were found to interfere with bacterial clearance and phagocytosis in crayfish. Pre-incubation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> with E2 followed by injection into the animals did increase the number of bacteria in circulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). Similarly with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, the number of bacteria was the highest in the S9 isoform of r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam pre-incubated group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g006">Figure 6D</xref>). This result clearly indicates that the specific r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam could interfere with bacterial binding to the hemocytes. These results were in agreement with the phagocytosis assay, since if <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were coated with the E2 and S9 isoforms respectively, this resulted in a significant decrease in the phagocytic activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g006">Figure 6F</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> effect of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene silencing on WSSV replication</title><p>The role of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam during a WSSV infection was investigated using <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam RNAi to suppress the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam expression. The <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene was completely knocked down in an HPTcell culture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g007">Figure 7A</xref>) whereas the 40S ribosomal gene was unaffected. However, <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam silencing did not have any effect on WSSV replication as shown with no changes in transcription level of WSSV structural protein transcript VP28 between control and <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam silenced groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g007">Figure 7B and 7C</xref>). Moreover, this result also indicates that the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was not affected by WSSV infection. This agrees with our previous experiment where we injected WSSV to live crayfish and the transcript level of Dscams was not affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002062-g004">Figure 4E</xref>).</p><fig id="ppat-1002062-g007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002062.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam silencing on viral replication of WSSV <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</title><p>A) Silencing of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam using dsRNA in cultured HPT cells was confirmed by RT-PCR before WSSV inoculation. B) WSSV VP28 expression in <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam silenced animals (lane 7–9) and the control (lane 4–6). UV-killed WSSV was served as control (lane 1–3), analyzed by semi-quantitative RT-PCR. C) Statistical analysis after comparing different band intensity of the results shown in (B). Significant differences are indicated by asterisks (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;0.05</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The typical domain structure of Dscam with an extracellular domain, a single transmembrane domain and a C-terminal cytoplasmic tail, is highly conserved within arthropods and vertebrates <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Yamakawa1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Schmucker1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. This domain architecture was also found in <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. Diversity in <italic toggle="yes">Dscam</italic> is generated through alternative splicing and variable alternative exons were found in the N-terminal half of Ig2 and Ig3, in the entire Ig7 domain and in the complete transmembrane domain <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Wojtowicz1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. These four variable domains are highly conserved within arthropods, including the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. It is noticeable that the alternative splicing of these exons clearly contributes to separate Dscam of vertebrates from invertebrates in our phylogenetic analysis <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Schmucker1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.</p><p>The Dscam was initially identified for its essential roles in neuronal wiring, so its transcript is present in high quantity in neuronal organs <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Schmucker2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was also detected in the neural system of crayfish. However, recently a putative role of Dscam in host defense was shown in <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. gambiae</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watson1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Both <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. gambiae</italic> Dscams were required for host resistance and phagocytosis of bacteria <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Stuart1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Dscams of the mosquito respond to pathogen infection by generating specific isoforms and these pathogen-specific isoforms of Dscam can bind directly to pathogens <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. The response of IgSF molecules to pathogens does not only generate specific isoforms, but also an increase in the number of these isoforms, such as is the case with the fibrinogen-related proteins (FREPs) in snails <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. FREP production is enhanced following parasitic invasion, and these proteins can bind to parasitic invaders or their products. In crayfish challenge with both Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria induced higher transcription of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. A high transcription of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was obtained after LPS injection, whereas PG or viral injection of WSSV had no such effect. Most Gram-positive bacterial cell walls or cell membranes contain several components, including PG, lipoteichoic acid (LTA), and lipoproteins <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Beveridge1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The high transcription of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam achieved as a response to <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> injection but no response to PG may indicate that the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam respond to other components of the <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> cell wall, such as LTA which has similar physiochemical properties to LPS from Gram-negative bacteria <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Takeuchi1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p><p>Previous results from <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. vannamei</italic> showed that the hemocytes of immune challenged animals exhibited higher variability of the Ig2 and Ig3 domains but only a few Ig7 variants compared to normal animal <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watson1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Chou1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. This is the reason why we studied bacteria specific induced isoforms and produced recombinant proteins covering only the Ig1-Ig3 region. Interestingly, <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> injected crayfish mainly encoded “VNKEYIIRGDSA(F/I)LKCSIPSFVA(D/N)” and “EIGSPATFTCRAQAHPVPQY” motifs at the N-terminal part of the Ig2 and Ig3 domains, respectively. This implies that these two motifs might be important parts of the specific <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>-infected crayfish. This is consistent with results from our bacterial binding assay, which showed that the recombinant proteins containing these two motifs (E2), could bind to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> better than the other isoforms (N6 and S9). In addition, binding of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>-induced isoforms (S9) to <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was also higher than E2 and N6. These results indicate that the pathogen induced isoforms of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam have a specific binding property to each type of challenged bacteria. This specific interaction may be associated with some immune defense reaction as shown with mosquito Dscam <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. To address this question, recombinant proteins (N6, E2 and S9) were pre-incubated with bacteria or FITC conjugated heat killed bacteria to study bacteria clearance and phagocytosis <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. When, the bacteria-induced <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms were coated on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and then injected into live animals, this resulted in lowered clearing rates of bacteria in the hemolymph. This implies that the specific <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam fragments covered the binding sites of the bacteria so they could not bind to the membrane bound <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam on the hemocytes and hence the bacterial number increases since the clearance of bacteria by phagocytes is inhibited.</p><p>In the case of mosquito, <italic toggle="yes">Ag</italic>Dscam is not only a determinant of resistance to bacteria but also affects the resistance towards the malaria parasite <italic toggle="yes">Plasmodium</italic>
<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Dong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. This implies that Dscam might be involved in other host pathogens reactions in crayfish. The Dscam belongs to a subfamily of the Immunoglobulin super family (IgSF). Indeed, many members of IgSF proteins have been reported to interact with and promote entry of numerous virus, including for example the junctional adhesion molecule A (JAM A), that could bind with and facilitate entry of reovirus <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Barton1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Prota1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. So, it is possible that <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam could bind to virus like the other members of IgSF and maybe facilitate entry of virus into crayfish hemocytes. WSSV is a virulent pathogen that causes death in many species of crustaceans such as crayfish <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Watthanasurorot1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> and therefore we tested a possible relationship between <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and this important arthropod virus. We performed experiments to reveal whether WSSV challenge could increase transcription of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and whether <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam RNAi had any effect on WSSV replication. However, we could not detect any increase in <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam mRNA expression after WSSV infection, and more important, if the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene was completely silenced this could not affect WSSV infection or replication.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Crayfish</title><p>Healthy intermolt freshwater crayfish (<italic toggle="yes">P. leniusculus</italic>) were obtained from Lake Hjälmaren, Sweden and maintained in aerated tap water at 10°C.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Cloning of full length <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic> cDNA</title><p>Total RNA (at least 1 µg) was extracted from the heart and converted into cDNA using ThermoScript (Invitrogen). The degenerate primers were designed from the conserved region of insect Dscam including <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Apis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Aedes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tribolium</italic> (DSCAM-e5 F: 5′-AARCAYMGIYTIACIGGIGARAC-3′; DSCAM-e7 R: 5′-GTI ARIACIGTYTCIACI SWYTC-3′). The resulting PCR product was purified and cloned into a TOPO vector (Invitrogen) and sequenced. A partial sequence was used for the further step. Gene specific primers for Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) technique (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s004">Table S1</xref>) were designed from the partial sequence and 5′ or 3′ RACE-PCR was performed with a SMART universal primer A mix (SMARTer RACE cDNA Amplification Kit user manual, Clontech). Thermal cycling was as follows: 25 cycles of 94°C 30 s, 68°C 30 s, and 72°C 3 min. The 5′ and 3′ RACE PCR products were cloned into TOP10 vector and sequenced.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam sequence analysis and phylogenetic analysis</title><p>The nucleotide sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was compared to others in Genbank using BlastX. Multiple sequence alignment was done by ClustalW (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw/index.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw/index.html</ext-link>). The deduced amino acid domain was predicted with SMART (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de/</ext-link>). A phylogenetic tree representing the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and other proteins was analyzed by the maximum likelihood (ML) and Bayesian inference (BI) methods. A PhyML program (under the Whelan and Goldman (WAG) and gamma model with four categories) was used in ML analysis <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. For the BI method, we used MrBayes program <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Huelsenbeck1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> with CAT model (3,000 cycles, first 1,000 cycles removed as burn-in, and the analysis was repeated three times with identical results). Internal blanch support values was from analysis of 1,000 ML bootstrap replicates. This evolutionary phylogram was based on the conserved region of Dscam from Ig8 to FNIII4, whereas phylogram for clustering of all <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms was based on the similarity of their amino acid sequence and were used with the same methods as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Tissue distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam mRNA</title><p>RNA from various tissues, including hepatopancreas, stomach, intestine, heart, hematopoietic tissue (Hpt), muscle, brain, hemocytes and nerves, was extracted following the instruction of GenElute Mammalian Total RNA Miniprep kit (Sigma) followed by treatment with RNase-Free DNase I (Ambion, Austin, TX). Complementary DNA was synthesized using ThermoScript. <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene specific primers (GSP-<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam-F, <named-content content-type="gene">5′- TGGGAAGTGATGCCAGGTTAGA-3′</named-content>; GSP-<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam-R, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TTGAATCAGCAGACATAACCAAAGC-3′</named-content>) were designed from full-length cDNA of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and its PCR product covered the conserved Dscam region (from Ig8 to FNIII3). A 40S ribosomal gene was used as internal control in all PCR experiments and its specific primers (40S-F, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CCAGGACCCCCAAACTTCTTAG-3′</named-content>; 40S-R, <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GAAAACTGCCACAGCCGTTG-3′</named-content>) were designed from <italic toggle="yes">P. leniusculus</italic> Lamda Zap Express library Hpt cDNA (Genbank accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="CF542417">CF542417</ext-link>). PCR conditions were as follows: 94°C 2 min, followed by 30 cycles of 94°C 20 s, 58°C 20 s, and 72°C 1 min for the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene and 25 cycles for 40S ribosomal gene. The PCR products were analyzed on 1.2% agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Identification of alternatively expressed regions in <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic>
</title><p>Due to the large size of full length of <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic>, it was necessary to use several pairs of primers for identification of the different variable regions. PCR of each region was performed with gene specific primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s004">Table S1</xref>) and thermal cycling was as follows: 94°C 2 min, followed by 30 cycles of 94°C 20 s, 60°C 20 s, and 72°C 1.30 min. The PCR products from four different tissues, such as heart, brain, hemocytes and HPT, were cloned into TOP10 vector and 25 individual clones from each tissue were sequenced.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Immune challenge, sample collection and <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam transcription analysis</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were cultured in LB broth at 37°C until OD <sub>600</sub> was ca 0.5. The bacteria were washed three times with 0.85% NaCl by centrifugation at 900 g for 10 min at room temperature. The pellets were resuspended in sterile 0.85% NaCl and adjusted to an approximate concentration of 2×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml. Two groups of three crayfish were injected in the base of the forth walking leg with 100 µl of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, respectively (approximately 2×10<sup>7</sup> CFU/crayfish). The control group was injected with 100 µl of 0.85% NaCl.</p><p>WSSV was purified with a method described by Xie et al.<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Xie1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. The purified virus was resuspended in sterile crayfish saline buffer (CFS: 0.2 M NaCl, 5.4 mM KCl, 10 µM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, pH 6.8) at a concentration of 2×10<sup>7</sup> copies/ml. One hundred microliter of WSSV (equivalent to 2×10<sup>6</sup> copies) or CFS (as control group) was injected as previously described. The experimental setup was made in triplicates.</p><p>Two groups of three crayfish received injections with 100 µl lipopolysaccharides (LPS: Sigma, from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>) or peptidoglycan (PG: Sigma, from <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>) in a sterile CFS with a concentration of 0.2 mg/ml. One hundred microliter of CFS was used for the controls.</p><p>Hemolymph of crayfish from all experiments was collected at 0, 6, 12 and 24 h post injection and the hemocytes were separately isolated for RNA extraction. The transcript levels of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam were detected by quantitative RT-PCR using the QuantiTect SYBR green PCR kit (QIAGEN). The expression of PlDscam was normalized to the expression of the mRNA encoding the crayfish ribosomal protein gene (R40s) for each sample. The primers used are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s004">Table S1</xref>. The qPCR reactions contained 5 µl of 1∶10 diluted cDNA template, 1× QuantiTect SYBR Green PCR master mix (QIAGEN) and 5 µM forward and reverse primers in a 25-µl reaction volume. The following amplification profile was used: 95°C for 15 min, followed by 45 cycles of 94°C for 15 s, 58°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 30 s. All qPCR reactions were performed in duplicate. The hemocytes from a least three crayfish were used for each time point.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Transcription analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms in response to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>
</title><p>The variable region, from the signal peptide to the Ig3 domain region, was amplified from hemocyte cDNA templates from groups of crayfish injected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, respectively, and the control group at 12 h post injection with F1 and R2 primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002062.s004">Table S1</xref>). The PCR products from each of these groups were subcloned into TOP10 vector and fifty colonies of each group were sampled and subsequently sequenced. Multiple sequence alignment was done by ClustalW and clustering tree of the different isoforms was constructed as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Recombinant protein of the <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms</title><p>The ORFs without the signal peptide encoding different <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms were amplified from the original templates N4, E1 and S7 with Dscam-expression-BamHI-Forward (<named-content content-type="gene">5′-TTTTGGATCCAACCCGACAACCGTGTGGACTTCA-3′</named-content>) and Dscam-expression-XhoI-Reverse (<named-content content-type="gene">5′- TTTCTCGAGCCAGGTAACAGACTTGACGGGGTTG-3′</named-content>) primers. The resulting insert was cloned into pGEX-4T-1(GE healthcare) at BamHI and XhoI and transformed into BL21 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Single colonies were grown in LB medium containing 100 µg/ml ampicillin to OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.6 and induced with 1 µM IPTG for 5 h at 37°C. The protein was expressed as a fusion product with a glutathione S-transferase part at the N-terminus of r<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. After purifying this GST-fusion protein on a GST-trap FF column (GE healthcare), the presence of the recombinant protein was confirmed by western blot. The protein samples were subjected to 12% SDS-PAGE and then transferred electrophoretically to PDVF membranes. The membrane was blocked by immersion in 10% skimmed milk in TBST for 1 h and washed three times in 1 x TBST (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, containing 150 mM NaCl and 0.1% Tween 20). The membrane was then incubated with 1: 2,000 dilution of a primary antibody for GST (Sigma) in TBST for 1 h. Then, the previous washing procedure was repeated before the membrane was incubated with anti-mouse-IgG peroxidase-linked species-specific whole antibody from sheep (GE Healthcare) at 1: 3,000 in 1xTBST for 1 h and washed with TBST for 3×10 min. For detection, the ECL Western blotting reagent kit (Amersham Biosciences) was used according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Bacterial binding assay</title><p>A bacterial binding assay was modified from the method described by Yu et al.<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> Briefly, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was prepared as previously described. An aliquot 100 µl of the bacteria was immobilized on 96 well plates at approximately 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/well by incubating for 30 min at room temperature and then shifted to incubation at 4°C overnight. The bacteria were then blocked with 3% (w/v) BSA in TBS buffer at room temperature for 1 hour. To access the binding of the proteins to the bacteria, 20 µg of each <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoform (with GST fusion tag) or GST diluted in 1% BSA in TBS were added to the wells and incubated at room temperature for 2 h. Following three careful washes with TBS, the bound <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam protein was detected with the GST antibody (1∶2,000) followed by rabbit antimouse HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (1∶3000). After adding 100 µl tetramethylbenzidine or TMB substrate (Sigma) for 20 min and 100 µl of stop solution (0.5 M sulfuric acid), the absorbance of the resulting color was measured at 450 nm. All binding assays were performed in triplicates and experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Bacteria clearance assay</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were washed six times in 0.9% NaCl at 1,200× g for 10 min and then incubated with 10 µg recombinant proteins of each <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms for 1 h at 4°C, followed by washing six times with 0.9% NaCl. One hundred microliter of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> at concentrations of 6×10<sup>8</sup> and 3×10<sup>9</sup> CFU/ml, respectively, in CFS were injected into crayfish. The bacteria count was carried out in hemolymph collected 40 min and 3 h after the bacterial injection. The homonym was serial diluted serially and was then dotted onto LB agar (10 µl for each dot) and then incubated at 37°C overnight followed by counting the bacterial colony forming units (CFU).</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Phagocytosis assay</title><p>Both, heat killed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were conjugated with fluoresce in isothiocyanate (FITC) using a method previously described by Hed <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Hed1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Briefly, heat-killed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> were washed six times in 0.9% NaCl at 1,200× g for 10 min and then incubated at concentration of 10<sup>9</sup> particles/ml in 0.1 M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> containing 0.1 mg/ml FITC (Sigma), pH 9.5 for 30 min at 37°C, followed by washing six times with 0.9% NaCl as above. The FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria were incubated with 10 µg recombinant proteins of each <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoforms for 1 h at 4°C. The bacteria were washed five times as described above and resuspended at a concentration of 10<sup>8</sup> particles/ml in CFS. Two hundred microliter of FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria coated with recombinant <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam isoform (4×10<sup>6</sup> particles/ml in CFS) was injected into the animals via the base of the fourth walking leg. Hemocytes were bled for phagocytosis detection at 1.5 h post FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria injection. The fluorescence of FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacteria particles was quenched by adding 20 µl of 0.04% trypan blue (Pfaltz &amp; Bauer, Waterbury, CT). The ingested bacteria were easily detected under the UV light microscope due to their fluorescence. The percentage of phagocytosing cells was determined by counting 10 individual fields and dividing the number of cells with ingested fluorescent bacteria with the total number of counted cells. Each experiment was performed in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Crayfish Hpt cell culture and maintenance</title><p>The hematopoietic tissue was dissected according to Söderhäll et al.<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Sderhll1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The Hpt was washed with CPBS (crayfish phosphate buffered saline: 10 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 10 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 150 mM NaCl, 10 µM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 10 µM MnCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 6.8) and incubated in 600 µl of 0.1% collagenase (type I and IV) (Sigma) in CPBS at room temperature for 45 min to separate the Hpt cells. The separated cells were washed twice with CPBS by spinning down at 800× g for 5 min at room temperature. The cell pellet was re-suspended in modified L-15 medium and subsequently cells were seeded at a density of 2.5×10<sup>6</sup> cells/150 µl in 96-well plates. The Hpt cells were supplemented with partially purified plasma as a source of astakine <xref rid="ppat.1002062-Sderhll2" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> after 1 h of attachment at room temperature and the culture plates were incubated at 16°C, and 1/3 of the medium was changed at 48 h intervals.</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Generation of dsRNA</title><p>dsRNA of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam was designed from the conserved region during Ig8-FNIII3. Gene specific primers for <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and GFP was incorporated with a T7 promoter sequence (italic letters) at 5′ ends (DscamRNAi-F, <named-content content-type="gene">5′- <italic toggle="yes">TAATACGACTCACTATAGGG</italic>GCATCAAGCTGAGTGGACAA-3′</named-content>; DscamRNAi-R, <named-content content-type="gene">5′- <italic toggle="yes">TAATACGACTCACTATAGGG</italic> GAAGCCAGGTAGGGGAAATC -3′</named-content> and GFP 63+, <italic toggle="yes"><named-content content-type="gene">TAATACGACTCACTATAGGG</named-content></italic>
<named-content content-type="gene">CGACGTAAACGGCCACAAGT</named-content>; GFP 719-, <italic toggle="yes"><named-content content-type="gene">TAATACGACTCACTATAGGG</named-content></italic>
<named-content content-type="gene">TTCTTGTACAGCTCGTCCATG</named-content>) and used to amplify PCR products as template for dsRNA synthesis. A GFP transcript was amplified with the pd2EGFP-1 vector (Clontech) as template and used as control. The amplified products were then purified using GenElute Gel extraction kit (Sigma) followed by <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> transcription using the MegaScript kit (Ambion). The dsRNA was purified with the Trizol LS reagent (Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec id="s4n"><title>RNAi <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</title><p>The Hpt cells were divided into three groups with four replicates in each group. The Hpt cells received different treatments as follows: group 1: GFP dsRNA plus UV-killed WSSV, group 2: GFP dsRNA plus WSSV and group 3: <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam dsRNA plus WSSV. The dsRNA transfection and WSSV infection into Hpt cell cultures were performed as described by Liu et al.<xref rid="ppat.1002062-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Briefly, 4 µl of dsRNA (250 ng/µl) was mixed with 3 µl of histone H2A (1 mg/ml) and with 20 µl of modified L15 and added to one well of 1-day-old Hpt cell cultures. The cells were then incubated at 16°C. At day 3, one replicate of group 2 and 3 were subjected to RNA extraction to determine RNAi efficiencies. For remaining replicates, the medium was replaced with 150 µl of L15 medium together with 5 µl of WSSV stock suspension and 5 µl crude astakine preparation and were further incubated for 36 h at 20°C followed by isolation of RNA. Total HPT RNA was extracted to determine <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and WSSV VP28 transcripts by semi-quantitative RT-PCR. PCR was performed with three oligonucleotide primers (WSSV VP28 (Genbank accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AF502435">AF502435</ext-link>):-F: <named-content content-type="gene">5′-TCACTCTTTCGGTCGTGTCG-3′</named-content> and -R: <named-content content-type="gene">5′- CCACACACAAAGGTGCCAAC-3′</named-content>; previous primer for 40s ribosomal and <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam gene). The PCR conditions were as follows: 94°C 2 min, followed by 30 cycles of 94°C 20 s, 60°C 20 s, and 72°C 30 s for <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam and VP28, while 25 cycles for 40S ribosomal gene.</p></sec><sec id="s4o"><title>Statistic analysis</title><p>The relative expression levels of different time groups were examined by One-way ANOVA followed by Duncan's new multiple range test and Tukey test. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;0.05</italic>. Results are expressed as the mean ± SE.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Variable regions in the cytoplasmic tail of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. A) Multiple alignment of amino acid sequence of seven different cytoplasmic tails of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. B) Amino acid sequence alignment of the cytoplasmic tail of <italic toggle="yes">Pacifastacus leniusculus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam), <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Dm</italic>Dscam: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAF71926">AAF71926</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Apis mellifera</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Am</italic>Dscam: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AAT96374">AAT96374</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Aedes aegypti</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Aa</italic>Dscam: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="EAT37388">EAT37388</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Tribolium castaneum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Tc</italic>Dscam: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="NP_001107841">NP_001107841</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">Daphnia pulex</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Dp</italic>Dscam: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ACC65888">ACC65888</ext-link>). The squares highlight homologous regions and some conserved motifs are indicated by different colors, including SH3-binding motif (violet), endocytosis motif (yellow), SH2-binding motif (green), Polyproline motif (blue), PDZ motif (red) and ITIM motif (in a box).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Diagram showing the binding locations of primers that were used in this study. The locations of primers that were used for RACE-PCR (A), identification of alternatively expressed regions in <italic toggle="yes">PlDscam</italic> (B) and quantification of PlDscam expression (C).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s002.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Dscam is important for phagocytosis of crayfish hemocytes. Phagocytosis of FITC-conjugated heat killed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> particles were determined using normal or UV light microscopy. A) phagocytosis of FITC conjugated heat-killed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> after pre-incubation with different isoforms (N2, E6 or S9) of recombinant proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. B) phagocytosis of FITC conjugated heat-killed <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> after pre-incubation with different isoforms (N2, E6 or S9) of recombinant proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Pl</italic>Dscam. The white, black and red arrows represent ingested FITC-conjugated heat-killed bacterial particles, nodule formation and nodules that contain several ingested bacterial particles, respectively.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Primer pairs used in this study. All primer sequences are given in the format 5′-sequence-3′.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s004.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Comparison of Dscam Ig2 and Ig3 combinations in normal, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> injected and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> injected crayfish. Fifty individual cDNAs, expressed in each group, were sent to sequence.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s005.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1002062.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>The chosen clones were used for construction of the clustering phylogram and the clones in bold letters were expressed as recombinant proteins.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ppat.1002062.s006.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This work has been done under financial support from the Swedish Science Research Council. (621-2009-5715). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1002062-Garver1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garver</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Immunoglobulin superfamily members play an important role in the mosquito immune system.</article-title><source>Dev Comp Immunol</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18036658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dci.2007.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2483948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Dermody1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dermody</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guglielmi</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stehle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Immunoglobulin superfamily virus receptors and the evolution of adaptive immunity.</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1000481</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19956667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2777377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Hutter1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plenefisch</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proenca</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Conservation and novelty in the evolution of cell adhesion and extracellular matrix genes.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>287</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.287.5455.989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Watson1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puttmann-Holgado</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamar</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Extensive diversity of Ig-superfamily proteins in the immune system of insects.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>309</volume><fpage>1874</fpage><lpage>1878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16109846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1116887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Zhang1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adema</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kepler</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Diversification of Ig superfamily genes in an invertebrate.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>305</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1088069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Dong1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>AgDscam, a hypervariable immunoglobulin domain-containing receptor of the Anopheles gambiae innate immune system.</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>e229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16774454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1479700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Yamakawa1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huot</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haendelt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>DSCAM: a novel member of the immunoglobulin superfamily maps in a Down syndrome region and is involved in the development of the nervous system.</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9426258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/7.2.227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Agarwala1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Cloning and functional characterization of DSCAML1, a novel DSCAM-like cell adhesion molecule that mediates homophilic intercellular adhesion.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11453658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/bbrc.2001.5214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Hattori1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojtowicz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zipursky</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Dscam-mediated cell recognition regulates neural circuit formation.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18837673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.24.110707.175250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2711549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Boehm1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Two in one: dual function of an invertebrate antigen receptor.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni1007-1031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Schmucker1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmucker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Dscam and DSCAM: complex genes in simple animals, complex animals yet simple genes.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1752909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Wojtowicz1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojtowicz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zipursky</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Alternative splicing of Drosophila Dscam generates axon guidance receptors that exhibit isoform-specific homophilic binding.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2004.08.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2691713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Schmucker2"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmucker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worby</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Drosophila Dscam is an axon guidance receptor exhibiting extraordinary molecular diversity.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10892653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)80878-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Stuart1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezekowitz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Phagocytosis and comparative innate immunity: learning on the fly.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18219310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nri2240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Williams1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Drosophila hemopoiesis and cellular immunity.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>4711</fpage><lpage>4716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17404248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.178.8.4711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Beveridge1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Ultrastructure, chemistry, and function of the bacterial wall.</article-title><source>Int Rev Cytol</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6166584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0074-7696(08)61198-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Takeuchi1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Differential roles of TLR2 and TLR4 in recognition of gram-negative and gram-positive bacterial cell wall components.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10549626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1074-7613(00)80119-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Chou1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The putative invertebrate adaptive immune protein Litopenaeus vannamei Dscam (LvDscam) is the first reported Dscam to lack a transmembrane domain and cytoplasmic tail.</article-title><source>Dev Comp Immunol</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>1258</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19635499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dci.2009.07.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Barton1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Junction adhesion molecule is a receptor for reovirus.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(01)00231-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Prota1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prota</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schelling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Crystal structure of human junctional adhesion molecule 1: implications for reovirus binding.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>5366</fpage><lpage>5371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0937718100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC404559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Watthanasurorot1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watthanasurorot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiravanichpaisal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>A gC1qR prevents white spot syndrome virus replication in the freshwater crayfish Pacifastacus leniusculus.</article-title><source>J Virol</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>10844</fpage><lpage>10851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JVI.01045-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2950596</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4702658"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Guindon1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood.</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10635150390235520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Huelsenbeck1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Xie1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A simple and efficient method for purification of intact white spot syndrome virus (WSSV) viral particles.</article-title><source>Virus Res</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.virusres.2004.08.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Yu1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The pancreatic zymogen granule membrane protein, GP2, binds Escherichia coli Type 1 fimbriae.</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19627615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-230X-9-58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2726147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Hed1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Methods for distinguishing ingested from adhering particles.</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3102897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0076-6879(86)32008-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Sderhll1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangyeekhun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Hemocyte production and maturation in an invertebrate animal; proliferation and gene expression in hematopoietic stem cells of Pacifastacus leniusculus.</article-title><source>Dev Comp Immunol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12798363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0145-305x(03)00039-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Sderhll2"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiravanichpaisal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>An ancient role for a prokineticin domain in invertebrate hematopoiesis.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>174</volume><fpage>6153</fpage><lpage>6160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.174.10.6153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ppat.1002062-Liu1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiravanichpaisal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söderhäll</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Antilipopolysaccharide factor interferes with white spot syndrome virus replication in vitro and in vivo in the crayfish Pacifastacus leniusculus.</article-title><source>J Virol</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>10365</fpage><lpage>10371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JVI.01101-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1641759</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>