
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="other" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncoimmunology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncoimmunology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1816</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">oncoimmun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101570526</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ONCI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title xml:lang="en">Oncoimmunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2162-4011</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2162-402X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3376981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3376981.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3376981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3376981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22720261</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/onci.1.2.18241</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2011ONCOIMM0055</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">18241</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Author's View</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>FOXO3</article-title><subtitle>A master switch for regulating tolerance and immunity in dendritic cells</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names initials="SK">Stephanie K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names initials="AA">Arthur A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Tumor Immunity and Tolerance Section; Laboratory of Molecular Immunoregulation; Cancer and Inflammation Program; NCI-Frederick; Frederick, MD USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Arthur A. Hurwitz; Email: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hurwitza@mail.nih.gov">hurwitza@mail.nih.gov</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">211113</issue-id><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Landes Bioscience</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License. The article may be redistributed, reproduced, and reused for non-commercial purposes, provided the original source is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="onci-1-252.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Oncoimmunology" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4910716"><article-title>Editorial retraction</article-title><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><date><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><elocation-id seq="57">e1173506</elocation-id><source>Oncoimmunology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4910716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27467965</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Recent findings demonstrate that dendritic cells in prostate tumors induce immune tolerance in tumor antigen-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. We propose that DC tolerogenicity can be regulated by expression of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3;</italic> silencing <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression enhances anti-tumor immune responses and renders FOXO3 a potential target for immunotherapy.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>dendritic cells</kwd><kwd>Foxo3</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>tolerance</kwd><kwd>tumor</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Dendritic cells (DC) are among the most versatile cells of the immune system. DC are essential to the initiation of a productive immune response by presenting Ag to T cells and secreting pro-inflammatory cytokines, but are also responsible for controlling over-active immunity by regulating immune tolerance. While tolerance is an essential component of preventing autoimmune disease, it is also a complication and major hurdle to overcome in the quest to improve immune-based therapies for cancer.</p><p>Tumors create a highly complex microenvironment rich in cytokines, chemokines and other factors that attract various populations of immune cells including DC and T cells. Although the infiltration of immune cells is seemingly beneficial, the suppressive tumor microenvironment (TME) quickly neutralizes anti-tumor responses and cells such as antigen-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL) with the potential to control tumor burden lose their function.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><sup>1</sup></xref> Several therapies have aimed to target and neutralize DC-produced immunosuppressive factors such as Interleukin (IL)-10, indoleamine-2,3-dioxygenase (IDO), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and epidermal growth factor (EGF) in an attempt to enhance T cell responses to tumors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><sup>2</sup></xref> However, inhibition of select suppressive factors has proven to be insufficient for sustaining anti-tumor immunity. Therefore, we sought to gain a better understanding of the mechanisms that regulate tumor-associated DC (TADC)-induced immune tolerance.</p><p>We initially confirmed that tolerogenic mediators present in the tumor microenvironment (IDO, Arginase, TGFβ) dampened responsiveness of adoptively transferred CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. However, blocking these TADC-derived tolerogenic mediators, individually or in combination, only transiently enhanced T cell effector function. In contrast, depleting TADC restored anti-tumor effector functions of tumor-infiltrating T cells. Subsequent in vitro studies demonstrated that TADC were not only poor stimulators of T cells, but they actively induced T cell tolerance and were capable of inducing suppressive activity, confirming our previous observations using an adoptive transfer model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><sup>3</sup></xref> Importantly, our results observed in the TRansgenic Adenocarcinoma of the Mouse Prostate (TRAMP) model were consistent with studies using TADC isolated from human prostate tumor tissue sections suggesting that our results may have significant clinical relevance.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><p>Increased FOXO3 expression is associated with TADC induced tolerance. (A) TADC produce tolerogenic mediators: IDO, arginase, TGFβ, and express increased PD-L1 and FOXO3. Interaction between TADC and CTLs induced T cell tolerance. (B) Inhibiting <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> or providing a potent pro-inflammatory stimulus converts TADC to immune stimulating and promotes CTL effector functions and anti-tumor immunity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="onci-1-252-g1.jpg"/></fig><p>Analysis of gene expression patterns in TRAMP TADC revealed increased expression of chemokines (<italic toggle="yes">Cxcl10, Cxcl9</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ccl5</italic>), growth factors (<italic toggle="yes">Vegfa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfβ</italic>), and other genes associated with tolerance <italic toggle="yes">(Ido1, Arg1, Cd274</italic>). Additionally, increased expression of the gene <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> was observed in TADC compared with non-tumor-associated prostate DC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). FOXO3 is a member of the Forkhead box transcription factor class-O family and was previously reported to play a role in the regulation of DC function through a “reverse signaling” process mediated by CTLA-4 interaction with B7 molecules, leading to increased in IDO levels.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><sup>5</sup></xref> Therefore, to determine the role of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression in controlling TADC tolerogenicity, we silenced <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression using siRNA and observed reduced DC tolerogenicity, decreased expression of suppressive factors <italic toggle="yes">Tgfβ, Arg1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ido1</italic> and a concomitant increase in expression of the co-stimulatory molecule CD80 and the pro-inflammatory cytokine, IL-6.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>Interestingly, we previously reported that TRAMP TADC could be activated or “licensed” in situ by tumor-antigen specific CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, resulting in more stimulatory DC.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><sup>6</sup></xref> We now observed that the activation induced by CD4<sup>+</sup> helper cells also resulted in reduced TADC tolerogenicity concomitant with downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><sup>4</sup></xref> In general, our findings suggest that the downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> allows for the conversion of tolerogenic DC to immune stimulatory, including increased expression of B7, MHC and CD40 molecules as well as an increase in pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-12, IL-15 and IL-6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). These data suggest that TADC can be a useful target in immune based therapies and furthermore, that FOXO3 may be part of a regulatory mechanism that programs the inflammatory vs. tolerogenic potential of dendritic cells.</p><p>In summary, we conclude that TADC are critical in determining the effectiveness of anti-tumor immune responses, especially with respect to maintaining activation of Ag-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. We reported that TADC tolerogenicity is regulated by <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> in both murine and human prostate cancer as well as murine models of melanoma and renal cell carcinoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><sup>4</sup></xref> However, the mechanisms responsible for increased <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression in TADC as well as the mechanism(s) by which FOXO3 mediates tolerogenicity are unclear and are currently under investigation. <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> expression may be induced in response to stimuli such as reactive oxygen species<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><sup>7</sup></xref> in the TME or in response to interactions with other inflammatory cells (e.g., macrophages or mast cells) and their products within the TME. FOXO3 may induce expression of genes associated with tolerance, such as <italic toggle="yes">Ido, Tgfβ,</italic> and/or <italic toggle="yes">Il-10.</italic> A second possible hypothesis is that FOXO3 may play a less direct or active role in inducing expression of genes associated with tolerance, but rather, may mediate the inactivation of pro-inflammatory signals such as inhibition of NFκB or STATs. Lin et al. previously reported that FOXO3 regulates helper T cell activation to control autoimmunity by inhibiting NFκB.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><sup>8</sup></xref> This is an interesting perspective as similar mechanisms have been described involving transcription factors overexpressed in inflammatory cells that infiltrate tumors, such as p53.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><sup>9</sup></xref> Elucidation of these mechanisms may be critical to unveiling the balance between inflammation and tolerance in DC.</p><p>In terms of therapy, given that FOXO3 is also important for cell cycle regulation by activating genes that induce apoptosis,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><sup>10</sup></xref> it may be most beneficial to utilize an approach that specifically targets silencing expression to dendritic cells, thus preventing downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> in tumor cells. One such approach currently under investigation is to administer small molecule and peptide-based inhibitors to FOXO3. Ideally, these inhibitors could be linked to molecules that would be taken up by DC-specific receptors, such as DEC-205. A second strategy may be to inhibit DNA binding by administering decoy DNA containing the motif recognized by <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> thus preventing the induction of <italic toggle="yes">Foxo3</italic> regulated genes associated with tolerance. These discoveries may have great impact for not only efficiently targeting and improving DC function in cancer immunotherapy, but may also have significant implications for designing therapeutics to utilize DC to dampen inflammation in autoimmune disease.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge the critical review of Dr. Scott Durum. Some research described in this manuscript was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, NCI.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Previously published online: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.landesbioscience.com/journals/oncoimmunology/article/18241/">www.landesbioscience.com/journals/oncoimmunology/article/18241</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer-Weaver</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tolerization of tumor-specific T cells despite efficient initial priming in a primary murine model of prostate cancer</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2007</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>1268</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.178.3.1268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinzon-Charry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dendritic cell dysfunction in cancer: a mechanism for immunosuppression</article-title><source>Immunol Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1711.2005.01371.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16174093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer-Weaver</surname><given-names>KA.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cutting Edge: Tumor-specific CD8+ T Cells infiltrating prostatic tumors are induced to become suppressor cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>183</volume>:<fpage>4848</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.0900848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6948842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riboldi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer-Weaver</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stagliano</surname><given-names>KER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sklavos</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Foxo3a programs tumor associated dendritic cells to become tolerogenic in Human and Murine Prostate Cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2011</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1361</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI44325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3069771</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4463220"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejean</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beisner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ch’en</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerdiles</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcription factor Foxo3 controls the magnitude of T cell immune responses by modulating the function of dendritic cells</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19363483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2712214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer-Weaver</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyguine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvord</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunity to murine prostatic tumors: continuous provision of T-cell help prevents CD8 T-cell tolerance and activates tumor-infiltrating dendritic cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>6256</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-4516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2732120</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4873322"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forkhead transcription factor FOXO subfamily is essential for reactive oxygen species-induced apoptosis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>2008</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2007.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hron</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of NF-kappaB, Th activation, and autoinflammation by the forkhead transcription factor Foxo3a</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2004.06.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15308101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komarova</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krivokrysenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neznanov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chernov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komarov</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p53 is a suppressor of inflammatory response in mice</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1096/fj.04-3213fje</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkers</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lammers</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koenderman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of the pro-apoptotic Bcl-2 family member Bim is regulated by the forkhead transcription factor FKHR-L1</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(00)00728-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050388</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>