
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">482</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jcellbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0375356</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jcb</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4639868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4639868.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4639868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4639868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553932</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201504073</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201504073</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The DYRK-family kinase Pom1 phosphorylates the F-BAR protein Cdc15 to prevent division at cell poles</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Pom1 inhibits Cdc15 for division plane positioning</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ullal</surname><given-names initials="P">Pranav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names initials="NA">Nathan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="JS">Jun-Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo Presti</surname><given-names initials="L">Libera</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names initials="RH">Rachel H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names initials="KL">Kathleen L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names initials="SG">Sophie G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Fundamental Microbiology, University of Lausanne, CH-1015 Lausanne, Switzerland</institution></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Nashville, TN 37232</institution></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor3">Correspondence to Sophie G. Martin: <email>Sophie.Martin@unil.ch</email></corresp><fn id="afn4" fn-type="present-address" specific-use="present-address"><p>L. Lo Presti's present address is Max Planck Institute for Terrestrial Microbiology, D-35043 Marburg, Germany.</p></fn><fn id="afn5" fn-type="present-address" specific-use="present-address"><p>R.H. Roberts-Galbraith's present address is Howard Hughes Medical Institute and Dept. of Cell and Developmental Biology, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL 61801.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>211</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">260555</issue-id><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Ullal et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="JCB_201504073.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_thumb.gif"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="J Cell Biol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5346964"><article-title>Retraction: The DYRK-family kinase Pom1 phosphorylates the F-BAR Cdc15 to prevent division at cell poles</article-title><volume>216</volume><issue>3</issue><date><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5346964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209645</pub-id></related-article><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>In rod-shaped fission yeast cells, the DYRK-family kinase Pom1, which localizes at cell poles, inhibits the formation of the contractile actomyosin ring at these regions by phosphorylating the key ring component, F-BAR protein Cdc15, allowing the ring to slide toward the middle of the cell.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Division site positioning is critical for both symmetric and asymmetric cell divisions. In many organisms, positive and negative signals cooperate to position the contractile actin ring for cytokinesis. In rod-shaped fission yeast <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> cells, division at midcell is achieved through positive Mid1/anillin-dependent signaling emanating from the central nucleus and negative signals from the dual-specificity tyrosine phosphorylation-regulated kinase family kinase Pom1 at the cell poles. In this study, we show that Pom1 directly phosphorylates the F-BAR protein Cdc15, a central component of the cytokinetic ring. Pom1-dependent phosphorylation blocks Cdc15 binding to paxillin Pxl1 and C2 domain protein Fic1 and enhances Cdc15 dynamics. This promotes ring sliding from cell poles, which prevents septum assembly at the ends of cells with a displaced nucleus or lacking Mid1. Pom1 also slows down ring constriction. These results indicate that a strong negative signal from the Pom1 kinase at cell poles converts Cdc15 to its closed state, destabilizes the actomyosin ring, and thus promotes medial septation.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s01"><title>Introduction</title><p>The position of the cell division site is crucial for both cellular function and integrity. Studies in prokaryotic and eukaryotic systems have revealed two major positioning systems: local positive signals and distal inhibitory ones (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Oliferenko et al., 2009</xref>). In rod-shaped bacteria, the division plane is positioned mainly via inhibitory signals arising from the cell poles and the nucleoids, which prevent the formation of the division ring, leaving only the cell middle as the permissive site for ring assembly. In animal cells, the mitotic spindle positions the division site by conferring both stimulatory signals to the medial cortex for furrow formation and distal relaxation signals (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Eggert et al., 2006</xref>). Stimulatory and inhibitory mechanisms for division site positioning have also long been described in the fission yeast <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe.</italic> Thus, in many cells, proximal stimulatory and distal inhibitory signals cooperate to position the division site.</p><p>Like animal cells, rod-shaped fission yeast cells assemble an actomyosin ring for division, which is placed at midcell for symmetric division. Division site positioning is defined by the nucleus, which is normally centered in the cell by microtubule pushing forces (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Tran et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Daga and Chang, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Tolic´-Nørrelykke et al., 2005</xref>). This positive nuclear signal depends on Mid1, an anillin-related protein that shuttles in and out of the nucleus and marks the overlying cell cortex, where it forms interphase nodes, early precursors of the actomyosin ring (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Sohrmann et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Paoletti and Chang, 2000</xref>). These interphase nodes contain additional proteins, in particular the SAD-family kinase Cdr2, which controls the timing of mitotic entry and promotes the interaction of Mid1 with the plasma membrane (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Almonacid et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Martin and Berthelot-Grosjean, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Moseley et al., 2009</xref>). Negative signals from cell poles contribute to restricting interphase nodes to midcell. These arise from the dual-specificity tyrosine phosphorylation-regulated kinase (DYRK) family Pom1 kinase, which forms plasma membrane–associated concentration gradients nucleated by the Tea1/Tea4 complex transported to cell ends by microtubules (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Tatebe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Celton-Morizur et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hachet et al., 2011</xref>). Pom1 restricts interphase nodes to midcell, in part through direct phosphorylation of Cdr2 (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Rincon et al., 2014</xref>). Pom1 also delays mitotic commitment by phosphorylating Cdr2 on a distinct site (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Bhatia et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kettenbach et al., 2015</xref>). In sum, Mid1 localization to midcell relies on positive nuclear signals and negative cell-tip signals.</p><p>At mitotic entry, before spindle pole body (SPB) separation, Mid1-containing interphase nodes mature into cytokinetic nodes, losing some proteins (such as Cdr2) and recruiting others, such as myosin II Myo2, the F-BAR protein Cdc15, and the formin Cdc12 (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Akamatsu et al., 2014</xref>). Actin filament nucleation by formin and capture by myosin II from these nodes leads to the proposed “search, capture, pull, release” model of ring assembly, in which stochastic interactions between these nodes permit their progressive condensation into an actomyosin ring (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Vavylonis et al., 2008</xref>). The ring then matures with the arrival of additional proteins (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Pollard and Wu, 2010</xref>), before constriction and disassembly. Assembly of the septum by β-glucan synthases terminates the division process and also contributes to actomyosin ring stability and constriction (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Pardo and Nurse, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Proctor et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>In the absence of <italic toggle="yes">mid1</italic>, cells remain competent for division, but the contractile ring appears to condense from strands of cytokinetic proteins scattered over the cortex, or from a single location rather than from nodes (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Mishra and Oliferenko, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith and Gould, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Saha and Pollard, 2012</xref>). In these cells, contractile ring orientation and placement are aberrant, leading to oblique, often off-centered rings relative to the long axis of the cell (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Sohrmann et al., 1996</xref>). However, inhibitory signals arising from the cell poles remain in place to prevent the assembly of the cytokinesis apparatus at the cell poles, such that division occurs within the medial portion of the cell (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). Similar to the control of Mid1 medial localization, these <italic toggle="yes">mid1</italic>-independent inhibitory cell end signals require the Tea1/Tea4 complex and the Pom1 kinase. Indeed, deletion of any of these cell end factors is synthetic lethal with <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic>, and double mutants form septa at cell ends (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). Earlier work suggested that the F-BAR protein Cdc15 may be a target of this so-called tip occlusion pathway because a C-terminally tagged Cdc15-GFP allele blocked tip septation in double <italic toggle="yes">tea1Δ mid1-18</italic> mutants (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p>Cdc15 is an essential component of the actomyosin ring (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>). It is the founding member of the <italic toggle="yes">pombe cdc15</italic> homology family of proteins (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Lippincott and Li, 2000</xref>), which share a conserved domain architecture of a C-terminal SH3 domain and an N-terminal BAR domain, which generally serves to bind membranes. Cdc15 localizes to cell ends during interphase, where it plays a role in endocytosis (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carnahan and Gould, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Arasada and Pollard, 2011</xref>). It arrives to the cytokinetic nodes early, at the time of SPB separation (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2003</xref>). It forms complexes with a large number of ring components, including the formin Cdc12, paxillin Pxl1, the Rho-GEF Rgf3, Spa2, and the C2 domain protein Fic1, and serves to stabilize the contractile ring during anaphase (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carnahan and Gould, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Pinar et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arasada and Pollard, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Willet et al., 2015</xref>). Cdc15 activity is under strong cell cycle–dependent phospho-regulation: it is hyperphosphorylated during G2 phase and hypophosphorylated during actomyosin ring assembly before being rephosphorylated toward the later stages of cytokinesis (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>). Phosphorylation of Cdc15 generates a closed conformation and inhibits its interaction with the membrane and early ring components, whereas dephosphorylation induces an open conformation allowing its oligomerization, membrane binding, and scaffolding activities (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). The Cdc14-like phosphatase Clp1 partially dephosphorylates Cdc15 during mitosis to stabilize its ring localization (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Wachtler et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Clifford et al., 2008</xref>). However, the identification of Cdc15 kinases has remained elusive.</p><p>In this study, we show that Pom1 is a direct Cdc15 kinase. Pom1-mediated Cdc15 phosphorylation antagonizes Cdc15 function by interfering with its membrane and protein partner binding. The enhanced dynamics of Cdc15 resulting from Pom1 phosphorylation promotes ring sliding toward the cell middle, thus avoiding septum assembly at cell ends. Therefore, the Pom1 kinase forms a strong negative signal at cell poles to destabilize Cdc15 and the actomyosin ring and to promote medial septation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s02"><title>Results</title><sec id="s03" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 kinase activity is required to prevent division septum assembly at cell tips</title><p>To investigate whether the signals for tip occlusion occur via Pom1 kinase activity, we used the conditional allele of Pom1, <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic>, to specifically inhibit kinase activity with 3MB-PP1 (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Bhatia et al., 2014</xref>). We introduced this allele into <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mid1-366</italic> cells (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Sohrmann et al., 1996</xref>), which have misplaced and/or tilted septa and a very small percentage of tip septa (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). Upon addition of 3MB-PP1, we observed tip septation in most cells in both <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1-366</italic> strains, even at the permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>; and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp1">Fig. S1 A</ext-link>). The percentage of cells with tip septa in the <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> double mutant increased with time and drug concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>), with &gt;90% of cells showing tip septa after a 2-h incubation with 1 µM 3MB-PP1. Tip septa were of three types (Fig. S1 C): (1) one or two septa at the very cell ends; (2) septa anchored at both cell ends and spanning the long cell axis; (3) septa anchored at only one cell end. These phenotypes were not observed in either of the single mutants or in the double mutants treated with vehicle (Fig. S1, A and B). To ensure that tip septation was not a result of a previous cytokinesis event, we arrested cultures of <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> in S phase with hydroxyurea before releasing them in the presence of 3MB-PP1 (Fig. S1 D). The double-mutant <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> showed a considerable increase in the number of septa at the tip in the first round of cell division after release.</p><fig id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 kinase activity prevents division septum assembly at cell tips.</bold> (A) Cells of indicated genotypes were treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 at 25°C for 2 h and stained with calcofluor. Arrowheads indicate cells with tip septa. (B) Quantification of tip septa among septated cells treated as in A or with methanol as in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp2">Fig. S1 B</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 300). (C) Quantification of tip septa in 3MB-PP1–treated <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> septated cells over time (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 300). Cells of indicated genotypes were treated as in A at indicated time points. (D) Quantification of tip septa in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> septated cells with increasing concentrations of 3MB-PP1 at 25°C for 2 h (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 300). (E) Pom1 kinase activity prevents tip septation in <italic toggle="yes">mid1+</italic> cells. <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> nmt81::myo52N-RFP-nup146</italic> cells were treated for 4 h with 1 µM 3MBPP1 to inactivate Pom1<sup>as1</sup>, or 25 µg/ml MBC to displace the nucleus, or both, and stained with calcofluor. Red arrowheads indicate misplaced septa, purple arrowheads indicate tip septa. (F) Quantification of tip septa in septated cells as in E (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 35 for each sample). (G) <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ nmt81::myo52N-RFP-nup146</italic> cells show displaced nuclei (red arrowheads) and tip septa (far right). (H) Quantification of tip septa in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ nmt81::myo52N-RFP-nup146</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 180). Bars, 5 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>Collectively, these experiments suggest that among Tea1, Tea4, and Pom1 implicated in tip occlusion (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>), the specific signals that prevent formation of division septa at cell tips arise from Pom1 kinase activity.</p></sec><sec id="s04" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 kinase activity is required for tip occlusion in <italic toggle="yes">mid1+</italic> cells</title><p>We tested whether Pom1 kinase activity is required to prevent septation at cell tips in the presence of Mid1. We used a chimeric protein of the Myosin V Myo52 motor and coiled-coil domains with a nuclear pore complex protein Nup146 (Myo52N-RFP-Nup146; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lo Presti et al., 2012</xref>) to displace the nucleus and Mid1 signal from midcell, through transport along actin cables. Whereas the nucleus was centered in almost all cells containing the Myo52N-RFP-Nup146 chimera, microtubule depolymerization with methyl benzimidazol-2-yl-carbamate (MBC) for 4 h led to nuclear displacement toward growing cell poles in &gt;60% of cells (Fig. S1, E and F), as previously shown (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lo Presti et al., 2012</xref>). Consequently, Mid1 signal and the septa were shifted toward one cell pole in these cells, but, importantly, the septa were not seen at cell ends in <italic toggle="yes">pom1+</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 E</xref>). In contrast, additional inhibition of Pom1<sup>as1</sup> with 3MB-PP1 led to tip septation in ∼60% of cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, E and F</xref>). In these conditions, Mid1 was also observed to spread around the entire cell cortex (Fig. S1 G). In fact, <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> cells containing Myo52N-RFP-Nup146 showed nuclear displacement toward the growing cell pole (probably because of imbalance of actin-dependent forces in these monopolar cells) and tip septation even without the addition of MBC, whereas <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> cells with centered nuclei had only a low level of tip septation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, G and H</xref>). Together, these analyses suggest that the signals for tip occlusion are produced by Pom1 even in the presence of Mid1. These signals likely become important to prevent tip septation when cytokinetic nodes are widely distributed, either in the absence of Mid1 (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Saha and Pollard, 2012</xref>) or when Mid1 localization is affected (upon nuclear displacement).</p></sec><sec id="s05" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 phosphorylates and binds the F-BAR protein Cdc15</title><p>C-terminal tagging of Cdc15 with GFP prevented tip septa formation in <italic toggle="yes">mid1-18 tea1Δ</italic> cells, showing that this allele, also called <italic toggle="yes">cdc15-gc1</italic>, is hypomorphic. This suggests that complete Cdc15 function is required for tip occlusion (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). We found that the <italic toggle="yes">cdc15-gc1</italic> allele prevented tip septation in the <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>) and in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> upon nuclear displacement (unpublished data), whereas N-terminally GFP-tagged Cdc15 or C-terminally V5-tagged Cdc15 did not. These data led us to consider whether Cdc15 may be a direct Pom1 substrate.</p><fig id="fig2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 phosphorylates and binds the F-BAR protein Cdc15.</bold> (A) Compromising Cdc15 function rescues tip septation in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells. Cells of indicated genotypes were treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C and stained with calcofluor. Arrows indicate tip septa. Bar, 5 µm. The three tagged <italic toggle="yes">cdc15</italic> alleles used are schematically shown on the right. (B) Quantification of tip septa in septated cells treated as in A (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 250). (C) Cdc15 is phosphorylated in a Pom1-dependent manner in vivo. Cdc15-V5 was detected after Western blotting using anti–V5-HRP antibodies in indicated backgrounds. 1 µM 3MB-PP1 was added to the two samples on the right. Tubulin is used as loading control. (D) In vitro kinase assays performed with immunoprecipitated Pom1-FLAG and recombinant MBP-Cdc15N and MBP-Cdc15C. Phosphorimager detection of <sup>32</sup>P incorporation (bottom) and Coomassie-stained gels of substrates input, including the MBP-only control (top) are shown. (E) Coimmunoprecipitation of Cdc15 with Pom1-GFP, Pom1<sup>kd</sup>-GFP, and Pom1<sup>PxxP*</sup>-GFP precipitated using anti-GFP antibodies. The top blot shows the input, the two middle blots show the anti-GFP IP. CDK was used as a loading control in the bottom blot. (F) In vitro binding assays between Pom1 and Cdc15 using purified recombinant MBP, MBP-Cdc15C, and MBP-Cdc15N incubated with recombinant GST or GST-Pom1. Amylose beads were washed and bound proteins were run on SDS-PAGE and detected by Coomassie staining (top) and anti-GST antibodies (bottom).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig2.jpg"/></fig><p>Cdc15 is phosphorylated on more than 30 sites during interphase (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>), and several of these match the consensus of DYRK kinases (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Himpel et al., 2000</xref>). Indeed, we found that the slow-migrating, phosphorylated forms of Cdc15 were reduced in both <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 C</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp3">Fig. S2, A and B</ext-link>). Furthermore, Pom1 immunoprecipitated from cell extracts or recombinant Pom1, but not recombinant kinase-dead Pom1 (Pom1<sup>kd</sup>), efficiently phosphorylated the C-terminal half of Cdc15 (Cdc15C; aa 441-end) in vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 D</xref>; and Fig. S2, C and D), even resulting in an up-shift of the fragment (Fig. S2 D). Thus, Cdc15 is phosphorylated in a <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic>-dependent manner in vivo and directly by Pom1 in vitro.</p><p>Interestingly, Cdc15 also coimmunoprecipitated Pom1-GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 E</xref>), and in vitro pull-down assays showed that this interaction is direct and occurs with Cdc15C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 F</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Pom1<sup>PxxP*</sup></italic> mutant, in which all polyproline motifs are mutated (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hachet et al., 2011</xref>), still bound Cdc15 in vivo and in vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 E</xref> and Fig. S2 E), indicating that the binding does not occur through canonical SH3-PxxP binding. The Pom1-Cdc15 interaction did not depend on Pom1 activity or phosphorylation status, as Cdc15 also bound Pom1<sup>kd</sup> both in vivo and in vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 E</xref> and Fig. S2 E). Furthermore, Pom1 truncation analysis showed that Pom1 binds Cdc15 via its kinase domain, suggesting a kinase–substrate interaction (Fig. S2, F–H). Collectively with the genetic analyses, these data indicate a direct regulation of Cdc15 by Pom1.</p></sec><sec id="s06" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 phosphorylates Cdc15 to prevent septum formation at cell tips</title><p>To identify phosphorylation sites, we performed in vitro kinase assays using purified Cdc15C and Pom1, or Pom1<sup>kd</sup> as control (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp4">Fig. S3 A</ext-link>), followed by mass spectrometry analysis (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp5">Fig. S4</ext-link>). We identified 14 phosphorylation sites in Cdc15C, all upstream of the SH3 domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 A</xref> and Fig. S4). All but one of these had been previously identified as phosphorylated in vivo (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Mutation of these 14 sites to alanine strongly reduced but did not eliminate Pom1 phosphorylation (unpublished data). Five additional sites match the loose DYRK kinase consensus (RxxS), with two previously identified in vivo and three present in small tryptic peptides that would have been difficult to detect by mass spectrometry. Mutation of these five sites to alanine in combination with the first 14, yielding a <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutant, essentially abolished Cdc15 phosphorylation by Pom1 in vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 phosphorylates Cdc15 to prevent septum formation at cell tips.</bold> (A) Schematic representation of Pom1 phosphorylation sites mutated on the Cdc15 C-terminal fragment. Asterisks mark sites previously identified in vivo. Red and black sites were identified by mass spectrometry after in vitro phosphorylation of Cdc15 by Pom1. Black sites were mutated in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RxxS13A orD</sup></italic> (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>) and red sites newly mutated here. The five blue sites were identified from sequence analysis. Black, red, and blue sites are all mutated in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A or D</sup>.</italic> The same sites, except the three overlaid with the black line, are mutated in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>16D</sup>.</italic> (B) In vitro kinase assays performed with purified recombinant GST-Pom1 and recombinant MBP-Cdc15C wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">19A</italic> fragments. Phosphorimager detection of <sup>32</sup>P incorporation (bottom) and Coomassie-stained gels of substrates input (top) are shown. (C) Calcofluor-stained cells of indicated genotypes treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 or methanol for 2 h at 25°C. Arrows indicate tip septa. (D) Quantification of tip septa in septated cells of indicated genotypes that were treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 200). (E) meGFP-Cdc15 (green) imaged live at 25°C in wild-type, <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ&lt;</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells. <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells were treated with 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C before imaging. Separation of the SPB, marked by Sid4-mRFP (purple), was used as time reference. Arrows indicate actomyosin ring formation at cell tips. (F) <italic toggle="yes">meGFP-Cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> imaged live at 25°C in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells. Arrows indicate actomyosin ring formation at cell tips. (G) Rlc1-GFP imaged live at 25°C in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic>. Cells were treated with 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C before imaging. (H) <italic toggle="yes">meGFP-Cdc15<sup>16D</sup></italic> imaged live at 25°C in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells. Cells were treated with 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C before imaging. Bars, 5 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig3.jpg"/></fig><p>We tested the function of these 19 phosphorylation sites in vivo by mutating them to alanine (to abolish phosphorylation) or aspartic acid (to mimic phosphorylation) and integrating the mutant <italic toggle="yes">cdc15</italic> alleles at the endogenous locus. Both phosphomutants were viable, although the <italic toggle="yes">19D</italic> mutant showed defects in cytokinesis, with 25% of cells showing a multiseptated phenotype and &gt;10% of cells showing curved septa (Fig. S3, B and C). Remarkably, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> almost completely rescued tip septation in 3MB-PP1–treated <italic toggle="yes">pom1-as1 mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 D</xref>). In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup> mid1Δ</italic> double-mutant cells showed tip septa, even in the presence of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>), consistent with the idea that this allele is no longer regulated by Pom1. To test whether Pom1 specifically regulates Cdc15 for tip occlusion via these sites, we additionally used previously characterized Cdc15 phospho-alleles (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>), in which either a subset of the 19 identified sites (<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13A</sup></italic>
<sup>or</sup>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>D</sup></italic>; 10 sites in common with the 19 mutated here) or a distinct set of 11 SP sites (<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>SP11A</sup></italic>
<sup>or</sup>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>D</sup></italic>; five sites in common with the 19 mutated here) is mutated. The <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13A</sup></italic>
<sup>or</sup>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>D</sup></italic> alleles showed effects similar to those of <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic>
<sup>or D</sup>, respectively, although less penetrant. In contrast, consistent with the lower overlap of the 11 SP sites with the 19 Pom1 phosphorylation sites, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>SP11D</sup></italic> only marginally rescued tip septation in 3MB-PP1–treated <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells, and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>SP11A</sup></italic> caused only a small increase of tip septa in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>). We conclude that Pom1 regulates tip occlusion by phosphorylating Cdc15 on specific sites.</p><p>The tip occlusion pathway prevents tip septation, but not actomyosin ring assembly; ring components assemble at cell tips in <italic toggle="yes">mid1</italic> mutant cells but then slide away before septation (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). We tested whether ring sliding is controlled by Pom1 phosphorylation of Cdc15. Whereas meGFP-Cdc15 assembled in a ring-like structure at the tips of 77% of <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells (27 of 35 cells) and then slid away, Cdc15 was unable to slide toward the cell middle in 3MB-PP1 treated <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 E</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp6">Videos 1 and 2</ext-link>). Similarly, N-terminally meGFP-tagged <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells assembled ring-like structures at cell tips and failed to slide toward the cell middle in &gt;90% of the cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 F</xref>). In contrast, imaging the ring with myosin light chain protein Rlc1-GFP in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> mutants showed ring sliding in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> background in addition to unstable, sliding and double rings in <italic toggle="yes">mid1+</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 G</xref> and Fig. S3 I). However, imaging of meGFP-Cdc15<sup>19D</sup> revealed a reduced intensity of Cdc15 at cell tips, in the ring and more globally in the cell. Western blotting confirmed that Cdc15<sup>19D</sup> is present at lower levels than wild-type Cdc15 (Fig. S3, E–H), suggesting this allele is unstable. This finding opens the possibility that the observed rescue of tip occlusion is caused by the lower levels of the allele rather than its phospho-mimetic action. To address this point, we generated <italic toggle="yes">cdc15</italic> alleles with fewer mutations. We found that a <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>16D</sup></italic> allele with three fewer mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 A</xref>), which could still be weakly phosphorylated by Pom1 (Fig. S3 D), was expressed at levels as wild type (Fig. S3, E–H) yet displayed rescue of tip septation and ring sliding as the <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C, D, and H</xref>; and Fig. S3, B and J). Thus, all observed phenotypes are due to phospho-mimetic effects rather than the low expression levels <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic>.</p><p>In summary, Pom1 phosphorylates Cdc15 directly in vitro on multiple residues, at least 15 of which are phosphorylated in vivo. This causes ring instability and allows the ring to slide away from the cell tips in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> strains, thus preventing septa from forming at the cell poles.</p></sec><sec id="s07" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 promotes Cdc15 dynamics in vivo</title><p>Cdc15 localizes to cell tips during interphase and the cytokinetic ring for cell division (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carnahan and Gould, 2003</xref>). Pom1 localizes prominently to cell tips from which it forms concentration gradients (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hachet et al., 2011</xref>), but we found it also localizes to the division site both in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> and wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp7">Fig. S5 B</ext-link>). Indeed, Pom1 is detected at the actomyosin ring during ring formation in both wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells after SPB separation, which were labeled with the SPB marker Sid4-mRFP (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2003</xref>). Pom1 remained colocalized with meGFP-Cdc15 until cell division (Fig. S5 A). Thus, Pom1 is partly coincident with Cdc15 at cell tips and the division site.</p><fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 promotes Cdc15 dynamics in vivo<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></bold> (A) Localization of Pom1-tdTomato (purple) and meGFP-Cdc15 (green) at cell tips and at the division site. The SPB marker Sid4-mRFP (purple) was used as time reference. Arrowheads indicate Pom1 at the cell middle. (B) meGFP-Cdc15 in wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> backgrounds treated with 3MB-PP1 for 4 h at 25°C. Arrowheads indicate stable GFP dots at the cell tips in time lapse images. (C) Quantification of meGFP-Cdc15 localization in cells as in B. meGFP-Cdc15 dots had to remain stable for &gt;10 min to be counted as stable structures (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50 dots). (D) meGFP-Cdc15 in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> cdc25-22</italic> cells arrested in G2 at 36°C for 4 h and treated with vehicle only (methanol; left) or 3MB-PP1 (right) for 10 min. Arrows indicate medial localization and filament-like meGFP-Cdc15 structures. (E) Quantification of meGFP-Cdc15 medial structures in cells as in D (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50). (F) meGFP-Cdc15 FRAP half times (top) and mobile fractions (bottom) in wild type, <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ&lt;</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 4 h, and in meGFP-cdc15<italic toggle="yes"><sup>19A</sup></italic> during interphase, ring formation, and constriction. SPB marker Sid4-mRFP was used to determine cytokinesis stages (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 15). (G) Quantification of the duration of the cytokinetic ring formation and constriction in wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1,</sup> pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> cells. <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells were treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 4 h (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 10). Error bars are standard deviations. ***, P &lt; 0.001. Bars, 5 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig4.jpg"/></fig><p>We examined the effects that the loss of Pom1 has on Cdc15 localization and dynamics by imaging Cdc15 in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> backgrounds, again using Sid4-mRFP as a cell cycle marker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 E</xref> and not depicted). When compared with the wildtype strain, these mutants showed no changes in timing of Cdc15 recruitment to cytokinetic nodes, which occurred at T0 (unpublished data). However, when we arrested cells in G2 by use of a conditional <italic toggle="yes">cdc25-22</italic> allele, inhibition of Pom1<sup>as1</sup> with 3MB-PP1 led to the formation of large, aberrant Cdc15 foci at the cell middle, which were not present in untreated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, D and E</xref>). This aberrant localization happened even in cells with a single, unseparated SPB structure, suggesting it was not caused by bypass of the <italic toggle="yes">cdc25-22</italic> G2 block (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Martin and Berthelot-Grosjean, 2009</xref>). Consistently, a large percentage of <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> mutant cells showed large, static Cdc15 dot structures during interphase, mostly at cell tips, whereas Cdc15 localized in dynamic spots around the cell cortex in interphase wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, B and C</xref>). We also observed large, static Cdc15 dot structures during interphase in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutants. In contrast, in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells, Cdc15 was as dynamic as in wild-type cells (Fig. S5 C). Finally, we noted that Cdc15, which is exclusively at the ring during cytokinesis in wild-type cells, was present at cell tips during cytokinesis in a significant fraction of <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutant cells (Fig. S5 D). Thus, Cdc15 appears to form more stable structures in the absence of Pom1.</p><p>Fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) experiments confirmed that Cdc15 is more stable in the absence of Pom1, both at the cell cortex in interphase and at various stages of cytokinesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 F</xref>). To measure turnover during interphase, we photobleached the entire cell tip; meGFP-Cdc15 recovered with a half time of 4 s in wild-type and <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells, whereas in 3MB-PP1–treated <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells, meGFP-Cdc15 recovered with a half-time of 12 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 F</xref>). Similar results were obtained in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic> backgrounds (unpublished data). To measure Cdc15 turnover during cytokinesis within the actomyosin ring, we photobleached half the ring at two different stages: during ring formation and during ring constriction when the septum forms. In both cases, we observed a significant increase in Cdc15 FRAP halftimes in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells treated with 3MB-PP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 F</xref>). Consistently, FRAP of meGFP-Cdc15<sup>19A</sup> showed slow halftimes during interphase and cytokinesis. Concomitant with the increase recovery halftimes, meGFP-Cdc15 mobile fractions were significantly reduced in <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutants compared with wild-type or <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 F</xref>).</p><p>As Pom1 controls tip occlusion even in <italic toggle="yes">mid1+</italic> cells and promotes Cdc15 dynamics at the normal medial division site, we tested whether Pom1 modulates the timing of ring formation, maturation, and constriction in otherwise wild-type cells. Remarkably, the timing of ring constriction was significantly faster in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> treated with 3MB-PP1 and in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic> cells compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 G</xref>).</p><p>In summary, these data show that Pom1-mediated phosphorylation of Cdc15 promotes Cdc15 dynamics in vivo. These effects likely permit displacement of the cytokinetic ring toward the cell middle when it has formed at the tips but also delay ring constriction at the normal medial location.</p></sec><sec id="s08" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 inhibits Cdc15 binding to Fic1 and Pxl1</title><p>To characterize the molecular consequences of Pom1-mediated Cdc15 phosphorylation, we sought to identify other factors involved in the Pom1-Cdc15 regulatory pathway by searching for mutants that prevented septa formation at tips in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells. Loss of function in several actomyosin ring components (Rlc1, Fim1, Ain1, Myp2, Rng2, Cdc12, and F-actin) failed to restore tip occlusion to <italic toggle="yes">mid1-18 tea1Δ</italic> cells (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). Similarly, deletion of several actin patch mutants (Wsp1, Dip1, and End4) did not restore tip occlusion in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells (Fig. S5 E). In contrast, deletion of cytokinetic ring components Fic1 or Pxl1 efficiently restored tip occlusion in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>). Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">pxl1</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ myo52N-RFP-nup146</italic> cells also prevented septation at cell tips upon nuclear displacement (unpublished data). This suggests that Pxl1 and Fic1 are required for dephosphorylated Cdc15 to promote tip septation.</p><fig id="fig5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 inhibits Cdc15 binding with Fic1 and Pxl1.</bold> (A) Cells of indicated genotypes treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 (top) or no drug (bottom) for 2 h at 25°C, and stained with calcofluor. Bar is 5 µm. (B) Quantification of tip septa in septated cells as in A (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 200). (C) Pom1 phosphorylation inhibits Cdc15-Fic1 interaction. Recombinant Fic1-His was immobilized on nickel beads and incubated with recombinant MBP or MBP-Cdc15C, prephosphorylated or not by recombinant GST-Pom1. Beads were washed and bound proteins were run on SDS-PAGE and detected by Coomassie-staining and Western blotting using anti-MBP antibodies. One fifth of each MBP protein input is shown as control. (D) Recombinant Fic1-His was immobilized on nickel beads and incubated with recombinant MBP, MBP-Cdc15C<sup>19A</sup>, or MBP-Cdc15C<sup>19D</sup>. Beads were washed and bound proteins were run on SDS-PAGE and detected by Coomassie staining and Western blotting using anti-MBP antibodies. One fourth of each MBP fragment input is shown as control. (E) Pom1 phosphorylation inhibits Cdc15-Pxl1 interaction. Recombinant GST-Pxl1 was immobilized on glutathione beads and incubated with recombinant MBP, MBP-Cdc15C, prephosphorylated or not by recombinant purified GST-Pom1 or GST-Pom1<sup>kd</sup>, MBP-Cdc15C<sup>19A</sup>, or MBP-Cdc15C<sup>19D</sup>. Beads were washed and bound proteins were run on SDS-PAGE and detected by Coomassie staining and Western blotting using anti-MBP antibodies. One fifth of each MBP protein input is shown as a control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig5.jpg"/></fig><p>Cdc15 directly binds Fic1 and Pxl1 via its C-terminal SH3 domain (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bohnert and Gould, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2015</xref>). We tested whether Pom1 regulates Cdc15 binding with Pxl1 and Fic1 through in vitro pull-down assays. Indeed, whereas MBP-Cdc15C bound Fic1-HIS, the binding was completely lost when GST-Pom1 and ATP were added to MBP-Cdc15C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 C</xref>). In contrast, addition of GST-Pom1<sup>kd</sup> (which also directly binds Cdc15C; Fig. S2 E) did not block the Cdc15-Fic1 interaction (Fig. S5 F). Thus, Pom1-dependent phosphorylation of Cdc15, not Pom1 protein, prevents Cdc15 from binding Fic1 in vitro. Consistently, purified MBP-Cdc15<sup>19A</sup>, but not MBP-Cdc15<sup>19D</sup>, bound Fic1-HIS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 D</xref>). Phosphorylation of Cdc15 by Pom1 also inhibited its binding to Pxl1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 E</xref>). In contrast, we found that both MBP-Cdc15<sup>19A</sup> and MBP-Cdc15<sup>19D</sup> were able to bind Pom1 in vitro (Fig. S5 G). We conclude that Pom1 phosphorylation of Cdc15 inhibits its interaction with downstream binding partners.</p><p>We tested the effect of Pom1-dependent Cdc15 phosphorylation on Fic1 and Pxl1 in vivo. In wild-type cells, Fic1 localizes to cell tips during interphase and to the actomyosin ring (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic>, Fic1 localized more strongly at cell tips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A and B</xref>). Fic1 also localized to additional dot structures reminiscent of the Cdc15 dots observed in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 A</xref>; compare with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref> and Fig. S5 C), suggesting that Fic1 is part of the stable Cdc15 structures. Furthermore, in G2-arrested cells, inhibition of Pom1<sup>as1</sup> with 3MB-PP1 led to the formation of Fic1 structures at the cell middle, similar to the Cdc15 structures seen in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 C</xref>; compare with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 D</xref>). These data are consistent with the precocious recruitment of downstream ring components by previously characterized Cdc15 alanine mutants (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Fic1 localization to the ring was unaffected in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 A</xref>), consistent with previous data showing that its localization at the ring does not solely depend on Cdc15, but also on Imp2 (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>). In contrast, Pxl1 localization to the ring was abolished in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>16D</sup></italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 D</xref>). Collectively, these experiments suggest that Pom1 phosphorylation blocks Cdc15 interaction with Fic1 and Pxl1 in vivo and in vitro.</p><fig id="fig6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><bold>Pom1 regulates Fic1 and Pxl1 binding to Cdc15 in vivo<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></bold> (A) Fic1-GFP in wildtype, <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> backgrounds treated with 3MB-PP1 for 4 h at 25°C. Arrows indicate Fic1-GFP localization at the cell tips. (B) Quantification of Fic1-GFP tip localization as in A (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 10 cells and tips). (C) Fic1-GFP in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> cdc25-22</italic> cells arrested in G2 at 36°C for 4 h and treated with methanol (left) or 3MB-PP1 (right) for 10 min. Arrows indicate medial localization of Fic1-GFP. (D) Pxl1-GFP in wild-type, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>16D</sup></italic> cells. (E) meGFP-Cdc15 FRAP halftimes (left) and mobile fractions (right) in wild-type, <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ&lt;</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">fic1Δ</italic> during interphase, ring formation, and constriction. SPB marker Sid4-mRFP was used to determine cytokinesis stage (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 15). (F) Quantification of the duration of the cytokinetic ring constriction in wildtype, <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ&lt;</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> pxl1Δ</italic> cells (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 10) treated with 3MB-PP1 for 4h. (G) Cells of indicated genotypes treated with 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 2 h at 25°C, and stained with calcofluor. Arrowheads indicate cells with tip septa. (H) Quantification of tip septa in septated cells as in E (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> &gt; 100). Bars, 5 µm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JCB_201504073_Fig6.jpg"/></fig><p>We tested how Fic1 and Pxl1 modulate Cdc15 dynamics. FRAP experiments showed that Cdc15 is more dynamic in the ring in <italic toggle="yes">fic1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ</italic> cells compared with wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 E</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">fic1Δ</italic> but not <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ</italic> cells, we observed a significant decrease in Cdc15 FRAP halftime during ring formation, whereas both <italic toggle="yes">fic1Δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ</italic> cells showed a decrease in Cdc15 FRAP halftime during constriction. Corresponding increases in Cdc15 mobile fractions were also observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 E</xref>). Cdc15 dynamics were not affected at cell tips in these mutants. Thus, the loss of Cdc15-binding partners increases Cdc15 dynamicity during cytokinesis.</p><p>Finally, because deletion of <italic toggle="yes">pxl1</italic> causes delays in ring constriction (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ge and Balasubramanian, 2008</xref>), we tested epistasis with <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic>, which we showed above causes increased constriction rates (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 G</xref>). In <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> pxl1Δ</italic> double mutants treated with 3MB-PP1, the duration of ring constriction was as in <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 F</xref>). This is consistent with the idea that the fast constriction time in <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic> mutants is due to increased Pxl1 binding to hypophosphorylated Cdc15. Together, these data further support the notion that phosphorylation of Cdc15 by Pom1 antagonizes Fic1 and Pxl1 binding, thus keeping Cdc15 in a dynamic state, favoring ring sliding and increasing the duration of ring constriction.</p></sec><sec id="s09" sec-type=""><title>Loss of Bgs1 function restores tip occlusion</title><p>The underlying cause of ring sliding upon Pom1-mediated Cdc15 phosphorylation may be a delay in septum assembly. The septum is thought to anchor the cytokinetic ring by depositing new cell wall material (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Pardo and Nurse, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz et al., 2013</xref>), and Cdc15 participates in the activation and recruitment of the β-glucan synthase Bgs1 for septum assembly (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arasada and Pollard, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2015</xref>). Indeed, the hypomorphic Bgs1 mutation <italic toggle="yes">cps1-191</italic> prevented the formation of tip septa in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells, suggesting that compromising septum formation allows the ring to slide away from cell tips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, G and H</xref>). Additionally, we observed that septa were orthogonal to cell length in the <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ cps1-191</italic> double mutant, contrasting with the tilted septum phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 G</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s10"><title>Discussion</title><p>The DYRK-family kinase Pom1 plays a critical role in cell division positioning. Pom1 inhibits the anillin-like protein Mid1 from localizing to cell tips (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Celton-Morizur et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>). It also prevents septation at cell tips independently of Mid1 (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). In this study, we dissected the mechanism by which Pom1 prevents tip septation. We show that Pom1 inhibits the F-BAR protein Cdc15 by phosphorylating it on multiple sites, thus blocking its binding to the cytokinetic ring components Fic1 and Pxl1 and possibly antagonizing its membrane binding (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). This promotes Cdc15 dynamic turnover, extends ring constriction, and delays septation. This also allows sliding of the ring away from the cell pole. Thus, Pom1 guards against septum assembly at cell poles by inhibiting Cdc15 function.</p><sec id="s11" sec-type=""><title>The F-BAR protein Cdc15, a new Pom1 target</title><p>The pleiotropic phenotypes observed in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>kd</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1Δ</italic> cells (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bähler and Pringle, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bähler and Nurse, 2001</xref>) indicate that Pom1 has multiple substrates. The phosphorylation of the SAD-like kinase Cdr2 by Pom1 has been well characterized and plays a role in both delaying mitotic commitment and positioning the septum via the Mid1-dependent pathway (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Celton-Morizur et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Almonacid et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Martin and Berthelot-Grosjean, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Moseley et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Bhatia et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Rincon et al., 2014</xref>). We now provide strong evidence that the F-BAR protein Cdc15, essential for cytokinesis (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>), is another important Pom1 substrate. Our biochemical analysis shows that Pom1 directly binds and phosphorylates Cdc15.</p><p>A previous study on the specificity of DYRK-family kinases defined a preferred phosphorylation sequence, RxxSP (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Himpel et al., 2000</xref>). However, there is substantial variation in the actual substrate phosphorylation sites for several mammalian DYRK-family kinases (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Soundararajan et al., 2013</xref>), as well as for Pom1 (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hachet et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kettenbach et al., 2015</xref>). We find here that 15 of the 19 Pom1-dependent sites on Cdc15 are within an RxxS motif, but only four of these sites are RxxSP motifs, suggesting that substrate specificity does not simply lie within the phosphorylation motif. We found that Pom1 also directly binds Cdc15 through part of its kinase domain, suggesting that this direct binding may contribute to substrate specificity after conventional kinase–substrate interactions (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Ubersax and Ferrell, 2007</xref>). Precise mapping of the binding sites on both Pom1 and Cdc15 may help define the substrate specificity determinants of DYRK kinases.</p></sec><sec id="s12" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 converts Cdc15 to its closed, dynamic conformation</title><p>Phosphorylation has long been implicated in regulating Cdc15 function, with dephosphorylation promoting its function in cytokinesis (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Fankhauser et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Cdc15 is likely phosphorylated by multiple kinases, but none had so far been identified. The evidence that Pom1 is a genuine Cdc15 kinase is strong: Most sites phosphorylated by Pom1 in vitro were previously identified as phosphorylated in vivo (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutant, lacking all Pom1-dependent sites, largely mimics the phenotypes observed in the absence of Pom1 activity. However, <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutant cells display a stronger phenotype than <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic> mutants, suggesting that these sites are likely to be targets of additional kinases. Other identified phosphorylation sites on Cdc15 are not Pom1 targets (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Thus, Pom1 is the first characterized, but not the sole, kinase phosphorylating Cdc15.</p><p>We propose that phosphorylation of Cdc15 by Pom1 converts Cdc15 to its closed, more dynamic conformation. Previous work showed that the phosphorylation status of Cdc15 determines its conformation: hypophosphorylated Cdc15 forms an elongated filamentous shape that binds several partners, whereas the hyperphosphorylated form adopts a globular conformation that fails to bind membrane and contractile ring components (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Consistent with the idea that Pom1 converts Cdc15 to its closed form, Pom1 phosphorylation and the Cdc15 phosphomimetic allele Cdc15<sup>19D</sup> inhibit Cdc15-Pxl1 and Cdc15-Fic1 interactions in vitro. We note that Pom1 phosphorylates Cdc15 outside the SH3 domain, which is sufficient to bind Fic1 and Pxl1 (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bohnert and Gould, 2012</xref>). This suggests that Cdc15 phosphorylation leads to masking of the SH3 fragment, rather than to a direct block of Fic1 and Pxl1 binding sites.</p><p>In vivo, the lack of Pxl1 recruitment at the ring of <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> mutant cells is consistent with inhibition of its interaction with Cdc15. The double-ring phenotypes observed in <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> mutants are also reminiscent of the phenotype observed in <italic toggle="yes">pxl1Δ</italic> cells (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Ge and Balasubramanian, 2008</xref>). We note that the phenotypes of <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> mutant cells may be the result of both phospho-mimetic effects and reduced Cdc15 levels. However, the reduction in Cdc15<sup>19D</sup> levels is mild (less than threefold, as assessed by fluorescence quantification) compared with the 60-fold Cdc15 depletion that led to ring sliding in a previous study (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arasada and Pollard, 2014</xref>). Our finding that <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>13D</sup></italic> mutants exhibit partial <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> phenotypes but are expressed at levels similar to wild-type Cdc15 (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>) also suggests that phospho-mimetic effects explain a large part of the observed phenotype. Conversely, the strong, stable localization of Cdc15 and Fic1 at cell poles of interphase <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells is consistent with the idea that the hypophosphorylated Cdc15 forms stable complexes with its downstream partners at the wrong time and location (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Willet et al., 2015</xref>). FRAP experiments also demonstrated that Pom1 modulates the dynamic turnover of Cdc15, with Cdc15 showing slower exchange at cell poles and at the contractile ring in absence of Pom1-dependent phosphorylation or in the <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> mutant. Thus, our data on Cdc15 localization, turnover, and binding to Fic1 and Pxl1 all concur in showing that phosphorylation by Pom1 promotes a closed Cdc15 state.</p></sec><sec id="s13" sec-type=""><title>Pom1 provides an error-correction mechanism for division site positioning</title><p>How does the Pom1-induced closed Cdc15 state prevent septation at cell poles? The key factor appears to be that the actomyosin rings assembled at cell tips in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> can slide toward the cell middle, leading to the tilted septa predominantly seen in these cells (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). This sliding was completely abolished in absence of Pom1-dependent Cdc15 phosphorylation, leading to tip septation, but was restored in Cdc15 phospho-mimetic mutants. Similarly, deletion of <italic toggle="yes">fic1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">pxl1</italic>, but not of actin patch components (<italic toggle="yes">wsp1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">end4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">dip1</italic>), or mutations in a host of other ring components (<italic toggle="yes">cdc12</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">rlc1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">fim1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ain1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">myp2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">rng2</italic>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>) prevented tip septation. Although Pom1 is detected at the division site, it is present prominently at cell poles, from where it forms concentration gradients. The enrichment of Pom1 at the cell poles is likely to be critical for its role in tip occlusion. Indeed, Pom1 activity is critical when rings are assembled at cell poles, but it affects cell division only mildly at the medial location. In addition, previous data showed that both Tea1 and Tea4, required for Pom1 localization (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Padte et al., 2006</xref>), are necessary to prevent tip septation (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2007</xref>). Together, these data indicate that the graded activity of Pom1 from the cell poles preferentially prevents the binding of Fic1 and Pxl1 to Cdc15 and the formation of stable Cdc15 complexes at cell poles, thus destabilizing the ring and allowing it to slide toward the cell middle.</p><p>The role of Pom1 likely extends beyond Cdc15 phosphorylation. Indeed, Cyk3, Rga7, and Imp2, three proteins involved in cytokinesis, are phosphorylated in a Pom1-dependent manner in vivo and at least Rga7 is a Pom1 substrate in vitro (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kettenbach et al., 2015</xref>). Rga7 and Imp2 associate in vivo and, like Cdc15, form complexes with Fic1 and Pxl1 to promote ring stability (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Martín-García et al., 2014</xref>). Cyk3 also associates with Fic1 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bohnert and Gould, 2012</xref>). We have also observed that Pom1 can phosphorylate Fic1 and Pxl1 in vitro (unpublished data). Indeed, the role of Pom1 in prolonging ring constriction may rely on its ability to phosphorylate Pxl1, in addition to Cdc15. Thus, Pom1-dependent destabilization of the ring may rely on it regulating a global Cdc15-centered network.</p><p>We suggest that this Pom1-dependent regulation eventually impinges on septum synthesis because partial inactivation of the β-glucan synthase Bgs1 efficiently prevented tip septation in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ pom1<sup>as1</sup></italic> cells. This is in agreement with several previous studies showing physical and functional links between Cdc15 and septum synthesis (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Vjestica et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arasada and Pollard, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2015</xref>), which is required for stable division site placement (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Pardo and Nurse, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz et al., 2013</xref>). Septum synthesis also contributes force for ingression (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Proctor et al., 2012</xref>). Thus, our observation that ring constriction occurs faster in absence of Pom1 activity is also consistent with the idea that Pom1-dependent phosphorylation of Cdc15 and associated factors delays septum assembly. Future work should reveal the specific molecular links between Cdc15 complex phospho-regulation and septum assembly.</p><p>We note several parallels with other systems. At the molecular level, there is an interesting parallel between our discovery that Pom1 prevents Cdc15 interaction with its partners and the role of the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> DYRK family kinase Minibrain, which phosphorylates the BAR protein amphiphysin to inhibit its binding to endophilin (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Murakami et al., 2006</xref>). Thus, phospho-inhibition of F-BAR proteins (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith and Gould, 2010</xref>) by DYRK and other kinases may represent a common strategy to keep their activity in check. The role of Pom1 gradients in destabilizing Cdc15 at cell poles is also highly reminiscent of the role of bacterial MinCDE protein gradients in destabilizing FtsZ assembly at cell poles (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Lutkenhaus, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Gregory et al., 2008</xref>), suggesting that at a more conceptual level, the destabilization of core components of the division apparatus may be a fundamental strategy to restrict the position of division.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s14"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s15" sec-type=""><title>Yeast strains, media, and genetic methods</title><p>Standard methods for <italic toggle="yes">S. pombe</italic> media and genetic manipulations were used throughout. Generally, for imaging, cells were grown in synthetic Edinburgh minimal medium (EMM) with appropriate supplements, whereas for biochemistry experiments, cells were grown in rich yeast extract medium. All strains used in this study are listed in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1" id="supp8">Table S1</ext-link>. Tagged and deletion strains were constructed by using a PCR-based approach (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bähler et al., 1998</xref>) and confirmed by PCR. Strain construction and tetrad analysis were accomplished through standard methods. For observation of septa and tip septation, strains were grown at 25°C to exponential phase before treatment with vehicle (methanol) or inhibitor (3MB-PP1 at 1 µM final concentration unless indicated otherwise). <italic toggle="yes">cdc25</italic>-22 arrests for imaging purposes were at 36°C for 4 h.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> phospho mutant alleles were created using the pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13A</sup></italic> and pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13D</sup></italic> integration vector, containing <italic toggle="yes">cdc15</italic> open reading frame and 5′ and 3′ noncoding regions (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). A multisite-directed mutagenesis kit (Affymetrix) was used to obtain the correct set of mutations after multiple rounds of site-directed mutagenesis. Integration of pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> and pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> at the endogenous locus was done as described previously (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>). In brief, pIRT2 <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19A</sup></italic> or <italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>19D</sup></italic> were transformed and integrated at the endogenous locus in a <italic toggle="yes">cdc15Δ::ura4+ heterozygous diploid strain</italic>. Transformed diploids were then sporulated and integrants were recovered on the basis of replacement of ura4+, generating resistance to 5-fluorourotic acid, and correct integration was verified by PCR. The integrations were then sequenced to ensure that no additional mutations were present. The mutants were subsequently tagged at their N terminus with meGFP using the <italic toggle="yes">pFA6a-kanMX6-Pcdc15-meGFP</italic> plasmid provided to us by T. Pollard (Yale University, New Haven, CT; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Pollard, 2005</xref>). Design of the chimeric protein of the Myosin V Myo52 motor and coiled-coil domains with a nuclear pore complex protein Nup146 (Myo52N-RFP-Nup146) was described by <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lo Presti et al. (2012)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s16" sec-type=""><title>Molecular biology methods</title><p>All plasmids were constructed using standard molecular biology techniques. N- (amino acids 1–420) and C- (amino acids 441–stop) terminal fragments were amplified by PCR from <italic toggle="yes">cdc15</italic> cDNA (Gould Laboratory, Vanderbilt University), and cloned into pMAL2c vectors using EcoRI and PstI sites. To make the recombinant MBP-cdc15C<sup>19A</sup> and MBP-cdc15C<sup>19D</sup> constructs, gene synthesis (Eurofins Genomics) was used to synthesize Cdc15 gene fragments coding for amino acids 441–732 with the A and D mutations noted on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 A</xref>. PCR stitching (primers available on request) was then used to stitch this fragment with a fragment coding for amino acids 733–928 amplified from pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13A</sup></italic> or pIRT2-<italic toggle="yes">cdc15<sup>RXXS13D</sup></italic> (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). The final product was then cloned into pMAL2c with flanking EcoRI and PstI sites. Multisite-directed mutagenesis (Affymetrix) was used to mutate the remaining sites, S813, S821, S831, and S836. Recombinant Fic1-HIS and Pxl1-GST constructs are described previously (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>). GST-Pom1 and GST-Pom1<sup>kd</sup> were also described previously (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hachet et al., 2011</xref>). To make Pom1 truncations, GST-Pom1 fragments of appropriate length were amplified from the GST-Pom1 plasmid and cloned into the pGEX-4T-1 vector using EcoRI and NotI sites. Details of primers and restriction sites used are available on request.</p></sec><sec id="s17" sec-type=""><title>Protein methods</title><p>For Western blot analysis of Cdc15, extracts from yeast grown in 100 ml yeast extract medium were prepared in CXS buffer (50 mM Hepes, pH 7.0, 20 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM EDTA, pH 7.5, and protease inhibitor cocktail) by grinding in liquid nitrogen with a mortar and pestle. After thawing, NaCl and Triton X-100 were added to final concentrations of 150 mM and 0.1%, respectively. For phosphatase treatments, 3.7 5U of PP1 phosphatase and 1× protein metallo<italic toggle="yes">phosphatase</italic> buffer (New England BioLabs) were added protein extracts prepared as above for 40 min at 30°C. For Fig. S2 B, protein lysates were prepared by denatured lysis of cell pellets in NP-40 lysis buffer and SDS lysis buffer as in (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gould et al., 1991</xref>). Lysates were run on an 8% polyacrylamide gel.</p><p>For coimmunoprecipitations, cell pellets were frozen in a dry ice/ethanol bath and lysed by bead disruption in NP-40 lysis buffer as previously described (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2010</xref>). Pom1-GFP proteins were immunoprecipitated with an anti-GFP antibody.</p><p>Standard protocols were used for SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis, except for phospho-shift assays, where the samples were run at a low voltage (90 V) for 3 h to see a good shift. Antibodies used on Western blots were anti-Cdc15(1–405) polyclonal antibody (VU326; Cocalico Biologicals; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Roberts-Galbraith et al., 2009</xref>), anti-PSTAIR antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) for CDK detection, DM1a for α-tubulin detection, anti–V5-HRP (Invitrogen), mouse monoclonal anti-GFP (Roche), anti-MBP (Cell Signaling), and anti-GST (Sigma-Aldrich).</p><p>Recombinant proteins were produced in BL21 cells and purified on GST-Sepharose (GE Healthcare), amylose beads (New England BioLabs), or His<sup>pur</sup> cobalt resin (Pierce Biotechnology) according to the manufacturers' protocols.</p><p>Radioactive hot kinase assays, were performed in 30 mM Tris, 100 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EGTA, 10% glycerol, 20 mM ATP, and 2 mCi [<sup>32</sup>P] ATP (PerkinElmer BLU502A250UC) with equivalent amounts of GST-Pom1 and GST-Pom1<sup>kd</sup> in a 1-µl final volume reaction. After a 30-min incubation at 30°C, the reaction was stopped by boiling in sample buffer and analyzed by SDS-PAGE. <sup>32</sup>P-incorporation was detected in a Phosphorimager (Molecular Dynamics, Inc.). Cold assays for the identification of phosphorylation sites were performed the same way except without hot ATP and with 40 mM ATP. A second dose of GST-Pom1 was added after 45 min and the reaction arrested after 90 min. Samples were resolved by SDS-PAGE for Coomassie staining and autoradiography.</p><p>For hot kinase assays using Pom1 from cell extracts, <italic toggle="yes">pom1</italic>-FLAG<sub>3</sub> cell pellets were snap frozen and lysed by bead disruption in NP-40 lysis buffer as described previously (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gould et al., 1991</xref>), except with the addition of 0.5 mM diisopropyl fluorophosphate (Sigma-Aldrich). Pom1-FLAG<sub>3</sub> was immunoprecipitated using an anti-FLAG antibody (M2; Sigma-Aldrich). Pom1 kinase assays were performed as previously published (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bähler and Nurse, 2001</xref>). In brief, bead-bound Pom1-FLAG<sub>3</sub> was incubated in a reaction with recombinant MBP, MBP-Cdc15N, or MBP-Cdc15C and AB buffer with 10 µM cold ATP and 0.5 µl γ<sup>32</sup>P-ATP. AB buffer consists of 25 mM MOPS, pH 7.0, 60 mM β-glycerolphosphate, 7 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 7 mM MnCl, 0.1 mM sodium vanadate, 40 µg/ml aprotinin, 20 µg/ml leupeptin, 1 mM PMSF, and 2 mM benzamidine (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bähler and Nurse, 2001</xref>). Kinase assays were incubated at 30°C for 40 min. Samples were resolved by SDS-PAGE for Coomassie staining and autoradiography.</p><p>For in vitro binding assays, recombinant proteins were first incubated and immobilized on the respective resin for 2 h at 4°C, washed and incubated with the binding partner for 2 h at 4°C. In the case of the Pom1-Cdc15 binding experiments shown, the incubation was overnight, but binding was similarly observed after 2-h incubation at 4°C. The binding buffers were as follows: for MBP assays, 50 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM KCl, 10 mM maltose; for GST assays, 1× PBS; and for HIS assays, 6 M guanidine-HCL, 50 mM sodium phosphate, 300 mM sodium chloride, 10 mM imidazole, pH 7.4. The wash buffers were in all cases the same as the binding buffer but supplemented with 150 mM NaCl and 0.1% Triton X-100. For the experiments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>, MBP-Cdc15C was first incubated with GST-Pom1-FL or GST-Pom1<sup>kd</sup> in cold kinase buffer (AB buffer with 10 µM cold ATP) for 90 min. The reaction was then added to immobilized Pxl1 or Fic1. The beads were washed three times for 10 min, and proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE for Coomassie staining or Western blot analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s18" sec-type=""><title>Phosphorylation site identification by mass spectrometry</title><p>TCA-precipitated proteins were digested and analyzed by two-dimensional liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry as described previously (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>), except that the following modifications were made. Proteins were digested by trypsin, chymotrypsin, and elastase. The number of salt elution steps was reduced to 6 (i.e., 0, 25, 50, 100, 600, 1,000, and 5,000 mM ammonium acetate). Peptide identifications were filtered and assembled using Scaffold (version 3.6.5; Proteome Software) and phosphorylation sites were analyzed using Scaffold PTM (version 2.1.3) using the following filters: minimum of 99.9% protein identification probability, minimum of five unique peptides, minimum of 95% peptide identification probability.</p></sec><sec id="s19" sec-type=""><title>Microscopy and image analysis</title><p>A DeltaVision epifluorescence system (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bendezú and Martin, 2013</xref>) and/or a spinning disk confocal microscope (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bendezú et al., 2012</xref>) were used to acquire images of cells in mid log growth at 25°C. The DeltaVision platform (Applied Precision) composed of a customized Olympus IX-71 inverted microscope and a UPlan Apo 60×/1.42 NA oil objective, a CoolSNAP HQ2 camera (Photometrics), and an Insight SSI 7 color combined unit illuminator was used for visualizing septa after staining with Calcofluor White (Sigma-Aldrich). Images were acquired with <italic toggle="yes">softWoRx</italic> software (Applied Precision). Spinning disk microscopy was performed using a Leica DMI4000B inverted microscope equipped with HCX PL APO X100/1.46 (NA) oil objective and a PerkinElmer Ultraview Confocal system (including a Yokagawa CSU22 real-time confocal scanning head and solid-state laser and a cooled 14-bit frame transfer EMCCD C9100-50 camera). The spinning disk was used for high-temporal resolution and time-lapse fluorescence imaging. For time-lapse imaging, cells were placed on EMM agarose pads, covered with coverslip and sealed using Valap (a Vaseline, lanolin, and paraffin mixture). For spinning disk confocal imaging, optical slices were acquired every 0.6 µm using Volocity software (PerkinElmer), except <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 G</xref> and Fig. S1 F, for which the slices were obtained every 0.3 µm. All panels show maximum projections, unless otherwise indicated. All images were assembled using ImageJ (National Institutes of Health) and Adobe Photoshop and Adobe Illustrator (Adobe). Tip septa were measured by counting cells that showed calcofluor signal at cell poles. Cells that showed septa as shown in Fig. S1 C were counted as tip septated cells.</p><p>For nuclear displacement cells were grown for 16–24 h at 30°C in EMM-AL to induce expression of the Myo52-Nup146 construct. They were then treated with MBC (Sigma-Aldrich), which was used at final concentration of 25 µg/ml from a stock of 2.5 mg/ml in DMSO and/or 1 µM 3MB-PP1 for 4 h.</p><p>Timing of cytokinetic events was measured using the SPB as reference. Splitting of the SPB was marked as T0. Ring formation and constriction timing were measured in strains expressing tagged myosin light-chain protein Rlc1-GFP. To time ring constriction, the time point at which the diameter of the ring started decreasing was used to mark the start of constriction, and the end of constriction was marked by the disappearance of Rlc1.</p><p>For measuring Cdc15 dot stability, images were taken every 4 min for 12 min. Cells that showed stable dots over this period of time were counted.</p><p>FRAP was performed with the photokinesis unit of the spinning disk system (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bendezú and Martin, 2011</xref>). A circular zone of 1-µm diameter was used for the ring, and the polygon tool was used to draw a line by hand around the cell tip. Images were recorded before photo bleaching and immediately after, every second for 90 s. For FRAP analysis, the mean fluorescence intensities were measured over time in three regions: (1) the photobleached region, (2) the background outside the cell, and (3) another nonbleached cell. The background fluorescence was subtracted from the fluorescence intensities of the photobleached and the nonbleached cell. The loss of signal as a result of imaging was corrected by dividing the adjusted bleached regions intensity by the adjusted intensity of the nonbleached cell. All values were normalized so that the prephotobleaching value equals 1. Mobile fractions (F<sub>m</sub>) and half-time (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>) values were calculated from the best-fit curve equation: y = a (1 − e<sup>−bx</sup>), where a = F<sub>m</sub> and In0.5/b = <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>, using CurveExpertPro software. A <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used to evaluate whether results were significantly different for F<sub>m</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>.</p><p>Fluorescence intensity at cell tips, cytokinetic ring, and whole cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figs. 3, E and F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6 B</xref>) was measured on a sum projection of spinning disk confocal z-stacks of an individual cell. For measurement of fluorescence intensity, the polygon tool in ImageJ was used to draw a line by hand around the cell tip, cytokinetic ring, or whole cell and the mean fluorescence intensity within this area was obtained using the Analyze &lt; Measure tool. The fluorescence intensity measured was corrected for the background fluorescence intensity (measured just outside the cell examined) and the fluorescence intensity of an untagged cell (acquired and measured for fluorescence intensity in the same way ).</p></sec><sec id="s20" sec-type=""><title>Online supplemental materials</title><p>Fig. S1 shows further characterization of Pom1 kinase activity in preventing septum formation at cell tips. Fig. S2 shows further biochemical characterization of Cdc15 phosphorylation by Pom1 and binding with Pom1. Fig. S3 shows the in vivo characterization of Cdc15 phospho mutants. Fig. S4 shows the mass spectra of a representative phosphopeptide from each of the identified Pom1 phosphorylation sites on Cdc15 in vitro. Fig. S5 shows the localization of Pom1 to the actomyosin ring in wild type and <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> background, Cdc15 dynamics at cell tips in different mutant backgrounds, quantification of tip septation in actin patch mutants and in vitro assays that further characterize interactions of Cdc15 with Pom1 and Fic1. Video 1 shows ring sliding away from cell tips in <italic toggle="yes">mid1Δ</italic> cells. Video 2 shows the lack of ring sliding observed in <italic toggle="yes">pom1<sup>as1</sup> mid1Δ</italic> cells. Table S1 lists the genotypes of all the strains used in this study. Online supplemental material is available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201504073/DC1</ext-link>. Additional data are available in the JCB DataViewer at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201504073.dv." id="urilnk44954a03-b228-918c-32b-4685ac055b8c">http://dx.doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201504073.dv.</ext-link></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplemental Materials</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_211_3_653__index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_jcb.201504073_JCB_201504073_sm.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_jcb.201504073_JCB_201504073_V2.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_jcb.201504073_JCB_201504073_V1.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Tom Pollard, Rajesh Arasada, Mohan Balasubramanian, and Viesturs Simanis for strains and reagents and members of the Martin and Gould laboratories for careful reading of the manuscript. </p><p>N.A. McDonald was supported by American Heart Association fellowship 15PRE21780003. Research in the Gould laboratory was supported by National Institutes of Health grant GM101035 to K.L. Gould. Research in the Martin laboratory is funded by a European Research Council starting grant (GeometryCellCycle) and a Swiss National Science Foundation grant (31003A_155944) to S.G. Martin. </p><p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fnd0e6039"><p>
<def-list><title>Abbreviations used in this paper:</title><def-item><term>DYRK</term><def><p>dual-specificity tyrosine phosphorylation-regulated kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBC</term><def><p>methyl benzimidazol-2-yl-carbamate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPB</term><def><p>spindle pole body</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akamatsu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tebbs</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Cytokinetic nodes in fission yeast arise from two distinct types of nodes that merge during interphase</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>204</volume>:<fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>988</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201307174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24637325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3998791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almonacid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janvore</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayeux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraisier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Spatial control of cytokinesis by Cdr2 kinase and Mid1/anillin nuclear export</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>961</fpage>–<lpage>966</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.04.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19427212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arasada</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Distinct roles for F-BAR proteins Cdc15p and Bzz1p in actin polymerization at sites of endocytosis in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1450</fpage>–<lpage>1459</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.07.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21885283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3350781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arasada</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Contractile ring stability in S. pombe depends on F-BAR protein Cdc15p and Bgs1p transport from the Golgi complex</article-title>. <source>Cell Reports.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1533</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.07.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4163078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bähler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Fission yeast Pom1p kinase activity is cell cycle regulated and essential for cellular symmetry during growth and division</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1064</fpage>–<lpage>1073</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.5.1064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC145493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bähler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Pom1p, a fission yeast protein kinase that provides positional information for both polarized growth and cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1356</fpage>–<lpage>1370</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.12.9.1356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9573052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC316787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bähler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtine</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steever</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Heterologous modules for efficient and versatile PCR-based gene targeting in <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic></article-title>. <source>Yeast.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>951</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(199807)14:10&lt;943::AID-YEA292&gt;3.0.CO;2-Y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendezú</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Actin cables and the exocyst form two independent morphogenesis pathways in the fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E10-08-0720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3016976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendezú</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Cdc42 explores the cell periphery for mate selection in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.10.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23200991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendezú</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincenzetti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Fission yeast Sec3 and Exo70 are transported on actin cables and localize the exocyst complex to cell poles</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e40248</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hachet</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hersch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthelot-Grosjean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalessi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basterra</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Distinct levels in Pom1 gradients limit Cdr2 activity and localization to time and position division</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage> 538</fpage>–<lpage>552</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24316795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.27411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Cytokinesis-based constraints on polarized cell growth in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1003004</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23093943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3475658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carnahan</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The PCH family protein, Cdc15p, recruits two F-actin nucleation pathways to coordinate cytokinetic actin ring formation in <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>–<lpage>862</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200305012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12939254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2172828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celton-Morizur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Racine</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sibarita</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Pom1 kinase links division plane position to cell polarity by regulating Mid1p cortical distribution</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>4710</fpage>–<lpage>4718</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.03261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17077120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woollard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of fission yeast mutants defective in the assembly and placement of the contractile actin ring</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8834798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/jcs.109.1.131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broadus</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feoktistova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Comprehensive proteomics analysis reveals new substrates and regulators of the fission yeast clp1/cdc14 phosphatase</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1074</fpage>–<lpage>1086</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M112.025924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3650322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The Clp1/Cdc14 phosphatase contributes to the robustness of cytokinesis by association with anillin-related Mid1</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200709060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2287289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daga</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Dynamic positioning of the fission yeast cell division plane</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>8228</fpage>–<lpage>8232</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0409021102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1142117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldissard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kettenbach</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Dueling kinases regulate cell size at division through the SAD kinase Cdr2</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4055034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggert</surname><given-names>U.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Animal cytokinesis: from parts list to mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.74.082803.133425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16756502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Utzig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Simanis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The S. pombe cdc15 gene is a key element in the reorganization of F-actin at mitosis</article-title>. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90432-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7634333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Pxl1p, a paxillin-related protein, stabilizes the actomyosin ring during cytokinesis in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1680</fpage>–<lpage>1692</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E07-07-0715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18272786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2291416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sazer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Phosphorylation at Thr167 is required for <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> p34cdc2 function</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3297</fpage>–<lpage>3309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1655416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1991.tb04894.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC453056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pogliano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Bacillus subtilis MinC destabilizes FtsZ-rings at new cell poles and contributes to the timing of cell division</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>3475</fpage>–<lpage>3488</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1732408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19141479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2607072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hachet</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthelot-Grosjean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokkoris</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincenzetti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moosbrugger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>A phosphorylation cycle shapes gradients of the DYRK family kinase Pom1 at the plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>1116</fpage>–<lpage>1128</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21703453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Himpel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tegge</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leder</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joost</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Specificity determinants of substrate recognition by the protein kinase DYRK1A</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>2431</fpage>–<lpage>2438</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.4.2431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Polarity determinants Tea1p, Tea4p, and Pom1p inhibit division-septum assembly at cell ends in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Dev. Cell.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2007.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Assembly of normal actomyosin rings in the absence of Mid1p and cortical nodes in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>183</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>988</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200806151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19075108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2600752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kettenbach</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldissard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adamo</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Quantitative phosphoproteomics reveals pathways for coordination of cell growth and division by the conserved fission yeast kinase pom1</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1275</fpage>–<lpage>1287</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M114.045245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4424399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippincott</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Involvement of PCH family proteins in cytokinesis and actin distribution</article-title>. <source>Microsc. Res. Tech.</source>
<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0029(20000415)49:2&lt;168::AID-JEMT9&gt;3.0.CO;2-T</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10816256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo Presti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Myosin Vs organize actin cables in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>4579</fpage>–<lpage>4591</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E12-07-0499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23051734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3510019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutkenhaus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Assembly dynamics of the bacterial MinCDE system and spatial regulation of the Z ring</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.75.103004.142652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17328675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthelot-Grosjean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Polar gradients of the DYRK-family kinase Pom1 couple cell length with the cell cycle</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>459</volume>:<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>856</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Tea4p links microtubule plus ends with the formin for3p in the establishment of cell polarity</article-title>. <source>Dev. Cell.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>491</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2005.02.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín-García</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>F-BAR domain protein Rga7 collaborates with Cdc15 and Imp2 to ensure proper cytokinesis in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>4146</fpage>–<lpage>4158</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.146233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25052092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliferenko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Cytokinesis: Catch and drag</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>R247</fpage>–<lpage>R250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayeux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A spatial gradient coordinates cell size and mitotic entry in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>459</volume>:<fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>860</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cortés</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sipiczki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clemente-Ramos</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribas</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Extracellular cell wall β(1,3)glucan is required to couple septation to actomyosin ring contraction</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>203</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201304132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24165938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3812973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen-Hwang</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieraszko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Phosphorylation of amphiphysin I by minibrain kinase/dual-specificity tyrosine phosphorylation-regulated kinase, a kinase implicated in Down syndrome</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>23712</fpage>–<lpage>23724</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M513497200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16733250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliferenko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Positioning cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1772009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19299557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Padte</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The cell-end factor pom1p inhibits mid1p in specification of the cell division plane in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2480</fpage>–<lpage>2487</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.11.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17140794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Analysis of mid1p, a protein required for placement of the cell division site, reveals a link between the nucleus and the cell surface in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2757</fpage>–<lpage>2773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.11.8.2757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10930468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC14954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Equatorial retention of the contractile actin ring by microtubules during cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>300</volume>:<fpage>1569</fpage>–<lpage>1574</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1084671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12791993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rincón</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Schizosaccharomyces pombe Pxl1 is a paxillin homologue that modulates Rho1 activity and participates in cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1727</fpage>–<lpage>1738</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E07-07-0718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18256290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2291433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Understanding cytokinesis: Lessons from fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20094054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2819279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boudaoud</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Contributions of turgor pressure, the contractile ring, and septum assembly to forces in cytokinesis in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1601</fpage>–<lpage>1608</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.06.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22840513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3443309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willet</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feoktistova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The Cdc15 and Imp2 SH3 domains cooperatively scaffold a network of proteins that redundantly ensure efficient cell division in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E14-10-1451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4294673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bicho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman-Vendrell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraisier</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borek</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dingli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loew</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rappsilber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Pom1 regulates the assembly of Cdr2-Mid1 cortical nodes for robust spatial control of cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>206</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201311097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24982431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4085711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Stepping into the ring: The SIN takes on contractile ring assembly</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>3082</fpage>–<lpage>3088</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1748908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Setting the F-BAR: Functions and regulation of the F-BAR protein family</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>4091</fpage>–<lpage>4097</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.9.20.13587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20948299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The SH3 domains of two PCH family members cooperate in assembly of the <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> contractile ring</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>184</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200806044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19139265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2615086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Galbraith</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohi</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballif</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Dephosphorylation of F-BAR protein Cdc15 modulates its conformation and stimulates its scaffolding activity at the cell division site</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell.</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20603077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2916701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Anillin-related protein Mid1p coordinates the assembly of the cytokinetic contractile ring in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>3982</fpage>–<lpage>3992</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E12-07-0535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22918943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3469514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohrmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodbeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Simanis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The dmf1/mid1 gene is essential for correct positioning of the division septum in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2707</fpage>–<lpage>2719</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.10.21.2707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8946912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soundararajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savitsky</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Filippakopoulos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kettenbach</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eswaran</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Elkins</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Structures of Down syndrome kinases, DYRKs, reveal mechanisms of kinase activation and substrate recognition</article-title>. <source>Structure.</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>986</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2013.03.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23665168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3677093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatebe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uzawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morigasaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shiozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Wsh3/Tea4 is a novel cell-end factor essential for bipolar distribution of Tea1 and protects cell polarity under environmental stress in S. pombe</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1006</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.04.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15936270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolic´-Nørrelykke</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacconi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stringari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavone</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Nuclear and division-plane positioning revealed by optical micromanipulation</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>1216</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.05.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16005294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>P.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doye</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoué</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Microtubule-dependent nuclear positioning and nuclear-dependent septum positioning in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces [correction of Saccharomyces] pombe</article-title>. <source>Biol. Bull.</source>
<volume>199</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1542900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11081738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubersax</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrell</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of specificity in protein phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17585314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavylonis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Shaughnessy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Assembly mechanism of the contractile ring for cytokinesis by fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>319</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1151086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vjestica</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X.Z.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliferenko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The actomyosin ring recruits early secretory compartments to the division site in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1125</fpage>–<lpage>1138</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E07-07-0663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2262985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wachtler</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karagiannis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Cell cycle-dependent roles for the FCH-domain protein Cdc15p in formation of the actomyosin ring in <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>3254</fpage>–<lpage>3266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E05-11-1086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1483054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willet</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The F-BAR Cdc15 promotes contractile ring formation through the direct recruitment of the formin Cdc12</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>208</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201411097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25688133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4332253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Counting cytokinesis proteins globally and locally in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>310</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1113230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Spatial and temporal pathway for assembly and constriction of the contractile ring in fission yeast cytokinesis</article-title>. <source>Dev. Cell.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(03)00324-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirotkin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beltzner</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Assembly of the cytokinetic contractile ring from a broad band of nodes in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200602032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2064235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>