
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4011703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4011703.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4011703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4011703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24801871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-27168</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrine System</subject><subject>Renal System</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Signal Transduction</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Signaling</subject><subj-group><subject>Signaling Cascades</subject><subj-group><subject>Insulin Signaling Cascade</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrine Physiology</subject><subject>Renal Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Diabetic Endocrinology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impaired Insulin Signaling Affects Renal Organic Anion Transporter 3 (Oat3) Function in Streptozotocin-Induced Diabetic Rats</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Insulin Signaling and Renal Oat3 in Diabetes</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lungkaphin</surname><given-names initials="A">Anusorn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arjinajarn</surname><given-names initials="P">Phatchawan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pongchaidecha</surname><given-names initials="A">Anchalee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srimaroeng</surname><given-names initials="C">Chutima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatsudthipong</surname><given-names initials="L">Lisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatsudthipong</surname><given-names initials="V">Varanuj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Physiology, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Medicine, Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Physiology, Faculty of Science, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names initials="H">Hideharu</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Tokushima, Japan</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>onanusorn@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AL PA AP CS LC VC. Performed the experiments: AL PA. Analyzed the data: AL PA. Wrote the paper: AL PA. Edited and revised the manuscript: AL AP LC VC. Final approved the version to be published: AL PA AP CS LC VC.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">237130</issue-id><elocation-id>e96236</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-21 14:25:33.030"><day>21</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Lungkaphin et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lungkaphin et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0096236.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6103518"><article-title>Retraction: Impaired Insulin Signaling Affects Renal Organic Anion Transporter 3 (Oat3) Function in Streptozotocin-Induced Diabetic Rats</article-title><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><date><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><elocation-id>e0202898</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6103518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30130374</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Organic anion transporter 3 (Oat3) is a major renal <bold><italic toggle="yes">Oats</italic></bold> expressed in the <bold><italic toggle="yes">basolateral</italic></bold> membrane of renal <bold><italic toggle="yes">proximal tubule</italic></bold> cells. <bold><italic toggle="yes">We have recently reported decreases in</italic></bold> renal Oat3 function and expression in diabetic rats and these changes were recovered after insulin treatment for four weeks. However, the mechanisms by which insulin restored these changes have not been elucidated. In this study, we hypothesized that insulin signaling mediators might play a crucial role in the regulation of renal Oat3 function. Experimental diabetic rats were induced by a single intraperitoneal injection of streptozotocin (65 mg/kg). One week after injection, animals showing blood glucose above 250 mg/dL were considered to be diabetic and used for the experiment in which insulin-treated diabetic rats were subcutaneously injected daily with insulin for four weeks. Estrone sulfate (ES) uptake into renal cortical slices was examined to reflect the renal Oat3 function. The results showed that pre-incubation with insulin for 30 min (short term) stimulated [3H]ES uptake into the renal cortical slices of normal control rats. In the untreated diabetic rats, pre-incubation with insulin for 30 min failed to stimulate renal Oat3 activity. The unresponsiveness of renal Oat3 activity to insulin in the untreated diabetic rats suggests the impairment of insulin signaling. Indeed, pre-incubation with phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K) and protein kinase C zeta (PKCζ) inhibitors inhibited insulin-stimulated renal Oat3 activity. In addition, the expressions of PI3K, Akt and PKCζ in the renal cortex of diabetic rats were markedly decreased. Prolonged insulin treatment in diabetic rats restored these alterations toward normal levels. Our data suggest that the decreases in both function and expression of renal Oat3 in diabetes are associated with an impairment of renal insulin-induced Akt/PKB activation through PI3K/PKCζ/Akt/PKB signaling pathway.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Faculty of Medicine Research Fund (Grant #105/2555), Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand and National Research Council of Thailand (Grant #2556A10402022) AL. The URLs of the funder's websites are <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.med.cmu.ac.th">http://www.med.cmu.ac.th</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nrpm.nrct.go.th">http://nrpm.nrct.go.th</ext-link>, respectively. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Renal tubular secretion of organic anionic xenobiotics occurs sequentially by the concerted functions of two distinct transport steps in the basolateral and brush-border membranes of the tubular cells <xref rid="pone.0096236-Inui1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Inui2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Organic anion transporter 3 (Oat3), the major renal Oat expressed in the basolateral membrane of renal proximal tubule cells, plays a major role in the uptake of anionic substrates from the blood for further secretion. This uptake is the rate-limiting step <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sweet1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. A variety of endogenous and toxic exogenous substances including drugs <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sekine1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> such as diuretics, antihypertensives, antibiotics, antivirals, and anticancer agents are organic anions at physiological pH. These compounds are subjected to active tubular secretion which, in turn, impacts their pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and toxic effects. Therefore, functional disturbances in renal excretion of organic anions are of clinical importance, especially in the use of drugs with high toxicity or a narrow therapeutic range.</p><p>The regulations of Oat3 function have been studied extensively in the last decade. Recently, it was reported that a decreased Oat3 activity was observed via nonspecific protein kinase C (PKC) activation <xref rid="pone.0096236-VanWert1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Since PKC is one of insulin signaling mediators, impaired PKC and other mediators in the kidney of diabetic rat may be a vital mechanism leading to renal Oat3 dysfunction. The insulin signaling cascade is initiated by the binding of insulin to its <bold><italic toggle="yes">receptor</italic></bold> and activates the insulin receptor substrate (<bold><italic toggle="yes">IRS</italic></bold>) protein, which, in turn, triggers phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K) activity and induces activation of downstream signaling molecules such as Akt/protein kinase B (Akt/PKB) and atypical protein kinase C ζ (PKCζ) <xref rid="pone.0096236-Saltiel1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Akt and PKCζ are implicated in the regulation of glucose metabolism <xref rid="pone.0096236-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Bandyopadhyay1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. The link between the Akt signaling pathway and diabetic nephropathy has been <bold><italic toggle="yes">reported</italic></bold>. Hyperglycemia and insulin both modulate Akt activity in diabetic renal tissue <xref rid="pone.0096236-Zdychov1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sheu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Moreover, it has been reported that renal mesangial hypertrophy and renal tubular cell proteolysis are regulated by Akt <xref rid="pone.0096236-Nagai1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Shen1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. <bold><italic toggle="yes">Similar to</italic></bold> Akt, activation of PKCζ has been <bold><italic toggle="yes">shown</italic></bold> to <italic toggle="yes">increase</italic> the vascular endothelial growth factor and collagen IV expression in mesangial cells <bold><italic toggle="yes">under high-glucose conditions</italic></bold>
<xref rid="pone.0096236-Kwan1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Xia1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. However, the exact role of insulin signaling in the context of hyperglycemia-induced dysfunction of renal Oat3 has not yet been explored. Although our previous studies found the impairments of renal Oat3 function and expression in mice <xref rid="pone.0096236-Lungkaphin1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and rats <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> in the diabetic condition, the mechanisms by which diabetes affects renal Oat3 function are poorly identified. In this study, we tested the hypothesis that renal Oat3 dysfunction in the diabetic condition was associated with the impairment of insulin signaling in the kidney, and insulin treatment following diabetes development could maintain the insulin signaling cascade concomitant with the improved Oat3 function and expression.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Materials</title><p>Streptozotocin (STZ), unlabeled ES, Wortmannin and CelLytic MT mammalian tissue lysis/extraction reagent were purchased from Sigma Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). PKCζ-pseudosubstrate (PKCζ-PS) inhibitor was obtained from Tocris (Ellisville, MO). Complete protease inhibitor cocktail was purchased from Roche Applied Science (Indianapolis, IN). [<sup>3</sup>H]ES was purchased from Perkin Elmer (Norwalk, CT, USA). Human insulin, Humulin N and Humulin R, were obtained from Eli Lilly Inc. (Indianapolis, IN). Glucose and triglyceride assay kits were purchased from Biotech (Bangkok, Thailand). Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) assay kit was obtained from Cayman Chemical Company (Ann Arbor, MI). Polyclonal antibody against Oat3 was purchased from Cosmo Bio Co. Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan). Polyclonal antibody against PKCζ was bought from Invitrogen (Invitrogen Corp., Carlsbad, CA). Polyclonal antibodies against phosphorylated PKCζ, phospho-PKCζ (Thr410/Thr403), and PI3 Kinase p85 were obtained from Cell Signaling Technology, Inc. (Beverly, MA). Polyclonal antibody against Akt, monoclonal antibody against phosphorylated Akt (Ser473) and anti-β-actin antibody were purchased from Millipore (Billerica, MA). Horseradish peroxidase (HRP) conjugated goat anti-rabbit and anti-mouse secondary antibodies were purchased from Amersham (Arlington Heights, IL). Monoclonal mouse anti-Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase was obtained from Novus biological (Littleton, CO). All other chemicals used were commercially available high-grade products.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Animals</title><p>Male Wistar rats (150–180 g) from the National Laboratory Animal Centre, Mahidol University, Salaya, Nakornpathom were housed in the animal room with controlled temperature (23±2°C) under 12∶12 hr light/dark cycle and fed with normal pellet diet and water <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>. This study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The protocol was approved by the Committee on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of the Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University (Permit Number: 18/2555). All surgery was performed under sodium pentobarbital anesthesia, and all efforts were made to minimize suffering.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Diabetes induction and experimental design</title><p>Diabetes was induced by a single intraperitoneal injection of streptozotocin (STZ) dissolved in 0.1 M citrate buffer of pH 4.5 at a dose of 65 mg/kg body weight while the control rats were injected with citrate buffer (pH 4.5) as a vehicle. One week after the STZ injection, animals showing blood glucose above 250 mg/dL were considered to be diabetic and used for the experiment. The diabetic rats were then randomly divided into two groups: untreated diabetic and insulin-treated diabetic (DM-treated) rats. The insulin-treated group received subcutaneous injections of human insulin (Humulin N, 100 U/mL) at an initial dosage of 40 U/kg followed by daily supplemental doses for four weeks. Blood glucose levels were monitored daily using a One Touch glucometer (LifeScan Inc., Milipitas, CA) and the insulin dose was adjusted as needed based on blood glucose levels. The doses used were as follows: for blood glucose of 100–150 mg/dL, 10 U/kg; for 150–200 mg/dL, 20 U/kg; for 200–250 mg/dL, 30 U/kg; for &gt;250 mg/dL, 40 U/kg <xref rid="pone.0096236-Moglia1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Rats with a plasma glucose level below 150 mg/dL were considered to be controlled diabetics. All groups of rats were maintained for four weeks.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Blood and tissue sample collections</title><p>At the end of the four-week study period, animals were weighed and sacrificed by ether inhalation. Blood samples were collected via cardiac puncture for determinations of glucose and triglycerides. The abdomen was then opened with a midline incision, and the kidneys were flushed in situ with an ice-chilled HEPES-sucrose buffer (containing 250 mM sucrose, 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.42–7.44) through the abdominal aorta. Thereafter, the kidneys were removed, decapsulated and weighed for calculation of kidney to body weight (KW/BW) ratio. They were then processed and kept for further study.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Determinations of biochemical parameters</title><p>Concentrations of plasma glucose and triglycerides were measured by enzymatic colorimetric methods using commercial kits (Biotech, Bangkok, Thailand) and the data were reported as mg/dL.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Determinations of oxidative stress in renal cortical tissues</title><p>For renal oxidative stress determination, malondialdehyde (MDA) level in the supernatant of the renal cortical homogenates was determined using the thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) assay kit (Cayman Chemical Company, Ann Arbor, MI). The amount of MDA was expressed as nmol/mg protein. Total proteins of renal cortical tissues were determined using a DC protein assay kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Tissue preparation and Western blot analysis</title><p>Only renal cortex was used for Western blot analysis. The renal cortex was gently cut from the outer part of the kidney and extended down for approximately 3–4 mm using microtome. Each cellular compartment, whole cell lysate, membrane and cytosolic fractions were prepared from renal cortical slices using differential centrifugation as previously described <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Briefly, renal cortical slices were homogenized in Mammalian cell Lytic buffer with protease cocktail inhibitor. Homogenates were centrifuged at 5,000×g for 15 min at 4°C. Some of the supernatants were collected as total cell lysates, and the remaining portion was centrifuged at 100,000×g for 2 hr at 4°C to obtain membrane (pellet) and cytosolic (supernatant) fractions. The 5,000×g pellet was resuspended and centrifuged at 10,000×g 4°C for 10 min. The supernatant fraction from the spin was designated as the nuclei fraction. Total cell lysates, cytosolic and membrane fractions from the renal cortex were subjected to 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), and subsequently transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane (Millipore, MA). The membranes were then blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk in TBS containing 0.1% tween-20 (TBST) solution for one hour at room temperature and subsequently probed with primary antibodies overnight at 4°C. To confirm the enrichment of the membrane fraction, the Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase expression was used as a membrane fraction marker. The β-actin was used as loading control for all samples. The membranes were washed three times with TBST and incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-rabbit or anti-mouse secondary antibody (Amersham, IL) at room temperature for one hour and developed with ECL enhanced chemiluminescence agent (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire). Each membrane was stripped and re-probed with mouse anti-β-actin antibody that served as a loading control or another antibody for further detection of protein expression. The densities of the protein signals on X-ray films was analyzed using the histogram function of Adobe Photoshop CS5 (Adobe Corp., CA) scanning. Protein levels were normalized by β-actin as a loading control.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Stripping and reprobing</title><sec id="s2h1"><title>Stripping</title><p>After the first detection, the membrane was washed three times with TBST and submerged in stripping buffer (100 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 2% sodium dodecyl sulphate, 62.5 mM Tris-HCl, pH 6.7) at 60°C for 30 min with occasional agitation. After stripping a blot, the complete removal of the antibody was tested before reprobing step. Primary antibody removal was confirmed by incubation the membrane with an HRP-conjugated secondary antibody and detected by incubation with ECL enhanced chemiluminescence agent. If remaining antibody is detected using these tests, the blot will be re-striped before subsequent reprobing step.</p></sec><sec id="s2h2"><title>Reprobing</title><p>The membrane was then blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk in TBS containing 0.1% tween-20 (TBST) solution for one hour at room temperature and subsequently probed with primary antibodies and secondary antibody before the detection with ECL enhanced chemiluminescence agent as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Determination of renal Oat3 function</title><p>Uptake of radiolabeled estrone sulfate ([<sup>3</sup>H]ES), a specific Oat3 substrate <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sweet2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Aslamkhan1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, into the renal cortical slice, which reflects the renal Oat3 function, was examined in the presence or absence of insulin at room temperature. For this study, the kidneys were removed from the animal, decapsulated and placed into freshly-oxygenated ice-cold modified Cross and Taggart saline buffer (containing: 95 mM NaCl, 80 mM mannitol, 5 mM KCl, 0.74 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 9.5 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.4). Thin renal cortical slices (≤0.5 mm; 5–15 mg/slice; wet weight) were cut using a Stadie-Riggs microtome. Slices were pre-incubated for 30 min with or without 30 µg/mL insulin (Humulin R 100 IU/mL). The purpose of pre-incubating the renal slices with insulin for 30 min (short term treatment) prior to measuring Oat3 function is to activate the insulin signaling cascades, PIK3, Akt and PKCζ according to the study of Barros et al. <xref rid="pone.0096236-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. In our study, we would like to see whether diabetic rat has any impairment of the insulin signaling cascades. After pre-incubation, uptake of 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES into renal cortical slice was performed at room temperature for 30 min. At the end of the uptake period, the slices were washed in 0.1 M MgCl<sub>2</sub>, blotted on filter paper, weighed, and dissolved in 0.5 mL of 1 M NaOH. Tissue samples were then neutralized with 0.5 mL of 1 M HCl and assayed for [<sup>3</sup>H]ES by liquid scintillation counter (Pharmacia, Turku, Finland). The [<sup>3</sup>H]ES uptake was calculated as tissue to medium ratios (dpm/mg of tissue ÷ dpm/µL of medium).</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Effects of PI3K and PKCζ inhibitors on renal Oat3 function in renal cortical slices</title><p>To determine the mediator(s) of insulin signaling that might affect renal Oat3 function, the uptake of [<sup>3</sup>H]ES into renal cortical slices in the presence or absence of insulin after pre-incubation with a selective PI3K inhibitor, 100 nM Wortmannin, or PKCζ pseudosubstrate inhibitor (PKCζ-PS), 2 µM PKCζ-PS, were examined. First, renal cortical slices were pre-incubated with a selected inhibitor for 20 min. After that the slices were further incubated with insulin for another 30 min (short term insulin treatment). Then the uptake of [<sup>3</sup>H]ES was determined at room temperature as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data are expressed as means ± SEM and analyzed using SPSS version 10 statistical programs (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Newman-Keuls tests was used to determine statistically-significant differences among compared groups. A P value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Effects of diabetes on physiological and biochemical parameters</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0096236-t001">Table 1</xref>, the diabetic rats had significantly lower body weights and marked renal hypertrophy as indicated by the greater KW/BW ratio compared with that of the control rats (p&lt;0.01). The diabetic rats also exhibited hyperglycemia and hypertriglyceridemia as shown by the significant increases in plasma glucose and triglyceride concentrations compared with the control rats (p&lt;0.01). However, the abnormalities in these parameters were effectively improved after treatment with insulin for 4 weeks soon after the development of diabetes.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0096236-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Effects of diabetes and insulin treatment on physiological and biochemical parameters.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0096236-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BW (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KW (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KW/BW (mg/g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PG (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (mg/dL)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal Cortical MDA (nmol/mg protein)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490±4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48±0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21±0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.71±1.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.17±8.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4±0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238±13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96±0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.09±0.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">435.55±16.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294.26±12.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15±0.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">**</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM-treated</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505±9 <sup>##</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75±0.06<sup>##</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41±0.08 <sup>##</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.52±1.92<sup> ##</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.26±2.30<sup>##</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6±0.16<sup>##</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>BW: body weight; KW: kidney weight; KW/BW: kidney weight to body weight; PG: plasma glucose; TG: serum triglyceride; MDA: malondialdehyde; DM: diabetic rat; DM-treated: insulin-treated diabetic rat. Values are expressed as means ± SEM of 10 rats/group.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>**<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to diabetic (DM).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To examine oxidative stress in renal cortical tissue, the level of malondialdehyde (MDA), a major marker of lipid peroxidation, was measured by the TBARS method. The diabetic rats showed a significant increase in the level of renal cortical MDA compared with that of the control rats (p&lt;0.01). Treatment with insulin for 4 weeks significantly decreased the MDA level in the diabetic rats (p&lt;0.01). These results demonstrate a significant generation of oxidative stress in the diabetic condition and insulin treatment is the effective therapy for ameliorating the oxidative stress in diabetes.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Lack of insulin-stimulated ES uptakes in renal cortical slices of untreated diabetic rats</title><p>The function of renal Oat3 in diabetic rats was examined by the uptake of 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES, a prototypical organic anion, into renal cortical slices. A significant decrease in basal ES uptake was observed in diabetic rats compared to that of control rats (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In contrast, the insulin-treated diabetic rats (DM-treated) showed a significant increase in the basal ES uptake toward the control level (p&lt;0.01). These results indicate that basal renal Oat3 function was attenuated in the diabetic condition and this impairment could be restored by insulin treatment.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Effects of diabetes on basal and short term insulin-stimulated ES uptake in renal cortical slices.</title><p>Renal cortical slices from control, diabetic (DM) and diabetic with insulin-treated rats (DM-treated) were pre-incubated for 30 min in buffer alone (C), or buffer containing 30 µg/mL insulin (In) at room temperature. After pre-incubation, renal cortical slices were incubated in buffer containing 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES for 30 min. Values are expressed as means of T/M ± SEM. from five animals (5 slices/experimental group/animal). <sup>††</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to the corresponding control; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to the control (non DM rats); <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to the diabetic rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>We then evaluated whether renal Oat3 dysfunction resulted from the impaired insulin signaling in the kidney of diabetic rats. As insulin has been shown to stimulate Oat3 function in renal cortical slices <xref rid="pone.0096236-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, the effect of short term insulin-stimulated ES uptake was determined in both control and diabetic conditions. In this study, short-term insulin treatment prior to measuring Oat3 function was intended to activate the insulin signaling cascades, PIK3, Akt and PKCζ, which subsequently activate Oat3 function. Our results showed a significant increase in ES uptake into renal cortical slice after pre-incubation with insulin for 30 min in normal (control) rats (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), suggesting that renal Oat3 function could be regulated by insulin. Interestingly, insulin failed to stimulate ES uptake in the kidney slices obtained from the untreated diabetic group (without insulin treatment) as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g001">Figure 1</xref>. This result suggests that the insulin signaling cascades was impaired in the untreated diabetic rats. In contrast, the function of Oat3 in the insulin-treated diabetic rats (DM-treated) was significantly improved and short-term insulin treatment further enhanced its function (p&lt;0.01). This indicates that insulin treatment of diabetes for four weeks could correct the impairment of insulin signaling mediators, which, in turn, improve the function and expression of Oat3. These results support that the down-regulation of renal Oat3 function in this study may be due to the impairment of insulin signaling pathway in diabetic rats without insulin treatment.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Effect of diabetes on renal Oat3 protein expression</title><p>We further tested the hypothesis that the decreased function of renal Oat3 partly resulted from the down-regulated expression of Oat3 at the basolateral membrane in the diabetic condition. Therefore, the Oat3 expression in membrane and whole cell lysate fractions of renal cortex from various groups were determined by Western blotting. The Oat3 expression level in the membrane fraction was significantly decreased in the diabetic compared to that of the control rats (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), while the expression level in the insulin-treated rats (DM-treated) increased significantly with respect to that of diabetic rats without insulin treatment (p&lt;0.01). However, the Oat3 level in whole cell lysate fraction did not change. These results indicate that diabetic condition only down-regulates the expression of Oat3 at the membrane of renal tubular cells which could be recovered by insulin treatment.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effect of diabetes on Oat3 expression in the renal cortex.</title><p>(A) and (C); Western blot analysis for Oat3 in the membrane and whole cell lysate fractions of renal cortical tissues in control, diabetic (DM) and diabetic with insulin-treated (DM-treated) rats, respectively. (B) and (D); The signal intensity of Oat3 in membrane and whole cell lysate fractions normalized to β-actin, respectively. Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase and β-actin expressions were used as a membrane marker and loading control, respectively. Bar graphs indicate means ± SEM from five independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to diabetes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Effects of PI3K inhibitor on basal and short term insulin-stimulated ES uptakes in renal cortical slices</title><p>Previously, Soodvilai and his colleagues found that PI3K played a role in the regulation of Oat3 activity in the S2 segments of rabbit renal proximal tubules <xref rid="pone.0096236-Soodvilai1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. To verify the roles of the PI3K pathway and insulin on the activity of Oat3 in our study, a selective PI3K inhibitor, Wortmannin, was employed. The renal cortical slices were pre-incubated with control medium containing Wortmamnin (100 nM) for 20 min, then incubated with control medium containing 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES for 30-min uptake measurement. As expected, insulin significantly stimulated ES uptake whereas exposing the renal cortical slices to Wortmannin significantly reduced the uptake of ES by about 40% of control (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). However, the stimulatory effect of insulin on ES uptake was abolished in the presence of Wortmannin (p&lt;0.01). Our findings provide an evidence for an essential role of PI3K pathway in the regulation of both basal and insulin-stimulated Oat3 activities in the kidney.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Effect of Wortmannin on ES uptake in renal cortical slices.</title><p>Tissue slices prepared from rat renal cortex were pre-incubated under different experimental conditions as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref> section. Following pre-incubation, the slices were incubated for 30 min with 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES. Values are expressed as means ± SEM from five animals per group (6 slices/animal). **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>††</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to insulin alone.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Effects of PKCζ inhibitor on basal and short term insulin-stimulated ES uptakes in renal cortical slices</title><p>The atypical protein kinase C (PKC) isoform ζ (PKCζ) activation was shown to stimulate Oat3-mediated transport in rodent renal cortical slices <xref rid="pone.0096236-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. We then examined the effect of PKCζ pseudosubstrate inhibitor (PKCζ-PS) on the basal and the short term insulin-stimulated ES uptakes in rat renal cortical slices. The slices were pre-incubated with control medium containing PKCζ-PS for 20 min and then incubated with control medium containing 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES for 30-min uptake. Pre-incubation with insulin stimulated ES uptake whereas PKCζ-PS alone had no effect on basal ES uptake. Pre-incubating the renal cortical slices with PKCζ-PS, however, significantly abolished the short term insulin-stimulated ES uptake (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Our findings, therefore, suggest that PKCζ plays a role in mediating the effect of insulin-stimulated Oat3 function.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effect of PKCζ inhibitor on ES uptake in renal cortical slices.</title><p>Tissue slices prepared from rat renal cortex were pre-incubated under different experimental conditions as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref> section. Following pre-incubation, the slices were incubated for 30 min in 50 nM [<sup>3</sup>H]ES. Values are expressed as means ± SEM from five animals per group (6 slices/animal). **p&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>††</sup>p&lt;0.01, compared to insulin alone.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Effects of diabetes on phosphoinositide 3-kinases (PI3K) expression in the renal cortex</title><p>PI3K is an important signaling molecule in the insulin signaling pathway and has been reported to be involved in diabetic nephropathy including regulation of the renal mesangial hypertrophy <xref rid="pone.0096236-Nagai1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Shen1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. We postulated that the PI3K activity linked with Oat3 function in diabetes. We, therefore, determined the expression of PI3K in the membrane and cytosolic-enriched fractions of the renal cortex tissue obtained from both control and diabetic rats. Indeed, diabetic rats showed decreased PI3K expressions in both membrane and cytosolic fractions compared to those of the control rats (p&lt;0.01) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Insulin treatment, on the other hand, reversed these changes in the diabetic rats. Our observations clearly support the notion that diabetes leads to Oat3 dysfunction, at least in part, by the impaired insulin signaling mediator through the PI3K pathway.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Effect of diabetes on PI3K expression in the renal cortex.</title><p>(A) and (C); Western blot analysis for PI3K in the membrane and cytosolic fractions of renal cortical tissues in control, diabetic (DM) and diabetic with insulin-treated (DM-treated) rats, respectively. (B) and (D); The signal intensity of PI3K in membrane and cytosolic fractions normalized to β<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>actin, respectively. Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase and β-actin expressions were used as a membrane marker and loading control, respectively. Bar graphs indicate means ± SEM from five independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to diabetes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>Effects of diabetes on Akt expression in renal cortex</title><p>Based on our findings, we proposed that the impairment of PI3K function in diabetes (without insulin treatment) might cause abnormalities in the PI3K downstream signaling molecules including Akt/PKB and PKCζ. Therefore, we determined the expression levels of Akt and phospho-Akt. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g006">Figure 6</xref> shows marked decreases in Akt and phosphorylation of Akt in both the membrane and cytosolic fractions of renal cortex of the diabetic rats compared to the control rats. Conversely, insulin treatment significantly restored the Akt and phosphorylated Akt protein expressions of the diabetic rats. These results suggest that hyperglycemia induces pathogenesis of renal tubular function, at least in part, by impaired insulin signaling through the Akt/PKB signaling pathway as well.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effects of diabetes on Akt and phospho-Akt expressions in the renal cortex.</title><p>(A) and (C); Western blot analysis for Akt and phospho-Akt in the membrane and cytosolic fractions of renal cortical tissues in control, diabetic (DM) and diabetic with insulin-treated (DM-treated) rats, respectively. (B) and (D); The signal intensity of Akt and phospho-Akt in the membrane and cytosolic fractions normalized to β<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>actin, respectively. Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase and β-actin expressions were used as a membrane marker and loading control, respectively. Bar graphs indicate means ± SEM from five independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to diabetes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3h"><title>Effects of diabetes on PKCζ expression in renal cortex</title><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g007">Figure 7</xref>, the expression levels of PKCζ and phospho-PKCζ in both the membrane and cytosolic fractions from the renal cortical tissue were significantly decreased in diabetic rats compared to controls (p&lt;0.01). However, in the diabetic rats with insulin treatment (DM-treated rats), the expressions of PKCζ and phospho-PKCζ were restored. These data also support the idea that the defect of PKCζ signaling is, in part, involved in the dysfunction of renal tubular transport of Oat3.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Effects of diabetes on PKCζ and phospho-PKCζ expressions in the renal cortex.</title><p>(A) and (C); Western blot analysis for PKCζ and phospho-PKCζ in the membrane and cytosolic fractions of renal cortical tissues in control, diabetic (DM) and diabetic with insulin-treated (DM-treated) rats, respectively. (B) and (D); The signal intensity of PKCζ and phospho-PKCζ in the membrane and cytosolic fractions normalized to β<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>actin, respectively. Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase and β-actin expressions were used as a membrane marker and loading control, respectively. β<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>actin for the membrane fractions of PKCζ (A) and phospho-PKCζ (C) were obtained from the same membrane/loading protein. Bar graphs indicate means ± SEM from five independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to control; <sup>##</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01, compared to diabetes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The STZ-induced diabetic rats in this study showed hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, growth retardation and renal hypertrophy as inferred from an increased kidney weight to body weight ratio. Moreover, a significant increase in renal cortical MDA content associated with hyperglycemia and/or hyperlipidemia was observed. We found that treatment of the diabetic rats with insulin for four weeks significantly improved these parameters toward the control values.</p><p>Previously, we have shown that diabetic condition down-regulated renal Oat3 activity concomitant with the decreased membrane expression of renal Oat3 in rats <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and mice <xref rid="pone.0096236-Lungkaphin1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Furthermore, it was found that renal Oat3 activity was attenuated by PKCα stimulation in diabetes but was restored by insulin treatment <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In the present study, we showed that Wortmannin, a selective inhibitor of PI3K activity, inhibited not only basal ES uptake, but also abolished insulin-stimulated ES uptake in renal cortical tissues of normal rats. These findings are consistent with the study in S2 segments of rabbit renal proximal tubules, showing that Wortmannin inhibited Oat3 activity in a dose-dependent manner <xref rid="pone.0096236-Soodvilai1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Our data imply that Oat3 function is modulated by the activity of PI3K in both physiological and insulin-stimulated conditions. Interestingly, the decreased ES uptake after insulin stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) was associated with the reduced renal PI3K membrane expression in diabetic rats. These data suggest that insulin modulated Oat3 function through the activation of PI3K. In addition, our results corroborate with a previous study showing that PI3K protein levels were decreased in the livers of STZ diabetic rats and insulin treatment led to an increase in the PI3K protein expression <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sheu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Based on these data, it could be suggested that the down-regulation of Oat3 in diabetes may result from an impaired insulin signaling function, at least in the part, of PI3K pathway and/or the signaling downstream of PI3K.</p><p>PI3K, a downstream effector of insulin signaling, has been shown to play important role in various cellular processes such as protein trafficking, protein sorting and receptor internalization. Importantly, it was also found to regulate the activity of several transporters in the kidney, including the sodium bicarbonate cotransporter (Na/HCO3 cotransporter, NBC1), Na-H exchanger 3 (NHE3) and Oat3 <xref rid="pone.0096236-Soodvilai1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Bernardo1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Chu1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-DuCheyron1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Gabriels1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. We, therefore, postulated that an impaired PI3K signaling and/or the signaling downstream of PI3K in the diabetic condition might lead to a decreased trafficking of Oat3 to the plasma membrane. However, the exact mechanisms involved in this process require further studies. It appears that a marked down-regulation of Oat3 arises from an internalization of transport protein by the activation of PKCα <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Duan1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. As the profiles of Oat3 activity was closely associated with an impairment of PIK3 function in diabetes in the present study, it is, therefore, reasonable to hypothesize that the effects of PI3K on Oat3 activity observed here may result from modulation of Oat3 trafficking to renal plasma membrane.</p><p>Protein kinase B (PKB)/Akt, as a family of serine/threonine protein kinases, is a major downstream mediator of tyrosine kinase receptor in response to stimuli such as insulin or insulin growth factors and is activated by PI3K <xref rid="pone.0096236-FresnoJA1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Hyperglycemia and insulin have been shown to modulate Akt activity in diabetic renal tissue <xref rid="pone.0096236-Zdychov1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Sheu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Moreover, numerous lines of evidence also indicate that atypical PKCζ acts downstream of PI3K to relay insulin signals to activate PKB. It has been reported that PKCζ inhibition attenuated not only PKCζ activity, but also eliminated the activity of PKB simultaneously <xref rid="pone.0096236-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. In addition, it was suggested that PKCζ acts as an adaptor to interact with PKB and mediates PKB phosphorylation <xref rid="pone.0096236-Hodgkinson1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Thus, PKCζ is involved in insulin-induced PKB activation via PI3K/PKCζ/PKB signaling pathway. Similar to PI3K signaling, the defects in Akt and PKCζ pathways were also found in the diabetic condition in the present study. Our findings are in agreement with the previous studies showing the decrease in both Akt protein and phosphorylation of Akt in the retinal tissue and myocardiocytes of STZ diabetic rats <xref rid="pone.0096236-Feliers1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Laviola1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, and the decreased PKCζ protein expressions in both the renal cortical and myocardial tissues of diabetic animals <xref rid="pone.0096236-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. It is important to note that PKCζ plays a central role in up-regulation of both Oat1 and Oat3 transports by increasing the trafficking of these transporters to the membrane <xref rid="pone.0096236-Barros1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> whereas activation of the conventional PKC isoforms leads to their down-regulation <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Duan1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Soodvilai2" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Takano1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0096236-Wolff1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Our previous study revealed that the decreased renal Oat3 expression and function in diabetes might partly be due to the internalization of the Oat3 following the hyperglycemia-stimulated PKCα activity <xref rid="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. In the present study, the inhibition of insulin-stimulated ES uptake in diabetes might, in part, be due to the impaired PKCζ function in insulin signaling pathway leading to the decreased trafficking and expression of Oat3 to the membrane. It is important to note that an alteration of Oat3 trafficking in the kidney is difficult to investigate although the immunohistochemistry technique showing cell surface or intracellular retention might be doable. However, in the present study, we provide the functional evidence for an increased Oat3 activity in the presence of insulin which correlated well with increased Oat3 expression in the membrane fraction of the DM-treated rats. Taken together, we conclude that the down-regulation of renal Oat3 in diabetes might partly result from at least two possible mechanisms. The first arm is an increased internalization of membrane Oat3 to the cytoplasm via the activation of PKCα and another arm is the down-regulation of Oat3 function by decreased translocation or trafficking of Oat3 to plasma membrane resulted from the impaired renal insulin signaling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0096236-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). In support to this hypothesis, the restoration of Akt and PKCζ activities along with Oat3 function were observed after treatment of diabetic rat with insulin for four weeks.</p><fig id="pone-0096236-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096236.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>A hypothetical model for the regulation of renal Oat3 in diabetic condition.</title><p>Insulin regulates Oat3 function by activating PKCζ and PKB through PI3K leading to up-regulation of Oat3 function and increased trafficking of Oat3 to plasma membrane and subsequently increased transport function. The impairment of renal insulin signaling in diabetes down-regulates Oat3 function through PI3K/PKCζ/Akt/PKB-mediated pathway. The hyperglycemia-induced activation of PKCα in diabetes leads to internalization of Oat3 to cytoplasm resulting in down-regulation of Oat3 function. Alterations in the internalization and trafficking, the regulatory proteins, and the expression of Oat3 lead to decreased renal Oat3 function in diabetes. These changes can be recovered after insulin treatment for four weeks.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0096236.g008.jpg"/></fig><p>In conclusion, our study provides evidence showing that insulin regulates Oat3 function through the PI3K/PKCζ/Akt/PKB-mediated pathway. The impaired renal insulin signaling in diabetes affects the Oat3 function likely by altering its regulatory function, trafficking to the plasma membrane and then decreased its membrane expression. These events could be restored by long-term insulin treatment in diabetes. This insulin treatment could improve the regulatory proteins of Oat3 through insulin signaling mediators resulting in changes in their expressions, localizations, and activities.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to acknowledge Prof. Dr. Chumpol Pholpramool for his valuable comments of this manuscript and the technical support of Miss Sasivimon Promsan for the assistance with the biochemical assay.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0096236-Inui1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cellular and molecular mechanisms of renal tubular secretion of organic anions and cations</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Nephrol</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Inui2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cellular and molecular aspects of drug transport in the kidney</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>958</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1523-1755.2000.00251.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Sweet1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Organic anion transporter 3 (Slc22a8) is a dicarboxylate exchanger indirectly coupled to the Na+ gradient</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source>
<volume>284</volume>: <fpage>F763</fpage>–<lpage>F769</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12488248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.00405.2002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Sekine1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The multispecific organic anion transporter (OAT) family</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
<volume>440(3)</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s004240000297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-VanWert1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>VanWert</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gionfriddoa</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Organic Anion Transporters: Discovery, Pharmacology, Regulation and Roles in Pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>Biopharm Drug Dispos</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19953504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bdd.693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Saltiel1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saltiel</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Insulin signaling and the regulation of glucose and lipid metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>414</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/414799a</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Wang1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Somwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bilan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase B/Akt participates in GLUT4 translocation by insulin in L6 myoblasts</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>4008</fpage>–<lpage>4018</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.19.6.4008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC104360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Bandyopadhyay1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Standaert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avignon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Activation of protein kinase C (α, β, and ζ) by insulin in 3T3/L1 cells: transfection studies suggest a role for PKC-ζ in glucose transport</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>272</volume>: <fpage>2551</fpage>–<lpage>2558</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8999972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.272.4.2551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Zdychov1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zdychová</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veselá</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kazdová</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Renal activity of Akt kinase in experimental type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Physio Res</source>
<volume>57(5)</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.33549/physiolres.931337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17949249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Lee1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feliers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariappan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sataranatarajan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahimainathan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A role for AMP activated protein kinase in diabetes-induced renal hypertrophy</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>292(2)</volume>: <fpage>F617</fpage>–<lpage>F627</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.00278.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17018841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Sheu1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Activation of phosphoinositide 3-kinase in response to high glucose leads to regulation of reactive oxygen species-related nuclear factor-κB activation and cyclooxygenase-2 expression in mesangial cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharm</source>
<volume>66(1)</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1124/mol.66.1.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15213311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Nagai1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Gas6 induces Akt/mTOR-mediated mesangial hypertrophy in diabetic nephropathy</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>68(2)</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16014032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1523-1755.2005.00433.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Shen1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dice</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franch</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Akt and mammalian target of rapamycin regulate separate systems of proteolysis in renal tubular cells</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
<volume>17(9)</volume>: <fpage>2414</fpage>–<lpage>2423</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16885413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1681/ASN.2005111157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Kwan1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>In high glucose protein kinase C-ζ activation is required for mesangial cell generation of reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>2526</fpage>–<lpage>2541</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16316329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1523-1755.2005.00660.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Xia1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Reactive oxygen species, PKC-β1, and PKC-ζ mediate high-glucose-induced vascular endothelial growth factor expression in mesangial cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source>
<volume>293</volume>: <fpage>E1280</fpage>–<lpage>E1288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17711990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpendo.00223.2007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Lungkaphin1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lungkaphin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arjinajarn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srimaroeng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatsudthipong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Function and expression of renal organic anion transporters in experimental diabetes in mice</article-title>. <source>ScienceAsia</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Arjinajarn1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arjinajarn P, Srimaroeng C, Chatsudthipong V, Lungkaphin A (2013) Decreased renal organic anion transporter 3 expression in type 1 diabetic rats. Am J Med Sci: In press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Moglia1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moglia</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Changes in surfactant protein A mRNA levels in a rat model of insulin-treated diabetic pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8825794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1203/00006450-199602000-00009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Sweet2"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Impaired organic anion transport in kidney and choroid plexus of organic anion transporter 3 (Oat3 (Slc22a8)) knockout mice</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277(30)</volume>: <fpage>26934</fpage>–<lpage>26943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M203803200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Aslamkhan1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aslamkhan</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bleasby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The flounder organic anion transporter fOat has sequence, function, and substrate specificity similarity to both mammalian Oat1 and Oat3</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source>
<volume>291(6)</volume>: <fpage>R1773</fpage>–<lpage>R1780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16857889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpregu.00326.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1832143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Barros1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srimaroeng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dembla-Rajpal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Activation of protein kinase C zeta increases OAT1 (SLC22A6)- and OAT3 (SLC22A8)-mediated transport</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>284(5)</volume>: <fpage>2672</fpage>–<lpage>2679</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M808078200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2631969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Soodvilai1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soodvilai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dantzler</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatsudthipong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Involvement of tyrosine kinase and PI3K in the regulation of OAT3-mediated estrone sulfate transport in isolated rabbit renal proximal tubules</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source>
<volume>289</volume>: <fpage>F1057</fpage>–<lpage>F1064</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15956776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.00185.2005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Bernardo1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Espiritu</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The role of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) in CO2 stimulation of the Na/HCO3 cotransporter (NBC)</article-title>. <source>J Membr Biol</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12533781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00232-002-1051-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Chu1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuganezawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Role of tyrosine kinase pathways in ETB receptor activation of NHE3</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>C763</fpage>–<lpage>C771</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpcell.1996.271.3.C763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8843705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-DuCheyron1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Du Cheyron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalumeau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Defontaine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kellermann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin II stimulates NHE3 activity by exocytic insertion of the transporter: role of PI 3-kinase</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>–<lpage>949</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12911544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1523-1755.2003.00189.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Gabriels1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriels</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werners</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mauss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greven</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Evidence for differential regulation of renal proximal tubular p-aminohippurate and sodium dependent dicarboxylate transport</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
<volume>290</volume>: <fpage>710</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Duan1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin II inhibits activity of human organic anion transporter 3 through activation of protein kinase C alpha: accelerating endocytosis of the transporter</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>
<volume>627(1-3)</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejphar.2009.10.048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4016820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Zhang1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Short-term and long-term effects of protein kinase C on the trafficking and stability of human organic anion transporter 3</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Mol Biol</source>
<volume>3(2)</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3388735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-FresnoJA1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fresno JA</surname><given-names>Vara</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cejas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belda-Iniesta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>PI3K/Akt signalling pathway and cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15023437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctrv.2003.07.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Liu1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L-Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>L-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The pivotal role of protein kinase C zeta (PKCzeta) in insulin- and AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK)-mediated glucose uptake in muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Signal</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1513</fpage>–<lpage>1522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20570724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cellsig.2010.05.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Hodgkinson1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgkinson</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sale</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Characterization of PDK2 activity against protein kinase B gamma</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>41(32)</volume>: <fpage>10351</fpage>–<lpage>10359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12162751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi026065r</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Feliers1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feliers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duraisamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Activation of renal signaling pathways in db/db mice with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>60(2)</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1523-1755.2001.060002495.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Laviola1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laviola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belsanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davalli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Napoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Effects of streptozocin diabetes and diabetes treatment by islet transplantation on in vivo insulin signaling in rat heart</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<volume>50(12)</volume>: <fpage>2709</fpage>–<lpage>2720</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11723053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.50.12.2709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Kang1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maasch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchwalow</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of protein kinase C isoforms in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<volume>56(5)</volume>: <fpage>1737</fpage>–<lpage>1750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1523-1755.1999.00725.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Soodvilai2"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Soodvilai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatsudthipong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dantzler</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Acute regulation of OAT3-mediated estrone sulfate transport in isolated rabbit renal proximal tubules</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source>
<volume>287(5)</volume>: <fpage>F1021</fpage>–<lpage>F1029</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.00080.2004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Takano1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuhara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Regulation of p-aminohippurate transport by protein kinase C in OK kidney epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>F469</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8770181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.1996.271.2.F469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0096236-Wolff1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhnke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase C activation downregulates human organic anion transporter 1-mediated transport through carrier internalization</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
<volume>14(8)</volume>: <fpage>1959</fpage>–<lpage>1968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12874449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.asn.0000079040.55124.25</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>