
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4018274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4018274.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4018274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4018274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24820971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-50005</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Death</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cytometry</subject><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematology</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematologic Cancers and Related Disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Leukemias</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Basic Cancer Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Tumor Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cancers and Neoplasms</subject><subject>Cancer Treatment</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Spectrum Analysis Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Spectrophotometry</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytophotometry</subject><subj-group><subject>Flow Cytometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>S100A8 Contributes to Drug Resistance by Promoting Autophagy in Leukemia Cells</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">S100A8 and Autophagy in Leukemia</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="M">Minghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="P">Pei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="L">Liangchun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="D">Daolin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names initials="L">Lizhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha Hunan, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Infectious Diseases, Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan, China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Surgery, University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names initials="SB">Spencer B.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Manitoba, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yamahua123@163.com</email> (MY); <email>caolizhi318@163.com</email> (LC)</corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MY LC. Performed the experiments: MY PZ RK YY LY DT. Analyzed the data: MY DT LC. Wrote the paper: MY LC.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">237130</issue-id><elocation-id>e97242</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Yang et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yang et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0097242.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7406071"><article-title>Retraction: S100A8 Contributes to Drug Resistance by Promoting Autophagy in Leukemia Cells</article-title><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><date><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>e0237489</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0237489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7406071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32756612</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Autophagy is a double-edged sword in tumorigenesis and plays an important role in the resistance of cancer cells to chemotherapy. S100A8 is a member of the S100 calcium-binding protein family and plays an important role in the drug resistance of leukemia cells, with the mechanisms largely unknown. Here we report that S100A8 contributes to drug resistance in leukemia by promoting autophagy. S100A8 level was elevated in drug resistance leukemia cell lines relative to the nondrug resistant cell lines. Adriamycin and vincristine increased S100A8 in human leukemia cells, accompanied with upregulation of autophagy. RNA interference-mediated knockdown of S100A8 restored the chemosensitivity of leukemia cells, while overexpression of S100A8 enhanced drug resistance and increased autophagy. S100A8 physically interacted with the autophagy regulator BECN1 and was required for the formation of the BECN1-PI3KC3 complex. In addition, interaction between S100A8 and BECN1 relied upon the autophagic complex ULK1-mAtg13. Furthermore, we discovered that exogenous S100A8 induced autophagy, and RAGE was involved in exogenous S100A8-regulated autophagy. Our data demonstrated that S100A8 is involved in the development of chemoresistance in leukemia cells by regulating autophagy, and suggest that S100A8 may be a novel target for improving leukemia therapy.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by The National Natural Sciences Foundation of China (81100359 to MY, 30973234 and 31171328 to LC) and a grant from the National Institutes of Health (R01CA160417 to DT). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Autophagy is a catabolic process involving the degradation of intracellular aggregated or misfolded proteins, and damaged organelles through lysosomal machinery in response to stress or starvation <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Kroemer1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Deregulation of autophagy is implicated in several human diseases including cancers. Depending on the type of tumor and stage of disease, autophagy induces both tumor cell survival and death during the initiation, progression, maturation and maintenance of cancer <xref rid="pone.0097242-Helgason1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>It has been well documented that autophagy plays an important role in the resistance of cancer cells to chemotherapy <xref rid="pone.0097242-Zhu1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Consequently, pharmacological inhibition of autophagy enhances chemotherapeutic drug-induced cytotoxicity and apoptosis in leukemia cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Zhu1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0097242-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. We recently found that damage associated molecular pattern molecules (DAMPs) such as high mobility group box 1 (HMGB1) contribute to chemotherapy resistance though upregulating autophagy in leukemia <xref rid="pone.0097242-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. S100A8 (also designated MRP8 or calgranulin A) is a member of DAMPs, differentially expressed in a wide variety of cell types and abundant in myeloid cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Schafer1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Foell1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. S100A8 is involved in the progression of various cancers, including leukemia, and induces cell death by functional linkage with Bcl-2 family members <xref rid="pone.0097242-Ghavami1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. We previously found that the expression level of S100A8 correlates with poor clinical outcomes in childhood acute myeloblastic leukemia (AML). Accordingly, knockdown of S100A8 by siRNA-treated myeloid leukemia cells showed sensitization to arsenic trioxide, accompanied with the attenuation of autophagy and disassociation of the BECN1-Bcl-2 complex <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The data suggest that S100A8 contributes to chemoresistance <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> regulating the autophagy in leukemia.</p><p>In this study, we found that S100A8 enhances drug resistance by upregulating autophagy through promoting the formation of BECN1-PI3KC3 [PI3KC3, phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase class 3] complex, providing a novel potential target for the treatment of leukemia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Antibodies and reagents</title><p>The antibodies against S100A8 and p62 were obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Sana Cruz, CA, USA). The antibodies to Actin, BECN1, PI3KC3, C-PARP, ULK1, Bcl-2 and P-ULK1 were from Cell Signaling Technology (Boston, MA, USA). The antibodies to LC3 and TLR-4 were purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, USA). Anti-Atg7 antibody was from Novus (Denver-Littleton, CO, USA). Vincristine (VCR), adriamycin (ADM), rotenone (Rot), thenoyltrifluoroacetone (TTFA), antimycin A (AA), E64D, anti-RAGE antibody and pepstatin were from Sigma (Milpitas, CA, USA). Full-length human S100A8 cDNA (pLPCX-S100A8) was a gift from Dr. RW Stam (Erasmus Medical Center/Sophia Children's Hospital, Netherlands). FITC-Annexin V Apoptosis Detection kit and the Nuclear and Cytoplasmic Protein Extraction kit were purchased form Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology (Beijing, China). S100A8 protein was obtained from Novus Biologicals. Contaminating LPS was removed by Triton X-114 extraction. LPS content was always below 0.5 ng/mg protein, which did not cause an effect in our assays.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Cell culture</title><p>The human leukemia cell lines, K562 (chronic myeloid leukemia cells), HL-60 (acute myeloid leukemia cells), MV-4-11 (biphenotypic B myelomonocytic leukemia cells), Jurkat (T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia cells), and K562/A02 (multidrug resistance K562) were from the American Type Culture Collection; HL-60/ADR (multidrug resistance HL-60) was from the Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital of Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College. Cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated FBS and 2 mM glutamine in a humidified incubator with 5% CO2 and 95% air.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>Cell viability was assessed by MTT assay. Briefly, leukemia cells were seeded in 96-well plates (4000 cells/well) the day before treatment. Following treatment with ADR for 72 h, 25 µL MTT [3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol–2-yl)- 2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide; Sigma] was added to each well and incubated for 3.5 h, followed by the addition of 100 µL of N,Ndimethylformamide (D4551; Sigma). The plates were left at room temperature overnight to allow complete lysis of the cells, and read at 450 nm the following day. Half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC50) was calculated using MS Excel, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang3" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Cell lysates were prepared with cell lysis buffer [20 mmol/L Tris-HCl, pH 7.5; 150 mmol/L NaCl; 1 mmol/L Na2EDTA; 1 mmol/L EGTA; 1% Triton; 2.5 mmol/L sodium pyrophosphate; 1 mmol/L b-glycerophosphate; 1 mmol/L Na3VO4; 1 mg/mL leupeptin; 1 mmol/L phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride (PMSF); and 1 mmol/L PMSF], and cleared by centrifugation. Total protein concentration was determined with the bicinchoninic acid assay Kit (Bio-Rad). Proteins were resolved on a denaturing 10% SDS-PAGE gel and subsequently transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> semidry transfer. The membrane was blocked with 5% dried milk or 3% bovine serum albumin in Tris-buffered saline and Tween 20 (10 mmol/L Tris, pH 7.5; 100 mmol/L NaCl; and 0.1% Tween20), incubated with primary antibodies, and then with horseradish peroxidase–conjugated secondary antibodies. The signals were visualized by enhanced chemiluminescence.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol (Invitrogen, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Reverse transcription (RT) was performed with 2 µg of total RNA with HiFi-MMLV Enzyme Mix (CWbio, China). Twenty ng cDNA was subjected to real-time quantitative PCR (TaqMan probes) for the evaluation of the relative S100A8 mRNA, with beta actin as an internal control with gene specific primers and fluorogenic probes (S100A8: forward primer <named-content content-type="gene">5′- CCTAACCGCTATAAAAAGGAG -3′</named-content>, reverse primer <named-content content-type="gene">5′- ATGATGCCCACGGACTTGCC</named-content> -3, probe 5′ FAM-CCTCTCAGCCCTGCATGTCTCTT -TAMRA 3′; ACTB: forward primer 5′- GGCACCCAGCACAATGAAGA-3, reverse primer <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CGTCATACTCCTGCTTGCTG-3′</named-content>, probe 5′FAM-CTGGAAGGTGGACAGCGAGGC-TAMRA 3′.) in an LightCycler 480 <bold>System</bold> (Roche). Quantification was determined by the standard curve and 2-ΔΔCt methods <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang3" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Immunoprecipitation analysis</title><p>Cells were lysed at 4°C in ice-cold radioimmunoprecipitation assay lysis buffer (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). Cell lysates were cleared by a brief centrifugation (12,000 g, 10 min). Protein concentration in the supernatant was determined by bicinchoninic acid assay. Before immunoprecipitation, equal amounts of proteins were pre-cleared with Protein A or protein G agarose/sepharose (Millipore) at 4°C for 3 h and subsequently incubated with various irrelevant immunoglobulin-G or specific antibodies (5 µg/ml) in the presence of protein A or G agarose/sepharose beads for 2 h or overnight at 4°C with gently shaking. Following incubation, agarose/sepharose beads were washed extensively with phosphate buffered saline. Proteins were eluted by boiling in 2×SDS sample buffer before SDS–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and immunoblot analysis, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang3" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Liu2" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Gene transfection and RNAi</title><p>Cells were transfected with S100A8 pLPCX constructs by square-pulse electroporation at 600 V for 2 msec and cultured under selection of neomycin (1 mg/ml; Gibco BRL, USA) and puromycin (10 mg/ml; Sigma) in order to obtain a pure population of transfected cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-SpijkersHagelstein1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Lipofectamine 2000 Transfection Reagent (Invitrogen) was used to transfect S100A8-shRNA, BECN1-shRNA, PI3KC3-shRNA, ULK1-shRNA, RAGE-shRNA, TLR4-shRNA and Atg7 shRNA (Sigma) <xref rid="pone.0097242-Liu2" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. As a control experiment, another S100A8-shRNA was obtained from Gene Pharma (Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Apoptosis assays</title><p>Apoptosis was assessed using the FITC Annexin V Apoptosis Detection kit, which involves staining cells with Annexin V-FITC (a phospholipid-binding protein that binds to disrupted cell membranes) in combination with PI (a vital dye that binds to DNA penetrating into apoptotic cells). Flow cytometric analysis (FACS) was performed to determine the percentage of apoptotic cells (Annexin V<sup>+</sup>/PI).</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>Electron microscopy</title><p>Leukemia cells were collected and fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde for at least 3 h. Then cells were treated with 2% paraformaldehyde at room temperature for 60 min, 0.1% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate for 2 h, post-fixed with 1% OsO4 for 1.5 h, dehydrated with graded acetone, and embedded in Quetol 812. Ultrathin sections were observed using a Hitachi H7500 electron microscope (Tokyo, Japan) <xref rid="pone.0097242-Klionsky1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Immunofluorescence and confocal microscopy</title><p>Cells were collected, fixed and permeabilized with 0.3% triton X-100 for 10 min, incubated with anti-LC3 for 1 h and then FITC-conjugated Anti-LC3A/B antibody (Abcam, ab58610) for 1 h at room temperature. Cell nuclei were stained using ProLong Gold Antifade Reagent with DAPI (Life Technologies). Samples were examined under an Olympus FV1000 confocal microscope. For evaluating tandem fluorescent LC3 puncta, cells were washed with PBS, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde, mounted with DAPI and viewed under a confocal microscope <xref rid="pone.0097242-Klionsky1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title>Autophagy assays</title><p>To analyze autophagic flux, we monitored the formation of autophagic vesicles by the mRFP–GFP–LC3 method (Invitrogen). Due to the quenching of GFP in the acidic lysosomal environment <xref rid="pone.0097242-Klionsky1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, we could distinguish the autophagosomes and autolysosomes through detecting both mRFP and GFP signals, followed by only the mRFP signal. K562 cells were transfected with mRFP-GFP-LC3 expressing pLenti6 lentivirus (Nanjing Mergene Life Science, Nanjing, China). Autophagic flux was determined by evaluating the punctuated pattern of GFP and mRFP (punctae/cell were counted). Fluorescence was analyed on an Olympus (Aartselaar, Belgium) cell imaging station using Cell M software. The protein levels of LC3 and p62 were determined by Western blotting. Transmission electron microscopic (TEM) assessment of autophagosomes-like structures was performed as previously described <xref rid="pone.0097242-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were performed in at least triplicates per group, and data are reported as mean±SEM, unless otherwise indicated. Data were analyzed by 2-tailed Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test or ANOVA least significant difference test, and P&lt;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>S100A8 was overexpressed in drug resistance leukemia cells and anticancer agents increased S100A8 expression in leukemia cells</title><p>S100A8 was differentially expressed in different cell lines, with relatively low S100A8 in Jurkat cells. We found that S100A8 protein was significantly increased in the drug resistance leukemia cell line K562/A02, relative to the nondrug resistant cell line K562 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Elevated S100A8 protein level was also observed in the drug resistance HL-60/ADR cells compared to HL-60 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Furthermore, there were relatively high levels of S100A8 mRNAs in HL-60, K562 and MV4-11 cells in comparison to Jurkat cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>), and significantly increased S100A8 mRNAs in K562/A02 and HL-60/ADR compared with K562 and HL-60, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). These results showed that drug-resistant leukemia cells overexpress S100A8.</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>S100A8 was elevated in drug resistance leukemia cells and chemotherapy agents induced S100A8 expression in leukemia cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Protein level of S100A8 was analyzed by Western blotting in Jurkat, HL-60, K562 and MV4-11 cells (n = 3, <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). (<bold>B and C</bold>) S100A8 mRNA level in leukemia cells was analyzed by real time RT-PCR (n = 3, <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Jurkat cells in <bold>B</bold> and <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus HL-60 or K562 in <bold>C</bold>, Jurkat group set as 1). (<bold>D</bold>) Basal LC3-I/II level was analyzed by Western blotting in leukemia cells (n = 3, <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> Jurkat cells ). (<bold>E and F</bold>) IC50 levels of adriamycin (ADR) in Jurkat, K562, HL-60, MV-4-11, K562/A02, and HL-60/ADR cells (n = 3, <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Jurkat cells in <bold>E</bold>, <sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus HL-60 or K562 in <bold>F</bold>). (<bold>G</bold>) Jurkat, HL-60, K562 and MV4-11 cells were treated with ADR (1 µg/ml), VCR (1 µg/ml) or As2O3 (5 µM) for 24 hours and S100A8 protein level was analyzed by Western blotting (n = 3, *P&lt;0.05 vs. UT, untreated group). AU, arbitrary unit. (<bold>H</bold>) Jurkat, HL-60, K562 and MV4-11 cells were treated with ADR (1 µg/ml), vincristine (VCR, 1 µg/ml) or arsenic trioxide (As2O3, 5 µM) for 24 hours and S100A8 mRNA level was analyzed by real time RT-PCR (n = 3, *P&lt;0.05 versus control group, control group set as 1).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>At the same time, we found the basal authophagy level in the drug resistant leukemia cells was higher compared to the non-drug resistant cell lines. We evaluated basal authophagy in leukaemia cells and compared the levels of autophagy with S100A8 expression. Basal authophagy in leukaemia cells was low. Moreover, we found there were no significant difference in levels of LC3-II/LC-I in HL-60, K562 and MV4-11 cells in comparison to Jurkat cells. However, the authophagy level were increased in K562/A02 relative to K562, and HL-60/ADR compared to HL-60 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>).</p><p>To explore the functions of S100A8 in drug resistance, we next analyzed the relationship between the IC50 of adriamycin and the expression level of S100A8. Increased expression of S100A8 was correlated with higher IC50 of adriamycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1E</xref>). Overexpression of S100A8 in K562/A02 and HL-60/ADR cells was coincident with dramatic increase in IC50 of adriamycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1F</xref>), indicating that S100A8 plays an important role in the drug resistance of leukemia cells.</p><p>It was reported that chemotherapeutic drugs induce S100A8 in the supernatants of cell cultures <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. To further determine the potential role of S100A8 in leukemia in response to chemotherapy, we quantified S100A8 of leukemia cells following treatment with vincristine (VCR, 1 µg/ml), adriamycin (ADR, 1 µg/ml), and arsenic trioxide (As2O3, 5 µM), which are widely used for the treatment of hematological malignancies. Treatment of K562, HL-60, Jurkat and MV4-11 cells with VCR, ADR and As2O3 for 24 h led to significant upregulation of S100A8 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1G</xref>) and mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g001">Fig. 1H</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Suppression of S100A8 rescued the chemotherapy sensitivity in drug resistance leukemia cells</title><p>To evaluate whether overexpression of S100A8 results in drug resistance, we knocked down S100A8 by shRNA in HL60/ADR and K562/A02. S100A8 shRNA transfection led to a significant decrease of both S100A8 protein and mRNA in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). Knockdown of S100A8 significantly sensitized these cells to adriamycin and Vincristine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>), accompanied with high levels of apoptotic cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>) and an increase in cleaved PARP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). Moreover, S100A8 knockdown increased the activation of the proapoptotic protein caspase-3 by both adriamycin and Vincristine, which was abolished by addition of the pan-caspase inhibitor Z-VAD-FMK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2E</xref>). In addition, knockdown of S100A8 in HL60/ADR cells by another S100A8 shRNA from Gene Pharma also increased the sensitivity to DRN- and VCR-induced suppression of cell proliferation and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g002">Fig. 2F</xref>). These data demonstrated that S100A8 increased the resistance of leukemia cells to cytotoxic agents and knockdown of S100A8 restored the sensitivity of K562/A02 and HL60/ADR cells to adriamycin and vincristine.</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Suppression of S100A8 sensitized drug resistance leukemia cells to chemotherapy.</title><p>
<bold>(A)</bold> HL60/ADR and K562/A02 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours. Protein and mRNA level of S100A8 was assayed by Western blot and real time RT-PCR, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) HL60/ADR and K562/A02 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours, then treated with adriamycin (ADR) and vincristine (VCR) for an additional 24 hours. Cell viability was analyzed by MTT. (<bold>C and D</bold>) HL60/ADR and K562/A02 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours, treated with ADR (12.5 µg/mL), VCR (12.5 µg/mL) for additional 24 hours. Apoptosis was analyzed by measuring positive percentage of Annexin V cells via flow cytometry (<bold>C</bold>; n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05); cleaved PARP was analyzed by Western blotting (<bold>D</bold>). (<bold>E</bold>) HL60/ADR and K562/A02 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours, and then treated with ADR (12.5 µg/mL), VCR (12.5 µg/mL) for additional 24 hours with or without ZVAD-FMK (20 µmol/L). Activation of caspase-3 was analyzed (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). (<bold>F</bold>) HL60/ADR cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA (from Gene Pharma, China) for 48 hours and then treated with ADR (12.5 µg/mL), VCR (12.5 µg/mL) for 24 hours. S100A8 protein was determined by Western blot; Cell viability was analyzed by MTT; apoptosis was analyzed by flow cytometry (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Overexpression of S100A8 increases the resistance of leukemia cells to chemotherapy</title><p>To further determine the role of S100A8 in leukemia cells after chemotherapy, we transfected K562 leukemia cells with a plasmid containing full-length human S100A8 cDNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Ectopic overexpression of S100A8 in K562 cells promoted resistance to apoptosis induced by adriamycin and vincristine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Autophagy and apoptosis can be triggered simultaneously by common upstream signals <xref rid="pone.0097242-Maiuri1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. During autophagy, microtubule-associated protein light chain 3 (LC3) is processed post-translationally into soluble LC3-I, and subsequently converted to membrane-bound LC3-II, a marker for autophagosome <xref rid="pone.0097242-Mizushima1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Overexpression of S100A8 increased LC3-II following treatment with either ADR or VCR in K562 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>). Meanwhile, BECN1, which is necessary for the formation of autophagosomes during the autophagic sequestration process <xref rid="pone.0097242-Kihara1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, was significantly increased in S100A8 expressing leukemia cells treated with adriamycin or vincristine for 24 h compared with the untreated and control groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3C,D</xref>). The polyubiquitin-binding protein SQSTM1/aequestosome 1 (p62) has LC3 binding domains, which target p62 for incorporation into the autophagosomes, thus serving as a selective substrate of autophagy <xref rid="pone.0097242-Pankiv1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. We found that overexpression of S100A8 increased LC3-II but decreased p62, indicating that p62 degradation is dependent on S100A8-induced autophagy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3D,E</xref>). Electron microscopy analysis demonstrated that there was increased number of multiple autophagosome-like vacuoles with double-membrane structures in the S100A8 overexpressing cells compared with that of the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3F</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Overexpression of S100A8 increased the resistance of leukemia cells to chemotherapy.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) K562 cells were transfected with control pLPCX or pLPCX-S100A8 plasmids. Protein level of S100A8 was assayed by Western blot. (<bold>B</bold>) K562 cells transfected with control pLPCX or pLPCX-S100A8 plasmids were treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) or VCR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Apoptosis was analyzed by measuring Annexin V–positive cells with flow cytometry (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). (<bold>C</bold>) K562 cells were treated as B, LC3-I/II and BECN1 levels were assayed by Western blot analysis. <bold>UT,</bold> untreated group of K562 cells transfected with S100A8 plasmids. <bold>Control,</bold> K562 cells were transfected with control pLPCX plasmids. (<bold>D</bold>) K562 cells were transfected with pLPCX control or pLPCX -S100A8 cDNA for 48 hours and then treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours in the presence or absence of bafilomycin A1 (Baf; 100 nmol/L). The protein levels of LC3 and p62 were assayed by Western blot. (<bold>E</bold>) K562 cells were transfected pLPCX or pLPCX-S100A8 cDNA with or without the indicated shRNA for 48 hours. Protein levels of S100A8, PI3KC3, BECN1, Atg7, LC3, and p62 were assayed by Western blots. (<bold>F</bold>) K562 cells transfected with control pLPCX or pLPCX-S100A8 cDNA were subjected to TEM analysis. Autophagosomes were highlighted by arrows. (<bold>G</bold>) K562 cells transfected with PLPCX-S100A8 cDNA were treated with bafilomycin A1 (Baf; 100 nmol/L) or 3-methyladenine (3-MA; 10 mmo/L) for 12 hours. LC3 were assayed by Western blot. <bold>Control,</bold> K562 cells were transfected with control pLPCX. (<bold>H</bold>) K562 cells transfected the indicated shRNA were treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) and VCR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Cell viability was analyzed by MTT assay (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). NS, not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>We further found that increase of S100A8 during anticancer therapy could induce autophagic flux in leukaemia cells. Accumulation of LC3-II was observed in the presence of bafilomycin A1 (an inhibitor of late phase autophagy) in k562 cells both before and after treatment with adriamycin for 24 h compared with the absence of bafilomycin A1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>). At the same time, overexpression of S100A8 induced autophagic p62 degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p><p>Bafilomycin A1 increased the induction of LC3-II by S100A8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig 3D</xref>), whereas 3-methyladenine, an inhibitor of early-phase autophagy <xref rid="pone.0097242-Mizushima1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, inhibited S100A8-induced LC3-II expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3G</xref>). PI3KC3, BECN1 (the mammalian ortholog of yeast Vps30/Atg6), and ATG7 are key regulators of the classical autophagy pathway in mammalian cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Levine1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. To extend our observation that S100A8 promotes anticancer drug resistance by enhancing autophagy, we knocked down PI3KC3, BECN 1, and Atg7 by shRNA and found that silencing of these genes inhibited LC3-II formation and prevented autophagic p62 degradation in S100A8 overexpressing K562 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3E</xref>). Moreover, downregulation of these genes reversed S100A8-induced protection against chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g003">Fig. 3H</xref>). These findings indicate that autophagy is required for S100A8-mediated resistance to anticancer agents.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>S100A8 regulates autophagy during chemotherapy in leukemia cells</title><p>S100A8 is required for the initiation of As2O3-reduced autophagy in leukemia cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. To further explore the mechanism by which S100A8 regulates autophagy in leukemia cells, we detected LC3-I to LC3-II conversion by immunoblot analysis and LC3 puncta formation by fluorescent imaging analysis. Knockdown of S100A8 inhibited ADR-induced LC3-II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). LC3 is lipidated and recruited to the autophagosomal membrane following autophagosome formation. Accordingly, accumulation of LC3-II was observed in the presence of bafilomycin A1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Moreover, knockdown of S100A8 inhibited the accumulation of LC3 puncta in leukemia cells as detected by immunofluorenscence with a LC3 antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). In addition, ultrastructural analysis revealed that cells transfected with S100A8 shRNA exhibited fewer autophagosomes during chemotherapy compared with cells transfected with control shRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). To test whether S100A8 influences autophagic flux, we evaluated the expression of p62. Indeed, knockdown of S100A8 inhibited autophagic p62 degradation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). These findings further support a critical role for S100A8 in the regulation of autophagy in leukemia cells.</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>S100A8 regulated the chemotherapy–induced autophagy in leukemia cells.</title><p>(<bold>A and B)</bold> K562 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours and then treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) and VCR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours in the presence or absence of bafilomycin A1 (Baf; 100 nmol/L). The protein levels of LC3 and p62 were assayed by Western blot (<bold>A</bold>); LC3 puncta were analyzed by LC3 antibody or mRFP–GFP–LC3 (Magnification is 10×60 oil) (<bold>B</bold>) (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). (<bold>C</bold>) K562 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours and then treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) and VCR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Autophagosome-like structures (indicated by the red arrows) were assayed by TEM (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). Bar = 2 µm. (<bold>D and E</bold>) K562/A02 cells were transfected with control shRNA or S100A8 shRNA for 48 hours. After pretreatment with rapamycin (Rap; 100 nmol/L) for 6 hours, cells were treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Apoptosis was analyzed by measuring Annexin V–positive cells with flow cytometry (<bold>D</bold>). Autophagy was analyzed by measuring LC3 puncta formation (<bold>E</bold>; n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Rapamycin induces autophagy by inhibiting the mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) <xref rid="pone.0097242-Ravikumar1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Rapamycin pretreatment prevented ADR from inducing apoptosis in K562/A02 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). However, rapamycin conferred less protection in K562/A02 cells transfected with S100A8 shRNA probably due to diminished autophagic capacity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g004">Fig. 4E</xref>). These results suggest that S100A8 is an important regulator of autophagy-mediated leukemia cell survival.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>S100A8 regulates the formation of BECN1–PI3KC3 complex but not ULK1–mAtg13 complex</title><p>Mammalian autophagy is a multi-step process including initiation, nucleation, elongation, closure, maturation, and finally degradation or extrusion, and regulated by a core family of ATG proteins <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Klionsky2" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. To explore the underlying molecular mechanism of S100A8-mediated autophagy, we analyzed the early autophagic signaling event of ULK1 complex formation. ULK1 is essential for autophagy induction and is comprised of a large complex that includes a mammalian homologue of Atg13 (mAtg13). Knockdown of S100A8 did not affect the formation of ULK1-mAtg13 complex and phosphorylation of ULK1 at Ser55 following ADR treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). However, S100A8 knockdown significantly reduced the formation of the BECN1-PI3KC3 complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>), which mediates vesicle nucleation during autophagy. Consistent with the previous studies <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, S100A8 formed a complex with BECN1 in leukemia cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>). Moreover, knockdown of ULK1 inhibited the interaction between S100A8 and BECN1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>) and potentiated anticancer agent-induced cell apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>). These data suggest that S100A8 is a downstream signaling molecule from the ULK1-mAtg13 complex and facilitates autophagy in leukemia cells by interacting with BECN1.</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>ULK1-mAtg13 regulated the fomation of S100A8-BECN1 complex formation in leukemia cells.</title><p>(<bold>A-C</bold>) K562 cells were transfected with S100A8 shRNA (A and B) or ULK1 shRNA (C) for 48 hours and then were treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Cells were then processed for immunoprecipitation (IP) or Western blotting (IB) as described in Materials and Methods. All data are representative of 3 experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) K562 cells transfected with S100A8 shRNA (A and B) or ULK1 shRNA (C) for 48 hours were treated with ADR (1 µg/mL) or VCR (1 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Apoptosis was analyzed by measuring Annexin V–positive cells with flow cytometry (n = 3;<sup> *</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g005.jpg"/></fig><sec id="s3e1"><title>RAGE was involved in exogenous S100A8-induced autophagy</title><p>To investigate whether extracellular S100A8 induce autophagy in leukemia cells, we treated K562 cells with 1 µg/ml S100A8 protein for 24 h and detected LC3-I/LC3-II and P62 by immunoblot analysis. We found that S100A8 treatment increased the expression of LC3-II, and decreased the expression of p62. To test the role of RAGE and TLR4 in S100A8-induced autophagy, we knocked down RAGE and TLR4 by shRNA in K562 cells. We found that silencing RAGE inhibited LC3-II formation and prevented autophagic p62 degradation. In contrast, knock down of TLR4 did not influence S100A8-induced autophagic flux. These findings indicate that RAGE is involved in exogenous S100A8-induced autophagy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g006">Fig. 6</xref>)</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Exogenous S100A8 regulate autophagy through RAGE receptor.</title><p>K562 cells were transfected with control shRNA, RAGE shRNA or TLR4 shRNA for 48 hours, and then treated with S100A8 protein (1 µg/ml) for 24 hours. LC3, p62, RAGE and TLR4 were assayed by Western blot. All data were representatives of 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Chemotherapy is the major treatment strategy for nearly all types of childhood leukemia <xref rid="pone.0097242-Pui1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Rubnitz1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>; however, drug resistance often renders chemotherapy ineffective and negatively impacts long-term event-free survival <xref rid="pone.0097242-Norgaard1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Multidrug resistance results from multiple mechanisms including dysfunctional membrane transport, resistance to apoptosis, and the persistence of stem cell-like leukemia cells. Thus, attenuating drug resistance is a current challenge for the treatment of leukemia.</p><p>S100A8 is expressed in a wide variety of cell types and abundant in myeloid cells. Elevated expression of S100A8 has been found in disorders including rheumatoid arthritis, inflammatory bowel disease, and vasculitis <xref rid="pone.0097242-Nacken1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. S100A8 and HMGB1 are the ligands of receptor for advanced glycation endproducts (RAGE). RAGE/RAGE ligand interaction is associated with survival of cells expressing this receptor, and is involved in the development and progression of cancer <xref rid="pone.0097242-Chavakis1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Inhibition of RAGE interaction with S100p enhanced the anti-tumor activity of conventional chemotherapy in a xenograft model of pancreatic cancer <xref rid="pone.0097242-Arumugam1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. We previously found that HMGB1-induced autophagy enhances chemotherapy resistance in leukemia cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Liu2" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It was reported that S100A8 protein balances tumor cell growth and apoptosis in a concentration-dependent manner <xref rid="pone.0097242-Ghavami2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Furthermore, variation of S100A8 transcripts has been found in AMLs and correlates with the FAB (French-American-British classification) subtype, or the differentiation of AML <xref rid="pone.0097242-Cui1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Nevertheless, the role of S100A8 in the pathogenesis of leukemia is unknown.</p><p>A number of anticancer therapies, including DNA-damaging chemotherapeutic drugs, induce the accumulation of autophagosomes in tumor cell lines, while pharmacologic inhibition of autophagy or genetic knockdown of phylogenetically conserved autophagy-related genes, such as Atg5 and Atg7, enhanced drug-induced cytotoxicities <xref rid="pone.0097242-EisenbergLerner1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. The ability to affect chemotherapy sensitivity by regulating autophagy in leukemia cells is a novel function of S100A8 <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. In this study, we showed that A100A8-mediated autophagy is a significant contributor to drug resistance in leukemia. We found that S100A8 level was elevated in drug resistance leukemia cells relative to the nondrug resistant cells, and vincristine, adriamycin and arsenic trioxide enhanced the expression of S100A8 in human leukemia cells. Further, inhibition of S100A8 or autophagy increased the drug sensitivity of leukemia cells, and knockdown of S100A8 by shRNA increased cell death and suppressed leukemia cell growth. As a member of DAMPs, S100A8 demonstrate an anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidative, and protective effect on cells <xref rid="pone.0097242-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yonekawa1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The expression of S100A8 in AML patients is associated with worse prognosis and a predictor of poor survival <xref rid="pone.0097242-Nicolas1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus, it is intriguing to propose that release of S100A8 by dying leukemia cells may help process and present leukemia antigens to immune effector cells.</p><p>Cancer cells respond to chemotherapy in a variety of ways, ranging from the activation of survival pathways to the initiation of cell death. Increased autophagy is observed in leukemia cells when exposed to chemotherapy drugs <xref rid="pone.0097242-Han1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0097242-Evangelisti1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. In general, autophagy is a "programmed cell survival" mechanism to prevent the accumulation of damaged or unnecessary components, but also functions to facilitate the recycling of these components to sustain homoeostasis. Therefore, autophagy functions as a double-edged sword in cancer development and progression by inducing both tumor cell survival and death. In tumor cells, the role of autophagy may depend on the type of tumors and the stage of tumorigenesis <xref rid="pone.0097242-Dikic1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. We found that inhibition of autophagy increases leukemia cell death and reverses S100A8-mediated drug resistance. A systematic study on cells exposed to many compounds showed that no single cytotoxic agent can induce cell death by autophagy <xref rid="pone.0097242-Shen1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, supporting the observation that autophagy is mostly a cytoprotective mechanism. Here, we found that knockdown of S100A8 decreased LC3 II formation and p62 degradation, which was associated with a decreased number of membrane-bound autophagosomes, as detected by TEM in leukemia cells.</p><p>We previously found that S100A8 interacts with BECN1 and displaces Bcl-2 <xref rid="pone.0097242-Yang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. In the current study, we found that the ULK1-mAtg13 complex is required for the interaction between S100A8 and BECN1, which promotes BECN1-PI3KC3 complex formation. However, the assembly of the BECN1 complexes is complicated and seems to differ in a cell- or tissue-dependent manner <xref rid="pone.0097242-Kang1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) is a key molecular player in energy homeostasis and important for the activation of ULK1 <xref rid="pone.0097242-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Further studies are needed to test whether AMPK or other kinases are involved in regulating the interaction between S100A8 and BECN1. Finally, we and found that exogenous S100A8 regulates autophagy through its receptor, RAGE, but not TLR4.</p><p>In conclusion, we showed that chemotherapy-induced S100A8 expression in leukemia cells promoted autophagy, which in turn inhibited apoptosis and increased drug resistance, indicating that S100A8 is an important regulator of autophagy. Moreover, suppression of S100A8 expression significantly increased drug sensitivity of leukemia cells, suggesting that S100A8 may be a novel target for leukemia therapy. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097242-g007">Fig 7</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0097242-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097242.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Scheme of S100A8-mediated autophagy promoting drug resistance in leukemia.</title><p>Leukemia is the most common type of cancer occurs in childhood. Vincristine and adriamycin are the commonly used cytotoxic anticancer drugs in the treatment of patients with Leukemia. These drugs increase endogenous mRNA and protein expression of S100A8 in Leukemia cells by an unknown mechanism. Upregulated S100A8 competes with BCL-2 to bind BECN1, which increases the formation of the BECN1-PtdIns3KC3 complex and stimulates autophagosome maturation and autophagy. As an upstream signal, activation of the ULK1-mATG13 complex is required for the interaction between S100A8 and BECN1. Knockdown of S100A8 or inhibition of autophagy increase apoptosis, and reverses drug resistance in leukemia cells. Furthermore, exogenous S100A8 regulates autophagy through the RAGE receptor. Thus S100A8-mediated autophagy is a potential therapeutic target for leukemia.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0097242.g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0097242-Yang1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klionsky</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Eaten alive: a history of macroautophagy</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>814</fpage>–<lpage>822</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20811353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncb0910-814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3616322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Kroemer1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Autophagy and the integrated stress response</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20965422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.09.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3127250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Helgason1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Helgason</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karvela</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holyoake</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Kill one bird with two stones: potential efficacy of BCR-ABL and autophagy inhibition in CML</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>118</volume>: <fpage>2035</fpage>–<lpage>2043</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2011-01-330621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Zhu1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) Inhibiting autophagy potentiates the anticancer activity of @/IFNalpha in chronic myeloid leukemia cells. <article-title>Autophagy</article-title>. <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/auto.22923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3590253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Han1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Autophagy inhibition enhances daunorubicin-induced apoptosis in K562 cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e28491</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22164300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0028491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3229606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Yu1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Targeting microRNA-30a-mediated autophagy enhances imatinib activity against human chronic myeloid leukemia cells</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1752</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22395361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/leu.2012.65</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Liu1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>DAMP-mediated autophagy contributes to drug resistance</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/auto.7.1.14005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3039734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Schafer1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heizmann</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The S100 family of EF-hand calcium-binding proteins: functions and pathology</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>134</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8701470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0968-0004(96)80167-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Foell1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Foell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittkowski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>S100 proteins expressed in phagocytes: a novel group of damage-associated molecular pattern molecules</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16943388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1189/jlb.0306170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Ghavami1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghavami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chazin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kadkhoda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>S100A8/9 induces cell death via a novel, RAGE-independent pathway that involves selective release of Smac/DIABLO and Omi/HtrA2</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1783</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18060880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2007.10.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Cross1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamdy</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deloulme</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Expression of S100 proteins in normal human tissues and common cancers using tissue microarrays: S100A6, S100A8, S100A9 and S100A11 are all overexpressed in common cancers</article-title>. <source>Histopathology</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2559.2005.02097.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Nicolas1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arlotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouamrani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Expression of S100A8 in leukemic cells predicts poor survival in de novo AML patients</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21072048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/leu.2010.251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-SpijkersHagelstein1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spijkers-Hagelstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hulleman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Elevated S100A8/S100A9 expression causes glucocorticoid resistance in MLL-rearranged infant acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1255</fpage>–<lpage>1265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22282267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/leu.2011.388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Yang2"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>S100A8-targeting siRNA enhances arsenic trioxide-induced myeloid leukemia cell death by down-regulating autophagy</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Med</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21971985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijmm.2011.806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Yang3"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>WAVE1 regulates P-glycoprotein expression via Ezrin in leukemia cells</article-title>. <source>Leuk Lymphoma</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21281239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/10428194.2010.538776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Liu2"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>HMGB1-induced autophagy promotes chemotherapy resistance in leukemia cells</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20927132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/leu.2010.225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Klionsky1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klionsky</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeliovich</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acevedo-Arozena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Guidelines for the use and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22966490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/auto.19496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3404883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Maiuri1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maiuri</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zalckvar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Self-eating and self-killing: crosstalk between autophagy and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17717517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm2239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Mizushima1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Methods in mammalian autophagy research</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>140</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20144757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2010.01.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Kihara1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kabeya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Beclin-phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase complex functions at the trans-Golgi network</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11306555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/embo-reports/kve061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1083858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Pankiv1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pankiv</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamark</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruun</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>p62/SQSTM1 binds directly to Atg8/LC3 to facilitate degradation of ubiquitinated protein aggregates by autophagy</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>282</volume>: <fpage>24131</fpage>–<lpage>24145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17580304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M702824200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Levine1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Autophagy in the pathogenesis of disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18191218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2007.12.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2696814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Ravikumar1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ravikumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of mTOR induces autophagy and reduces toxicity of polyglutamine expansions in fly and mouse models of Huntington disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng1362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Klionsky2"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klionsky</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cregg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>WA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emr</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A unified nomenclature for yeast autophagy-related genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14536056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1534-5807(03)00296-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Pui1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pui</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robison</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Look</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>371</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>1043</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18358930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60457-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Rubnitz1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rubnitz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Childhood acute myeloid leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>
<volume>159</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22966788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bjh.12040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3468705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Norgaard1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Norgaard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hokland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Changing picture of cellular drug resistance in human leukemia</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15094158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1040-8428(03)00173-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Nacken1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nacken</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>S100A9/S100A8: Myeloid representatives of the S100 protein family as prominent players in innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Microsc Res Tech</source>
<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12645005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jemt.10299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Chavakis1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chavakis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bierhaus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nawroth</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>RAGE (receptor for advanced glycation end products): a central player in the inflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1219</fpage>–<lpage>1225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micinf.2004.08.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Arumugam1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logsdon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Effect of cromolyn on S100P interactions with RAGE and pancreatic cancer growth and invasion in mouse models</article-title>. <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1806</fpage>–<lpage>1818</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/djj498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4461034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Ghavami2"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ghavami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rashedi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dattilo</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eshraghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chazin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>S100A8/A9 at low concentration promotes tumor cell growth via RAGE ligation and MAP kinase-dependent pathway</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>–<lpage>1492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18339893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1189/jlb.0607397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2737328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Cui1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Proteomic analysis of human acute leukemia cells: insight into their classification</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>6887</fpage>–<lpage>6896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-04-0307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-EisenbergLerner1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg-Lerner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bialik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Life and death partners: apoptosis, autophagy and the cross-talk between them</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>975</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cdd.2009.33</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Sun1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sroussi</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The anti-oxidative, anti-inflammatory, and protective effect of S100A8 in endotoxemic mice</article-title>. <source>Mol Immunol</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23127860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molimm.2012.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3595546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Yonekawa1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yonekawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neidhart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altwegg</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Myeloid related proteins activate Toll-like receptor 4 in human acute coronary syndromes</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source>
<volume>218</volume>: <fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2011.06.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Evangelisti1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Evangelisti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tazzari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabellini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Battistelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Targeted inhibition of mTORC1 and mTORC2 by active-site mTOR inhibitors has cytotoxic effects in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Leukemia</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21331075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/leu.2011.20</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Dikic1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dikic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Selective autophagy in cancer development and therapy</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>3431</fpage>–<lpage>3434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20424122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-4027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Shen1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kepp</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minoux</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Association and dissociation of autophagy, apoptosis and necrosis by systematic chemical study</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>4544</fpage>–<lpage>4556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21577201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2011.168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Kang1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeh</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Beclin 1 network regulates autophagy and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21311563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cdd.2010.191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3131912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0097242-Kim1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viollet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>AMPK and mTOR regulate autophagy through direct phosphorylation of Ulk1</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21258367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncb2152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3987946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>