
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="other" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neurosci Rural Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Neurosci Rural Pract</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1549</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jnruralp</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101533710</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JNRP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Neurosciences in Rural Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0976-3147</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-3155</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Scholar</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4898114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4898114.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4898114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4898114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27365963</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0976-3147.182779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JNRP-7-435</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Series</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of intracranial metastases from neuroendocrine tumors/carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragab Shalaby</surname><given-names initials="AM">Ahmed M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazuei</surname><given-names initials="H">Hoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koichi</surname><given-names initials="H">Honma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naguib</surname><given-names initials="S">Saeed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Menawei</surname><given-names initials="LA">Lubna A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><italic toggle="yes">Department of Oncologic Pathology, Kameda Hospital and Oncology Center, Kamogawa Chiba, Japan</italic></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label><italic toggle="yes">Department of Immunology, Damanhour National Medical Institute, Damanhour, Egypt</italic></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label><italic toggle="yes">Department of Pathology, KAAZ Hospital and Oncology Center, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ahmed M. Ragab Shalaby, Apt. 503173, Ahmad Shawki Street, Roushdi, Alexandria, Egypt. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="teshtawy@gmail.com">teshtawy@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">270683</issue-id><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2017-05-12 00:12:19.440"><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2017</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © Journal of Neurosciences in Rural Practice</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="J Neurosci Rural Pract" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5402520"><article-title>Retraction: Assessment of intracranial metastases from neuroendocrine tumors/carcinoma</article-title><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><date><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2017</year></date><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><source>Journal of Neurosciences in Rural Practice</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5402520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479828</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The most common sites of origin for neuroendocrine carcinoma are gastrointestinal tract and its accessory glands, and lungs.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>One-hundred fifty cases diagnosed with metastatic brain lesions were retrieved from hospital records within 5 years. For these cases, the primary neoplasm, histopathological classification, metastasis, treatment, and fate all were studied.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Intracranial deposits were detected in 10%. The primary lesion was in the lungs in 87% of patients, and 1 patient in the breast and 1 in esophagus. Pathological classification of the primary lesion was Grade 2 (MIB-1: 3–20%) in 1 patient and neuroendocrine carcinoma (MIB-1: ≥21%) in 14 patients. The median period from onset of the primary lesion up to diagnosis of brain metastasis was 12.8 months. About 33% of patients had a single metastasis whereas 67% patients had multiple metastases. Brain metastasis was extirpated in 33% of patients. Stereotactic radiotherapy alone was administered in 20% of patients, and brain metastasis was favorably controlled in most of the patients with coadministration of cranial irradiation as appropriate. The median survival period from diagnosis of brain metastasis was 8.1 months.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Most of patients with brain metastasis from neuroendocrine carcinoma showed the primary lesion in the lungs, and they had multiple metastases to the liver, lymph nodes, bones, and so forth at the time of diagnosis of brain metastasis. The guidelines for accurate diagnosis and treatment of neuroendocrine carcinoma should be immediately established based on further analyses of those patients with brain metastasis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Intracranial metastases</kwd><kwd>neuroendocrine carcinoma</kwd><kwd>radiotherapy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Neuroendocrine tumor (NET)/carcinoma is characterized by secretion of many active hormones and the presence of intracytoplasmic secretory granules.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p><p>They may develop in all body organs, and many of them also have a malignant course. The World Health Organization (WHO) therefore attempted to grade NETs based on systematic clinical pathological classification, but classifications with different criteria were proposed for NETs originating from the favored sites (pancreas and gastrointestinal tract) and NETs originating from the lungs.</p><p>Neurosurgeons are increasingly experiencing patients with brain metastasis from tumors diagnosed as neuroendocrine carcinoma.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] However, few reports examined brain metastasis of such patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>All cases of neuroendocrine carcinoma were searched among histopathological diagnoses of all neoplasm specimens obtained during surgical procedures at Kameda Hospital and Oncology Center; Kamogawa – JAPAN during the 5 years between January 2011 and December 2015. As a result, 150 patients were confirmed carrying their diagnosis. The age of patients ranged between 21 and 91 years (median: 64.5-year-old) and there were 90 men and 60 women. The primary site of NETs was the lungs in 51 patients, rectum in 18 patients, pancreas in 13 patients, stomach in 10 patients, mammary glands in 10 patients, uterus in 9 patients, lymph nodes in 8 patients, and duodenum in 6 patients. Other sites of onset were the thymus gland in 4 patients, esophagus in 3 patients, ileum in 3 patients, liver in 2 patients, colon in 2 patients, pharynx in 2 patients, paranasal sinus in 1 patients, kidneys in 1 patients, urinary tract in 1 patients, and ovaries in 1 patients and 5 cases of unknown primary.</p><p>This study was conducted in Kameda Hospital and Oncology Center; Kamogawa-Chiba-JAPAN.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Clinical data</title><p>Age of patients ranged between 34 and 78 years (median: 68-year-old) and 20 of them were men and 10 of them were women [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical, Pathological, Imaging and Therapeutic Data</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g001.jpg"/></table-wrap><p>The period from histopathological detection of primary lesion up to diagnosis of brain metastasis ranged between 0 and 33.4 months (median: 12.8 months) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Period from histopathological diagnosis of the primary tumor till discovery of intracranial deposits</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Fate and outcomes</title><p>The follow-up period after treatment of metastatic brain tumors was from 1 to 34 months (median: 5.8 months), and 29 of 31 patients were deceased by the time of completion of examinations. Analysis by the Kaplan–Meier survival curve revealed a median survival period of 8.1 months [Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Radiologic patterns. (a) Single/nodular type. (b) Single/cystic type. (c) Multiple/nodular type. (d) Multiple/cystic type</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Survival period after diagnosis of metastatic brain tumor</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(a) Chest computed tomography scan shows a small lesion on the mediastinum at right S2. (b) Sagittal contrast-enhanced T1-weighted head magnetic resonance imaging reveals two tumors in the pineal body and the cerebellum accompanied by obstructive hydrocephalus. (c) H and E, stain image of neuroendoscopic biopsy tissues (—200). (d) anti-synaptophysin antibody stain image (—200). (e) Anti-chromogranin A antibody stain image (—200). (f) MIB-1 stain image (×200). (g) Bone scintigraphy shows multiple metastases to the cervical vertebrae</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(a and b) Horizontal contrast-enhanced T1-weighted head magnetic resonance imaging shows multiple tumors with cysts in the right occipital lobe and the parietal lobe. (c) H and E, image of the isolated parietal lobe tumor tissues (—200). (d) Anti-synaptophysin antibody stain image (—200). (e) Anti-CD56 antibody stain image (—200). (f) Anti-TTF-1 antibody stain image (—200). (g and h) Horizontal contrast-enhanced T1-weighted head magnetic resonance imaging after cranial irradiation therapy</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="JNRP-7-435-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Carcinoid has been the description of NETs for any years. It was later considered that NETs should be treated as clinically malignant tumors and the term “carcinoid” was eliminated from the WHO classification in 2000. Subsequently, NETs were categorized into five types, namely, NET Grade 1, NET Grade 2, NEC (large cell or small cell), mixed adenoneuroendocrine carcinoma, and hyperplastic and neoplastic lesions, in the 2010 WHO classification according to the grading by the Ki-67 labeling index.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><p>The incidence of NETs among all tumors was 4.44% in Caucasians and 6.5% in African Americans, and male patients were slightly predominant; the incidence increased by 37% in Caucasians and 40% in African Americans compared with the statistical data between 1993 and 1997.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The site of onset of NETs in Caucasian patients was the lungs/bronchus in 31.9%, small intestine in 17.7%, unknown in 13.5%, and rectum in 12.3% whereas that in African American patients was the rectum in 27%, small intestine in 21%, and lungs/bronchus in 18.3%. Thus, a slight ethnic difference was observed.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Also, in the percentage of NETs against all types of tumors in each site of origin, NETs accounted for the highest (1.42%) in the lungs/bronchus in Caucasian patients whereas NETs accounted for the highest (1.65%) in the rectum in African American patients.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] The pancreas accounted for 4% of all types of the NETs and for approximately 0.3% of all pancreatic cancers,[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] being a very rare disease. Regarding the metastasis of NETs to other organs, distant metastasis was observed in 20–30% of patients at the time of diagnosis.</p><p>We retrieved 150 patients with NETs who were diagnosed at our hospital over the past 5 years. The site of onset was the lungs in 51 patients, rectum in 18 patients, and pancreas in 13 patients, which were almost comparable with the site of onset in Caucasian patients, and the number of patients with NETs in the pancreas was higher in Japanese patients. Brain metastasis was observed in 15 patients (10.0%) and it was interesting that 13 (87%) of them were metastasis from the primary lung NETs. Primary brain metastasis is mainly caused by primary lung NETs.</p><p>The European Neuroendocrine Tumor Society (ENETS) in 2012 published the consensus guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of NETs for each site of onset.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] During preparation of the guidelines, the ENETS advisory board, and experts have published the analytical results on metastasis to other organs from NETs.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] The description of brain, and ovarian metastasis in the article stated that brain metastasis from primary lung NETs accounted for 45–71% of patients with the median period of 1.5 years from the diagnosis of the primary lesion until confirmation of brain metastasis.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Lymph node metastasis and liver metastasis were present in 75% and 50% of the patients with brain metastasis,[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] respectively, which were comparable to the results of our present study. Approximately 1.4% of metastatic brain tumors were NETs whereas the incidence of brain metastasis from NETs was 1.5–5%.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] The incidence of primary lung NETs was higher in our present study and that would be the cause of slightly higher incidence in brain metastasis at 10.3%. A report that summarized 24 patients was the highest number of patients and only 57 patients were reported during the 46 years between 1962 and 2007.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] The report of ENET[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] did not contain a definite description of pathological findings and grading.</p><p>When limited to lung NETs, brain metastasis occurs in 30% or more of the large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma (LCNEC) patients and in 24% of the small cell carcinoma patients.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] In the present study, the strategy of surgery and radiotherapy for the patients was determined based on the symptoms, PS, and imaging findings (number of brain metastases), and such action would be the standard concept for metastatic brain tumors at present. On the other hand, prophylactic cranial irradiation is also a possible option for small cell lung cancer.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] The median survival period from diagnosis of brain metastasis was 8.1 months in the present study, and it was not greatly different from that of brain metastasis in all lung cancer patients.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Lately, various therapies such as combination chemotherapy, epidermal growth factor receptor-tyrosine kinase inhibitors, and angiogenesis inhibitors have become available for brain metastasis originating from lung cancer.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Approximately 10% of NET patients developed brain metastasis at slightly longer than 1 year after diagnosis, and metastasis originating from LCNEC or small cell carcinoma occurred in most of them. The treatment options for brain metastasis varied depending on the symptoms due to brain metastasis, performance status, and metastatic images. Most of the metastases were controlled by applying active therapy to the brain lesion, but the mean survival period was 8 months from diagnosis of brain metastasis, mainly because of aggravation of the primary lesion or metastasis to other organs. Standardization of clinical and pathological interpretation of NETs can give better help by establishment of optimal guidelines for diagnosis and treatment of brain metastasis originating from NETs.</p><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberndorfer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Karzinoide tumoren des dünndarms</article-title><source>Frankf Z Pathol</source><year>1907</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gompel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parney</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain carcinoid metastases: Outcomes and prognostic factors</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2013</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23394337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3171/2013.1.JNS121556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy for pulmonary large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma: Similar to that for small cell lung cancer or non-small cell lung cancer?</article-title><source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2012.04.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma diagnosed in a brain metastasis</article-title><source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22400077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3294230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Second cancers in patients with neuroendocrine tumors</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e86414</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24392036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0086414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3877400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsugu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumae</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain metastasis from large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma of the urinary bladder</article-title><source>Surg Neurol Int</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>84</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21748036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/2152-7806.82250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3130460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeichner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cusnir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francavilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Typical bronchial carcinoid metastasizing to the brain: A case presentation</article-title><source>Case Rep Oncol</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22291640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000335557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3268525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinik</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woltering</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caplin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Dorisio</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NANETS consensus guidelines for the diagnosis of neuroendocrine tumor</article-title><source>Pancreas</source><year>2010</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20664471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MPA.0b013e3181ebaffd</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauso</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldum</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drozdov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuroendocrine tumor epidemiology: Contrasting Norway and North America</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>2655</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18853416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.23883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>European Neuroendocrine Tumor Society</source><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2015 Feb 12</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.enets.org">http://www.enets.org</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaltsas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinmüller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ENETS consensus guidelines for the management of brain, cardiac and ovarian metastases from neuroendocrine tumors</article-title><source>Neuroendocrinology</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20453466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000287277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological characteristics and treatment outcomes of metastatic or recurrent neuroendocrine tumors: Tumor grade and metastatic site are important for treatment strategy</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>448</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20731845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2407-10-448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2936327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of brain metastasis from lung cancer</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2100</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24281220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers2042100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3840463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akimoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuhara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinicopathological analysis in patients with neuroendocrine tumors that metastasized to the brain</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26801624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-015-1999-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4724130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Antonio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gori</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Signore</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Migliorino</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bone and brain metastasis in lung cancer: Recent advances in therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24790650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1758834014521110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3987652</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>