
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4452711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4452711.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4452711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4452711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26035306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128753</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-10020</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic Variants in DNA Double-Strand Break Repair Genes and Risk of Salivary Gland Carcinoma: A Case-Control Study</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Variants in DSB Repair Genes and Salivary Gland Cancer Risk</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="L">Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Naggar</surname><given-names initials="AK">Adel K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names initials="P">Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturgis</surname><given-names initials="EM">Erich M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Head and Neck Surgery, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Gastrointestinal Medical Oncology, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pathology, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Division of Biostatistics and Human Genetics Center, School of Public Health, The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff005">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Epidemiology, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotterill</surname><given-names initials="S">Sue</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>St. Georges University of London, UNITED KINGDOM</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LX AKE EMS. Performed the experiments: LX HT. Analyzed the data: LX HT PW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HT PW. Wrote the paper: LX HT AKE PW EMS.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>esturgis@mdanderson.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">253619</issue-id><elocation-id>e0128753</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>06</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-10 14:25:16.620"><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Xu et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Xu et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0128753.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0128753.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="Fed Regist" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5959822"><article-title>Findings of Research Misconduct</article-title><volume>83</volume><issue>97</issue><date><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><fpage>23282</fpage><lpage>23282</lpage><source>Federal Register</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5959822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30356338</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="PLoS One" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6013161"><article-title>Retraction: Genetic Variants in DNA Double-Strand Break Repair Genes and Risk of Salivary Gland Carcinoma: A Case-Control Study</article-title><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><date><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><elocation-id>e0199690</elocation-id><source>PLoS ONE</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6013161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29928030</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>DNA double strand break (DSB) repair is the primary defense mechanism against ionizing radiation-induced DNA damage. Ionizing radiation is the only established risk factor for salivary gland carcinoma (SGC). We hypothesized that genetic variants in DSB repair genes contribute to individual variation in susceptibility to SGC. To test this hypothesis, we conducted a case-control study in which we analyzed 415 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 45 DSB repair genes in 352 SGC cases and 598 controls. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to calculate odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Rs3748522 in <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic> and rs13180356 in <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic> were significantly associated with SGC after Bonferroni adjustment; ORs (95% CIs) for the variant alleles of these SNPs were 1.71 (1.40-2.09, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=1.70 × 10<sup>-7</sup>) and 0.58 (0.45-0.74, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=2.00 × 10<sup>-5</sup>) respectively. The genetic effects were modulated by histological subtype. The association of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522 with SGC was strongest for mucoepidermoid carcinoma (OR=2.21, 95% CI: 1.55-3.15, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=1.25 × 10<sup>-5</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=74), and the association of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 with SGC was strongest for adenoid cystic carcinoma (OR=0.60, 95% CI: 0.42-0.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=6.91 × 10<sup>-3</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=123). Gene-level association analysis revealed one gene, <italic toggle="yes">PRKDC</italic>, with a marginally significant association with SGC risk in non-Hispanic whites. To our knowledge, this study is the first to comprehensively evaluate the genetic effect of DSB repair genes on SGC risk. Our results indicate that genetic variants in the DSB repair pathways contribute to inter-individual differences in susceptibility to SGC and show that the impact of genetic variants differs by histological subtype. Independent studies are warranted to confirm these findings.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported in part by The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center start-up funds (to EMS), National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant U01 DE019765-01 (to AKE, EMS is project 2 leader), and Cancer Center Support Grant CA016672 to The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center (to Dr. Ronald DePinho). PW was partially supported by NIH grant R01CA169122.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Salivary gland carcinoma (SGC) accounts for only 0.3% of all malignancies in the United States [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Although some exposures have been proposed to contribute to salivary gland carcinogenesis, including smoking [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], alcohol drinking [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], hormonal factors [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and dietary factors [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], the only well-established risk factor is exposure to ionizing radiation (IR). Several studies have shown significantly increased risks of SGC among atomic bomb survivors and patients who have undergone radiotherapy for various diseases of the head and neck [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. One of the major subtypes of SGC is mucoepidermoid carcinoma[<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Like the frequency of SGC, the frequency of the mucoepidermoid carcinoma subtype has been reported to be disproportionately high among atomic bomb survivors [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Intriguingly, about 80% of mucoepidermoid carcinomas are characterized by the t(11q21, 19p13) translocation [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Translocation occurs due to DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs), the most serious form of DNA damage caused by IR. However, only a very small proportion of individuals exposed to IR ultimately develop SGC, suggesting that there is a range of susceptibility to IR-induced salivary gland carcinogenesis. These observations underscore the crucial role of the defense system again DNA DSBs in salivary gland carcinogenesis and led us to hypothesize that inherited variants in DSB repair pathway genes contribute to individual variation in susceptibility to SGC.</p><p>To test our hypothesis, we evaluated the association of common genetic variations in 45 genes composing the DSB repair pathways with risk of SGC in 352 patients with SGC and 598 cancer-free controls. We analyzed both SNP-level and gene-level associations. In addition, we performed stratification analysis by age, sex, race, and other possible risk factors to study possible gene-environment interactions. We found that variant alleles of two SNPs were associated with SGC, and the associations were modified by histological subtype of SGC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Study population</title><p>The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board at The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, and all participants provided written informed consent before inclusion in the study. The case-control study included 352 SGC cases and 598 controls prospectively recruited between 2001 and 2014 at MD Anderson Cancer Center. The cases were patients diagnosed with SGC by pathological examination, and the controls were recruited from among unrelated visitors to the institution. Recruitment criteria included age of 18 years or older, no prior malignancy except nonmelanoma skin cancer, no blood transfusion in the past 6 months, and not taking immunosuppressant medications at the time of recruitment. All study participants were US residents. Each participant donated 20 ml of peripheral blood and completed a self-administrated questionnaire covering demographic and exposure factors. Race/ethnicity was categorized as non-Hispanic white and other. Ever-smokers were defined as individuals who had smoked more than 100 cigarettes in their lifetime, and ever-drinkers were defined as individuals who had used alcohol at least once a week for more than 1 year. Body mass index was calculated from self-reported height and weight at recruitment and categorized as underweight or normal weight (&lt;25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), overweight (25.0–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), or obese (≥30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) according to the World Health Organization definition.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Genotyping and gene and SNP selection</title><p>Genomic DNA extracted from peripheral blood was used for genotyping. The DNA concentration of each sample was measured by using a NanoDrop spectrophotometer (Thermo-Fisher, Wilmington, DE) and confirmed by using PicoGreen assay (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA). Qualified DNA samples were then genotyped using Illumina HumanCoreExome Beadchips (Illumina, SanDiego CA). The genotyping was performed on the Illumina iScan system at the Sequencing and Microarray Facility at MD Anderson Cancer Center, where the individuals performing the assay were blinded to case-control status.</p><p>After quality-control filtering, in which low-quality SNPs and uncommon variants (minor allele frequency &lt;5%) were removed, the remaining SNPs were annotated by using the UCSC genome browser data retrieval tool and assigned to genes on the basis of a 20-kb window on either side of the gene region defined by the human genome database version 19 [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Lists of genes in the DNA DSB repair pathways were obtained from the NCBI Biosystem database [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Overall, 415 SNPs in 45 genes in DNA DSB repair pathways were annotated and selected for association analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Demographic and exposure variables were compared between cases and controls using the chi-square test. An unconditional logistic regression model was used to derive odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of SGC risk at the SNP level, with adjustment for age, sex, race/ethnicity, obesity status, and radiotherapy history. The additive model of inheritance was employed in all SNP-level association analyses. The threshold of significance level was set at a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of 1.20 × 10<sup>–4</sup>, corresponding to Bonferroni correction for multiple tests (415 SNPs). The analysis of SNP-level association was further stratified by age, sex, race/ethnicity, smoking, alcohol drinking, first-degree family history of cancer, and obesity status to evaluate possible interactions between these variables and selected SNPs. The significance of interactions was evaluated with a likelihood ratio test that compared the fit of the full model with the interaction term versus the main effect model. Histological subtype-specific association analysis was also performed using multivariate multinomial logistic regression model. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value of &lt; 4.0 × 10<sup>–5</sup> was considered significant in the subtype-specific association analysis after Bonferroni correction (415 SNPs and multiple comparisons between subtypes and controls). The statistical analysis was performed using SAS software, version 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC). All statistical tests were two-sided.</p><p>Association analysis at the gene level was performed using the logistic kernel machine (LKM) test [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The logistic kernel machine model integrates a logistic regression model with a semidefinite linear kernel function and takes into account the joint effect of the set of SNPs belonging to the same gene/region to test gene-disease association [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The gene-level association analysis controlled for age, sex, radiotherapy history, smoking, alcohol drinking, family history of cancer, obesity status, and five principal components. The threshold of significance for the logistic kernel machine test was set at 1.11 × 10<sup>–3</sup> (Bonferroni correction of 0.05/45). The statistical analysis was performed using R software, version 3.1.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec006"><title>Results</title><p>Characteristics of the cases and controls are summarized in <xref rid="pone.0128753.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The majority of participants were non-Hispanic white. Cases were significantly more likely than controls to report a history of radiotherapy (2.9% vs. 0.5%), but the vast majority of the participants did not have such a history. Cases were more likely than controls to be obese (36.2% vs. 17.4%) but were less likely than controls to be an ever-drinker (49.9% vs. 57.5%) and to report a first-degree family history of cancer (53.1% vs. 61.7%). The most common histological subtypes were adenoid cystic carcinoma (35.0%), mucoepidermoid carcinoma (21.1%), and adenocarcinoma or salivary duct carcinoma not otherwise specified (14.2%). Histological subtype-specific association analysis was subsequently performed in these subtypes.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128753.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128753.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the study subjects at recruitment.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0128753.t001g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0128753.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Cases (n = 352)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Controls (n = 598)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race/ethnicity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-Hispanic white</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">453</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.949</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.691</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol drinking status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">342</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiotherapy history</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">587</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First-degree family history of cancer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Normal weight or underweight</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overweight</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Obese</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenoid cystic carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mucoepidermoid carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenocarcinoma or salivary duct carcinoma not otherwise specified</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Acinic cell carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The minor allele frequencies and corresponding risk estimates for the top eight SNPs associated with SGC risk are presented in <xref rid="pone.0128753.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Of these top eight SNPs, four were located within the <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic> gene region. Three <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic> SNPs (rs6452524, rs6452526, rs2662242) were in linkage disequilibrium but were independent of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 (r<sup>2</sup>&lt;0.25). Two SNPs were significantly associated with SGC risk after Bonferroni adjustment (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;1.20 × 10<sup>–4</sup>): rs3748522 in <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic> and rs13180356 in <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>; ORs (95% CIs) for the variant alleles of these SNPs were 1.71 (1.40–2.09) and 0.58 (0.45–0.74), respectively.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128753.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128753.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Top SNPs exhibiting significant association with risk of salivary gland carcinoma.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0128753.t002g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0128753.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAF</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNP</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Candidate gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allele</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs3748522</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 (1.40–2.09)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 × 10<sup>−7</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs13180356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.45–0.74)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs6452524</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.17–1.73)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 × 10<sup>–4</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs6452526</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 (1.16–1.70)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31 × 10<sup>–4</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs2662242</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.13–1.67)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 × 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs1859604</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">RPA3</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.58–0.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11 × 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs12334811</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">PRKDC</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&gt;A</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.43–0.81)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 × 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exm810950</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">DCLRE1C</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A&gt;G</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (1.18–2.05)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 × 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>MAF, minor allele frequency.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>
<sup>1</sup>Adjustment for age, sex, race/ethnicity, radiotherapy history, and obesity status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We further performed stratification analyses exploring possible interactions between each of these two SNPs and stratified variables (<xref rid="pone.0128753.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The association of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522 with SGC was stronger among women (OR = 2.00, 95% CI: 1.53–2.62) than among men (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = 0.085). <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 showed significant interaction effects with sex and age; the association with SGC risk was much stronger among women (OR = 0.39, 95% CI: 0.27–0.56) than among men and much stronger among individuals ≤50 years old (OR = 0.40, 95% CI: 0.26–0.61) than among older individuals. The association of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 with SGC risk was also stronger among ever-drinkers, individuals who reported a first-degree family history of cancer, and nonobese individuals; these interactions were marginally significant. The association of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522 with SGC was strongest for the mucoepidermoid carcinoma subtype (OR = 2.21, 95% CI: 1.55–3.15), reaching Bonferroni-adjusted significance; the association of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 with SGC was strongest for the adenoid cystic carcinoma subtype (OR = 0.60, 95% CI: 0.42–0.87).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128753.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128753.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Stratification analysis for associations between the SNPs XRCC4- rs13180356 and RAD52- rs3748522 and risk of salivary gland carcinoma.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0128753.t003g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0128753.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stratification variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95% CI)<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.61–1.24)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 (1.01–1.84)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 (0.27–0.56)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30 × 10<sup>–7</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 (1.53–2.62)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36 × 10<sup>–7</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 (0.26–0.61)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 (1.31–2.41)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 × 10<sup>–4</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.52–0.99)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (1.29–2.23)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 × 10<sup>–4</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race/ethnicity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic white</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.53–0.91)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11× 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 (1.26–2.00)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.64 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.39–0.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 × 10<sup>–4</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 (1.36–2.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.42–0.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (1.23–2.28)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21× 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol drinking status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Never</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.54–1.12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (1.09–1.98)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Ever</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.33–0.67)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 (1.42–2.48)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.24 × 10<sup>–6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First-degree family history of cancer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.49–0.96)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 (1.35–2.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.30–0.65)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 (1.36–2.55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.49 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity status</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.36–0.66)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59 × 10<sup>–6</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 (1.36–2.17)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45 × 10<sup>–6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 (0.58–1.49)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 (1.08–2.45)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenoid cystic carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 (0.42–0.87)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91× 10<sup>–3</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 (1.06–1.87)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mucoepidermoid carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 (0.36–0.92)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21 (1.55–3.15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 × 10<sup>–5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenocarcinoma or salivary duct carcinoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.49–1.41)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (1.04–2.51)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>Adjustment for age, sex, race/ethnicity, radiotherapy history, and obesity status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The gene-level association analysis in non-Hispanic whites (<xref rid="pone.0128753.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) showed that five genes were associated with risk of SGC at crude <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, but only <italic toggle="yes">PRKDC</italic> was marginally significant at Bonferroni-adjusted significance level after adjustment (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0014).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0128753.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128753.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Top DNA double-strand break repair genes associated with salivary gland carcinoma in non-Hispanic whites.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0128753.t004g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0128753.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of SNPs</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">PRKDC</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00048</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">RPA3</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">NHEJ1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">RAD50</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SHFM1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0035</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>Adjustment for age, sex, radiotherapy history, smoking, alcohol drinking, family history of cancer, obesity status, and five principal components.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec007"><title>Discussion</title><p>DNA DSB repair is a complex process that requires multiple proteins, and deficiencies in DSB repair can cause genomic instability and increase sensitivity to IR-induced carcinogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There are two DSB repair pathways, homologous recombination (HR) and nonhomologous end joining (NHEJ) [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. HR requires a template with homologous sequence for accurate repair of the damaged strand, whereas in NHEJ, broken ends of stands are repaired with little or no requirement for sequence homology. The main proteins involved in these two pathways are distinct. In the present study, we investigated the association of SGC risk with DNA DSB repair genes in these two pathways using multiple analyses, from single-SNP association test to SNP-environment interaction test to gene-level association test. We believe that this study is the first to comprehensively evaluate the genetic effect of DNA DSB repair genes on SGC risk.</p><p>The analysis of 415 SNPs in 45 DNA DSB repair genes revealed that two SNPs were significantly associated with SGC risk after Bonferroni correction, which suggests that these SNPs or the variants with which these SNPs are in linkage disequilibrium may have a role in salivary gland carcinogenesis. The variant allele (A) of SNP rs3748522, located in the intronic region of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>, was associated with increased risk of SGC. The protein product of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic> is a core component in the HR pathway and is also essential for single-stranded annealing and mitotic recombination [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The variant allele (A) of SNP rs13180356, located in the intronic region of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>, was associated with decreased risk of SGC. The protein product of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic> is required for NHEJ, acting as a scaffolding protein to facilitate the recruitment of other NHEJ proteins to the break ends [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Interestingly, subgroup analysis showed that the association of <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522 with SGC risk was the strongest in mucoepidermoid carcinoma, whereas the association of <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 with SGC risk was the strongest in adenoid cystic carcinoma. It is well known that mucoepidermoid carcinoma and adenoid cystic carcinoma differ remarkably in histological differentiation, clinical behavior, and mutation profile [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Our finding that histological subtype modified these associations of SNPs with SGC risk supports the observed difference and, if confirmed, could indicate etiological significance.</p><p>We found that <italic toggle="yes">XRCC4</italic>-rs13180356 was associated with SGC risk in women but not men; also, the interaction of this SNP with age was significant. Similarly, the association between <italic toggle="yes">RAD52</italic>-rs3748522 and SGC risk was more evident in women, although the interaction effect was not significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for interaction = 0.085). Results of an early study suggest that men are less sensitive than women to the influence of age-related decline of DNA DSB repair capacity [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. More recent studies have begun to show that many genes and chromosomal regions, on both autosomes and sex chromosomes, exhibit sex-specific differences in gene expression [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and likely contribute differentially to complex diseases [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Accordingly, although evidence linking these significant SNPs with sex is missing, a sex-specific differential association between DSB repair genes and risk of SGC is plausible.</p><p>The gene-level association analysis revealed a borderline significant gene, <italic toggle="yes">PRKDC</italic>. This gene encodes the catalytic subunit of the DNA-dependent protein kinase, which has been implicated in NHEJ, V(D)J recombination, modulation of chromatin structure, and telomere maintenance. Recent findings suggest that DNA-dependent protein kinase is also able to regulate HR and thereby play a critical role in determining which mechanism (HR or NHEJ) is chosen by the cell to repair a DSB [<xref rid="pone.0128753.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0128753.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>This study has both strengths and limitations. We took advantage of the large-scale genotyping data and explored almost all known DSB repair genes. We applied stringent statistical analyses to screen for SNPs and genes associated with SGC risk, with an expected false-positive rate smaller than 5%. However, given that the most significant SNPs were intronic SNPs, it is unlikely that these SNPs are causal SNPs driving the association; future functional studies should be carried out to identify the “real” functional SNPs. Among the limitations of the study is the relatively small sample size, especially for stratification analysis, even though to our knowledge this is the largest study of SGC so far. In addition, limitations inherent in the case-control study design and self-reported questionnaire variables could introduce bias in the association analysis. Bias due to selection of controls from hospital visitors may have occurred given the observation of larger proportion of subjects with family history of cancer in the control group than in the case group. We performed comparison analysis of minor allele frequency between controls with and without family history of cancer and found no significant difference (results not shown), which suggests that selection bias unlikely explains the risk associations.</p><p>In summary, our data indicate that genetic variants in the DSB repair pathways contribute to variation in susceptibility to SGC and show that the impact of genetic variants differs by histological subtype. However, more studies are needed to validate these findings in larger populations and populations with different racial/ethnic backgrounds.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Margaret Lung, Kathryn Patterson, Liliana Mugartegui, Caroline Hussey, and Jenny Vo for help with subject recruitment, Chong Zhao and Yingdong Li for DNA extraction, David P. Pollock for genotyping analysis, and Stephanie P Deming for manuscript editing.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0128753.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howlader</surname><given-names>N NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krapcho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garshell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altekruse</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosary</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatalovich</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>,<name name-style="western"><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (eds). <source>SEER Cancer Statistics Review</source>, <year>1975–2011</year>
<publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Cancer Institute</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horn-Ross</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Environmental factors and the risk of salivary gland cancer</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. Epub 1997/07/01. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/00001648-199707000-00011">00001648-199707000-00011</ext-link></comment> [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9209856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00001648-199707000-00011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muscat</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wynder</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>. <article-title>A case/control study of risk factors for major salivary gland cancer</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. Epub 1998/03/03. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/S0194599898000394">S0194599898000394</ext-link></comment> [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0194-5998(98)80013-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spitz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fueger</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Salivary gland cancer. A case-control investigation of risk factors</article-title>. <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. Epub 1990/10/01. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2206501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archotol.1990.01870100057012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horn-Ross</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Menstrual and reproductive factors for salivary gland cancer risk in women</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. Epub 1999/09/01. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/00001648-199909000-00009">00001648-199909000-00009</ext-link></comment> [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10468426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Salivary gland cancer: an exploratory analysis of dietary factors</article-title>. <source>Nutr Cancer</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. Epub 2008/06/28. 794508663 [pii]<comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01635580802143851">10.1080/01635580802143851</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18584480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/01635580802143851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saku</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahara</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Salivary gland tumors among atomic bomb survivors, 1950–1987</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1465</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. Epub 1997/04/15. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1097-0142(19970415)79:8&lt;1465::AID-CNCR4&gt;3.0.CO;2-A">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0142(19970415)79:8&lt;1465::AID-CNCR4&gt;3.0.CO;2-A</ext-link></comment> [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mabuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ochikubo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cancer incidence in atomic bomb survivors. Part II: Solid tumors, 1958–1987</article-title>. <source>Radiat Res</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>2 Suppl</issue>):<fpage>S17</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. Epub 1994/02/01. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8127952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berean</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Translocation (11;19)(q21;p13.1) in mucoepidermoid carcinoma of salivary gland</article-title>. <source>Cancer genetics and cytogenetics</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7736438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0165-4608(94)00187-g</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Petrovski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinzen</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genic intolerance to functional variation and the interpretation of personal genomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS genetics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e1003709</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1003709">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003709</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3749936.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23990802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3749936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The NCBI BioSystems database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>Database issue</issue>):<fpage>D492</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp858">10.1093/nar/gkp858</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2808896.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkp858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2808896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaub</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Annotation of functional variation in personal genomes using RegulomeDB</article-title>. <source>Genome research</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1790</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gr.137323.112">10.1101/gr.137323.112</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3431494.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.137323.112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3431494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adzhubei</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunyaev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>No evidence that selection has been less effective at removing deleterious mutations in Europeans than in Africans</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>. <year>2015</year>
<comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ng.3186">10.1038/ng.3186</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.3186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4310772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>DNA double-strand breaks: signaling, repair and the cancer connection</article-title>. <source>Nature genetics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/85798">10.1038/85798</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/85798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Symington</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Double-strand break end resection and repair pathway choice</article-title>. <source>Annual review of genetics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132435">10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132435</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21910633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-genet-110410-132435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Homologous DNA recombination in vertebrate cells</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>8388</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.111006398">10.1073/pnas.111006398</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC37448.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.111006398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC37448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mahaney</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lees-Miller</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Repair of ionizing radiation-induced DNA double-strand breaks by non-homologous end-joining</article-title>. <source>The Biochemical journal</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>417</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1042/BJ20080413">10.1042/BJ20080413</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2975036.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19133841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BJ20080413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2975036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caulin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kies</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saintigny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Detailed genome-wide SNP analysis of major salivary carcinomas localizes subtype-specific chromosome sites and oncogenes of potential clinical significance</article-title>. <source>The American journal of pathology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2048</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpath.2013.02.020">10.1016/j.ajpath.2013.02.020</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3668022.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajpath.2013.02.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3668022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adelstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koyfman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Naggar</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biology and management of salivary gland cancers</article-title>. <source>Seminars in radiation oncology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.semradonc.2012.03.009">10.1016/j.semradonc.2012.03.009</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22687949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.semradonc.2012.03.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences in age-related decline in DNA double-strand break damage and repair in lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Annals of human biology</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1952798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03014469100001702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Genome wide analysis of sex difference in gene expression profiles of bone formations using sfx mice and BXD RI strains</article-title>. <source>TheScientificWorldJournal</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>584910</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2014/584910">10.1155/2014/584910</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4123512.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25133246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2014/584910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4123512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schadt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram-Drake</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Tissue-specific expression and regulation of sexually dimorphic genes in mice</article-title>. <source>Genome research</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>995</fpage>–<lpage>1004</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/gr.5217506">10.1101/gr.5217506</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC1524872.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.5217506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1524872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Population-based sample reveals gene-gender interactions in blood pressure in White Americans</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/01.HYP.0000252029.35106.67">10.1161/01.HYP.0000252029.35106.67</ext-link></comment>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17159089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.HYP.0000252029.35106.67</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lees-Miller</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inhibition of homologous recombination by DNA-dependent protein kinase requires kinase activity, is titratable, and is modulated by autophosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Molecular and cellular biology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1719</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/MCB.01298-10">10.1128/MCB.01298-10</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC3126343.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.01298-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3126343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0128753.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Convery</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Inhibition of homologous recombination by variants of the catalytic subunit of the DNA-dependent protein kinase (DNA-PKcs)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1345</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0406466102">10.1073/pnas.0406466102</ext-link></comment>
; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC547837.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0406466102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC547837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>