
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Behav Brain Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Behav. Brain Res.</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8004872</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Behavioural brain research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0166-4328</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1872-7549</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4162858</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4162858.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4162858</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4162858</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS576069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632471</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2014.02.052</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS576069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA576069</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Involvement of Insulin-like Growth Factor-1 in Chemotherapy-related Cognitive Impairment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names initials="TL">Teresita L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names initials="J">Julie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadowska</surname><given-names initials="M">Magdalena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Adult Health, Wayne State University, Detroit, MI 48202</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biobehavioral Health Science, University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago, IL 60612</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author: Teresita L. Briones, Ph.D., Associate Professor, Department of Adult Health, Wayne State University, 5557 Cass Ave., Cohn Bldg, Rm 344, Detroit, MI 48202, Telephone: (313) 577-4143, Fax: (313) 577-4188, <email>tbriones@wayne.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>279</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">242626</issue-id><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>15</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-24 17:25:38.247"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>This file is available for text mining. It may also be used consistent with the principles of fair use under the copyright law.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms576069.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Behav Brain Res" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4756429"><article-title>Retraction notice</article-title><volume>296</volume><date><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><source>Behavioural brain research</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4756429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26754916</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="NIH Guide Grants Contracts (Bethesda)" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4437478"><article-title>Findings of research misconduct.</article-title><date><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><elocation-id>NOT-OD-15-093</elocation-id><source>NIH Guide for Grants and Contracts</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4437478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25898421</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="article-commentary" journal-id="Fed Regist" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5019518"><article-title>Findings of Research Misconduct</article-title><volume>80</volume><issue>66</issue><date><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><fpage seq="a">18638</fpage><lpage>18638</lpage><source>Federal Register</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5019518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27737269</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p id="P1">Here we examined the involvement of insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) on chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment. Sixty-four ovariectomized female Sprague-Dawley rats were included in the study and given cyclophosphamide, methothrexate, and 5-Fluorouracil (CMF) drug combination or saline (control). CMF was given once a week for 4 weeks. In one experiment, behavioral testing using the cued learning and spontaneous object recognition tasks were performed either: at the end of treatment or 4 weeks after treatment. In another experiment, rats from the chemotherapy and saline groups received either: continuous insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) or vehicle delivered subcutaneously via osmotic pump for 21 days (started the week after completion of therapy). Bromodeoxyuridine injections were given for 3 consecutive days starting at 2 weeks after completion of chemotherapy to assess the survival of proliferating cells. Increased levels of IGF-1 and activation of its receptor as well as increased activation of Akt and Erk1/2, its downstream signaling pathways was seen immediately after completion of chemotherapy but decreased 4 weeks after treatment. Behavioral testing showed CMF-induced cognitive impairment after completion of therapy and persisted for 4 weeks. We also found that giving IGF-1 significantly increased activation of its receptor, and the Akt and Erk1/2 pathways, and most importantly attenuated chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment. CMF-induced neuronal apoptosis was also seen and the ratio of surviving cells that proliferate was higher compared to the number of apoptotic cells in the CMF rats given IGF-1. These results suggest that IGF-1 is involved in CMF-induced cognitive impairment by modulating cell death and cell proliferation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Apoptosis</kwd><kwd>rat</kwd><kwd>Akt signaling</kwd><kwd>Erk1/2 signaling</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Women with breast cancer represent the second largest group within the community of cancer survivors [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Survivors of breast cancer increasingly complain of changes in cognitive functioning that range from subtle to a more pronounced symptomatology. The common complaints include deficits in attention and concentration, forgetfulness, difficulty in recalling information, and general lack of “mental sharpness” [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Furthermore, up to 35% of cancer survivors experience persistent cognitive impairment for months or years following treatment [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. These cognitive deficits make it problematic for patients to resume their professional, scholastic, and/or social activities that they engaged in prior to receiving chemotherapy; and in some instances, carrying out activities of daily living becomes a difficult task.</p><p id="P3">Although the existence of chemotherapy-induced cognitive deficits has become almost universally recognized, the wide range of prevalence (16% to 75%) reported in the literature and the inconsistent cognitive symptoms reported [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] make conclusions regarding a link between chemotherapy and cognitive impairment tenuous and underscore the need for further research in this area. There are several issues related to clinical studies on chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment and the most prominent is the common use of cross-sectional rather than prospective or longitudinal design. It is possible that the inferred cognitive deficits from cross-sectional data might be inflated compared to longitudinal data because comparison to a pre-treatment baseline is not possible [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Baseline comparison is important because it makes it possible to distinguish between cognitive impairment resulting from the treatment versus a pre-existing disorder. If the latter is true, then the cognitive impairment might be due to the disease itself rather than the treatment. This critical distinction argues for the utility of an animal model in studying the phenomenon of chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment.</p><p id="P4">Studies using animal models may provide insight into the effects of chemotherapy on cognitive function. For instance, reports show that cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, and 5-Fluorouracil given to rats intraperitoneally, alone or in combination, can cause a disruption in learning and memory across a variety of task such as water maze, avoidance conditioning, object recognition, as well as cue-specific and contextual fear conditioning tasks [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>-<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. But reports involving chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment using animal models are also not consistent. Several mechanisms have been proposed, both direct and indirect, that may underlie the cognitive changes associated with chemotherapy. For example, experimental studies show that methotrexate and cyclophosphamide when administered systemically can disrupt cell division in certain brain regions critical for learning and memory [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Chemotherapy may also induce indirect neurotoxic effects possibly through oxidative stress, vascular damage or immune response dysregulation [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. But to date, the exact mechanisms involved in chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment remain unclear.</p><p id="P5">In this study, we examined the involvement of insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) as a possible mechanism in chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment. IGF-I is an important mediator of neuronal growth, survival and function throughout the lifespan [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. IGF-I has also been proven to be an important modulator of brain activity, including higher functions such as cognition [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Many of the functions of IGF-1 can be ascribed to its tissue-remodeling activity as IGF-I modulates adult neurogenesis and angiogenesis [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. IGF-1 signaling in the brain proceeds mainly through the PI3K (phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase) - Akt (protein kinase B) pathway, which is involved in the regulation of synaptic plasticity and neuronal survival via the maintenance of the bioenergetic and metabolic capacities of mitochondria [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Extracellular signal-regulated kinases 1/2 (erK1/2) are also involved in IGF-1 signaling and reported to mediate a variety of growth and differentiation responses as well as play an essential role in learning and memory [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Thus, we hypothesized that IGF-1 and its receptor activation (phosphorylation) play a role in mediating chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment. We used the combination of cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, and 5-fluorouracil (CMF), an adjuvant chemotherapy used in breast cancer patients [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], to assess whether IGF-1 can regulate the effects of chemotherapy on hippocampal neurogenesis and apoptosis. Here we evaluated drug effects alone to avoid the confounding effects of disease on cognitive function. To evaluate chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment, we examined the hippocampus since this brain region is primarily involved in memory processing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><title>Animal Model</title><p id="P6">Ovariectomized female Sprague-Dawley rats (12-months old) obtained from Harlan Laboratories (Madison, Wisconsin) were housed in pairs in a pathogen-free vivarium under controlled condition (temperature 22 ± 1°C and humidity 70 ± 5%) and a 12:12 hour light:dark cycle was maintained. Twelve-month old female animals were used to closely parallel the clinical population of breast cancer survivors [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Furthermore, ovariectomized rats were used to control for the effects of estrogen on cognitive function. All animals were housed in the same room so that temperature, humidity, and lighting conditions are similar for all groups. Animals had free access to food (regular rat chow) and water delivered through an automated and filtered system. Animals were also handled daily throughout the study so that they could get acclimated to the research personnel thereby decreasing stress. Experiments started one week after arrival of the animals from the breeder and all experimental protocols in this study were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee and in accordance with the National Institutes of Health guidelines. We conducted a series of experiments using different rat groups for a total n=64.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Chemotherapeutic Regimen</title><p id="P7">Rats in the chemotherapy group received the drug combination of cyclophosphamide (40 mg/Kg; Sigma-Aldrich), methotrexate (37.5 mg/Kg; Wyeth Ayerst, Itasca, IL), and 5-fluorouracil (75 mg/Kg; Sigma-Aldrich) dissolved in normal saline. Rats in the control group received normal saline of equal volume to control for the effects of stress induced by the injection. The dosages selected were based on our previous work [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], which showed that animals tolerated these doses with minimal weight loss, fatigue, or death. Both CMF and normal saline injections were given intraperitoneally once a week for a total of 4 weeks and rats were weighed every other day during the chemotherapeutic regimen. Rats were also given DietGel Recovery (clearH<sub>2</sub>O) on the day of chemotherapy injection and 72 hours after to maintain hydration, stimulate appetite, and avoid excessive weight loss. Rats were also weighed and monitored daily for other possible toxicity effects of chemotherapy (n=0) such as apathy, excessive grooming, motor impairment, hair loss, and diarrhea.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Behavioral Testing</title><p id="P8">Rats were tested in two tasks: <italic toggle="yes">water maze cued learning</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">spontaneous object recognition</italic> (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). All testing were done approximately 2 hours prior to the onset of the dark cycle to ensure that it is close to the rats' active period. In the <italic toggle="yes">cued learning task</italic>, the water maze tub was filled with tepid water (22 ± 2°C) and made opaque by the addition of powdered milk. The pool was divided into four quadrants of equal surface area and the starting locations for testing were assigned north, south, east, and west (not actual compass positions but rather relative to the behavioral testing room). The behavioral testing walls were already painted white so just the other distal (to the water maze) visual cues in the rooms were removed during the habituation training and actual testing. Habituation training was conducted the day before actual testing in the cued spatial learning and memory (acquisition and recall) task for the purpose of teaching the rats to swim and locate the platform using the visible cue. Habituation training consisted of allowing the rats to swim to locate a visible goal, which is a 10 cm diameter flower pot positioned in one quadrant halfway between the center and the side of the pool and submerged 2 cm below the surface with a small brass rod attached and vertically protruding 10 cm above the water with a red plastic ball mounted at the top as a visual cue. The day of habituation training, rats received four trials with the goal/platform in a fixed location and fixed starting location (start position is east quadrant and the platform located in the west quadrant). Actual testing was conducted the day after completion of the habituation training, wherein the rats received 3 trials/day for 4 consecutive days and the starting location and visual goal positions were changed randomly for every trial. During the trials, swim latency to reach the platform was recorded by a video camera connected to an image analyzer (EthoVision XT<sup>®</sup> 8.5, Leesburg, VA). In addition, path length was recorded and swimming speed (path length/swim latency) was also measured to assess the motoric activity in performing the behavioral tasks.</p><p id="P9"><italic toggle="yes">Object recognition and temporal order memory</italic> were tested using the Y-maze 2 days after the cued learning task as previously described [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] with some modifications. Rats were habituated to the Y maze without any objects for 1 minute per day for 3 days to reduce anxiety. Tests in the Y maze consisted of: object-in-place and temporal order memory tasks. Briefly, all tests comprised of an acquisition phase (sample phase) and a recognition phase (test phase), separated by a time delay. The maze and objects were wiped with a wet cloth containing sodium hypochlorite solution after each session to eliminate odor cues. Exploratory behavior was defined as the animal directing its nose or sniffing toward the object at a distance of ∼2 cm. Behaviors such as looking around while sitting on or resting against the object were not considered exploratory behavior. The time spent exploring the objects was recorded for 2 minutes.</p><p id="P10">In the <italic toggle="yes">object-in-place task</italic>, the rat's ability to recognize objects it had experienced before that remained in the same location versus those that had changed location was assessed. In the acquisition phase, the rat was exposed to objects 4 different objects placed in the Y maze and the animal was allowed to explore all objects for 2 minutes. After a delay of 60 min, the test phase began in which two of the objects remained in the same position but the other two objects were moved or placed in different locations. Thus, all objects in the test phase were equally familiar, but two were in new locations and the other two remained stationary. The objects moved and the positions of the objects were counterbalanced between rats. If object-in-place memory is intact, the animal should spend more time exploring the two objects that are in different locations compared to the two objects that are in the same locations.</p><p id="P11"><italic toggle="yes">Temporal order memory task</italic> was started 24 hours after completion of the object-in-place test. This task comprised of two sample phases and one test trial. In each sample phase, the animals were allowed to explore two copies of an identical object for a total of 2 min. Different objects were used for sample phases 1 and 2, with a delay between the sample phases of 30 min. The test trial (2 min duration) was given 90 minutes after sample phase 2. During the test trial, a copy of the object from sample phase 1 and a copy of the object from sample phase 2 were used. The positions of the objects in the test and the objects used in sample phases 1 and 2 were counterbalanced between the animals. If temporal order memory is intact, the rats should spend more time exploring the object from sample 1, i.e., the object presented less recently, compared with the object from sample 2, i.e., the new object.</p><p id="P12">In all the tasks, the rats were placed in the Y maze start box and the guillotine door was opened to allow the rat entry into the main area of the apparatus; the door was closed immediately once the rats had vacated the start box to prevent reentry into this area. Timing of the exploration session did not begin until the rat had exited the start box. The Y shape maze with clear walls was used to reduce the spatial and contextual information and test only object recognition abilities of the animals. All sessions (acquisition and testing) were taped and exploration time was calculated after the sessions were completed. The total time exploring each object and the discrimination ratio, which is the difference in time exploring novel and familiar objects divided by the total time were calculated.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>IGF-1 and Bromodeoxyuridine Administration</title><p id="P13">Recombinant rat IGF-1 was obtained from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN) diluted in saline and given at 4 μg/Kg/day as a continuous subcutaneous infusion using the Alzet osmotic mini-pumps (Model 2006, flow rate 1 μl/hr; Durect Co, Cupertino, CA). For the control group, equal volume of saline was loaded into osmotic pumps. Amount of IGF-1 was based on our pilot study and previous report [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Isofluorane was used for anesthetic induction and maintenance during surgical implantation of the pump subcutaneously (above the scapula) for each animal. Topical lidocaine was applied at the incision site after isofluorane induction for pain management. In addition, post-operative acetaminophen (200 mg/kg) was delivered in the drinking water 24 hours after pump implantation.</p><p id="P14">The thymidine analog Bromodeoxyuridine (Chemicon, Temecula, CA) was also given to label proliferating neural progenitor cells. Bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) was dissolved in 0.9% sterile NaCl and filtered at 22 μm. The resulting solution was injected at 75 mg/kg intraperitoneally. BrdU injections were given for 3 consecutive days starting at two weeks after completion of the chemotherapeutic regimen.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Tissue Preparation</title><p id="P15">At the end of the experimental protocol, all rats were euthanized. Euthanasia involved use of CO<sub>2</sub> inhalation followed by decapitation once rats became unresponsive. At the time of sacrifice, hippocampal tissues used for Western blot and ELISA were removed and placed in liquid nitrogen until processed. Brains used for terminal transferase dUTP nick end-labeling (TUNEL) and double labeling immunohistochemistry were placed in a fixative solution (4% paraformaldehyde, pH 7.4) overnight and cryoprotected before sectioning using a cryostat. Tissue sections were obtained at 20μm thickness.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Western Blot</title><p id="P16">Briefly, 0.5 gram of frozen hippocampal tissue from each rat was homogenized in extraction buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, protease inhibitor mixture (Sigma, St. Louis, MO), and 100 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). Following addition of 1% SDS, the homogenates were centrifuged at 10,000 × g for 10 minutes then the supernatants were collected, and the total protein concentration was determined using the BCA-Protein assay (Pierce, Rockford, IL). After determination of protein concentration, the supernatant was mixed with solubilizer containing SDS, glycerine, EDTA, Tris, bromphenol blue, and dithiothreitol, boiled for 5 minutes at 95°C, and stored at -20°C until use.</p><p id="P17">Equal amounts of protein (40 μg) from each rat were loaded and separated by SDS-PAGE gel electrophoresis as previously described [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The nitrocellulose membranes containing the protein bands were stained with 0.5% Ponceau Red to visualize protein loading, then destained and non-specific binding sites were blocked by incubation of the membranes in 5% powdered milk in Tris-buffered saline containing 0.5 ml/L Tween-20. After blocking, membranes were incubated overnight at 4°C with the primary antibody. The primary antibodies used were: (1) IGF-1 receptor (IGF-1R; 1:1000, monoclonal mouse); (2) phosphoIGF-1R (1:1000, monoclonal mouse); (3) Akt (1:1000, monoclonal rabbit); (4) phosphoAkt (1:1000, monoclonal rabbit); (5) Erk1/2 (1:1000, monoclonal rabbit); and (6) phosphoErk1/2 (1:1000, monoclonal mouse). All primary antibodies were obtained from Cell Signaling (Danvers, MA). Immunocomplexes were visualized using horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies (Sigma Aldrich) and chemiluminescence (Pierce). Samples were analyzed in triplicates and measurements were averaged and used as one individual data point for statistical analysis. Quantification was done by densitometric analysis (Scion Image Beta 4.0.2; Frederick MD) using β-actin as an internal control.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)</title><p id="P18">The Quantikine Rat/Mouse IGF-1 Immunoassay kit (R&amp;D Systems) was used to determine IGF-1 protein expression. ELISA was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 96-well plates were precoated with monocolonal antibody specific for IGF-1. Assay diluents were added to each well (50 μL/well). Standards were diluted serially (1:2) and both standards and samples were incubated together for 2 hours at room temperature. The wells were then rinsed in wash buffer 5 times then incubated in polyclonal anti-mouse IGF-1 antibody overnight at 4°C. The plates were washed then incubated with anti-mouse IgG horseradish peroxidase conjugate for 1 hour in the dark at room temperature. Tetramethyl benzidine/peroxidase substrate solution was added to the wells to produce the color reaction. Color reaction was stopped with 1N HCl (100 μl) and reaction was read in a microplate reader (Bio-Tek, Winooski, VT) at a wavelength of 450 nm (650-nm reference wavelength). Protein concentration was determined from the regression line for the IGF-1 standard corrected for the total amount of protein in the sample and assay sensitivity ranged from 1.6-8.4 pg/ml. Assay was performed in triplicates and measurements were averaged and used as one individual data point for statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>TUNEL Assay</title><p id="P19">To visualize apoptosis, TUNEL staining was performed using an In Situ Cell Death Detection Kit<sup>®</sup> (Roche, Indianapolis, IN) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The sections were incubated with proteinase K (100 μg/ml), rinsed, and incubated in 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, permeabilized with 0.5% Triton X-100, rinsed again, and incubated in the TUNEL reaction mixture. The sections were rinsed and visualized using 0.03% 3,3″- diaminobenzidine (DAB). Hematoxylin (DAKO, Carpinteria, CA) was used as a counterstain, and the sections were mounted on gelatin-coated slides. Slides were air-dried overnight at room temperature, and coverslipped using Permount<sup>®</sup>.</p><p id="P20">Quantification of TUNEL staining was done using the stereological Cavalieri-point counting technique [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] with a grid that has a known number of intersections or points (110 intersection) placed randomly over the digital images. The area occupied by TUNEL-positive cells was approximated by the number of intersections that falls upon the stained cells summed over all sampled images (6 images/rat) multiplied by the area of the granular cell layer of the dentate gyrus (where most of the staining were observed). In addition, the disector volume of the granular cell layer (V<sub>dis</sub>) was estimated using the Cavalieri principle in which V<sub>dis</sub> = A<sub>frame</sub> • <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> • <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>, where A<sub>frame</sub> is the unbiased counting frame <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is section thickness (20 μm) and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the number of sections through which the counting was done. To obtain an estimated number of TUNEL-positive nuclei, the point counting results were multiplied by the disector volume.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Double Immunofluorescent Labeling</title><p id="P21">After antigen retrival, sections were incubated with 3% donkey serum in 0.1 M Tris–HCl (pH 7.5) for 30 min followed by 50 μl of TUNEL reaction mixture on each sample for 60 min at 37°C in a moisture chamber for TUNEL and BrdU double labeling. Tissue sections were then washed and incubated with mouse monoclonal anti-BrdU (1:200; Chemicon) for 2 hours at room temperature. The secondary antibodies used were: (1) sheep anti-digoxigenin-fluorescein-coupled, Fab fragments (1:100; Roche, Indianapolis, IN) for TUNEL; or (2) Texas red anti-rabbit IgG (1:200; Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA) for BrdU × 60 min at room temperature.</p><p id="P22">The phenotype of TUNEL-positive cells was also determined using antibodies against NeuN (neuron), glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP; astrocytes), or OX-42 (microglia). After TUNEL staining, the sections were incubated with mouse monoclonal anti-NeuN (1:400, Chemicon), or rabbit polyclonal anti-GFAP (1:1000, Sigma Aldrich), or mouse monoclonal anti-OX-42 (1:100, Chemicon). The secondary antibodies used were: (1) sheep anti-digoxigenin-fluorescein-coupled, Fab fragments (1:100; Roche) for TUNEL; or (2) Texas red anti-rabbit IgG (1:200; Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA) for either NeuN, GFAP, or OX-42 × 60 min at room temperature. After washing, the sections were mounted in gelatin-coated slides using Prolong Anti-Fade medium (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY).</p><p id="P23">Fluorescent signals were imaged with a confocal laser microscope equipped with a krypton/argon mixed-gas laser (Zeiss) using individual collections of wavelengths to minimize artifactual detection of nonspecific fluorescent emission. To assess BrdU-positive nuclei and the ratio of TUNEL and BrdU staining, 6 tissue sections (240 μm apart) from each rat were analyzed using the stereological method of Cavalieri-point counting as described above. Phenotype of TUNEL-positive cells was assessed qualitatively.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P24">Two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to examine effects of experimental condition (CMF versus saline groups), timing of euthanasia (immediately after CMF versus 4 weeks after CMF), and experimental condition and timing of euthanasia interaction. As well, 2-way ANOVA was used to examine effects of experimental condition (CMF versus saline groups), IGF-1 administration (IGF-1 versus vehicle), and experimental condition and IGF-1 administration interaction. When appropriate, the SAS CONTRAST statement was used for post hoc analysis and repeated measures ANOVA was used to analyze behavioral performance. All error bars represent ± standard error of the mean (SEM) of the sample size used in the study.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S13"><title>Results</title><p id="P25">The main goal of the study was to determine the involvement of IGF-1 in chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment. We examined IGF-1 expression and the different pathways activated in IGF-1 receptor (IGF-1R) phosphorylation such as Akt and Erk1/2. The rationale for choosing IGF-1 was based on its role in neuronal processes involving pro-survival and anti-apoptotic activities.</p><sec id="S14"><title>Experiment 1</title><sec id="S15"><title>Chemotherapy-induced Changes in IGF-1 Expression and IGF-1R Activation</title><p id="P26">Initially we examined the effects of CMF on IGF-1 expression and cognitive function and for this purpose, rats were randomly assigned to either CMF or saline therapy. After 4 weeks of therapy, rats from each group were either subjected to behavioral testing (n=7 CMF and n=7 saline) or allowed to recover for another 4 weeks then subjected to behavioral testing (n=7 CMF and n=7 saline). All rats were euthanized after completion of behavioral testing. We examined hippocampal tissues for IGF-1 protein expression using ELISA and the activation of IGF-1R using Western blot. Our results indicated significant main effect of chemotherapy in that changes in IGF-1 levels (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 9.29, p&lt;0.05) and IGF-1R phosphorylation (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 10.05, p &lt;0.05) were seen in the CMF-treated rats when compared to the saline-treated animals (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A and 2B</xref>). However, no significant main effect of time of euthanasia was observed in IGF-1 levels (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.17, p = 0.09) and IGF-1R phosphorylation (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 3.04, p = 0.11). On the other hand, a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and time of euthanasia wherein IGF-1 levels (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 9.04, p&lt;0.05) and phosphorylation of IGF-1R (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 8.03, p&lt;0.05) increased immediately after CMF treatment but both of them significantly decreased 4 weeks after treatment. These data suggest that there is a temporal pattern in the CMF-induced changes in IGF-1 level and phosphorylation of IFG-1R.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Chemotherapy-induced Changes in Akt and Erk1/2 Phosphorylation</title><p id="P27">Since IGF-1 signaling involves activation of downstream pathways, we examined phosphorylation of Akt, a main downstream pathway activated by IGF-1R, using Western blot. We also examined Erk1/2 phosphorylation since it has been reported that this pathway is activated by IGF-1R. No significant group differences were seen in the total levels of Akt (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 3.71, p=0.10) and Erk1/2 (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 2.17, p=0.16). A significant main effect of chemotherapy was seen in the phosphorylation of Akt (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 8.87, p&lt;0.05) where increased levels were seen in the CMF-treated animals compared to the saline-treated group (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>). Though no significant main effect of timing of euthanasia was seen in the phosphorylation of Akt (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 3.24, p=0.10), a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and time of euthanasia in that Akt phosphorylation increased immediately after treatment and then significantly decreased after 4 weeks (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 7.21, p&lt;0.05). A significant main effect of chemotherapy (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 6.19, p &lt;0.05) but no main effect of timing of euthanasia (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.19, p = 0.09) were seen in Erk1/2 phosphorylation. A significant interaction effect was also seen between CMF and time of euthanasia (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 7.51, p &lt;0.05) wherein the CMF-induced increased in Erk1/2 phosphorylation returned to normal levels 4 weeks after therapy (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref>) as shown in the representative Western blots (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2E</xref>). These results suggest that both Akt and Erk1/2 mediate IGF-1 signaling.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Persistence of Chemotherapy-induced Cognitive Impairment</title><p id="P28">Repeated measures ANOVA showed within-subjects effect in both mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 11.01, p&lt;0.05) and path length (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 10.66, p&lt;0.05) in the cued learning and memory task wherein a continuous decreased in the time and path taken to reach the goal were seen over the test days. A significant main effect of chemotherapy was also seen where CMF-treated rats showed increase mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 9.03, p&lt;0.05) and took a longer path to reach the goal compared to the saline-treated group (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A and 3B</xref>). However, no significant main effect of time was seen in both mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 2.22, p=0.12) and mean path length (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 3.22, p=0.11). Furthermore, no significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and time of euthanasia in both mean swim latency and path length. Additionally, no significant group differences were seen when swimming speed was assessed (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.30, p=0.09).</p><p id="P29">A significant main effect of CMF was also seen in the behavioral performance in the object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 10.10, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory tests (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 9.44, p &lt;0.05) where rats that received the chemotherapy showed lower discrimination ratio when compared to the saline-treated group; but no significant main effect of time of euthanasia (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.14, p=0.09) was seen wherein the lower discrimination ratio seen in the CMF group remained evident 4 weeks after completion of CMF treatment (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>). Analysis of exploration times showed significant main effect of CMF in the object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 8.83, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 7.94, p &lt;0.05) tasks. Though significant main effect of timing of euthanasia did not show significance in object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 3.90, p=0.10) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.01, p=0.09) task as seen in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> where animals that received the chemotherapy spent less time exploring in both the object recognition and temporal order memory tasks compared to the saline-treated groups. Moreover, no significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and time of euthanasia in both the object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.21, p=0.09) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.90, p=0.08) tasks wherein the decreased exploration time seen immediately after CMF treatment continued 4 weeks after therapy. Together these results suggest the persistence of CMF-induced cognitive impairment.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Experiment 2</title><sec id="S19"><title>Effects of IGF-1 on Chemotherapy-induced Cognitive Impairment</title><p id="P30">In the next set of experiments we aimed at evaluating the role of IGF-1 on chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment. Rats were randomly assigned to receive either CMF or saline. Animals from each group were further randomized to receive either IGF-1 (n=9 CMF and n=9 saline) or vehicle (n=9 CMF and n=9 saline). Continuous IGF-1 was given subcutaneously for 21 days via an osmotic mini-pump beginning at one week after the end of the CMF or saline regimen. Rats were allowed to recover for 4 weeks after therapy before undergoing behavioral testing; and also the time when IGF-1 signaling is diminished as shown in our data. BrdU was injected 2 weeks after completion of the chemotherapy regimen as seen in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>. Repeated measures ANOVA showed significant with-in subjects effects in both mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 10.37, p &lt;0.05) and mean path length (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.71, p &lt;0.05) wherein time to reach the goal and path taken continuously decreased throughout the test days in all groups. A significant main effect of chemotherapy was also seen in mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.41, p &lt;0.05) and path length (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.88, p &lt;0.05) in the cued learning task (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A and 4B</xref>) where CMF-treated rats took more time and showed greater distance traveled to reach the goal when compared to the saline-treated groups. No significant main effect of IGF-1 administration was seen in both mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.41, p=0.09) and mean path length (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.53, p=0.09). Yet a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and IGF-1 administration in mean swim latency (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.99, p &lt;0.05) and mean path length (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.56, p &lt;0.05) in that CMF-treated animals given the exogenous IGF showed significantly decreased mean swim latency and took the shorter path to reach the goal when compared to the group given vehicle. No significant group differences were seen in swimming speed (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.88, p=0.10).</p><p id="P31">Significant main effect of CMF was seen in exploration times in the object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 7.77, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 8.13, p &lt;0.05) tasks while no significant main effect of IGF-1 administration was seen in the object recognition (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 4.87, p=0.11) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 5.01, p=0.08) tasks as shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. However, an interaction effect between CMF and IGF-1 administration was seen in explorations on the object recognition (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.12, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.07, p &lt;0.05) task where the decreased exploration times induced by CMF was attenuated by IGF-1 administration.</p><p id="P32">Analysis of discrimination ratio showed significant main effect of CMF in the object recognition (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.57, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.21, p &lt;0.05) tasks in that chemotherapytreated rats showed lower object discrimination ratio compared to the saline-treated groups (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C and 4D</xref>). No significant main effect of IGF-1 administration was seen in discrimination ratio on the object recognition (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 5.22, p=0.08) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.81, p=0.09) tasks but a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and IGF-1 administration in both the object recognition (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.50, p &lt;0.05) and temporal order memory (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.94, p &lt;0.05) tasks wherein the decreased discrimination ratio induced by chemotherapy was mitigated by the administration of IGF-1. These results suggest a role for IGF-1 in CMF-induced cognitive impairment.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>IGF-1 Enhances Signaling Through the Akt and Erk1/2 Pathways</title><p id="P33">A significant main effect of CMF on IGF-1R (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.11, p&lt;0.05) and Akt (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.93, p&lt;0.05) phosphorylation was seen but no significant main effect of IGF administration was seen on the phosphorylation of IGF-1R (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 3.21, p = 0.10) and Akt (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.01, p = 0.09). However, we found a significant interaction effect between CMF and IGF-1 wherein the decreased IGF-1R activation (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 10.03, p &lt;0.05) and Akt (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.22, p&lt;0.05) phosphorylation seen in the chemotherapy groups were prevented by the exogenous administration of IGF-1 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A and B</xref>). Examination of Erk1/2 phosphorylation showed a significant main effect of CMF (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.31, p &lt;0.05) but no significant main effect of IGF-1 administration (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 4.69, p = 0.08). A significant interaction effect was also seen between CMF and IGF-1 administration (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 7.72, p &lt;0.05) in that phosphorylation of Erk1/2 in the CMF-treated animals increased after exogenous IGF-1 was given. Together, these results suggest that administration of exogenous IGF-1 was able to augment the CMF-induced downregulation of IGF-1R phosphorylation and activation of its downstream signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>IGF-1 effects on CMF-induced changes in cell proliferation and apoptosis</title><p id="P34">Since BrdU was given ≈2 weeks before euthanasia, we were able to assess the survival of NPCs that proliferate in the dentate gyrus by examining fluorescent-labeled staining and a significant main effect of CMF (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.06, p &lt;0.05) and IGF-1 (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 8.50, p &lt;0.05) were seen wherein chemotherapy resulted in decrease survival of proliferating NPCs but this was mitigated by the administration of IGF-1 (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6A</xref>). An overall increased in the survival of proliferating cells was seen in saline-treated animals given IGF-1. A significant interaction effect was also seen between CMF and IGF-1 in the number of surviving proliferating cells (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.13, p &lt;0.05). Posthoc comparison showed although the number of surviving cells increased in the CMF-treated rats given vehicle, it was still significantly lower when compared to the saline-treated animals. Furthermore, significantly increased BrdU-positive cells were seen in the saline-treated animals given IGF-1.</p><p id="P35">CMF-induced cell death in the dentate gyrus was detected by TUNEL staining and we found significant main effect of CMF (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 10.16, p &lt;0.05) but no significant main effect of IGF-1 (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 3.99, p=0.11) was detected. However, a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and IGF-1 administration (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 9.47, p &lt;0.05) in that chemotherapy induced an increase in apoptosis in the the dentate gyrus but administration of IGF-1 modulated the cell death (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6B</xref>). TUNEL staining in the saline-treated groups was negligible. Significantly increased ratio of TUNEL-positive to BrdU-positive cells in the dentate gyrus (F<sub>(3,32)</sub> = 11.06, p &lt;0.05) was also observed in the CMF-treated rats that received vehicle when compared to the CMF group given IGF-1 (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig.6C</xref>). Use of double-labeling immunohistochemistry showed that cells displaying TUNEL-positive nuclei co-labeled with NeuN demonstrating neuronal identity (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6D</xref>). No TUNEL/GFAP or TUNEL/OX-42 co-labeling was seen. Additionally, a significant interaction effect was seen between CMF and IGF-1 on apoptosis (F<sub>(3,24)</sub> = 10.18, p &lt;0.05). No apoptosis was evident in the saline-treated animals. Together, these results suggested that IGF-1 is involved in regulating the effects of chemotherapy on cell proliferation and cell death.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P36">In the present study we show that CMF therapy results in persistent cognitive impairment and temporal changes in IGF-1 expression, and that IGF-1 is involved in CMF-induced cognitive dysfunction. These findings are supported by our data that: (1) immediately after CMF therapy IGF-1 expression as well as phosphorylation of IGF-1R, Akt, and Erk1/2 increased, but 4 weeks after treatment ended IGF-1 expression, IGF-1R phosphorylation, and Akt levels decreased while Erk1/2 phosphorylation returned back to baseline; (2) cognitive impairment resulting from CMF therapy persisted 4 weeks after the treatment ended; (3) subcutaneous administration of IGF attenuated CMF-induced cognitive impairment and enhanced IGF-1 signaling via the Akt and Erk1/2 pathways, and (4) the effects of IGF-1 in mitigating CMF-induced cognitive impairment may be mediated by modulating apoptosis and enhancing cell proliferation. Ultimately, these findings suggest the intricate involvement of IGF-1 in CMF-induced cognitive impairment and to our knowledge this is the first study to address this area of investigation.</p><p id="P37">IGF-1 is an insulin-like peptide involved in the activation of numerous cell processes underlying neuronal differentiation and growth [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. IGF-1 is a neurotrophic factor expressed by both neurons and glial cells whose actions are mediated by the activation of the two major signaling pathways, PI3/Akt and Erk1/2. Since cognition involves brain plasticity mechanisms and IGF-1 plays a role in brain plasticity processes [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], we examined this neurotrophic factor in the present study for the reason that little is known about its involvement in CMF-induced cognitive impairment. Our data show the temporal pattern of IGF-1 expression and signaling immediately after CMF treatment and later during the recovery period. The upregulation of IGF-1 levels and activation of the Akt and Erk1/2 pathways immediately after CMF therapy suggest a neuroprotective role aimed at maintaining normal brain function following a relatively stressful event, since there is increasing evidence that chemotherapy can induce both direct and indirect neurotoxicity [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The neuroprotective role of IGF-1 is underscored in our results showing that exogenous administration after CMF therapy was able to decrease the number of apoptotic cells and increase the survival of NPCs that proliferate. Conversely, our data that IGF-1R signaling through the Akt pathway significantly decreased 4 week after CMF therapy ended suggest the possibility of decreased endogenous IGF-1 expression most likely resulting from cell loss due to the neurotoxic effects of CMF. Indeed, our results show increased CMF-induced neuronal apoptosis in the dentate gyrus. However, an unexpected finding is that Erk1/2 activation returned back to normal levels 4 weeks after CMF therapy suggesting the possibility that this signaling pathway may also be activated by ligands other than IGF-1.</p><p id="P38">Although our study demonstrate the beneficial effects of IGF-1 in attenuating chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment, this growth factor has been reported to have an opposite effect on tumors. That is, IGF-1 is implicated in tumor growth because of its mitogenic properties [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and reports show that some cancer types can increase IGF-1 expression. Interestingly, even though studies show that increased IGF-1 expression is seen in cancer patients (reviewed in [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]), there are still reports on the incidence of chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment and this phenomenon is difficult to explain. To fully understand the intricate involvement of IGF-1 in cancer and chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment, it role should be examined in the context of other growth factors such as brainderived neurotrophic factor and other cytokines because of their shared signaling pathways.</p><p id="P39">An expected finding in the present study is the cognitive impairment seen immediately after therapy. It is possible that the poor behavioral performance of the CMF-treated rats after chemotherapy compared to the saline-treated group may be due to motor deficits induced by the cytotoxic drugs. However, it is highly unlikely for two reasons: 1) no significant difference was seen in swim speed between the CMF- and saline-treated animals, and 2) the path taken to reach the goal on the first day of testing in the cued learning task is similar between the CMF- and saline-treated groups. Our behavioral testing results of persistent cognitive impairment parallel those of others that demonstrate deficits in rats and mice following administration of either methotrexate alone, cyclophosphamide alone, or the combination of methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, our data are also at odds with others that showed no evidence of impaired cognitive performance in rats given cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, or 5-fluorouracil administration [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The discrepancy in findings between our study and those of others may be attributed to the type of testing procedure used and timing of behavioral testing; namely behavioral testing in our study used the cued learning task whereas others used contextual fear conditioning, and while others conducted behavioral testing more than a month after the last treatment we tested the rats two weeks after the last CMF injection in our study. It is possible that testing for cognitive impairment long after treatment ended may reflect some degree of recovery in cognitive function. It is also possible that the behavioral test used by others may be measuring different domains of cognition that may be intractable to chemotherapy. This line of reasoning is supported by clinical reports that cognitive dysfunction related to chemotherapy only affect certain cognitive domains (reviewed in [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]).</p><p id="P40">Our data on the lack of exogenous IGF-1 effect on the behavioral and biological measures in the saline-treated animals is perplexing. Though it is possible that a threshold exist in IGF-1R phosphorylation and the subsequent activation of its downstream signaling pathways. Specifically, if endogenous IGF-1 expression is sufficient to saturate receptor binding then exogenous administration of the peptide will not have any additive effect. But surprisingly, administration of IGF-1 in the saline-treated rats resulted in increased survival of proliferating cells in the dentate gyrus, which is hard to explain. Since a considerable proportion of all newly generated cells in the hippocampus will die before becoming fully differentiated [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], both under normal and pathological circumstances, the significant increased in BrdU-positive cells seen in the saline-treated rats given IGF-1 does not necessarily mean increased in cell proliferation but most likely suggest the ‘rescuing’ of the NPCs that proliferate.</p><p id="P41">In sum, our study shows that IGF-1 play an important role in CMF-induced cognitive impairment. The involvement of IGF-1 effects in improving the cognitive side effects of CMF therapy may be mediated by its pro-survival properties through the modulation of apoptosis. Because CMF-induced cognitive impairment was not completely abolished by subcutaneous administration of IGF-1 in our study, it also raises the question on whether the nature of the intrinsic activation of IGF-1 signaling resulting from CMF therapy may be different from the one activated by exogenous administration of the peptide. Future studies on the role of IGF-1 in CMF-induced cognitive impairment can address this issue.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="S23"><p>We are also grateful for the assistance of Maria Palu in tissue imaging. We would also like to thank Melanie Cortez and Marilyn Cruz for technical assistance in tissue processing. This work was supported in part by the National Institutes of Health, NINR grant # RO1 NR007666 (to TLB) and the Wayne State University Katharine Faville Endowment Funds (TLB).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold>: The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p content-type="publisher-disclaimer">This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer Statistics, 2007</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2007</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/canjclin.57.1.43</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahles</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saykin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer chemotherapy-related cognitive dysfunction</article-title><source>Clin Breast Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>S84</fpage><lpage>S90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12533268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3816/cbc.2002.s.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson-Hanley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agocha</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compas</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychological effects of treatments for adults with cancer: a meta-analysis and review of the literature</article-title><source>J Int Neuropsychol Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14738279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S1355617703970019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janelsins</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roscoe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palesh</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustian</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peppone</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckler</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognitive difficulties, fatigue, and sleep in cancer patients at pre-chemotherapy, post-chemotherapy, and at three months follow-up</article-title><source>Ann Behav Med</source><year>2010</year><fpage>39</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janelsins</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohile</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahles</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An update on cancer- and chemotherapy-related cognitive dysfunction: current status</article-title><source>Semin Oncol</source><year>2011</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21600374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2011.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3120018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quesnel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive impairments associated with breast cancer treatmenst; results from a longitudinal study</article-title><source>Breast Cancer res Treat</source><year>2009</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18629633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10549-008-0114-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherwath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehnert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schleimer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schirmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fehlauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreienberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuropsychological function in high-risk breast cancer survivors after stem-cell supoorted high-dose therapy versus standard-dose chemotherapy: evaluation of long-term treatment effects</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16357023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdj108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrykowski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive functioning after adjuvant chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy for early stage breast carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>2499</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.21482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2653200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sereika</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berga</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brufsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paraska</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive impairment associated with adjuvant therapy in breast cancer</article-title><source>Psychooncology</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16097037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pon.964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Awalker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5-Fluorouracil chemotherapy affects spatial working memory and newborn neurons in the adult rat hippocampus</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18702703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2008.06325.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seigers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schagen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boogerd</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Tellingen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-lasting suppression of hippocampal cell proliferation and impaired cognitive performance by methothrexate in the rat</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17854921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbr.2007.08.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deleo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahles</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saykin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucci</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer chemotherapy impairs contextual but not cue-specific fear memory</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17509697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbr.2007.04.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4012416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiriz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reolon</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pressler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosado</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>JAP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer chemotherapy and cognitive function in rodent models: memory impairment induced by cyclophosphamide in mice</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>5000</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-0138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winocur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannock</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of the anti-cancer drugs, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil, on cognitive function in mice</article-title><source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source><year>2006</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16935324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pbb.2006.07.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy-induced cognitive impairment is associated with decreases in cell proliferation and histone modifications</article-title><source>BMC Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>124</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22152030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2202-12-124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3252305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seigers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pourtau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schagen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koolhaas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konsman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of hippocampal cell proliferation by methotrexate in rats is not potentiated by the presence of a tumor</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>2010</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.brainresbull.2009.10.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogozinska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of ischemia-induced NMDAR1 activation by environmental enrichment decreases oxidative damage</article-title><source>J Neurotrauma</source><year>2011</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2485</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/neu.2011.1842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3235341</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4775871"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4437478"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="statement-of-misconduct" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5019518"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahles</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saykin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candidate mechanisms for chemotherapy-induced cognitive changes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc2073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3329763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17318212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Aleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward a comprehensive neurobiology of IGF-1</article-title><source>Dev Neurobiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20186710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/dneu.20778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Aleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating insulin-like growth factor I and cognitive function: neuromodulation throughout the lifespan</article-title><source>Prog Neurobiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19665513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2009.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Kusky</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Ercole</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type 1 insulin-like growth factor receptor signaling is essential for the development of the hippocampal formation and dentate gyrus</article-title><source>J Neurosci Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>2821</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19437543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jnr.22129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao-Kun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongpaisan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin, PKC signaling pathways and synaptic remodeling during memory storage and neuronal repair</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2008</year><volume>585</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18402935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejphar.2008.01.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer - 30 years later</article-title><source>NEJM</source><year>2006</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>1920</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17079767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMe068204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams-Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of cancer in the United States</article-title><source>Semin Oncol Nurs</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16293511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.soncn.2005.06.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing rat's to human age: how old is my rat in people years?</article-title><source>Nutrition</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15925305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nut.2005.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation in myelination mediated by persistent neuroinflammation: possible mechanisms in chemotherapy-related cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2013.07.175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23916895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darwish</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin D mitigates age-related cognitive decline through the modulation of pro-inflammatory state and decrease in amyloid burden</article-title><source>J Neuroinflammation</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23098125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1742-2094-9-244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3520725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubovitch</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarfstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intricate involvement of the insulin-like growth factor receptor signaling in mild traumatic brain injury in mice</article-title><source>Neurobiol Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nbd.2010.01.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gundersen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendtsen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korbo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcussen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The new stereological tools: disector, fractionator, nucleator and point sampled intercepts and their use in pathological research and diagnosis</article-title><source>Acta Pathol Microbiol Immunol Scand</source><year>1988</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1699-0463.1988.tb00954.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3056461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stereological methods for estimating the total number of neurons and synapses: issues of precision and bias</article-title><source>Trends in Neuroscience</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0166-2236(98)01362-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Aleman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The many faces of insulin-like peptide signaling in the brain</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22430016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrn3209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakane</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sezaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transnasal delivery of 5-fluorouracil to the brain in the rat</article-title><source>J Drug Target</source><year>1999</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10680979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/10611869909085506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruchim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attias</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting the IGF-1 axis in cancer proliferation</article-title><source>Expert Opin Ther Targets</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19663648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1517/14728220903201702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seigers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schagen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coppens</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Most</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koolhaas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Methotrexate decreases hippocampal cell proliferation and induces memory deficits in rats</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbr.2009.02.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rifkind</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Raman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamczarz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transient improvement in cognitive function and synaptic plasticity in rats following cancer chemotherapy</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16397043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-05-1286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fremouw</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fessler</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burguete</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preserved learning and memory in mice following chemotherapy: 5-Fluorouracil and doxorubicin single agent treatment, doxorubicin-cyclophosphamide combination treatment</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21930159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbr.2011.09.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dayer</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleaver</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term and long-term survival of new neurons in the rats dentate gyrus</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2003</year><volume>460</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12717714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cne.10675</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study Timeline</title><p>Depicts the timeline of the study in experiment 2.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>IGF-1 Signaling</title><p>Levels of IGF-1 (A), pIGF-1R (B), pAkt (C), and pErk1/2 (D) significantly increased immediately after CMF therapy compared to the saline group. However, significant decreased in IGF-1, pIGF-1R, and pAkt levels were seen 4 weeks after the CMF therapy ended in relation to the saline-treated animals while pErk1/2 returned to baseline level. No significant differences were seen in the saline treated animals. Legend: – = negative control lane using phosphate-buffered saline only; + = positive control lane using lysate only; p = phosphorylated. *p &lt;0.05, **p &lt;0.01 compared to the saline groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Behavioral Testing (experiment 1)</title><p>CMF treatment resulted in longer mean swim latency (A) and path taken to reach the goal (B) in the cued learning task; as well, impairment in the spontaneous object recognition (B), and temporal order memory (C) tasks is evident in the and decreased discrimination ratio. The CMF-induced cognitive impairment persisted 4 weeks after completion of the chemotherapy regimen. No significant difference was seen in the performance of the saline-treated animals in both behavioral tests. *p &lt;0.05 – significantly different from the saline groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Behavioral Testing (experiment 2)</title><p>Rats that received chemotherapy showed longer mean swim latency (A) and path taken to reach the goal in the cued learning task. Also, impairment in the object recognition (C) temporal order memory (C) tasks was seen in the CMF rats compared to the saline-treated animals. However, administering exogenous IGF-1 after CMF therapy attenuated the CMF-induced cognitive deficit. No significant difference was seen in the performance of the saline groups whether they received exogenous IGF-1 or vehicle. *p &lt;0.05, **p &lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f4.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Effects of Exogenous IGF-1 on Receptor Signaling</title><p>Level of phosphorylated IGF-1R (A) and phosphorylated Akt (B) were significantly decreased in CMF-treated rats but administration of exogenous IGF-1 upregulated IGF-1R and Akt activation to levels similar to the saline-treated animals. Conversely, level of phosphorylated Erk1/2 significant increased in the CMF rats given IGF-1 compared to all groups (C). No significant group differences were seen in the levels of total Akt and total Erk1/2. In addition, no significant differences were seen in Akt and Erk1/2 phosphorylation in the saline-treated animals. Representative Western blots are also shown (D). Legend: – = negative control lane using phosphate-buffered saline only; + = positive control lane using lysate only; p = phosphorylated; S/V = saline-treated given vehicle; S/I = saline-treated given IGF-1; C/V = CMF-treated given vehicle; C/I = CMF-treated given IGF-1. *p &lt;0.05, **p &lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>BrdU and TUNEL</title><p>Survival of proliferating NPCs was significantly decreased in the CMF-treated animals compared to the saline-treated animals but administration of exogenous IGF-1 attenuated the effects of chemotherapy (A). Significant increased in TUNEL staining was seen in the CMF rats but giving exogenous IGF-1 after the chemotherapy significantly attenuated the number of apoptotic cells (B). Representative photomicrographs of TUNEL staining in the dentate gyrus (upper panel B). Scale bar = 100 μm. Values for the saline-treated rats were omitted in the bar graph since TUNEL staining is negligible in this groups. The ratio of the number of apoptotic cells to proliferating cell survival also decreased in the CMF group that received exogenous IGF-1 (C). Representative photomicrographs of TUNEL (arrows) and BrdU (arrowhead) double-labeling are shown (upper panel C). The phenotype of apoptosis cells was mainly neuronal as seen in the representative micrograph (D). *p &lt;0.05, **p &lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms576069f6.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Exploration Time in the Spontaneous Object Recognition Tasks (Experiment 1)</title></caption><table frame="void" rules="none"><thead><tr><th valign="top" rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Object-in-place</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temporal Order Memory</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<hr/></th><th colspan="1" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Phase (s)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Phase (s)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline/Immediately after</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1 ± 4.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3 ± 3.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline/4 weeks after</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1 ± 3.66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.5 ± 4.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMF/Immediately after</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3 ± 3.33<xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9 ± 3.88<xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMF/4 weeks after</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 ± 3.82<xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7 ± 3.76<xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p>Mean exploration time expressed in seconds(s) during the test phase in the object-in-place and temporal order memory tests. Significant differences were seen in exploration times during the object-in-place tests and temporal order memory tasks. Significantly decreased exploration time in the object-in-place and temporal order memory tests after a time delay was seen after CMF-treatment and this impairment persistent for 4 weeks after the therapy ended.</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>*</label><p>p &lt;0.05 (significantly from the saline-treated groups)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Exploration Time in the Spontaneous Object Recognition Tasks (Experiment 2)</title></caption><table frame="void" rules="none"><thead><tr><th valign="top" rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Object-in-place</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temporal Order Memory</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<hr/></th><th colspan="1" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">
<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Phase (s)</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Phase (s)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline/Vehicle</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1 ± 3.47</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3 ± 2.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline/IGF-1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4 ± 3.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2 ± 1.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMF/Vehicle</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 ± 4.34<xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">*a</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 ± 2.43<xref rid="TFN4" ref-type="table-fn">*a</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMF/IGF-1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9 ± 4.40<xref rid="TFN5" ref-type="table-fn">*b</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4 ± 2.16<xref rid="TFN5" ref-type="table-fn">*b</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN3"><p>Mean exploration time expressed in seconds(s) during the test phase in the object-in-place and temporal order memory tests. Significant differences were seen in exploration times during the object-in-place tests and temporal order memory tasks. CMF-treated rats showed significantly decreased exploration time in the object-in-place and temporal order memory tests after a time delay compared to the saline-treated groups but administration of IGF-1 mitigated the effects of chemotherapy.</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><label>*a</label><p>p &lt;0.05 (significantly different from the saline-treated groups).</p></fn><fn id="TFN5"><label>*b</label><p>p &lt;0.05 (significantly different from the CMF/Vehicle group).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlights</title></caption><list list-type="simple" id="L1"><list-item><p>Cognitive impairment resulting from CMF therapy persisted 4 weeks after the treatment ended</p></list-item><list-item><p>Administration of IGF-1 attenuated CMF-induced cognitive impairment</p></list-item><list-item><p>IGF-1 modulated CMF-induced apoptosis and enhances cell proliferation</p></list-item></list></boxed-text></floats-group></article>