
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">EMBO Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">EMBO Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">emmolmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101487380</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">emmm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>EMBO Molecular Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1757-4676</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1757-4684</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4551341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4551341.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4551341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4551341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/emmm.201505088</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> responds to glucocorticoids used in asthma therapy by modulation of biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Earl</surname><given-names initials="CS">Chris S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keong</surname><given-names initials="TW">Teh Wooi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names initials="SQ">Shi-qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names initials="S">Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yvonne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garmendia</surname><given-names initials="J">Junkal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names initials="J">Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dow</surname><given-names initials="JM">J Maxwell</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="L">Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Toole</surname><given-names initials="GA">George A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names initials="RP">Robert P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Division of Molecular Microbiology, College of Life Sciences, University of Dundee</institution><addr-line>Dundee, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Singapore Centre on Environmental Life Sciences Engineering, Nanyang Technological University</institution><addr-line>Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>School of Microbiology, Biosciences Institute, University College Cork</institution><addr-line>Cork, Ireland</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Instituto de Agrobiotecnología, CSIC-Universidad Pública Navarra-Gobierno Navarra</institution><addr-line>Mutilva, Spain</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red de Enfermedades Respiratorias (CIBERES)</institution><addr-line>Madrid, Spain</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>Division of Molecular Medicine, College of Life Sciences, University of Dundee</institution><addr-line>Dundee, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au7"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Geisel School of Medicine at Dartmouth</institution><addr-line>Hanover, NH, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
* Corresponding author. Tel: +44 1382 384272; E-mail: <email>rpryan@dundee.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn><p><bold>Subject Categories</bold> Microbiology, Virology &amp; Host Pathogen Interaction; Pharmacology &amp; Drug Discovery; Respiratory System</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">257092</issue-id><fpage>1018</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-10 14:25:16.620"><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 The Authors. Published under the terms of the CC BY 4.0 license</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="companion" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="research-article" vol="7" page="992" journal-id="EMBO Mol Med" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4551337"><article-title>Glucocorticoids and antibiotics, how do they get together?</article-title><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><date><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><source>EMBO Molecular Medicine</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4551337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26077592</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="EMBO Mol Med" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC5887906"><article-title>Retraction: “<italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> responds to glucocorticoids used in asthma therapy by modulation of biofilm formation and antibiotic resistance”</article-title><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><date><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><elocation-id>e70001</elocation-id><source>EMBO Molecular Medicine</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5887906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29531022</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Glucocorticosteroids are used as a main treatment to reduce airway inflammation in people with asthma who suffer from neutrophilic airway inflammation, a condition frequently associated with <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> colonization. Here we show that glucocorticosteroids have a direct influence on the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> that may account for associated difficulties with therapy. Using a mouse model of infection, we show that corticosteroid treatment promotes <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence. Transcriptomic analysis of bacteria either isolated from infected mouse airway or grown in laboratory medium identified a number of genes encoding regulatory factors whose expression responded to the presence of glucocorticosteroids. Importantly, a number of these corticosteroid-responsive genes also showed elevated expression in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> within sputum from asthma patients undergoing steroid treatment. Addition of corticosteroid to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> led to alteration in biofilm formation and enhanced resistance to azithromycin, and promoted azithromycin resistance in an animal model of respiratory infection. Taken together, these data strongly suggest that <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> can respond directly to corticosteroid treatment in the airway potentially influencing biofilm formation, persistence and the efficacy of antibiotic treatment.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antibiotic resistance</kwd><kwd>asthma</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic></kwd><kwd>steroids</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>See also: <bold>J Reidl &amp; E Monsó</bold> (August 2015)</p><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Asthma is a chronic inflammatory condition of the airways, frequently distinguished by abnormal immune responses to environmental antigens and microbes, which leads to recurrent episodes of cough, wheezing and breathlessness (Wenzel, <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). An estimated 300 million people worldwide suffer from asthma. Up to 30% of these patients suffer from neutrophilic asthma, which is characterized by substantial increases in airway neutrophils. Chronic colonization by bacteria is evident in the airways of patients with neutrophilic asthma, with <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> being the species most frequently isolated.</p><p>Inhaled glucocorticosteroids, through their potent anti-inflammatory action, are the foundation of asthma therapy (Ito <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). However, in a very high proportion of cases, neutrophilic asthmatics respond poorly to glucocorticosteroid treatment (Essilfie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Chronic bacterial infection has been associated with steroid-resistant neutrophilic asthma, although the mechanisms producing treatment resistance in such infections are poorly understood (Beigelman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus</italic> spp.<italic toggle="yes">, Streptococcus</italic> spp. or <italic toggle="yes">Moraxella catarrhalis</italic> in the neutrophilic asthmatic airway has been positively correlated with sputum neutrophilia and lower FEV<sub>1</sub>. The presence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in particular has been associated with the activation of airway inflammation pathways in those asthmatics with relative steroid resistance (Green <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection has been shown to contribute in part to allergic airways disease through alterations in IL-17 (Simpson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Berry <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Furthermore, a strong relationship between chronic <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection and the development of steroid-resistant neutrophilic asthma has been suggested using murine models of ovalbumin (OVA)-induced allergic airway disease (Essilfie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In this model, the combination of infection and allergic airways disease promotes bacterial persistence leading to the development of a phenotype similar to steroid-resistant neutrophilic asthma. These findings indicate that targeting bacterial infection in steroid-resistant asthma may have a therapeutic benefit.</p><p>One aspect of the pathogenesis and therapy of neutrophilic asthma that has not received consideration is the potential direct influence of glucocorticosteroids on the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>. There are no reports of a direct antibacterial action of glucocorticosteroids; nevertheless, an impact on bacterial functions that promote persistence and tolerance to antibiotics might impinge on the efficacy of therapy. In this context, it is noteworthy that the severity of asthma appears to be increased in patients with bacterial infections who have received prolonged therapy with glucocorticosteroids.</p><p>Here we have examined the impact of glucocorticosteroid treatment on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> during respiratory infection and neutrophilic asthma, as well as investigating impacts of this therapeutic <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biology. Using a mouse model of acute infection, we show that the presence of glucocorticosteroids promotes <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence without influencing the host inflammatory response. Comparative transcriptional analysis of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> grown under standard laboratory conditions in the absence and presence of beclomethasone revealed that this glucocorticosteroid induces altered expression of genes implicated in biofilm formation and host colonization. Furthermore, the majority of these genes showed similar alterations in expression when transcriptomes of bacteria grown in medium without glucocorticosteroid were compared with those of bacteria isolated from the airway of infected mice. Importantly, many of the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes with expression that was responsive to corticosteroid <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> also had altered expression in bacteria within sputum samples from asthma patients undertaking inhaled steroid treatment. In parallel, we examined the influence of glucocorticosteroids on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> behavior by addressing the effects on biofilm formation and resistance to azithromycin, a frontline drug prescribed to asthma patients. Addition of glucocorticosteroids changed the architecture and increased the tolerance to azithromycin of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms developed in flow cells. Finally, we developed a mutant screen that allowed the identification of a potential role for the RpoE-MclA sigma factor–anti-sigma factor system (HI0628–HI0629) as a mediator of this glucocorticosteroid response. Taken together, these findings indicate that <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> can respond directly to glucocorticosteroid treatment in the lung where it may influence biofilm formation, persistence and the efficacy of antibiotic therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Glucocorticosteroids promote <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence in a mouse model</title><p>Mouse models of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> have been rarely reported since it is difficult for this bacterium to infect mice (Vallee <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Wu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Here, we pursued a new mouse model of lung infection in order to determine whether glucocorticosteroids have the ability to modulate <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection. We used 4-week-old C57BL/6 mice to assess the effects of supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> with beclomethasone, a model glucocorticosteroid used widely in the clinic (van den Berge <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), on the bacterial load in the lung. Generally, young immature mice are more susceptible to bacterial infection than fully grown mice. In addition, the mice were pretreated intraperitoneally with cyclophosphamide to induce granulocytopenia. When cyclophosphamide-pretreated mice were intranasally inoculated with 1 × 10<sup>9</sup> CFU of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>, the bacteria resided in the lungs of the mice at more than 10<sup>5</sup> CFU for up to 3–4 days post-inoculation.</p><p>Next, the cyclophosphamide-treated C57BL/6 mice were infected with <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> and treated by inhaling PBS with or without 50 μM beclomethasone, a clinically relevant dose based on the weight of the mice used (Daley-Yates <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The lung and spleen bacterial load was determined at 1, 3, 5 or 7 days post-infection. C57BL/6 mice infected with <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> with PBS cleared almost all bacteria from the lungs within 5 days (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1A</xref>). However, with the addition of beclomethasone, bacteria were still present in substantial numbers at 7 days (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1A</xref>), with ∼1,000-fold more bacteria present in the beclomethasone-treated mice versus control. Similar patterns were seen in the bacterial loads in the spleen, where after 7 days the numbers of bacteria in beclomethasone-treated mice were significantly higher (∼1.5 log higher) than in untreated mice (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1B</xref>). To extend this study, we also examined the influence of mometasone and prednisolone, two other glucocorticosteroids in clinical use, on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> survival in the cyclophosphamide-mouse model. Treatment with prednisolone (50 μM) gave a similar increased persistence phenotype as was observed for beclomethasone treatment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Supplementary Fig S1</xref>). Mometasone (50 μM) also appeared to promote <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence, although its influence was considerably less than the other two steroids tested.</p><fig id="fig01" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Administration of corticosteroids promotes the persistence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in mice</p><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
A–D C57BL/6 mice were infected with <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in PBS with or without supplementation with beclomethasone. Animals were killed at 1, 3, 5 and 7 days after infection, and 10-fold serial dilutions of the lung homogenates (A) and spleen homogenates (B) were plated to determine the bacterial load. Airway inflammation represented by total and differential cell counts in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF). The number of total leukocytes and in particular of neutrophils, monocytes and lymphocytes recruited in the airways was analyzed in BALF after day 3 (C) and day 7 (D) of infection.
</p></list-item></list></p><p>Data information: Values represent the mean ± standard deviation (SD). The data are pooled from three independent experiments. Statistical significance by two-tailed Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test is indicated: *<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f1.jpg"/></fig><p>The effects of beclomethasone on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence were also examined in C57BL/6 mice that did not receive the cyclophosphamide treatment. The same trend was observed where beclomethasone treatment enhanced <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence in the airway, although in this case, no dissemination to the spleen was seen (Supplementary Fig S2). Taken together, these data indicate that treatment with beclomethasone enhanced <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence in the airway and systemically in this model of infection.</p><p>Numerous previous studies have demonstrated <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection of the murine airway induces the recruitment of leukocytes and other inflammation markers, which mirrors in part what is seen in a clinical setting (Hansen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>; Essilfie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In the current study, the inflammatory response of challenged mice was examined in terms of total leukocyte recruitment in the airways (see Materials and Methods). In the first set of experiments, mice were pre-treated with cyclophosphamide. At 3 days post-infection, the cell numbers that influx into the airways (including neutrophils, lymphocyte and eosinophils) were similar in beclomethasone-treated mice and mice that were treated with PBS only (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1C</xref>). By 7 days post-infection, however, neutrophil numbers in the mice treated with beclomethasone remained at the level seen at 3 days and were significantly higher than those seen in PBS alone (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1D</xref>). In contrast, overall lymphocyte numbers were similar in mice treated with beclomethasone compared with mice treated with PBS alone (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1D</xref>). The effects of beclomethasone on the inflammatory response induced by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in C57BL/6 mice that did not receive the cyclophosphamide treatment were also examined. In this case, more neutrophils were recruited on day 3 as with the cyclophosphamide-treated mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Supplementary Fig S2</xref>), but this elevation returned to normal levels by day 4.</p><p>The observed continued recruitment of neutrophils at day 7 in the cyclophosphamide-mouse model of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection was unexpected. However, this observation is not unprecedented in the clinical setting; examination of neutrophilic asthma patients showed neutrophil numbers increase in those patients undergoing inhaled corticosteroid treatment (see Simpson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Overall, our results suggest that the presence of beclomethasone increases the capacity of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to persist in mice but these findings do not establish whether this is a direct effect of the glucocorticosteroid on the bacteria or whether this is an indirect effect, mediated through an influence on the host, including recruitment of immune cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Glucocorticosteroids induce specific changes in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> gene expression in culture</title><p>As an approach to understanding the possible direct influence of glucocorticosteroids on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>, we examined the impact of beclomethasone on gene expression of bacteria using high-throughput cDNA sequencing techniques. For these experiments, bacteria were grown in complex sBHI medium, which is brain–heart infusion medium supplemented with hemin and NAD (see Materials and Methods). RNA was derived from bacteria grown in the presence and absence of beclomethasone (50 μM) and, following rRNA depletion, the remaining RNA was fragmented, reverse-transcribed into cDNA and sequenced using the Illumina platform. Between 20 and 30 million reads were derived from each sample, which were aligned to non-rRNA sequences in the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genome, comprising the 1,788 annotated ORFs (Supplementary Table S1). The correlation of technical replicates was very high, suggesting that variations introduced during library construction and sequencing do not significantly contribute to differences in gene expression between samples. A total of 61 genes were significantly differentially expressed by at least threefold (P<sub>adj</sub> &lt; 1 × 10<sup>−5</sup>) during growth of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in sBHI in the presence or absence of beclomethasone (see Materials and Methods). Of the 61 genes regulated by beclomethasone, 29 genes were up-regulated and 32 genes were down-regulated (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd12">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig02" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes differentially regulated during growth in complex media and during lung infection in the presence of corticosteroids</p><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
A Venn diagram showing the overlap of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes whose expression is up-regulated or down-regulated by the presence of corticosteroids in sBHI medium (<italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>) or in the mouse model of infection (<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>). Genes that are divergently regulated in these conditions are not depicted in this Venn diagram but can be found in the complete RNA-Seq dataset detailed in Supplementary Table S2.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
B COG map detailing significantly enriched or scarce functional categories expressed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> during the presence of corticosteroids.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
C, D Comparison of relative fold changes between RNA-seq and qRT–PCR results <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (C) and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (D) in the presence of corticosteroids. All qRT–PCR results were normalized using the <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>s obtained for the 16S rRNA amplifications run in the same plate. The relative levels of gene transcripts are determined from standard curves. Values given are the mean and standard deviation of triplicate measurements (three biological and three technical replicates).
</p></list-item></list></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f2.jpg"/></fig><p>Those genes whose expression was increased by beclomethasone treatment included those with protein products involved in adaptive responses such as iron uptake (HI0994), biofilm formation (HI1344), stress response (HI0628) and antimicrobial resistance (HI1275) as well as the <italic toggle="yes">yfe</italic> operon (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359–HI0362</italic>), which encodes an ABC transporter putatively involved in metal ion uptake and previously implicated in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> virulence regulation, adherence to host cells and host immune evasion (Whitby <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Jalalvand <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Su <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>The effect of beclomethasone on the level of transcript was validated by quantitative reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT–PCR). The genes selected for these analyses represented those from diverse functional classes with some previously implicated in virulence and biofilm regulation in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> with a fold change of three or higher (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2C</xref>). Importantly, this subset of those genes that showed a response to beclomethasone showed a similar alteration in expression when <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> was cultured in the presence of prednisolone, another glucocorticosteroid taken by asthmatics (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd3">Supplementary Figs S3</xref> and S4). In contrast, many of these genes showed no alteration in expression in response to dehydroepiandrosterone, an unrelated steroid that is found abundantly in human tissue (Supplementary Fig S3).</p></sec><sec><title>Genes showing specific changes in expression during <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> infection include a subset that is influenced by glucocorticosteroids in culture</title><p>The effects of glucocorticosteroids on gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in culture raised the issue of whether similar alterations in gene expression occur in the mouse model treated with glucocorticosteroids. As with other opportunistic pathogens, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> modulates its gene expression upon colonization of its mammalian host. To gain understanding of this adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to the host environment (in the presence of beclomethasone treatment), we systematically cataloged the transcriptomes of bacteria grown <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, using high-throughput cDNA sequencing techniques. RNA was derived from organisms isolated directly from the lung homogenates of infected mice and, following rRNA depletion, the remaining RNA was fragmented, reverse-transcribed into cDNA and sequenced. Illumina-based RNA-seq was used for the characterization of bacteria within the lung tissue, which reach densities of 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml. We chose to profile the infection 3 days post-inoculation because this represents the midpoint of the trajectory of the infection.</p><p>A total of 35–40 million reads were derived from murine samples and were aligned to non-rRNA sequences in the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genome (Supplementary Table S1). To identify genes that are differentially expressed during murine infection and in sBHI medium with or without glucocorticosteroid, we compared the RNA-seq data for these conditions using DESeq, a differential expression analysis package for RNA-seq data that presumes that abundance of reads can be modeled by a negative binomial distribution (An <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). These analyses revealed that expression of 129 (7.2%) of the 1,788 annotated <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> ORFs was significantly altered (&gt; 3-fold, P<sub>adj</sub> &lt; 1 × 10<sup>−5</sup>) in the mouse model of infection by comparison with bacteria grown in culture without glucocorticosteroids; expression of 58 genes (3.2%) was up-regulated, whereas expression of 71 genes (4.0%) was down-regulated (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd12">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).</p><p>Comparison of these alterations in the transcriptome with those induced by the presence of beclomethasone in culture revealed a significant overlap (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd12">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Nevertheless, a large number of genes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 82) whose expression is altered in bacteria in the host are not regulated by glucocorticosteroids in culture, consistent with the contention that these are responses of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to other aspects of the host environment. While the majority of these differentially expressed genes were annotated as hypothetical proteins, several have recently been shown to encode factors required by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> for growth and/or colonization of the host. These included <italic toggle="yes">HI0174</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">mnmA</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">HI0274</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">gltX</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">HI0479</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">atpD</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">HI1547</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">aroG</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">HI1548</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">lolE</italic>) (Gawronski <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Additional regulated genes encoded factors that have been previously reported to contribute to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> virulence: <italic toggle="yes">HI1544</italic> which encodes a NAD(P)H oxidoreductase and <italic toggle="yes">HI1707</italic> which encodes the sensor kinase, FirS (Steele <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>To assess the reliability of RNA-seq data in determining the relative abundances of individual transcripts in the presence of beclomethasone, we used the same total RNA samples determined by qRT–PCR: the mRNA levels of five up-regulated genes (<italic toggle="yes">HI0075</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI0095</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI1275</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic>) and four down-regulated genes (<italic toggle="yes">HI0127</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI0811</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI1177</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI1431</italic>) (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2D</xref>). The ratios of the transcripts from samples determined by RNA-seq to those obtained by qRT–PCR were in concordance.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcript levels of glucocorticosteroid-responsive <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes in sputum from asthma patients</title><p>The above findings suggest that glucocorticosteroids may influence the expression of specific <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes in asthma patients. In order to test this hypothesis, the transcript level of three corticosteroid-responsive genes (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359, HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic>) was established by qRT–PCR on sputum samples collected from twenty-four asthma patients. A comparison of the demographics and asthma characteristics of these patients are shown in Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>. There were no significant differences in gender, smoking history (defined as % current and past smoker), obesity (defined as BMI ≥ 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), nasal disease, atopy and serum IgE. All patients were taking standard inhaled glucocorticosteroid therapy using beclomethasone or mometasone routinely.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of bacteria identified by culturing and the detection of bacterial gene transcription in the sputum from asthma patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sample no.</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Age (y) and sex</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">FEV1%</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Inhaled steroid treatment<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">a</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Detected bacterial strains<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">b</xref></th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">mRNA level<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">c</xref></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">HI0359</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Sp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (0.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, MRSA, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Sm, Mc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 (0.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (0.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (0.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (0.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sm, Mc</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (0.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, MRSA, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm, Sp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0 (0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (0.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (0.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4 (0.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (0.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (0.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Ko, Sm, Sp</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (0.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (0.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hi, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (0.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bec</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (F)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa, Sa, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa, Sa, MRSA, Ko, Sm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1-1"><label>a</label><p>Current steroid treatment, Bec (beclomethasone) or Mom (mometasone).</p></fn><fn id="tf1-2"><label>b</label><p>Abbreviations of microbes identified by culture-based methods: Hi (<italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>), Pa (<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>), Sa (<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>), Ko (<italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella oxytoca</italic>), Sm (<italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>)<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> MRSA (methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>), Sp (<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>) and Mc (<italic toggle="yes">Moraxella catarrhalis</italic>).</p></fn><fn id="tf1-3"><label>c</label><p>Fold change relative to 16S RNA gene expression (standard deviation).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Inhaled beclomethasone is prescribed much more frequently (in 90% of cases) than mometasone, probably because it is effective but of lower cost than mometasone (Friedman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). However, mometasone only needs to be administered once every 24 h, whereas beclomethasone is administered two or three times in the same period. The clinical choice between beclomethasone and mometasone is informed by cost, administration frequency as well as past experience (Friedman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>Patients had a significant load of pathogenic bacteria in their sputum as detected by culture methods. The bacteria detected included <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus aureus,</italic> methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (MRSA<italic toggle="yes">), Streptococcus pneumoniae, Moraxella catarrhalis, Achromobacter xylosoxidans, Klebsiella oxytoca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> was identified in 20 of the 24 sputum samples with <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> being even more commonly found. All patients had more than one bacterial species cultured.</p><p>Total RNA was isolated from the 24 sputum samples obtained from these asthma patients. Contaminating DNA was degraded, total RNA was quantified, and equal amounts were subjected to qRT–PCR. Overall, 20 of the 24 sputum samples from patients tested positive for the expression of the selected corticosteroid-responsive genes <italic toggle="yes">HI0359, HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic>. There was a direct correlation between the presence of a qRT–PCR amplicon and the presence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in sputum as revealed by culture but no correlation with the presence of any other pathogenic bacteria. Notably, the transcript level of these target genes was increased in patients who were currently using beclomethasone compared to those who were using mometasone (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> retain the ability to respond to glucocorticosteroid</title><p>Although an elevated level of expression of corticoid-responsive genes in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains in sputum from asthma patients is consistent with a direct response to beclomethasone, the findings do not exclude the possibility that clinical isolates have intrinsically higher levels of expression of these genes. To address this issue, the ability of a panel of seven <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> clinical isolates to respond to glucocorticosteroids was assessed by measurement of the expression of <italic toggle="yes">yfe</italic> operon (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359–HI0362</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic> by qRT–PCR. Addition of beclomethasone or prednisone to the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> isolates led to the up-regulation of <italic toggle="yes">yfe</italic> operon (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359–HI0362</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic> in all strains, although to varying degrees (Supplementary Table S3). However, the level of alteration in expression in response to mometasone was considerably reduced (Supplementary Table S3). Taken together, the findings indicate that clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> retain the ability to respond to beclomethasone.</p></sec><sec><title>Identities of genes that mediate the response of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to glucocorticosteroids</title><p>We next sought to understand the mechanism by which beclomethasone impacts bacterial gene expression. As outlined above, the addition of beclomethasone to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> cultures led to increased expression of <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic>, which encodes an iron–sulfur cluster repair protein (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2D</xref>). This observation formed the basis of a screen for genes involved in the beclomethasone response. A reporter strain was constructed in which the <italic toggle="yes">luxCDABE</italic> genes were put under control of the <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic> promoter in the wild-type background (see Materials and Methods). This <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">lux</italic> reporter strain was subjected to insertional mutagenesis using a kanamycin resistance (Kan<sup>R</sup>) cassette as described in the Materials and Methods. A panel of approximately 4,000 mutants was screened for altered bioluminescence in the presence of beclomethasone (50 μM). Initially, 34 mutants that demonstrated altered expression of the reporter fusion were isolated, and following a rescreening to reduce false negatives, 19 candidates with altered response were identified.</p><p>The sites of Kan<sup>R</sup> cassette insertion for the non-responsive mutants were mapped to the genome of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and sequencing of amplicons (see Materials and Methods). Southern blot analysis confirmed that only a single copy of the cassette was inserted into the chromosome in these non-responsive mutants. Insertion sites, which were all different, were mapped to seven genetic loci with three genes found more than once. None of the mutants showed impaired growth in complex or minimal media, suggesting that the altered response to corticosteroid could not be attributed to differences in growth (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Location of transposon insertions that influence activation of the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae HI1677</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">lux</italic> reporter by beclomethasone</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disrupted gene<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polar effect possible<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">b</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hits of individual transposon mutants<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">c</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene product</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI0334</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTP pyrophosphokinase, RelA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI0628</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA polymerase sigma factor, RpoE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI0910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutator protein, MutT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI0999</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribonuclease P, RnpA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI1275</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tellurite resistance protein, TehB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI1501</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HI1605</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothetical protein</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><label>a</label><p>None of these gene disruptions affect bacterial growth in complex media and minimal media.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>b</label><p>Possibility of Tn5 insertion affecting expression of other (downstream) genes. Y: yes; N: no.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-3"><label>c</label><p>Number of different Tn5 insertion mutations mapped to the same gene.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Mutations were found in several genes encoding proteins involved in stress response (such as <italic toggle="yes">HI0999</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI1275</italic>), in genes encoding hypothetical protein (<italic toggle="yes">HI1501</italic>) and in genes encoding regulatory proteins including RpoE (<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>). Other insertions were found in genes that have been implicated in adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to infection of the murine lung (<italic toggle="yes">HI0334</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HI0910</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI1605</italic>). RpoE (also known as σ<sup>E</sup>) belongs to the extracytoplasmic function (ECF) family of sigma factors (Craig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). These ECF sigma factors, often functioning together with a membrane-associated anti-sigma factor, act to transduce signals perceived outside the cell membrane into a transcriptional response. On the basis of their putative action in the perception of extracellular signals, subsequent work focused on the potential role of the RpoE (HI0628) in the response of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to glucocorticosteroids.</p></sec><sec><title>RpoE regulates the expression of a subset of the genes influenced by glucocorticosteroids</title><p>Previous studies demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>) is part of an extracytoplasmic stress operon that is required for intracellular survival of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> (Craig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic>), which is immediately downstream of <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>, encodes an anti-sigma factor that modulates the action of RpoE. To examine the extent of the overlap between those genes regulated by glucocorticosteroids and those regulated by <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic>, we first established the effect of deletion of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> on the global gene expression patterns. The transcriptomes of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> deletion mutants (constructed as described in Materials and Methods) were compared with the wild-type <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> using RNA-seq.</p><p>Comparative transcriptome profiling of the <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> deletion mutant and the wild-type parent established that expression of 68 genes was significantly influenced (&gt; 3-fold change) by the loss of the sigma factor (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd12">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). This analysis revealed that HI0628 controls expression of genes associated with a range of biological functions that include bacterial motility and attachment, stress tolerance, virulence, regulation, transport, multidrug resistance, detoxification and signal transduction. Genes associated with virulence and the formation of biofilms that are regulated by HI0628 include <italic toggle="yes">yfe</italic> operon (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359–HI0362</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">argR</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI1209</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">potD</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI1344</italic>).</p><fig id="fig03" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparative transcriptome profiling of the effects of the addition of corticosteroid or mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> on gene expression in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic></p><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
A Venn diagrams showing the overlap of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes whose expression is influenced by the mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> or by the presence of corticosteroids in sBHI medium (<italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>) or in the mouse model of infection (<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>). The complete set of regulated genes is depicted in Supplementary Table S2.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
B, C Comparison of relative fold changes between RNA-seq and qRT–PCR results for <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> mutants (B) and the <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> and the addition of corticosteroid to wild-type <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> (C). All qRT–PCR results were normalized using the <italic toggle="yes">Ct</italic>s obtained for the 16S rRNA amplifications run in the same plate. The relative levels of gene transcripts are determined from standard curves. Values given are the mean and standard deviation of triplicate measurements (three biological and three technical replicates).
</p></list-item></list></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f3.jpg"/></fig><p>Inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> led to significant alteration in the expression of 40 genes, the majority encoding hypothetical proteins. MclA and RpoE influenced expression of many of the same genes. For the majority of these genes, regulation was in opposite direction, which is consistent with the notion that MclA is a negative regulator of RpoE activity (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3B</xref>). Nevertheless, RpoE and MclA regulated a small number of genes in the same direction (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3B</xref>). The alteration in expression as revealed by the RNA-seq analysis was confirmed for selected genes by qRT–PCR (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3B</xref>).</p><p>Comparisons of the effect on the transcriptome profile of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>) mutation and the addition of exogenous corticosteroid revealed a number of genes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 66) whose expression appeared to be co-regulated (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd12">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Several transcriptional changes in co-regulated genes caused by <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> mutation and corticosteroid addition to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> were confirmed by qRT–PCR (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3C</xref>). As outlined above, MclA influenced many of these genes in the opposite directions to RpoE. Taken together, these findings are consistent with the contention that the RpoE–MclA system is modulated by glucocorticosteroids leading to altered expression of a specific subset of genes; however, our data also indicate that a subset of genes modulated by glucocorticosteroid addition are impacted independently of RpoE.</p></sec><sec><title>Glucocorticosteroids can influence biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae in vitro</italic></title><p>The influence of glucocorticosteroids on expression of genes implicated in biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> prompted us to examine the effect of beclomethasone on these phenotypes. For these experiments, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> was grown in μ-well chambers with sBHI medium and the bacteria were visualized with SYTO9 (see Materials and Methods). When grown alone, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> formed flat biofilms with little heterogeneity (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4A(i)</xref>). The addition of 1 μM glucocorticosteroid to the sBHI medium promoted the development of a biofilm with a similar biomass to the bacteria grown without addition, although the structure showed less dense packing of cells (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4A(ii)</xref>). This alteration in biofilm formation was not seen when dehydroepiandrosterone, a non-corticosteroid, was used in the assay (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd5">Supplementary Fig S5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig04" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Addition of corticosteroids affects biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance of H. influenzae</p><p><italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms were developed after 24 h in μ-well chambers in sBHI medium with and without corticosteroid and were then treated with the antibiotic azithromycin as specified.
</p><p><list list-type="alpha-upper"><list-item><p>
(i) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type with DMSO (solvent control); (ii) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type treated with 1 μM beclomethasone (BEC); (iii) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type treated with 150 μg/ml azithromycin (AZO); and (iv) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type treated with 1 μM beclomethasone (BEC) and 150 μg/ml azithromycin (AZO). For these experiments, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> was visualized with SYTO9 (green strain), as described in Materials and Methods. Scale bars = 20 μm. Images shown are representative of 12 images from five independent experiments.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
The biofilm biomass after treatments was quantified using COMSTAT. Data are presented as the average of five replicates, with error bar representing the standard deviation of the data. Statistical significance by two-tailed Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test is indicated: **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.
</p></list-item></list></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f4.jpg"/></fig><p>Previous studies have shown that <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms cultured in sBHI medium are extremely tolerant to antibiotic treatment, mimicking to an extent what is seen during infection (Swords <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Starner <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). To examine the influence of beclomethasone on antibiotic tolerance, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms generated in the presence and absence of 1 μM beclomethasone for 24 h were treated with azithromycin, an antibiotic often prescribed to asthma patients, at 150 μg/ml, which is a concentration measured in the lungs of patients (Starner <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). After 24 h of growth, the presence of azithromycin had substantially inhibited biofilm formation, with significantly decreased biofilm biomass and maximal thickness compared to the untreated control (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4A</xref>(iii) and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">B</xref>). The presence of 1 μM beclomethasone decreased the effect of azithromycin on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms, as indicated by a lesser effect on biofilm biomass (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">4A</xref>(iv) and B). In contrast, the addition of dehydroepiandrosterone, which is not a glucocorticoid, did not alter the effect of azithromycin on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd5">Supplementary Fig S5</xref>). These data suggest that glucocorticoid treatment of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilms results in an increase in the tolerance to azithromycin. Importantly, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains grown planktonically in the presence and absence of beclomethasone showed no difference in tolerance to azithromycin (Supplementary Fig S6).</p><p>The role of RpoE and MclA on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance was also investigated by the examination of biofilm grown in μ-well chambers with sBHI medium. The <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> mutant showed development of a biofilm with a similar biomass to the wild-type, although the bacteria within the structure were slightly less densely packed (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5A(i–iii)</xref>). Interestingly, mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> led to the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biofilm being more tolerant to azithromycin treatment compared to wild-type (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5A(iv-v)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd7">Supplementary Fig S7</xref>). Similarly, mutation of <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> mutant led to an increase in azithromycin tolerance (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd7">Supplementary Fig S7</xref>). Complementation restored these phenotypes toward wild-type (Supplementary Fig S7). To determine whether <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> has a similar influence in clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>, the gene was disrupted in two clinical isolates and mutants were assessed for alterations in phenotype. In these two strains, mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> led to an enhanced azithromycin tolerance (Supplementary Fig S8), indicating a similar role for RpoE in both clinical and laboratory strains.</p><fig id="fig05" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Mutation of genes encoding RpoE (HI0628) and MclA (HI0629) has similar effects on biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance in H. influenzae</p><p>Biofilms of different <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains were developed after 24 h in μ-well chambers in sBHI medium and were then treated with the antibiotic azithromycin as specified.
</p><p><list list-type="alpha-upper"><list-item><p>
(i) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type; (ii) <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>); (iii) <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic>); (iv) <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type treated with 150 μg/ml azithromycin; (v) <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic>) treated with 150 μg/ml azithromycin; (vi) <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic>) treated with 150 μg/ml azithromycin. For these experiments, <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> was visualized with SYTO9 (green strain), as described in Materials and Methods. Scale bars = 20 μm. Images shown are representative of 12 images from five independent experiments.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
The biofilm biomass after treatments was quantified using COMSTAT. Data are presented as the average of five replicates, with error bars representing the standard deviation of the data. Statistical significance by two-tailed Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test is indicated: **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.
</p></list-item></list></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Glucocorticosteroids reduce the efficacy of azithromycin treatment against <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> colonization in the mouse airway</title><p>There have been only a handful of reports addressing the effectiveness of antibiotic treatment against <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> during respiratory infection (Vallee <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Sekiya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Therefore, to build on our observations that beclomethasone increases the capacity of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to tolerate azithromycin in an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model, we wished to assess the effect of beclomethasone on the efficacy of azithromycin treatment in a mouse model of infection.</p><p>Using a slight modification of the mouse model described above (see Materials and Methods), the C57BL/6 mice were infected with 1 × 10<sup>8</sup> CFU of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> and treated by inhaling PBS with or without 50 μM beclomethasone. Azithromycin was administered at a concentration of 100 mg/kg/24 h, a dose reported by several studies (Azoulay-Dupuis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Girard <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The lung and spleen bacterial load was determined 3 days post-infection. C57BL/6 mice infected with <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> with PBS exhibited considerable colonization (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">B</xref>). Azithromycin appeared to be very effective in eradicating <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> from mice treated with PBS alone (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">B</xref>). However, with the addition of beclomethasone, bacteria appear to be present even after the mice had received 3 days of azithromycin treatment (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig06" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Corticosteroid treatment affects <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> clearance by antibiotic treatment in the mouse airway</p><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>
A, B Mice infected intranasally with 1 × 10<sup>8 </sup>CFU <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> and treated by inhaling PBS with or without 50 μM beclomethasone. Azithromycin was administered at a concentration of 100 mg/kg/24 h, daily for 3 days after infection. On day 3–4 after infection, the mice were harvested, and bacterial loads were determined in lung (A) and spleen (B) homogenates. Values represent the mean ± standard deviation (SD). The data are pooled from three independent experiments. Statistical significance by two-tailed Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test is indicated: *<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; 0.01.
</p></list-item></list></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-f6.jpg"/></fig><p>The role of RpoE in modulation of the efficacy of azithromycin treatment during airway infection of mice was also investigated by studies of the clearance of the <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> mutant. The <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> mutant showed similar persistence during azithromycin treatment as the wild-type <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> with added beclomethasone (Fig<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">B</xref>). Addition of beclomethasone to the <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> mutant had no additional effect in C57BL/6 mice. These results suggest that the presence of beclomethasone increases the capacity of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to persist in wild-type mice undergoing azithromycin treatment and that this persistence effect is modulated by RpoE.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The work in this paper suggests that glucocorticosteroids such as beclomethasone have a direct and specific effect on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>, influencing expression of a subset of genes that underpin alterations in phenotypes, which include biofilm architecture and tolerance to antibiotic treatment <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. In a mouse model, beclomethasone increased the persistence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> and reduced the efficacy of azithromycin in clearing the infection. These latter findings are consistent with previous observations using an infant mouse model of bacterial meningitis, where dexamethasone was shown to enhance the persistence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in blood and cerebral spinal fluid from mice undergoing treatment with the oral antibiotic cefuroxime (Rodriguez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). The effects of glucocorticosteroid on the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in mice may also be mediated by influences on the host as well as by direct effects on the bacterium. Indeed, it is now appreciated that the action of glucocorticoids can be more complex than simply acting as anti-inflammatory agents (reviewed in Cruz-Topete &amp; Cidlowski, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). For example, glucocorticoids synergistically enhance the expression of TLR2 by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in cultured human epithelial cells (Shuto <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p><p>Extrapolations from these models of infection to the asthma airway should be made cautiously; nevertheless, several lines of evidence support the notion that beclomethasone affects the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> in the asthma airway. Analysis of sputum taken from patients with asthma demonstrated elevated transcript level of three glucocorticosteroid-responsive genes (<italic toggle="yes">HI0359, HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic>), which was strongly correlated with the use of beclomethasone in patients colonized by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). In contrast, the transcript level of these target genes was lower in patients who were currently using mometasone (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>). Furthermore, testing of a panel of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> clinical isolates showed that each had a similar response to beclomethasone as the model strain in altered transcription of <italic toggle="yes">HI0359, HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0994</italic> (Supplementary Table S3). These findings indicate that these clinical isolates do not have an intrinsically higher level of expression of these target genes and support the conclusion that the pattern of gene expression of bacteria in sputum is, at least in part, a response to beclomethasone. These similarities to the behavior of the model strain further suggest that the presence of beclomethasone makes a contribution to the enhanced ability of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to persist during antibiotic treatment for asthma.</p><p>Glucocorticosteroid treatments of asthma patients are associated with anti-inflammatory properties, but this contrasts with the response observed in our mouse model following bacterial infection. In challenged mice, glucocorticosteroid treatment showed similar increase in neutrophils and other immune cells comparable to mice that did not receive treatment. The anti-inflammatory activities of glucocorticosteroids in this situation may be counterbalanced <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> by enhanced bacterial persistence. Furthermore, as mentioned above, glucocorticoids can have actions other than as anti-inflammatory agents, for example, in synergistic enhancement of the expression of TLR2 by <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> (Shuto <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p><p>The detailed mechanisms by which beclomethasone exerts its influence on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> gene expression and phenotypes such as biofilm formation and antibiotic tolerance remain obscure. Currently, no glucocorticosteroid receptors have been identified in bacterial cells. Our mutant screen coupled with comparative transcriptomics indicates that some of the effects of beclomethasone may be exerted through an influence on the regulation of the ECF sigma factor RpoE and its anti-sigma factor MclA. In the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genome, <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> is organized in an operon with <italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">rseA</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">rseB</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HI0630</italic>). Homologous genes are present and organized in the same manner in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> genome. In <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, RpoE is normally sequestered to the cytoplasmic face of the inner membrane by an anti-sigma factor, RseA, which interacts with the periplasmic protein, RseB. Under certain stress conditions, lipopolysaccharides (LPS) and outer membrane proteins (OMPs) are not incorporated into the outer membrane and accumulate in the periplasm. Periplasmic LPS binds RseB, freeing RseA to be cleaved by the OMP-activated protease DegS. This initiates further RseA degradation by the protease RseP, resulting in the release of RpoE into the cytosol (Barchinger &amp; Ades, <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Lima <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Over-expression of RseB down-regulates the RpoE pathway. In addition to this post-translational regulation, transcription of the <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> gene is positively auto-regulated. It is highly likely that <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> possesses a similar mechanism for the regulation of RpoE as in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, although <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> is essential in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> but not in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>. The overlapping effects on the transcriptome and phenotypes of the addition of beclomethasone, mutation of the sigma factor (<italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic>) and mutation of the anti-sigma factor (<italic toggle="yes">mclA</italic>) genes are not consistent with a model in which glucocorticosteroids activate the RpoE stress response, but suggest they act to suppress the action of RpoE. Consistent with this contention, beclomethasone had no effect on the profile of outer membrane proteins of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> (Supplementary Fig S9). Suppression of RpoE action could involve direct binding of glucocorticosteroids to the sigma factor. To address this possibility, we determined the ability of purified RpoE to bind beclomethasone by isothermal titration calorimetry (Supplementary Fig S10). The experimental data show no binding and therefore do not support a direct binding model. These experiments do not rule out other mechanisms of beclomethasone action that include an inhibition of the regulated proteolysis of MclA/RseA or an influence on the RpoE::MclA balance by differential influences on transcription.</p><p>Our data show that the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae rpoE</italic> mutant biofilms were more tolerant of antimicrobial treatment than the wild-type. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> mutants of other Gram-negative bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium and <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio cholerae</italic> have reduced survival in the presence of antimicrobials and attenuated virulence in various <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> models (Humphreys <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Osborne &amp; Coombes, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae mclA</italic> mutant biofilms showed similar tolerance to antibiotic treatment than the wild-type. These findings support the emerging view that biofilm formation in most bacteria instigates a completely different range of regulatory events to govern antimicrobial susceptibility than those activated during planktonic growth (Anderson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Osborne &amp; Coombes, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>Although the anti-inflammatory clinical benefits of glucocorticosteroid treatment are undeniable in many respiratory diseases, several recent studies have implicated such therapies in the development of bacterial pneumonia in asthma and COPD (Singanayagam <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In addition, chronic bacterial infections of neutrophilic asthma airways that involve <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> are connected to the development of airway disease that is steroid resistant (Essilfie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Our studies point to the need to consider the impact on bacterial behavior as one factor in the choice of which glucocorticosteroid to be used and in design of the treatment regime. For example, prednisolone triggered similar alterations in gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> to those seen with beclomethasone, whereas mometasone had little effect (Supplementary Fig S4). Would the use of mometasone therefore be preferential to other glucocorticosteroids for patients also being treated with azithromycin? Would stopping the glucocorticosteroid treatment before antibiotics are applied promote the antibacterial effect? While several clinical trials have reported an increased risk of bacterial pneumonia with the use of glucocorticosteroids in asthma and COPD patients, only specific patient trials designed to assess the above questions will inform clinicians. Overall, our data suggest the requirement for further studies to examine the action of glucocorticosteroids on bacteria that colonize the airway of individuals who rely on these therapeutic agents.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains, growth conditions and media</title><p>Strains and plasmids used in this study are described in Supplementary Table S4. <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains were grown (overnight at 37°C) on brain–heart infusion agar plates supplemented with 10 μg/ml of hemin and 10 μg/ml of NAD (referred to as sBHI). <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> was grown on Luria-Bertani (LB) broth or LB agar plates at 37°C. When appropriate, the following concentrations of antibiotics were used: 50 μg/ml of kanamycin (Kan), 100 μg/ml of erythromycin (Em) and 150 μg/ml of azithromycin. Antibiotics were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA manipulations</title><p>Molecular biological methods such as isolation of plasmid and chromosomal DNA, PCR, plasmid transformation as well as restriction digestion were carried out using standard protocols (Sambrook <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>). PCR products were cleaned using the PCR purification kit (Qiagen™), and DNA fragments were recovered from agarose gels using QIAquick minielute gel purification kit (Qiagen™). Oligonucleotide primers were purchased from Sigma-Genosys™.</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of mutants in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains</title><p>Mutants in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains were constructed using a modified protocol of the one described previously (Morey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Genes <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic> were amplified separately in two parts by PCR with Taq polymerase (Promega™) using Rd KW20 genomic DNA as the template. Primers were designed based on the genome sequence of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> Rd KW20 and detailed in Supplementary Table S5. The first part of each gene was amplified to include ∼200 bp of the region upstream of the predicted open reading frame, while the second part of the gene included ∼200 bp downstream of the predicted stop codon. As restriction sites external to these flanking regions, internal SmaI sites were incorporated onto each amplicon. The two separately amplified sequences were re-assembled in pBluescript and cloned into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5a. Restriction digest using SmaI allowed the integration of an erythromycin cassette, which was taken from pBSLErm (Allen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The construct was linearized and used to transform chemically competent Rd KW20 using standard protocols. Transformants, which had successfully undergone recombination, were selected on sBHI containing 10 μg/ml Em. Complementation of mutant <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains was carried out by inserting the relevant gene into open reading frame (ORF) HI0601.1; this ORF contains a frameshift in <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> Rd KW20. The approach has been deployed successfully in a previous study (Morey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Copies of <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic> genes were used to complement respective mutants (Supplementary Table S4).</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of chromosomal reporter fusions</title><p>The protocol used for the construction of the <italic toggle="yes">lux</italic> reporter fusion for <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic> was a modification of the RED recombination protocols previously described by Lesic and Rahme (<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and McCarthy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic> gene was amplified by PCR using forward and reverse primers HI1677-F and HI1677-R to include the region 250 bp upstream of the gene and was cloned into pGLuc. The <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">lux</italic> fusion was removed by restriction digest using HindIII and XbaI and cloned into pME6032-RedS cut with the same enzymes. This construct was electroporated into <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> wild-type. Transconjugants were grown in sBHI to an optical density at 600 nm of 0.4 at 37°C, and recombination was induced by the addition of 0.2% L-arabinose for 1.5 h. The correct integration of the reporter cassette was confirmed by colony PCR using a reverse primer specific to the reporter and a forward primer specific to the upstream region of the target gene.</p></sec><sec><title>Transposon mutagenesis and screening</title><p>A library of mutants in the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strain carrying the <italic toggle="yes">HI1677</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">lux</italic> fusion was constructed using EZ::Tn&lt;KAN-2&gt; Tnp transposome (Epicentre technologies) as directed by the manufacturer. Briefly, 100 ng of transposon-containing plasmid was electroporated into newly prepared electrocompetent <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> cells. Strains carrying the transposon insertion were identified by selection on Kan. The library of mutants was screened for loss of responsiveness of <italic toggle="yes">HI1677::lux</italic> expression to exogenous beclomethasone (50 μM). Strains were inoculated into microtiter wells containing sBHI medium with 50 μM beclomethasone by using a Qpix robot (Genetix™). The luciferase activity lysates of bacteria from each well were quantified as described previously (Deiwick <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Briefly, equal amounts of bacterial cells as adjusted by the determination of optical density at 600 nm (OD600) were harvested by centrifugation and lysed. Luciferase activity in bacterial cell lysates was assayed using Luciferase Assay Kit (Promega™) and quantified in black microtiter plates by a Wallac Victor 21420 Multilabel Counter plate reader (Perkin Elmer™).</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of transposon insertion sites</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from transposon mutants of interest as previously described (Sambrook <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>). To identify the genes that were interrupted by the EZ::Tn transposon, the random amplification of transposon ends (RATE) PCR method of Ducey and colleagues (Ducey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) was utilized. Amplicons were sequenced using the Inv-specific primers (Supplementary Table S5). Sequence data generated were examined with blastn and blastx (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/</ext-link>) software.</p></sec><sec><title>Enrollment of subjects and sputum sample collection</title><p>Sputum samples from 24 asthma patients (January 2012–September 2013) were collected from Cork University Hospital. All study participants provided written consent. The Clinical Research Ethics Committee of the Cork Teaching Hospitals (CREC) granted full approval to the project. All sputa were analyzed and then frozen at −80°C in 1-ml aliquots for further study. Patient clinical parameters were also recorded including the participant’s age, lung function, pulmonary administered steroids or antibiotics, and colonization by microorganisms identified by standard clinical laboratory cultivation techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Animal experiments were conducted in compliance with a protocol (# 16-051-11) approved by The Animal Experimentation Ethics Committee (AEEC) of University College Cork or Cork University Hospital. The Minister for Health accredits the University College Cork for conducting animal experiments. AEEC is guided by legislative requirements, in particular the Cruelty to Animals Act as amended and supplemented by the European Communities.</p></sec><sec><title>Infection and treatment of animals</title><p>Mouse infection was performed with modification of the procedures described by Sekiya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (<xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and Wu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (<xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Four-week-old female C57BL/6 mice (Charles River) were injected intraperitoneally with cyclophosphamide at 3 days pre-infection and on the day of infection at a dose of 66 μg/g of body weight. Sample size was always five unless otherwise stated. Bacterial strains used for the intranasal challenge were grown in sBHI broth to an optical density (600 nM) of approximately 0.25. Subsequently, 20 μl of culture to have a final inoculum of 1 × 10<sup>9</sup> colony-forming unit (CFU) was administered to each mouse. After every 24-h period, animals were treated with 100 μl of PBS or PBS containing beclomethasone (50 μM) was pipetted into the nares and involuntarily inhaled. Five mice were sacrificed by carbon dioxide asphyxiation at days 1, 3, 5 and 7 post-challenge. Bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid (100 μl) and blood (75 μl) were collected from each mouse. After exposure of the trachea, the nasopharynx was washed with 1 ml of buffer (0.5% trypsin, 0.02% EDTA in sterile PBS) by insertion of a 26-gauge needle sheathed in tubing into the tracheal end of the upper respiratory tract. Buffer was allowed to drip into the nasopharynx slowly and was collected from the nose, with each wash taking approximately 40 s. Both lungs and spleen were entirely removed, rinsed twice in PBS to remove excess blood, weighed and placed in 2 ml of sterile PBS. The lungs and spleen were then homogenized at 10,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for approximately 10 s. All blood, lung, spleen and BAL washout samples were then serially diluted and plated on agar to determine the number of viable bacteria. Total cells present in the BAL were counted, and a differential cell count was performed on cytospins stained with Diff Quick.</p><p>For animal experiments examining the effectiveness of azithromycin treatment against <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> during respiratory infection, mice were intranasally inoculated with 20 μl of the bacterial suspension in PBS (1 × 10<sup>8 </sup>CFU/mouse). Each mouse was administered azithromycin once daily over the course of infection. On day 3 after infection, the lung and spleen were removed, homogenized with PBS and plated on agar to determine the number of viable bacteria.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA extraction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> Rd KW20 strains (including mutants) were inoculated at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1 in sBHI [with 50 μM beclomethasone dipropionate (Sigma-Aldrich) if used]. Cultures were harvested during mid-log phase (OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.7), and RNA was extracted using the High Pure RNA Isolation Kit (Roche). For the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> RNA samples, infected animals as described above were euthanized &lt; 72 h post-infection. RNA was isolated from airway homogenate pellets using TRIzol according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Samples were treated with DNase, and then rRNA was removed from 1 to 5 μg of total RNA using the Ribo-Zero kit for Gram-negative bacteria (Epicentre). rRNA-depleted samples were concentrated by EtOH precipitation.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene expression profiling experiments</title><p>RNA quality was assessed on a Bioanalyser PicoChip (Agilent), and RNA quantity was measured using the RNA assay on QuBit fluorometer (Life Technologies). Ribosomal RNA was depleted with Ribo-Zero™ rRNA Removal Kits for Gram-negative bacteria (Epicentre). The percentage of rRNA contamination was checked on a Bioanalyser PicoChip (Agilent).</p><p>The rRNA-depleted sample was processed using the Illumina TruSeq RNA v2 sample preparation kit. In brief, the sample was chemically fragmented to ∼200 nt in length and the cleaved RNA fragments were primed with random hexamers into first-strand cDNA using reverse-transcriptase and random primers. The RNA template was removed, and a replacement strand was synthesized to generate ds cDNA. The ds cDNA was end-repaired to remove the overhangs from the fragmentation into blunt ends. A single “A” nucleotide was added to the 3′ ends on the blunt fragments, which is complementary to a “T” nucleotide on the 3′ end of the Illumina adapters. At this stage, adapters containing 6-nt barcodes were used for different samples to allow the pooling of multiple samples together. The resulted bar-coded samples were enriched by 10 cycles of PCR to amplify the amount of DNA in the library. The final cDNA libraries were sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq2000 as per the manufacturer’s instructions.</p><p>The fluorescent images were processed to sequences using the Pipeline Analysis software 1.8 (Illumina). Raw sequence data obtained in Illumina FASTQ-format were first separated by their barcode sequence by comparing the first six bases with the expected barcode sequences. Successfully detected barcodes were removed from the sequence leaving paired-end reads of 30 nt in length, while reads containing no recognizable barcode sequence were discarded.</p><p>Reads for each sample were aligned to the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenza</italic>e Rd KW20 GCA_000027305.1 genome assembly (Ensembl bacteria genome database) using Bowtie version 2.0 with default parameters and randomness which when the program is faced with a sequence that aligns to multiple parts of the genome equally well, chooses one region randomly and the others are discarded. Transcript abundance was determined using the feature counts program to estimate the level of transcription for each gene, and the number of reads that mapped within each annotated coding sequence (CDS) was determined.</p><p>Differential expression was assessed using DESeq2, which estimates variance-mean dependence in read counts and uses negative binomial distribution to test for differential expression. The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value for fold change is calculated and adjusted to remove the effects of repetition. The entire dataset has been deposited in the European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI) European Nucleotide Archive site under accession number ERG003569.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative real-time PCR assays</title><p>The effect of <italic toggle="yes">HI0628</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">HI0629</italic> mutation or the addition of 50 μM of various steroids [beclomethasone dipropionate, prednisone, mometasone, dehydroepiandrosterone (Sigma-Aldrich)] to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenza</italic>e strains (including clinical isolates) on expression of genes was monitored by qRT–PCR. RNA was isolated from cultures of wild-type strain, wild-type supplemented with 50 μM steroid or mutant grown to an OD600 of 0.7, converted to cDNA using AMV Reverse Transcriptase (Promega) using conditions specified by the manufacturer. The quantitative PCR was carried out using Platinum® SYBR® Green qPCR SuperMix-UDG (Invitrogen). The primers used to amplify the genes are listed in Supplementary Table S2. As a control, RT–PCR was similarly applied to analyze expression of the 16S rRNA gene. The reverse transcription and PCR protocols were performed as described previously. The amplified products were subjected to electrophoresis on 2.5% agarose gels and stained with ethidium bromide. RT–PCR analysis was repeated at least twice for each gene tested.</p></sec><sec><title>Cultivation and image analysis of biofilms</title><p><italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains were allowed to form biofilm in static μ-well chambers (Ibidi-iTreat) containing sBHI media incubated at 37°C as previously described (Jurcisek <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). These chambers have a physically treated cycloolefin polymer exterior with a surface energy of around 72 mN/m. When required, steroid at a concentration of 1 or 10 or 50 μM was added during initial biofilm formation. Biofilm antibiotic susceptibility testing was carried out on 24-h-old biofilms of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> strains grown as described above (in the presence or absence of steroid as required) and then treated with 150 μg/ml azithromycin for 3 h before visualization and quantification.</p><p>Biofilms were stained and visualized using SYTO 9 to color live biofilm cells green and propidium iodide stain (Life Tech), a normally cell-impermeable stain, to color dead cells red. All microscopic observations and image acquisitions were performed on a Zeiss LSM780 confocal laser scanning microscope equipped with an argon–krypton laser and with detectors and filter sets for monitoring SYTO 9 and for the recording of reflection (light) images. Images were obtained using a 63×/1.4 Plan-APOChromat differential interference contrast objective or a 40×/1.3 Plan-Neofluor oil objective. Multichannel simulated fluorescence projection (SFP) images, vertical <italic toggle="yes">xz</italic> sections through the biofilms and simulated three-dimensional (3D) images were generated using the IMARIS software package (Bitplane). Biofilm images were obtained to quantify biomass as described previously using COMSTAT software.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Significant differences between the means plus or minus standard deviations (SDs) of different groups were examined using a two-tailed unpaired Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t-</italic>test. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of less than 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. All variables remained significant after multiple testing.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Laura Filkins and Francesca Short for technical support and help with data analysis. We express gratitude to members of the Ryan laboratory for their helpful comments on the manuscript. We also must thank Paul Webster for the permission to use one of his wonderful scanning electron microscope images. The work of the authors has been supported in part by grants awarded by the Wellcome Trust (WT100204AIA senior fellowship grant to R.P.R.), European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme (Grant No. 603038 to R.P.R.) and the National Institutes of Health (R01 Grant 2 R37 AI83256-06 to G.A.O).</p></ack><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>CSE and RPR are responsible for the concept and design of the study. CSE, TWK, SA, SM, YM, JG, JMD, LY, GAO and RPR are responsible for data and laboratory analyses. JW contributed to data analysis and interpretation. CSE, SA, JMD, GAO and RPR are primarily responsible for writing the manuscript. All authors contributed to manuscript editing and approval.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p><boxed-text id="bx1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>The paper explained</title></caption><sec><title>Problem</title><p>Glucocorticosteroids are used as a main treatment to reduce airway inflammation in the majority of asthma patients. However, a large proportion of asthmatic patients that receive prolonged corticosteroid treatment develop chronic <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> infection along with reduced responsiveness to steroid therapy. One aspect of the pathogenesis and therapy of asthma that has not received consideration is the potential direct influence of glucocorticosteroids on the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic>. In particular, whether glucocorticosteroids have a direct impact on bacterial functions that promote persistence and tolerance to antibiotics remains an open question that we address in this paper.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We have examined the impact of glucocorticosteroid treatment on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> during respiratory infection and neutrophilic asthma, as well as investigating impacts on <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> biology <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. We show that the presence of beclomethasone promotes <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> persistence without influencing the host inflammatory response in a mouse model of acute infection. Comparative transcriptional analysis of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> grown under standard laboratory conditions in the absence and presence of beclomethasone revealed that this glucocorticosteroid induces altered expression of genes implicated in biofilm formation, host colonization and survival <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Importantly, examination of sputum samples from asthma patients undertaking inhaled steroid treatment showed that many of the <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> genes with expression that was responsive to corticosteroid <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> also had altered expression in bacteria during infection. Clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> showed similar alteration in the expression of specific target genes in response to beclomethasone or prednisone <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. A mutant screen and transcriptome profiling identified RpoE (HI0628) as an element in the corticosteroid response that acts to regulate a subset of the genes influenced by glucocorticosteroids. Mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> or addition of corticosteroid to <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> led to alteration in biofilm formation and enhanced resistance to azithromycin, an antibiotic often prescribed to asthma patients. Furthermore, in an animal model of respiratory infection, the presence of corticosteroid or mutation of <italic toggle="yes">rpoE</italic> promoted azithromycin resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Impact</title><p>These results reveal a previously unrecognized contribution of glucocorticosteroid treatment to bacterial airway infections particularly in the context of asthma. Specifically, the findings suggest that glucocorticosteroid treatment influences <italic toggle="yes">H. influenzae</italic> behavior in the airway affecting biofilm formation, persistence and the efficacy of antibiotic therapy. These observations may inform clinical practice in the use of glucocorticosteroids in the treatment of asthma. In particular, the work points toward the need to consider the impact on bacterial behavior as one factor in the choice of which steroid to be used and in design of the treatment regime in the context of respiratory disease.</p></sec></boxed-text></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apicella</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel sialic acid transporter of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2005</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>5291</fpage><lpage>5300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16113244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.73.9.5291-5300.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1231074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>S-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Febrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clissold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaithakottil</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swarbreck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution transcriptional analysis of the regulatory influence of cell-to-cell signalling reveals novel genes that contribute to <italic toggle="yes">Xanthomonas</italic> phytopathogenesis</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23617851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/mmi.12229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3744752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreau-Marquis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro analysis of tobramycin-treated <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> Biofilms on cystic fibrosis-derived airway epithelial cells</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2008</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1423</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18212077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.01373-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2292855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azoulay-Dupuis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedos</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muffatjoly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocidalo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prophylactic and therapeutic activities of azithromycin in a mouse model of pneumococcal pneumonia</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1991</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1656849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.35.6.1024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC284280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barchinger</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ades</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulated proteolysis: control of the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> σ<sup>E</sup>-dependent cell envelope stress response</article-title><source>Subcell Biochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23479440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-94-007-5940-4_6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beigelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacharier</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationships between environmental bacterial exposure, airway bacterial colonization, and asthma</article-title><source>Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ACI.0000000000000036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4121123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brightling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradding</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardlaw</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavord</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathological features and inhaled corticosteroid response of eosinophilic and non-eosinophilic asthma</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thx.2006.073429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2094295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cliffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>High</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival of nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> in macrophages</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2001.tb10820.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobbs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>High</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The extracytoplasmic sigma factor, sigma(E), is required for intracellular survival of nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> in J774 macrophages</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2002</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.70.2.708-715.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC127695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Topete</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cidlowski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One hormone, two actions: anti- and pro-inflammatory effects of glucocorticoids</article-title><source>NeuroImmunoModulation</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25227506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000362724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4243162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daley-Yates</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beclomethasone dipropionate: absolute bioavailability, pharmacokinetics and metabolism following intravenous, oral, intranasal and inhaled administration in man</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11421996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.0306-5251.2001.01374.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2014471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deiwick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hensel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental regulation of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> pathogenicity island 2 gene expression</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1759</fpage><lpage>1773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10209748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01312.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducey</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orvis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the iron-responsive genes of <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> by microarray analysis in defined medium</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>4865</fpage><lpage>4885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15995201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.187.14.4865-4874.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1169496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Essilfie</surname><given-names>A-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvat</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkley</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansbro</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenza</italic>e infection drives IL-17-mediated neutrophilic allergic airways disease</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1002244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21998577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3188527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Essilfie</surname><given-names>A-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkley</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansbro</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> respiratory infection and allergic airways disease drives chronic infection and features of neutrophilic asthma</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2012</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22387445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2011-200160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urdaneta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navaratnam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mometasone furoate versus beclomethasone dipropionate: effectiveness in patients with mild asthma</article-title><source>Am J Manag Care</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>e151</fpage><lpage>e156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20645660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawronski</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SMS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannoukos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akerley</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracking insertion mutants within libraries by deep sequencing and a genome-wide screen for Haemophilus genes required in the lung</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>16422</fpage><lpage>16427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0906627106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2752563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finegan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lame</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced efficacy of single-dose versus multi-dose azithromycin regimens in preclinical infection models</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jac/dki241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiriyachaiporn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grainge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehagia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentially pathogenic airway bacteria and neutrophilic inflammation in treatment resistant severe asthma</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e100645</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24955983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0100645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4067344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGehee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toews</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune enhancement of pulmonary clearance of nontypable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1988</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3257203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.56.1.182-190.1988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC259254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinhardt</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The alternative sigma factor, sigma(E), is critically important for the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella typhimurium</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1999</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1560</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10084987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.67.4.1560-1568.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC96497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on glucocorticoid action and resistance</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16522450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaci.2006.01.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalalvand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mörgelin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallgren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westergren-Thorsson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riesbeck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> protein F mediates binding to laminin and human pulmonary epithelial cells</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23230060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/infdis/jis754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurcisek</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggeman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakaletz</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro biofilm formation in an 8-well chamber slide</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3791/2481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3182645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahme</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the lambda Red recombinase system to rapidly generate mutants in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>BMC Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18248677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2199-9-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2287187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual molecular signals mediate the bacterial response to outer-membrane stress</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23687042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1235358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3928677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twomey</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolker-Nielsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahenthiralingam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sensor kinase recognizing the cell-cell signal BDSF (cis-2-dodecenoic acid) regulates virulence in <italic toggle="yes">Burkholderia cenocepacia</italic></article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1220</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07285.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viadas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Euba</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barberan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jesus Grillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonio Bengoechea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garmendia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative contributions of lipooligosaccharide inner and outer core modifications to nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> pathogenesis</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2013</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>4100</fpage><lpage>4111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23980106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.00492-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coombes</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RpoE fine tunes expression of a subset of SsrB-regulated virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2180-9-45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2651894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of dexamethasone or HWA-138 in combination with antibiotics in experimental <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> type b infection</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1991</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1980</fpage><lpage>1984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1759817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.35.10.1980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC245311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</source><year>1989</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><comment>Vol. 10, edn. Cold</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubukata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative efficacies of different antibiotic treatments to eradicate nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> infection</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18254980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2334-8-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2276502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imasato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rixter</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andalibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linthicum</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocorticoids synergistically enhance nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic>-induced toll-like receptor 2 expression via a negative cross-talk with p38 MAP kinase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>17263</fpage><lpage>17270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11867630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M112190200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory subtypes in asthma: assessment and identification using induced sputum</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2006.00784.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singanayagam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhaled corticosteroids and risk of pneumonia: evidence for and against the proposed association</article-title><source>QJM</source><year>2010</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/qjmed/hcq023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starner</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrout</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appelbaum</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subinhibitory concentrations of azithromycin decrease nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> biofilm formation and diminish established biofilms</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2008</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17954687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AAC.00607-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2223912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burpo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a ferrous iron-responsive two-component system in nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>6162</fpage><lpage>6173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.01465-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3486404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalalvand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mörgelin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riesbeck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> acquires vitronectin via the ubiquitous Protein F to subvert host innate immunity</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23387957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/mmi.12164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swords</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godzicki</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukofzer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitten</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VonCannon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sialylation of lipooligosaccharides promotes biofilm formation by nontypeable <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic></article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2004</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14688087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.72.1.106-113.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC343998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azoulaydupuis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocidalo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergogneberezin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity and local delivery of azithromycin in a mouse model of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> lung infection</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1992</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1412</fpage><lpage>1417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1324644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.36.7.1412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC191595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Berge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiemstra</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of glucocorticoids in asthma</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>2434</fpage><lpage>2435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22187996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMc1112547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asthma: defining of the persistent adult phenotypes</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16935691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)69290-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asthma phenotypes: the evolution from clinical to molecular approaches</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22561835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm.2678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitby</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanWagoner</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stull</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional profile of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic>: effects of iron and heme</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>5640</fpage><lpage>5645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.00417-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1540045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nahm</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briles</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intranasal immunization of mice with PspA (Pneumococcal surface protein A) can prevent intranasal carriage, pulmonary infection, and sepsis with <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9086139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/513980</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S1</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd1.tif" id="d35e4647" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S2</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd2.tif" id="d35e4652" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S3</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd3.tif" id="d35e4657" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S4</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd4.tif" id="d35e4662" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S5</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd5.tif" id="d35e4667" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S6</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd6.tif" id="d35e4672" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S7</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd7.tif" id="d35e4677" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S8</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd8.tif" id="d35e4682" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S9</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd9.tif" id="d35e4687" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Figure S10</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="tif" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd10.tif" id="d35e4692" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Table S1</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd11.docx" id="d35e4698" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd12" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Table S2</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd12.docx" id="d35e4703" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd13" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Table S3</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd13.docx" id="d35e4708" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd14" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Table S4</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd14.docx" id="d35e4713" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd15" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Table S5</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd15.docx" id="d35e4718" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd16" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Supplementary Legends</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd16.docx" id="d35e4723" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd17" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p><bold>Review Process File</bold></p><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="emmm0007-1018-sd17.pdf" id="d35e4728" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article>