
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1821</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">mtna</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101581621</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5862396</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5862396.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5862396</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5862396</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29499953</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2017.12.022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2162-2531(18)30001-5</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MicroRNA-140 Inhibits the Epithelial-Mesenchymal Transition and Metastasis in Colorectal Cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiazhi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names initials="K">Kun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="L">Lihui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenyue</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="L">Lu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names initials="S">Shujun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="B">Bo</given-names></name><email>songbo9177@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">∗∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="L">Lianhong</given-names></name><email>lilianhong917@126.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Dalian Medical University, Dalian 116044, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>The Key Laboratory of Tumor Stem Cell Research of Liaoning Province, Dalian Medical University, Dalian 116044, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Teaching Laboratory of Morphology, Dalian Medical University, Dalian 116044, China</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Oncology Radiology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian 116023, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author: Lianhong Li, MD, Department of Pathology, Dalian Medical University, No. 9 West Section, Lvshun South Road, Dalian 116044, China. <email>lilianhong917@126.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>Corresponding author: Bo Song, PhD, Department of Pathology, Dalian Medical University, No. 9 West Section, Lvshun South Road, Dalian 116044, China. <email>songbo9177@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">302819</issue-id><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>04</day><month>01</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="30" journal-id="Mol Ther Nucleic Acids" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9641031"><article-title>Retraction Notice to: MicroRNA-140 Inhibits the Epithelial-Mesenchymal Transition and Metastasis in Colorectal Cancer</article-title><volume>30</volume><date><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><source>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2022.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9641031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36381580</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="abs0010"><p>MicroRNA-140, a cartilage-specific microRNA, has recently been implicated in the cancer progression. However, the comprehensive role of miR-140 in the invasion and metastasis of colorectal cancer (CRC) is still not fully understood. In this study, we confirmed that miR-140 downregulates SMAD family member 3 (Smad3), which is a key downstream effector of the TGF-β signaling pathway, at the translational level in the CRC cell lines. Ectopic expression of miR-140 inhibits the process of epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT), at least partially through targeting Smad3, and induces the suppression of migratory and invasive capacities of CRC cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. miR-140 also attenuates CRC cell proliferation possibly via downregulating Samd3. Furthermore, overexpression of miR-140 inhibits the tumor formation and metastasis of CRC <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, and silenced Smad3 has the similar effect. Additionally, miR-140 expression is decreased in the clinical primary CRC specimens and appears as a progressive reduction in the metastatic specimens, whereas Smad3 is overexpressed in the CRC samples. Taken together, our findings suggest that miR-140 might be a key suppressor of CRC progression and metastasis through inhibiting EMT process by targeting Smad3. miR-140 may represent a novel candidate for CRC treatment.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>MicroRNA-140-5p</kwd><kwd>Smad3</kwd><kwd>metastasis</kwd><kwd>epithelial-mesenchymal transition</kwd><kwd>TGF-β signaling</kwd><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Metastasis is the biological feature and leading cause of death by malignant tumor. It consists of sequential and interrelated steps,<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and many of them are favored by epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT).<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Obtaining the mesenchymal state endows cells with enhanced migration and invasion, induces stemness, and prevents apoptosis and senescence, allowing their subsequent roles in the initiation of metastasis.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The EMT process has been reported in a variety of epithelial malignancies, including colorectal cancer (CRC).<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p id="p0015">CRC is the third leading cause of death from cancer, and it has been estimated to be responsible for 50,000 deaths per year in the United States.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Although surgery combined with adjuvant therapy has increased the prognosis of CRC, metastasis still occurs in approximately half of all CRC patients at the time of diagnosis or after intended curative treatment, giving rise to a poor 5-year survival rate of slightly greater than 10%.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> A good explanation of metastasis of CRC would be helpful for the development of effective therapeutic strategies.</p><p id="p0020">MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are noncoding small RNA molecules that post-transcriptionally regulate protein expression via binding to the 3′ UTR of the target genes.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Some studies have shown the importance of miRNAs in the regulation of EMT either as an inhibitor or as a promoter.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> SMAD family member 3 (Smad3) is one of the key downstream factors of transforming growth factor β (TGF-β signaling pathway, which is a critical inducer of the EMT in the malignant tumor, such as in CRC.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> TGF-β binds with its two transmembrane receptors, type I (TGFBRI) and type II (TGFBRII), leading to the phosphorylation of Smad2 and Smad3, which translocate to the nucleus with Smad4, where it can regulate the downstream EMT-related gene expression.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Importantly, Smad3 has been confirmed as the direct target of microRNA-140-5p (miR-140) in a pluripotent mouse embryonic fibroblast cell line and alveolar epithelial cells (AECs).<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> We previously found that the Smad3 protein is downregulated by miR-140 in CRC cells using western blot.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">miR-140 was first shown to be specifically expressed in the cartilage of developing zebrafish and mouse embryos during both long and flat bone development.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Later, Miyaki et al.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> reported that miR-140 loss induces osteoarthritis (OA)-like changes <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Our laboratory is the first one that investigated the mechanism of miR-140 in the tumorigenesis, to the best of our knowledge.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> We found that miR-140 expression is reduced in the CRC specimens and that the ectopic expression of miR-140 can suppress cell proliferation and induce cell-cycle G1 and G2 phase arrest, mediated in part through the downregulation of HDAC4 in the CRC and osteosarcoma cells.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Several recent studies have demonstrated that miR-140 can inhibit tumor invasion and metastasis in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) through downregulating TGFBRI, FGF9, or IGF1R.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> miR-140 can suppress CRC stem cell (CSC) survival and its metastatic potential by inhibiting Smad2 and autophagy.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Downregulation of miR-140 induces EMT and promotes esophageal cancer cell invasion via targeting Slug.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Zhang et al.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> reported that miR-140 inhibits the progression of CRC by targeting VEGFA. Our recent work showed that miR-140 suppresses CRC invasion and metastasis by targeting ADAMTS5 and IGFBP5.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> However, the impact and comprehensive mechanism of miR-140 in the invasion and metastasis of CRC still needs to be elucidated.</p><p id="p0030">In this study, we found that Smad3 is the direct target of miR-140 in the CRC cell lines via the luciferase assay, and miR-140 regulates the expression of Smad3 at the translational level. Ectopic expression of miR-140 inhibits the process of EMT, at least partially through targeting Smad3, and therefore suppresses the migratory and invasive capacities of CRC cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. miR-140 attenuates CRC cell proliferation, possibly via downregulating Samd3. Subcutaneous or tail vein injection of HCT 116 cells transfected with lentiviral vectors of miR-140 or short hairpin RNA (shRNA) against Smad3 significantly decreases the growth of local tumor nodules or inhibits the pulmonary metastasis potential in BALB/c mice, respectively. Furthermore, the expression level of miR-140 was significantly decreased in the clinical primary CRC specimens compared to the corresponding adjacent normal colorectal tissues. A progressive reduction of miR-140 was found from the primary tumors to the metastatic tumors. The expression level of Smad3 protein was significantly decreased in the corresponding adjacent normal colorectal tissues compared to the clinical primary CRC specimens. miR-140 might be a key inhibitor of CRC progression and metastasis through suppressing the EMT process by targeting the downstream Smad3 of the TGF-α signaling pathway.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>miR-140 Regulates Smad3 in CRC Cells</title><p id="p0035">Bioinformatics analysis indicated that the 3′UTR of Smad3 mRNA has a binding site of miR-140. To investigate the direct binding and repression effect between miR-140 and Smad3, a luciferase assay was carried out. As <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A shows, cotransfection of miR-140 and Smad3-3′UTR-wt (miR-140+Smad3-3′UTR-wt) reduced the luciferase activity, compared with cotransfection of negative miRNA and Smad3-3′UTR-wt (NC+Smad3-3′UTR-wt), and such suppressive effect was not found in the cotransfection of miR-140 and Smad3-3′UTR-mut (miR-140+ Smad3-3′UTR-mut). We then overexpressed miR-140 by transient transfection in HCT116 and RKO cells using Oligofectamine, and the successful transfection of miR-140 was confirmed by real-time qRT-PCR (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>). The siRNA against Smad3 (siSmad3) was used as a positive control. CRC cells (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>, Con) and the negative miRNA (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>, NC) were the negative controls. We accessed the expression level of Smad3 mRNA using real-time qRT-PCR. As <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B shows, there was only a slight decrease in Smad3 mRNA expression after miR-140 transfection; by contrast, knockdown of Smad3 dramatically induced the Smad3 mRNA degradation. We next measured the protein level of Smad3 using western blot. Overexpression of miR-140 significantly reduced the Smad3 protein expression in both of these two cell lines compared with the negative controls, while Smad3 siRNA transfection had a similar effect (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C). The active Smad3, phosphorylating Smad3 (p-Smad3) was reduced as well (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C). The real-time qRT-PCR and western blot results indicated that miR-140 significantly inhibits the expression of Smad3 protein without considerable degradation of mRNA.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Smad3 Is the Direct Target of miR-140 in CRC Cells</p><p>(A) A predicted miR-501 binding site existed in the 3′UTR of Smad3 mRNA (wt) and its mutant type (mut) were generated in the binding site. Transfection of miR-140 mimic reduced the firefly luciferase activity of Smad3-3′UTR-wt compared to the Smad3-3′UTR-mut; the negative miRNA transfection with Smad3-3′UTR-wt (Negative miRNA+Smad3-3′UTR-wt) was also the negative control. n = 3; *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01. (B) Ectopic expression of miR-140 decreased the mRNA level slightly, whereas siRNA against Smad3 dramatically degraded the Smad3 mRNA by real-time qRT-PCR. HCT116 and RKO cells were transfected with miR-140 mimic (miR-140) using Oligofectamine. CRC cells alone (Con) and negative miRNA (NC) were the negative controls, and siRNA against Smad3 (siSmad3) was the positive control. GAPDH was used as an endogenous control. n = 3; **p &lt; 0.01. (C) Transfection of miR-140 or Smad3 knockdown inhibited Smad3 and phosphorylating Smad3 (p-Smad3) protein levels using western blot analysis. The quantitative results of western blot were analyzed by Gel-Pro Analyzer 4.0 software, and GAPDH was used as an endogenous control. n = 3; **p &lt; 0.01. (D) Knockdown of endogenous miR-140 restored the expressions of Smad3 and p-Smad3 by western blot analysis. HCT116 and RKO cells were transfected with miR-140 inhibitor (140i) using Lipofectamine 2000. CRC cells (Con), scrambled miRNA inhibitor (i-NC), and co-transfection of miR-140 inhibitor and siRNA against Smad3 (140i+si) were the negative controls. The quantitative results of western blot were analyzed by Gel-Pro Analyzer 4.0 software, and GAPDH was used as an endogenous control. n = 3; **p &lt; 0.01. The data are presented as mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0040">To further confirm Smad3 is regulated by miR-140, we performed the loss-of-function experiment by knocking down the endogenous miR-140 with inhibitor of miR-140 in HCT116 and RKO cells. CRC cells (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D, Con) and scrambled miRNA inhibitor (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D, i-NC) were used as the negative controls. Meanwhile, to more accurately prove the relationship between miR-140 and Smad3, we co-transfected miR-140 inhibitor and siRNA against Smad3 (140i+si) into the CRC cells and considered it as a negative control. Our results showed that knocking down endogenous miR-140 could restore the expressions of Smad3 and p-Smad3, compared to the negative controls (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). Based on these data, Smad3 is directly regulated by miR-140 in the translational level in the CRC cells.</p><p id="p0045">Subsequently we examined the expressions of TGF-β signaling-pathway-related proteins Smad2 and Smad4 using western blot. Smad2 has previously been confirmed to be the direct target of miR-140.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Our results showed that ectopic expression of miR-140 reduced Smad2 protein expression in both of these cell lines compared with the negative controls, while Smad4 protein was also reduced (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref>). Smad4 was not found to be the predicting target of miR-140, using miRNA bioinformatics analysis. A recent study demonstrated that Smad4 protein is decreased in shRNA against Smad2-transfected bone-marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells (BMSCs).<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> In combination with these data, miR-140 could inhibit the TGF-β signaling-pathway-related proteins Smad2 and Smad3 directly and indirectly downregulate Smad4, possibly via decreased Smad2 expression.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>miR-140 Represses the CRC Cell Migration and Invasion</title><p id="p0050">Since Smad3 was confirmed to be the target of miR-140, we then investigated the role of miR-140 in the migration and invasion in CRC cells using scratch-wound and Transwell chamber assays. HCT116 and RKO cells were transfected with miR-140 mimic or siRNA against Smad3, and the successful transfection of miR-140 or Smad3 was confirmed by real-time qRT-PCR (data not shown). The scratch-wound assay and Transwell chamber assay without Matrigel showed that miR-140 overexpression significantly attenuated the migratory capacity in these two cell lines (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>A and 2B). Meanwhile, the Transwell chamber assay with Matrigel demonstrated that miR-140 overexpression dramatically decreased the number of CRC cells passing through the membrane (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>C). These repressive effects of miR-140 on migration and invasion were similar to those induced by Smad3 siRNA in CRC cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>A–2C).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>miR-140 Represses the Migratory and Invasive Capacities of CRC Cells</p><p>(A) The scratch-wound assay showed that miR-140 overexpression or silenced Smad3 attenuated the migratory capacity in HCT116 and RKO cells compared to the negative controls, CRC cells (Con) and negative miRNA (NC). **p &lt; 0.01. (B) miR-140 overexpression or silenced Smad3 decreased the migratory capacity measured by the Transwell migration assay. **p &lt; 0.01. (C) The Transwell invasion assay showed that the ectopic expression of miR-140 or silenced Smad3 decreased the CRC cells passing through the membrane. **p &lt; 0.01. (D) The scratch-wound assay showed that miR-140 knockdown enhanced the migratory capacity in HCT116 and RKO cells compared to the negative controls (Con, i-NC, and 140i+si). **p &lt; 0.01. (E) The transwell migration assay showed that miR-140 knockdown promoted the CRC cell migratory capacity. **p &lt; 0.01. (F) The transwell invasion assay showed that miR-140 knockdown enhanced the CRC cell invasive capacity. **p &lt; 0.01. Each independent experiment was repeated three times, and data are presented as mean ± SD. Similar results were obtained, and the representative photographs are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0055">On the contrary, knocking down of endogenous miR-140 expression by the inhibitor significantly enhanced the migratory and invasive capacities of HCT116 and RKO cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>D–2F). These results, therefore, indicated that miR-140 is a repressor of migration and invasion in CRC.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>miR-140 Suppresses the CRC Cell Proliferation</title><p id="p0060">We also investigated the impact of Smad3 on the CRC cell proliferation. First, a CCK-8 assay was performed. As <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A shows, either upregulated miR-140 or silenced Smad3 inhibited the CRC cell growth significantly when compared to the negative controls. We next performed the soft agar colony formation assay and counted the colonies on day 14 after plating. The results showed that both enforced expression of miR-140 and silenced Smad3 suppressed the number of colonies remarkably, as compared to the negative controls (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B). On the contrary, knockdown of the endogenous miR-140 reversed the suppressive effect on the cell growth and colony formation capacities mediated by miR-140 overexpression (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>C and 3D). Taken together, these findings revealed that manipulated expression of miR-140 inhibits the CRC cell proliferation via downregulation of Smad3.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>miR-140 Suppresses CRC Cell Growth</p><p>(A) Both enforced expression of miR-140 and silenced Smad3 decreased the cell proliferation and the number of colonies remarkably, as compared to the negative controls (Con and NC) measured by CCK-8 assay. **p &lt; 0.01. (B) The colony formation assay showed that miR-140 overexpression and silenced Smad3 decreased the number of colonies as compared to the negative controls (Con and NC). **p &lt; 0.01. (C) The CCK-8 assay showed that miR-140 knockdown promoted the CRC cell proliferative potential as compared to the negative controls (Con, i-NC, and 140i+si). **p &lt; 0.01. (D) The number of colonies was increased by miR-140 knockdown when compared to the negative controls (Con, i-NC, and 140i+si). **p &lt; 0.01. Each independent experiment was repeated three times, and data are presented as mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>miR-140 Inhibits EMT in CRC Cells</title><p id="p0065">Given the relationship between miR-140 and Smad3, and the suppression of miR-140/Smad3 in the CRC cell migration and invasion, we then investigated the role and the underlying mechanism of miR-140 in the EMT process. The expressions of the epithelial marker E-cadherin and the mesenchymal marker vimentin were examined by western blot. miR-140 overexpression increased the level of E-cadherin and decreased the level of vimentin compared with the negative controls, and siRNA against Smad3 resembled the effect of miR-140 overexpression (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). Conversely, knockdown of miR-140 suppressed the expression of E-cadherin and promoted the expression of vimentin (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>B). These changes in EMT-associated markers were further confirmed by the immunofluorescence assay (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref>C and 4D). Our data suggested that miR-140 represses the EMT process and the subsequent invasive phenotype in CRC cells.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>miR-140 Inhibits EMT in CRC Cells</p><p>(A) Enforced expression of miR-140 or siSmad3 increased E-cadherin protein levels and decreased vimentin and Zeb1 protein levels compared with the negative controls by western blot analysis. (B) Knockdown of miR-140 reversed the protein expressions of E-cadherin, vimentin, and Zeb1 compared to miR-140 overexpression. (C) Immunofluorescence assay showed that miR-140 overexpression and Smad3 knockdown promoted E-cadherin expression (red) and suppressed vimentin expression (green) as compared to the negative controls (Con and NC). (D) E-cadherin expression was inhibited and vimentin expression was increased by miR-140 knockdown as compared to the negative controls (Con, i-NC, and 140i+si). Scale bars, 25 μm. **p &lt; 0.01. Each independent experiment was repeated three times, and data are presented as mean ± SD.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0070">Transcriptional factors from the zinc-finger E-box-binding homeobox factor (Zeb) family have been reported to be the key regulators of EMT through interacting with Smads to enhance the TGF-β signaling pathway.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Compared to Zeb2, Zeb1 is reported to synergize with Smad-mediated transcriptional activation.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Previous studies have demonstrated that TGF-β signaling leads to the activation of Smad proteins, especially Smad3, and then induces the expression of E26 transformation-specific 1 (Ets1), an upstream component of Zeb1, which, in turn, stimulates the promoter activity of Zeb1. Zeb1 can repress the transcription of E-cadherin through binding to its E-box region of promoter.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Therefore, we examined the expression of Zeb1 using western blot. The results showed that upregulation of miR-140 inhibited the expression of Zeb1 protein, compared to the negative controls, and that siRNA against Smad3 showed the same trend as miR-140 overexpression did (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). Furthermore, knockdown of miR-140 reversed the expression level of Zeb1 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>B). miR-140 suppresses the migratory and invasive capacities by inhibiting the EMT process, and this is achieved, possibly, through targeting Samd3 and subsequent reduced Zeb1 expression to interrupt the TGF-β signaling pathway.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>miR-140 Inhibits the CRC Progression and Metastasis <italic toggle="yes">In Vivo</italic></title><p id="p0075">Given the observed effects of miR-140 on CRC cell proliferation, migration, and invasion <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, we subsequently explored whether miR-140 inhibits the tumor progression and metastasis <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. First, we infected HCT116 cells with either lentiviral vectors of miR-140 (Len-140) or shRNA against Smad3 (shSmad3). At 72 hr after infection, the green fluorescence was viewed under the microscope (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3</xref>A). The successful transfection of miR-140 and siRNA against Smad3 was then confirmed by real-time qRT-PCR (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S3</xref>B and S3C). We then injected the cells subcutaneously on the backs of BALB/c mice. The subcutaneous tumor growth was monitored for 4 weeks, and the mice were sacrificed. We found that the local tumor developed in all the mice. However, the tumor volumes in the miR-140-injected group were markedly smaller than those in the negative-control-injected group at all the time points (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>A and 5B), and silenced Smad3 by shRNA reduced the tumor volume similarly with the miR-140-injected group.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>miR-140 Inhibits the CRC Development and Metastasis <italic toggle="yes">In Vivo</italic></p><p>HCT116 cells were transduced with either lentiviral vectors of miR-140 (Len-140) or shRNA against Smad3 (shSmad3), and cells infected with lentivirus control were the negative control (Len-NC). (A) The HCT116 cells transduced with lentiviral vectors of miR-140 (Len-140), negative control (Len-NC), and shRNA against Smad3 (shSmad3) were injected subcutaneously on the backs of BALB/c mice respectively, and the subcutaneous tumor growth was monitored for 4 weeks (n = 6 for each group). (B) miR-140 overexpression or silenced Smad3 markedly decreased the tumor volume compared with the negative control. The values were shown as mean ± SD. **p &lt; 0.01. (C) The local tumors were fixed, paraffin embedded, cut into sections, and stained by immunohistochemistry. The expressions of Smad3, p-Smad3, Zeb1, and vimentin in the groups treated with either miR-140 or shRNA-Smad3 were significantly decreased as compared to the negative control, whereas E-cadherin was upregulated. Representative images were shown (left panel: 100×; right panel: 200×). Scale bars, 50 μm. (D) These proteins were examined by western blot in the mouse tumor tissues and showed the same tendency as immunohistochemistry did. Representative images are shown. (E) HCT116 cells infected with lentiviral vectors were injected into BALB/c mice through the tail vein and monitored for 8 weeks. Lungs and liver were collected for H&amp;E staining. The negative control group induced the visible pulmonary metastasis in all mice (n = 6). Overexpressing miR-140 by lentivirus induced pulmonary metastasis in 4 out of 6 mice, including 1 case of macroscopic metastatic nodules and 3 cases of microscopic nodules (n = 6). Knocking down Smad3 induced microscopic pulmonary metastasis in 4 out of 6 mice, and the remaining 2 mice failed to form pulmonary metastasis (n = 6). The liver was barely involved in all of the three groups. Representative images are shown (upper panel: 100×; lower panel: 200×). Scale bars, 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">We subsequently used immunohistochemistry to detect the expressions of Smad3, p-Smad3, Zeb1, E-cadherin, and vimentin in the three groups of mouse xenograft tumor tissues. As <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>C shows, the expressions of Smad3, p-Smad3, and the downstream effector Zeb1 in the groups treated with either miR-140 or shRNA-Smad3 were significantly decreased as compared to the negative control. The EMT marker E-cadherin was upregulated, whereas vimentin was downregulated. We also measured the levels of these proteins using western blot in the mouse tumor tissues. As expected, their expressions showed the same tendency as immunohistochemistry did (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>D). These data indicated that the miR-140/Smad3 axis inhibits the tumor progression <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><p id="p0085">To further understand the impact of miR-140 on the CRC metastasis, we injected HCT116 cells infected with lentiviral vectors into BALB/c mice through the tail vein. Eight weeks later, we euthanized the mice and dissected out the lungs and liver for H&amp;E staining. We found that the negative-control group induced the visible metastatic nodules in the lungs in all six mice (6/6; <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>E). However, overexpressing miR-140 by lentivirus induced pulmonary metastasis in 4 out of 6 mice, including 1 case of visible metastatic nodules and 3 cases of microscopic nodules (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>E). As for knockdown of Smad3, 4 out of 6 mice showed the microscopic pulmonary metastatic nodules, and the remaining 2 mice were not involved (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>E; <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The liver was barely involved in all of the three groups. Together, these results demonstrated that miR-140 has a suppressive impact on CRC metastasis.<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Pulmonary Metastasis Rate in Different Mice Models</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Len-NC</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Len-140</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">shSmad3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pulmonary metastasis rate (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 (6/6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7 (4/6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7 (4/6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">p Value</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.05<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.05<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0010">Compared to Len-NC.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>miR-140 Is Associated with CRC Progression and Metastasis</title><p id="p0090">To further determine the significance of miR-140 on CRC progression and metastasis, we detected the expression level of miR-140 on a cohort of CRC specimens, including 31 CRC cases, 11 cases with lymph node metastasis, and 2 cases with liver metastasis, by real-time qRT-PCR. We found that miR-140 was significantly downregulated in the primary CRC tissues compared to the adjacent normal mucosa (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A, p &lt; 0.05). We then selected the 13 out of 31 cases of CRC patients with lymph node or liver metastasis and extracted RNA from the metastatic tumor tissues. After comparing miR-140 expression levels in the paired primary and metastatic tumor tissues, we found that miR-140 was significantly downregulated in the lymph node and liver metastatic tumors (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>B, p &lt; 0.05). These results further confirmed that miR-140 might be a key repressor of CRC development and metastasis<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>miR-140 Expression Is Reversely Correlated with CRC Development and Metastasis, Whereas Smad3 Expression Is Positively Correlated with CRC Development</p><p>(A) A cohort of CRC specimens, including 31 paired CRC tissues and adjacent colorectal mucosa, were selected, and the expression levels of miR-140 were measured by real-time qRT-PCR. MiR-140 was significantly downregulated in the primary CRC tissues compared to the adjacent normal mucosa. (B) Then, 13 out of 31 cases of CRC patients with lymph node or liver metastasis were selected, and RNA was extracted from the metastatic tumor tissues. miR-140 was significantly downregulated in the lymph node, and liver metastatic tumors were compared with the paired primary tumor tissues. The expression level of miR-140 was normalized by the internal control RNU6B in each sample. (C) Immunohistochemistry analysis of Smad3 expression was performed in the CRC cohort. Smad3 protein was overexpressed in the CRC tissues compared to the adjacent normal mucosa. Each experiment was repeated 3 times; data are presented as means ± SD. *p &lt; 0.05. Scale bars, 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Smad3 Is Associated with the Development of CRC</title><p id="p0095">We also performed immunohistochemistry to assess the expression of Smad3 protein in the CRC cohort. Smad3 protein was located in the cytoplasm of colorectal glandular cells and CRC cells. Compared with the adjacent normal colorectal tissues, Smad3 protein was overexpressed in the CRC samples (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>C, p &lt; 0.05), indicating that Smad3 is related to the development of CRC. We noticed a tendency that miR-140 was downregulated, whereas Smad3 was upregulated, in the CRC tissues compared to the normal colorectal tissues, further implying the negative regulatory relationship between miR-140 and Smad3 in CRC.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0100">The regulation of EMT by miRNAs has recently been highlighted.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In the present study, we revealed a molecular mechanism of CRC development, invasion, and metastasis mediated by miR-140 through interrupting the EMT process.</p><p id="p0105">EMT is an indispensable process in the development, differentiation, and repair of multiple tissues and organs; however, inappropriate reactivation of EMT can promote carcinoma progression through a variety of mechanisms.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The TGF-β signaling pathway, an essential driver of EMT, can stimulate tumor invasion and metastasis in a Smad3-dependent manner.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> The knockdown of Smad3 in MDA-MB-231 cells can prolong the latency and delay the bone metastasis of breast cancer. Here, we confirmed that Samd3 was the direct target of miR-140 in the CRC cell lines via the luciferase assay and that the active p-Smad3 was reduced simultaneously (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Enforced miR-140 expression inhibited the CRC cell migration and invasion, and the inhibitory effect was due to the suppression of Smad3 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). It has been reported that the active phosphorylated Smad2/3 binds to Zeb1 to enhance the effect of the TGF-β signaling pathway on the EMT process.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Our results showed that miR-140 repressed the EMT process of CRC cells as a consequence of inhibition of Smad3, p-Smad3, and subsequent reduced Zeb1 expression (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), thus playing a critical role in the suppression of CRC cell migration and invasion. Consistent with this finding, a recent study found that downregulation of miR-140 induces EMT and promotes esophageal cancer cell invasion by targeting Slug.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> We further determined the impacts of miR-140 on the CRC metastasis by constructing a mouse metastatic model. Overexpression of miR-140 significantly inhibited the metastatic potential of CRC cells in BALB/c mice (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>; <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A recent study also reported that CRC stem cells with highly expressed miR-140 produce smaller tumor burden and fail to form the lung or liver metastasis, and this is mediated by the suppression of Smad2 and autophagy.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Our results both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> provide new evidence to support the involvement of miR-140 in the suppression of CRC invasion and metastasis via Smad3. We also confirmed the decrease of Smad2 protein by miR-140 in our study. Smad4 protein was decreased, possibly, due to the inhibition of Smad2 induced by the overexpression of miR-140.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Taken together, miR-140 inhibits EMT, possibly, via directly targeting TGF-β signaling-pathway-related proteins Smad2 and Smad3 and via indirectly downregulating Smad4, resulting in the suppression of migration, invasion, and metastasis in the CRC. Except the aforementioned targets of miR-140, VEGF-A, ADAMTS5, and IGFBP5 have been confirmed to be involved in the inhibition of CRC invasion and metastasis induced by miR-140.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Thus, miR-140 inhibits CRC invasion and metastasis through regulating multiple mRNAs and might be a key suppressive regulator.</p><p id="p0110">Moreover, we investigated the clinical relevance of miR-140 by comparing the expression level of miR-140 on a cohort of CRC specimens with and without metastasis using real-time qRT-PCR. We found that miR-140 was significantly downregulated in the primary CRC tissues as compared to the adjacent normal mucosa (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A). This is consistent with our previous study and a recent study.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Interestingly, we found that miR-140 was progressively downregulated in the lymph node and liver metastatic tumors as compared to the primary CRC tumors (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>B). In accordance with our findings, Zhai et al.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> also showed the same trend of miR-140 expression in 18 archival CRC patient samples with metastasis. The clinical significance of miR-140 on the CRC samples further confirms the role of miR-140 in the CRC metastasis. We also examined the expression of Smad3 protein in the CRC cohort and found that Smad3 was significantly overexpressed in the CRC specimens compared to the adjacent normal colorectal tissues (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>C). In line with our results, Korchynskyi et al.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> reported that Smad3 is upregulated in the CRC tissues, compared to the epithelial mucosa of normal colon, using immunohistochemistry. These findings suggest that Smad3 overexpression is correlated with the development of CRC.</p><p id="p0115">In addition to the inhibitory effect of miR-140 on the CRC invasion and metastasis, we revealed a function of miR-140 in the growth of CRC <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Our <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments showed that miR-140 suppresses the cell proliferation and colony formation capacity of CRC cells via downregulation of Smad3 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). It is well known that miRNAs exert their regulatory function on targeting multiple mRNAs. Previously, our group has reported that miR-140 inhibits CRC cell proliferation by the suppression of HDAC4.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Zhai et al.’s study showed that the suppressive effect of miR-140 on CRC cell proliferation is partially due to the downregulation of Smad2.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> We further examined the function of miR-140 in CRC development and found that miR-140 overexpression remarkably reduces the tumor burden and that silenced Smad3 has a similar effect (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>A and 5B). Taken together, our work reveals a novel regulatory mechanism of miR-140 in CRC growth, invasion, and metastasis.</p><p id="p0120">Recently several studies have suggested that miR-140 is a tumor suppressor in other solid tumors, including HCC, NSCLC, and esophageal cancer through targeting some oncogenes.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Judging from the combination of previous CRC studies and our present results, miR-140 might have the potential to be a therapeutic candidate for treating cancer.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Since the first miRNA, lin-4, was discovered in 1993, multiple miRNAs have been revealed as oncogenes or tumor suppressors in tumorigenesis and progression. The famous miR-34a has become the first miRNA to start the clinical trial, opening a novel era in cancer treatment.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Compared to traditional gene-based therapy, miRNAs have the ability to regulate several cellular pathways simultaneously and make them suitable for the treatment of the multipathway-induced diseases such as cancer.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref></p><p id="p0125">In conclusion, in this study, we provided the experimental evidence both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> to support the suppressive effect of miR-140 on CRC growth, invasion, and metastasis. This is achieved largely due to the downregulation of Smad3 and the subsequent repression of the EMT process. The reduced expression of miR-140 in the primary and metastatic samples of CRC further supports the role of miR-140 in CRC progression and metastasis. As miRNA-based therapy is currently in clinical trial, our results indicate that miR-140 may be a novel candidate for treating CRC.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Cell Lines and Culture</title><p id="p0130">The human CRC cell lines HCT116 and RKO were purchased from the Cell Bank of Type Culture Collection, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai, China. HCT116 cells were maintained in McCoy’s 5A media (GIBCO), and RKO cells were cultured in DMEM media (GIBCO) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; GIBCO) in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> container at 37°C.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Clinical CRC Specimens</title><p id="p0135">Specimens from 31 CRC patients who underwent surgical resection in the First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University, Dalian, China, were enrolled in this study. The use of human tissue samples was in accordance with institutional ethics requirements and was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee, The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University. Each patient sample contains normal colon mucosa, which were resected within at least 5 cm of the tumor margin. Eleven cases had lymph node metastasis, and 2 cases had liver metastasis. All patients provided written informed consent prior to participation in this study. The primary and metastatic CRC specimens were histologically examined by H&amp;E staining.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>miRNA and siRNA Transfections</title><p id="p0140">HCT116 and RKO cells were plated in six-well plates at 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> per well and then transfected with 100 nM of either miR-140 mimics or negative miRNA (Invitrogen) after 24 hr by Oligofectamine (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s protocols, respectively. Small interfering RNA (siRNA) against Smad3 (Invitrogen) was transfected by Oligofectamine at a final concentration of 100 nM in Opti-MEM I Reduced Serum Media (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The transfected cells were harvested for RNA isolation and protein extraction at 24 hr and 48 hr post-transfection, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>miR-140 Knockdown</title><p id="p0145">To knock down the endogenous miR-140, RKO and HCT116 cells were transfected with 100 nM scrambled miRNA inhibitor or miR-140 inhibitor (Invitrogen) using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) in six-well plates (2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well), respectively. Co-transfection of miR-140 inhibitor and siRNA against Smad3 in the CRC cells was used as a negative control.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Luciferase Assay</title><p id="p0150">The wild-type or mutant double-stranded oligonucleotides of Smad3 3′UTR were synthesized and inserted into the sites of SacI and XhoI of the GP-miRGLO vector (GenePharma, Shanghai, China). The sequences are listed in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>.</p><p id="p0155">HCT116 and RKO cells were plated in triplicate in 24-well plates. After 24 hr, cells in each well were co-transfected with 100 nM miR-140 mimic or negative miRNA and 200 ng GP-miRGLO constructs containing wild-type or mutant 3′UTR of Smad3 mRNA using Lipofectamine 2000. 20 ng pRL-TK Renilla plasmid (GenePharma, Shanghai, China) was used as the normalization. All the cells were harvested at 48 hr after transfection, and the luciferase activity was measured using the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega). Firefly luciferase activity was normalized to Renilla internal control for each condition and then compared to the negative miRNA-transfected wells.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Scratch-Wound Assay</title><p id="p0160">To evaluate the effect of miR-140 on CRC cell migration, a scratch-wound assay was performed in the HCT116 and RKO cells, miRNAs, miRNA inhibitors, or siRNA-transfected CRC cells. Upon reaching confluence, the monolayer cells were scraped with a 10-μL pipette tip to generate a scratch wound. The wounded surface was washed with 1× PBS to remove the cell debris and cultured in serum-free media. After 72 hr, the wound closures were photographed with a BZ-8100 microscope (Keyence, Osaka, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><title>Migration and Invasion Assays</title><p id="p0165">The <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> migration and invasion assays were performed using a Transwell chamber (Corning Costar), according to the protocol of the manufacturer. The HCT116 and RKO cells and miRNAs, miRNA inhibitors, or siRNA-transfected CRC cells were trypsinized and used for the migration and invasion assays at 48 hr after transfection, respectively.</p><p id="p0170">For the Transwell migration assay, the inserts were first rehydrated with serum-free media for 2 hr at room temperature. After rehydration, the media was carefully removed, and 200 μL of cell suspension with 3 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells in serum-free media was seeded into the upper chambers (24-well insert; pore size, 8 μm), respectively, while 600 μL of media supplemented with 10% FBS was added in the lower chambers. 24 hr after incubation, the non-migrating cells on the top side of the inserts were gently removed with a cotton swab. The inserts were then fixed by 4% methanol for 30 min and stained with 0.05% crystal violet for 15 min. The average migratory cells were counted by picking up 5 fields randomly each time under the microscope. The experiments were repeated 3 times.</p><p id="p0175">For the Transwell invasion assay, the inserts were coated with a thin layer of Matrigel. Briefly, 60 μL Matrigel was diluted by precooled serum-free media in 1:4 ratios and was added to the middle of the bottom of the Transwell chamber and incubated for 1 hr at 37°C. The remaining protocol was the same as for the Transwell migration assay.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p id="p0180">The parental and transfected CRC cells were trypsinized, resuspended, and seeded on the coverslips; cultured for 48 hr; and then fixed with 4% formalin, permeabilized in 0.5% Triton X-100, blocked with 2% BSA, and thereafter incubated with mouse anti-E-cadherin monoclonal antibody (mAb) (1:50; #610181, BD Transduction Laboratories) or rabbit anti-vimentin mAb (1:50; ab92547, Abcam) overnight at 4°C, respectively. The cells were then incubated with rhodamine (tetramethylrhodamine [TRITC])-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG ([immunoglobulin G] H+L) (1:50; Proteintech) or Alexa Fluor 488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (heavy chain and light chain [H+L]) (1:100, Proteintech). Nuclei were stained using DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich). The protein labeling was visualized using a laser scanning confocal microscope (Leica).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.9"><title>CCK-8 Assay</title><p id="p0185">Cells were replated in 96-well plates at 1 × 10<sup>3</sup> per well after transfection with miRNA mimics, siRNA against Smad3, or miRNA inhibitors for 24 hr. At 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 days after transfection, the absorbance at 450 nm was measured after incubation with 10 μL Cell Counting Assay Kit-8 solution (Sigma) for 2 hr. All experiments were performed three times independently.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.10"><title>Colony Formation Assay</title><p id="p0190">Cells were trypsinized, counted, and seeded in the six-well plates in triplicate at 5 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells per well for the colony formation assay. During the colony growth, the culture medium was replaced every 2 days. After 14 days’ culture, the colonies were stained with 0.02% crystal violet for 1 hr and then were counted under an inverted phase-contrast microscope (Olympus IX71).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.11"><title>RNA Extraction</title><p id="p0195">Total RNAs, including miRNAs, were isolated from the CRC cells with or without transfection, using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p><p id="p0200">For human CRC formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) specimens, approximately 0.005 g for each sample was extracted. These samples were deparaffinized with xylene, hydrated by ethanol, and digested with proteinase K. Total RNA was isolated using the High Pure RNA Paraffin Kit (Roche, Germany), according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.12"><title>Real-Time qRT-PCR</title><p id="p0205">For real-time qRT-PCR analysis of miRNAs, cDNA was synthesized using the TaqMan microRNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Life Technologies). Real-time qRT-PCR analysis was performed on an MX3000P real-time PCR system (Agilent). The primers for miR-140 and endogenous control RNU6B were purchased from Ambion. The gene expression C<sub>T</sub> values of miRNAs from each sample were calculated by normalizing to RNU6B, and relative quantitation values were plotted.</p><p id="p0210">For real-time qRT-PCR analysis of mRNA expression, cDNA was synthesized using the PrimeScript RT Reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser (TaKaRa, Dalian, China). The qRT-PCR amplification for mRNAs was performed with SYBR Premix Ex TaqII (TaKaRa) on an Agilent MX3000P instrument. The gene expression C<sub>T</sub> values of mRNAs from each sample were calculated by normalizing to GAPDH, and relative quantitation values were plotted.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.13"><title>Protein Extraction and Western Blot</title><p id="p0215">CRC cells with or without transfection were scraped and lysed in 1× RIPA buffer (Sigma), and the proteins were extracted. Equal amounts of protein extract (50 μg) were denatured with 10% SDS-PAGE, transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes (Millipore), and blocked with 5% non-fat milk in TBS-Tween (TBST; 0.1 M, pH 7.4). Protein abundance of GAPDH (1:500, AP50811, Abgent) served as a control for protein loading.</p><p id="p0220">Each sample was treated with the primary antibodies, including mouse anti-Smad3 mAb (1:1,000; sc-101154, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), rabbit anti-p-Smad3 (Ser423/425) mAb (1:500; #9520, Cell Signaling Technology), mouse anti-E-cadherin mAb (1:1,000; 610181, BD Transduction Laboratories), rabbit anti-vimentin mAb (1:1,000; ab92547, Abcam); rabbit anti-Smad2 mAb (1:1,000; 12570-1-AP, Proteintech), rabbit anti-Smad4 mAb (1:1,000; 10231-1-AP, Proteintech), and rabbit anti-Zeb1 mAb (1:1,000; 21544-1-AP, Proteintech) at 4°C overnight. Membranes were incubated with secondary antibody, horseradish-peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated rabbit/mouse anti-IgG (1:16,000, LI-COR Biosciences), for 2 hr at room temperature. Protein bands were detected by the Odyssey infrared imaging system (LI-COR Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.14"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p id="p0225">CRC and normal colorectal tissues were sectioned into 4-μm-thick slides and were incubated with rabbit anti-Smad3 mAb (1:100, 25494-1-AP, Proteintech) at 4°C in a humid container. A non-biotin horseradish peroxidase detection system and DAB substrate (Dako) were used to determine the staining. All samples were observed by two pathologists. Both the intensity and extent of immunostaining were considered for scoring. The positive expression of Smad3 protein was found mainly on the cytoplasm of cells, presenting as a brown granular material. The dominant staining intensity was scored as follows: 0 = negative, 1 = weak, 2 = moderate, and 3 = strong. The extent of the positive staining of cells was scored as follows: &lt;25% = 1, 25%–50% = 2, 51%–75% = 3, and &gt;75% = 4. The final score was determined by multiplying the intensity and the extent positivity scores, which yielded a range from 0 to 12. The mean score from each individual was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.15"><title>Lentivirus Transduction</title><p id="p0230">Lentiviral vectors of miR-140 and negative control and shRNA against Smad3 were purchased from GeneChem (Shanghai, China). HCT116 cells (2 × 10<sup>5</sup>) were plated in the six-well plates and cultured to about 70% confluence. A concentration of 2 μL was used to infect the cells for the subsequent <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments. The transduction efficiency was determined under a fluorescence microscope (Olympus IX73) after being infected for 3 days.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.16"><title>Mouse Subcutaneous Tumor Implantation and Colon Cancer Metastasis Model</title><p id="p0235">Animal care was conducted according to the protocol and guidelines approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Dalian Medical University. Thirty-three 6- to 8-week-old BALB/c mice were purchased from the Experimental Animal Center of Dalian Medical University. Mice were randomly divided into three groups; group 1 was injected with lentivirus miR-140-transduced cells, group 2 was injected with lentivirus control-transduced cells, and group 3 was injected with lentivirus shRNA against Smad3-transduced cells. Each group was injected subcutaneously on the back or through the tail vein. The transduced HCT116 cells were collected and resuspended at 2 × 10<sup>7</sup>/mL in McCoy’s 5A media with Matrigel (1:1). The mice were anesthetized by isoflurane inhalation.</p><p id="p0240">For the subcutaneous tumor implantation model, 100 μL cell suspension was injected subcutaneously on the backs of mice (5 per group). The tumor mass was measured using a caliper, and the tumor volume (V) was calculated by the formula V = length × width<sup>2</sup> × 0.5.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> For the CRC metastasis model, 100 μL cell suspension was injected through the tail vein (6 per group).<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> The mice that were injected subcutaneously were sacrificed at 4 weeks, and those that were injected through the tail vein were sacrificed at 8 weeks. The subcutaneous tumors, livers, and lungs were excised and frozen at −80°C until processing for protein isolation. The frozen mouse tumor tissues were crushed by a sterile steel ball in a cryotube. Then, extraction and solubilization were performed. The portions of tumors were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin, and paraffin-embedded and 4-μm sections were stained for H&amp;E. For immunohistochemistry, the consecutive sections were incubated with rabbit anti-Smad3 mAb (1:100; 25494-1-AP, Proteintech), rabbit anti-p-Smad3 mAb (1:100; ab52903, Abcam), rabbit anti-E-cadherin mAb (1:100; 20874-1-AP, Proteintech), rabbit anti-vimentin mAb (1:100; ab92547, Abcam), and rabbit anti-Zeb1 mAb (1:100; 21544-1-AP, Proteintech). The procedures and evaluation of immunostaining were briefly described earlier, in the <xref rid="sec4.14" ref-type="sec">Immunohistochemistry</xref> section.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.17"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0245">Statistical analysis was done using the SPSS software, v11.0. The results were expressed as the mean ± SD. Statistical differences were determined using a two-tailed Student’s t test between two groups (paired t test for matched clinical samples and unpaired t test for the unpaired two groups). For comparison of more than two groups, one-way ANOVA followed by a Bonferroni-Dunn test was performed. p &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="p0250">Conceptualization: B.S. and L.L.; Data Curation: J.L., K.Z., L.Y., and W.Z.; Formal Analysis: J.L., K.Z., L.Y., W.Z., Y.L., J.M., B.W., L.W., and S.F.; Investigation: J.L., K.Z., L.Y., and W.Z.; Methodology: J.L.; Project Administration: B.W.; Resources: J.L. and B.W.; Supervision: B.S. and L.L.; Validation: J.L.; Visualization: J.L. and K.Z.; Writing – Original Draft: B.S.; Writing – Review &amp; Editing: J.L., B.S., and L.L.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p id="p0255">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fidler</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenesis of cancer metastasis: the ‘seed and soil’ hypothesis revisited</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source><volume>3</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition in colorectal cancer metastasis: A system review</article-title><source>Pathol. Res. Pract.</source><volume>211</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.prp.2015.05.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiery</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acloque</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions in development and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>139</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2009.11.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition and its role in the pathogenesis of colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2689</fpage><lpage>2698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23803016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7314/apjcp.2013.14.5.2689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2015</article-title><source>CA Cancer J. Clin.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25559415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pox</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>383</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24225001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61649-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatem</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dancourt</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and patterns of recurrence after resection for cure of colonic cancer in a well defined population</article-title><source>Br. J. Surg.</source><volume>93</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1115</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16804870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bjs.5349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feinbaum</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The C. elegans heterochronic gene <italic toggle="yes">lin-4</italic> encodes small RNAs with antisense complementarity to <italic toggle="yes">lin-14</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>75</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8252621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(93)90529-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wightman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttranscriptional regulation of the heterochronic gene <italic toggle="yes">lin-14</italic> by <italic toggle="yes">lin-4</italic> mediates temporal pattern formation in C. elegans</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>75</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8252622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(93)90530-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bert</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs as regulators of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>7</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>3112</fpage><lpage>3118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.7.20.6851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azmi</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting miRNAs involved in cancer stem cell and EMT regulation: an emerging concept in overcoming drug resistance</article-title><source>Drug Resist. Updat.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20692200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drup.2010.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2956795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta during human colorectal carcinogenesis: the shift from epithelial to mesenchymal signaling</article-title><source>Inflammopharmacology</source><volume>14</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10787-006-1536-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernards</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-β: an emerging player in drug resistance</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>12</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2960</fpage><lpage>2968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23974105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.26034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3875670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bierie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta and cancer</article-title><source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16289860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cytogfr.2005.09.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krstić</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivanović</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mojsilović</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santibanez</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta and oxidative stress interplay: implications in tumorigenesis and cancer progression</article-title><source>Oxid. Med. Cell. Longev.</source><volume>2015</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>654594</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26078812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2015/654594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4452864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ci</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone demethylase RBP2 promotes malignant progression of gastric cancer through TGF-β1-(p-Smad3)-RBP2-E-cadherin-Smad3 feedback circuit</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>17661</fpage><lpage>17674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25974964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.3756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4627336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pais</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soond</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swingler</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chantry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing mRNA expression identifies Smad3 as a microRNA-140 target regulated only at protein level</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>16</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20071455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1261/rna.1701210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2822914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose paclitaxel ameliorates pulmonary fibrosis by suppressing TGF-β1/Smad3 pathway via miR-140 upregulation</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>e70725</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23967091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0070725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3744547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[MicroRNA-140 suppresses the migration and invasion of colorectal cancer cells through targeting Smad3]</article-title><source>Zhonghua Zhong Liu Za Zhi</source><volume>36</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuddenham</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ntounia-Fousara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajihosseini</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalmay</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cartilage specific microRNA-140 targets histone deacetylase 4 in mouse cells</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>580</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>4214</fpage><lpage>4217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16828749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2006.06.080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wienholds</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Saavedra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berezikov</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvitz</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauppinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA expression in zebrafish embryonic development</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>309</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1114519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakasa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-140 plays dual roles in both cartilage development and homeostasis</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1915510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2878654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruheim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botchkina</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Formentini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of chemoresistance mediated by miR-140 in human osteosarcoma and colon cancer cells</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>28</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>4065</fpage><lpage>4074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19734943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2009.274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2783211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-140-5p suppresses tumor growth and metastasis by targeting transforming growth factor β receptor 1 and fibroblast growth factor 9 in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><volume>58</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23401231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.26315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-140 suppresses tumor growth and metastasis of non-small cell lung cancer by targeting insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>e73604</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24039995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0073604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3769283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fesler</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of colorectal cancer stem cell survival and invasive potential by hsa-miR-140-5p mediated suppression of Smad2 and autophagy</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>19735</fpage><lpage>19746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25980495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.3771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4637317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of miR-140 induces EMT and promotes invasion by targeting Slug in esophageal cancer</article-title><source>Cell. Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1466</fpage><lpage>1476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25322669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000366351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-140-5p inhibits the progression of colorectal cancer by targeting VEGFA</article-title><source>Cell. Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000430237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>microRNA-140-5p inhibits colorectal cancer invasion and metastasis by targeting ADAMTS5 and IGFBP5</article-title><source>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>180</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27906093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13287-016-0438-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5134063</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7885506"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Kroon</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narcisi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitters</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaney Davidson</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Osch</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Kraan</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMAD3 and SMAD4 have a more dominant role than SMAD2 in TGFβ-induced chondrogenic differentiation of bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>43164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28240243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep43164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5327413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuxe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia de Herreros</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional crosstalk between TGF-β and stem cell pathways in tumor cell invasion: role of EMT promoting Smad complexes</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>9</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>2363</fpage><lpage>2374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.9.12.12050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirakihara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential regulation of epithelial and mesenchymal markers by deltaEF1 proteins in epithelial mesenchymal transition induced by TGF-beta</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><volume>18</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>3533</fpage><lpage>3544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1091/mbc.E07-03-0249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1951739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Grunsven</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schellens</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huylebroeck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SIP1 (Smad interacting protein 1) and deltaEF1 (delta-crystallin enhancer binding factor) are structurally similar transcriptional repressors</article-title><source>J. Bone Joint Surg. Am.</source><volume>83-A</volume><issue>Pt 1, Suppl 1</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>S40</fpage><lpage>S47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11263664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Postigo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Opposing functions of ZEB proteins in the regulation of the TGFbeta/BMP signaling pathway</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>2443</fpage><lpage>2452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12743038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/cdg225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC155983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarasewicz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeruss</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospho-specific Smad3 signaling: impact on breast oncogenesis</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>11</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2443</fpage><lpage>2451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22659843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.20546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3404875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzwonek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preobrazhenska</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cazzola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conidi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schellens</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dinther</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stubbs</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klippel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huylebroeck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad3 is a key nonredundant mediator of transforming growth factor beta signaling in Nme mouse mammary epithelial cells</article-title><source>Mol. Cancer Res.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1342</fpage><lpage>1353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19671686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-08-0558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardali</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Hoogen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Pluijm</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad2 and Smad3 have opposing roles in breast cancer bone metastasis by differentially affecting tumor angiogenesis</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>29</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/onc.2009.426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Korchynskyi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landström</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoika</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souchelnytskyi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of Smad proteins in human colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><volume>82</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10389752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(sici)1097-0215(19990719)82:2&lt;197::aid-ijc8&gt;3.0.co;2-v</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-34: from bench to bedside</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24657911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.1825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4011589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ShRNA targeting Notch1 sensitizes breast cancer stem cell to paclitaxel</article-title><source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1064</fpage><lpage>1073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23500524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2013.02.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palencia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>rNAPc2 inhibits colorectal cancer in mice through tissue factor</article-title><source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-0407</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="app2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><p id="p0270"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1–S3 and Table S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by grants from the <funding-source id="gs1">National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (no. 81172052 to B.S. and no. 81272430 to L.L.), from the “Yingcai” program of Dalian Medical University to B.S., and from the <funding-source id="gs2">Tumor Stem Cell Research Key Laboratory of Liaoning Province</funding-source> to L.L.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="app1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0265">Supplemental Information including three figures and one table can be found with this article online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.omtn.2017.12.022" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2017.12.022</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>