
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Chem Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Chem. Biol.</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101231976</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature chemical biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4450</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-4469</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5562517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5562517.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5562517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5562517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS864513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28628094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.2409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS864513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA864513</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A water-soluble DsbB variant that catalyzes disulfide bond formation <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizrachi</surname><given-names initials="D">Dario</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names initials="MP">Michael-Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names initials="G">Guoping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names initials="N">Na</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkmen</surname><given-names initials="M">Mehmet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLisa</surname><given-names initials="MP">Matthew P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref rid="FN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>School of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853 USA</aff><aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>New England Biolabs, 240 County Rd, Ipswich, MA, 01938, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence to: Matthew P. DeLisa, School of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853. Tel: 607-254-8560; Fax: 607-255-9166; <email>md255@cornell.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">297130</issue-id><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-06-17 18:25:16.870"><day>17</day><month>06</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms864513.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="20" journal-id="Nat Chem Biol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10922644"><article-title>Retraction Note: A water-soluble DsbB variant that catalyzes
disulfide-bond formation <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></article-title><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><date><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><source>Nature chemical biology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10922644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38242958</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p id="P1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> DsbB is a transmembrane enzyme that catalyzes the re-oxidation of the periplasmic oxidase DsbA by ubiquinone. Here, we sought to convert membrane-bound DsbB into a water-soluble biocatalyst by leveraging a previously described method for <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> solubilization of integral membrane proteins (IMPs). When solubilized DsbB variants were co-expressed with an export-defective copy of DsbA in the cytoplasm of wild-type <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells, artificial oxidation pathways were created that efficiently catalyzed <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> disulfide bond formation in a range of substrate proteins and in a manner that depended on both DsbA and quinone. Hence, DsbB solubilization was achieved with preservation of both catalytic activity and substrate specificity. Moreover, given the generality of the solubilization technique, the results presented here should pave the way for unlocking the biocatalytic potential of other membrane-bound enzymes whose utility has been limited by poor stability of IMPs outside of their native lipid bilayer context.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Integral membrane proteins (IMPs) account for 25–30% of all open reading frames in sequenced genomes<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. This class of proteins plays vital roles in diverse cellular functions, many of which involve material and/or information transfer across tightly sealed lipid bilayer membranes. Examples of these functions include molecular transport, energy generation, signal transduction, osmotic regulation, and membrane-associated biochemistry. Owing to their centrality in such a wide variety of cellular processes, it is not surprising that these proteins comprise a majority of known drug targets<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">From a structural perspective, IMPs are intrinsically hydrophobic and thus have low solubility in aqueous environments. As such, IMPs naturally exist within lipid membranes where they make extensive non-polar contacts with the hydrophobic core of the bilayer<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. The poor water solubility of IMPs creates a roadblock to characterizing their structure and function<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, and also represents one of the most substantial barriers to developing membrane protein technologies<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. To overcome this challenge, IMPs can be solubilized using detergents or detergent-like reagents (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, protein-based nanodiscs<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>, peptide-based detergents<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, and amphiphilic polymers<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>) that encircle the protein and provide a lipophilic niche inside a detergent micelle. However, identifying the optimal detergent for a given IMP often involves a time consuming process of trial and error<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. Moreover, the technological potential of IMPs solubilized by any of these methods can only be investigated <italic toggle="yes">in vitro.</italic></p><p id="P4">A radical alternative for IMP solubilization involves redesigning the protein to dissolve in water without the need for exogenous solubilizing agents. For example, a computational approach has been used to engineer a water-solubilized variant of the bacterial ion channel KcsA by mutating 29 of its lipid-contacting hydrophobic residues to more hydrophilic ones<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Indeed, following expression in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> cells, high soluble yields of this designed KcsA variant were recovered in the absence of detergent solubilization. Importantly, the water-soluble variant retained the intended functional and structural properties of the wild-type protein. Along similar lines, we recently described a method for <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> solubilization of IMPs that retained the correct fold and functional form of the protein without adding detergents or mutations to the IMP sequence<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. This technique, called SIMPLEx (solubilization of IMPs with high levels of expression), enables soluble expression of IMPs directly in living cells by genetically modifying an IMP target with a truncated version of human apolipoprotein A-I, which effectively shields the IMP from water and promotes its solubilization. In addition to being amphipathic, truncated ApoAI exhibits substantial structural flexibility that allows it to readily conform to a spectrum of different geometries as needed<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Importantly, because the water-soluble IMPs are expressed inside cells, the SIMPLEx method has the potential to enable <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> applications (<italic toggle="yes">e.g.</italic>, metabolic pathway engineering) that leverage the activity of solubilized IMPs.</p><p id="P5">To test this notion, we attempted to reconstitute the disulfide bond-promoting activity of the membrane-bound DsbB enzyme in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cytoplasm. In wild-type <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, the oxidation of cysteine pairs to form a disulfide bond occurs in the periplasm<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> and is catalyzed by DsbB, which is comprised of four transmembrane helices and two periplasmic loops<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, and DsbA, a soluble periplasmic enzyme that donates its own extremely reactive, oxidizing disulfide directly to other proteins as they enter the periplasmic space<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Each periplasmic loop of DsbB contains a pair of conserved cysteines that are required for the re-oxidation of DsbA<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Specifically, the Cys41–Cys44 residues form a disulfide bond in response to quinone reduction<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. This disulfide is subsequently transferred to Cys104–Cys130, which forms a disulfide that is donated to the active-site cysteines of DsbA<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. Hence, DsbB effectively bridges the electron transport chain with oxidative protein folding.</p><p id="P6">To create a cytoplasmic pathway for disulfide bond formation, we used the SIMPLEx method to convert DsbB into a water-soluble biocatalyst that could be functionally expressed in the cytoplasm. Specifically, we designed chimeras in which the C-terminus of DsbB was fused to truncated ApoAI while a highly soluble “decoy” protein was fused to its N-terminus. When these solubilized DsbB chimeras were co-expressed with an export-defective copy of DsbA, the normally periplasmic DsbB-DsbA pathway was completely recompartmentalized in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cytoplasm where it catalyzed <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> disulfide bond formation in a range of substrate proteins. While IMPs previously solubilized using SIMPLEx retained biological activity, as exemplified by ligand binding in the case of EmrE and stimulation of 17,20-lyase activity in the case of human cytochrome <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub> (cyt <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub>)<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, none of these were enzymes. Hence, the functional reconstitution of solubilized DsbB represents the first demonstration of catalytic activity in a solubilized IMP via SIMPLEx. The ability to generate solubilized variants of IMPs that are functional in non-native environments opens the door to harnessing other membrane-bound enzymes whose biocatalytic utility has been heretofore limited by the need for a lipid bilayer or for harsh detergents and/or mutations that serve to stabilize the IMP.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Engineering a water-soluble DsbB variant</title><p id="P7">Engineering a cytoplasmic DsbB-DsbA pathway (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>) required a strategy for making the transmembrane protein DsbB compatible with the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cytoplasm. To this end, we hypothesized that the SIMPLEx technique<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> could be used to create water-soluble DsbB variants that retain biocatalytic activity (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, re-oxidation of DsbA) in the cytoplasm (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>). Previously, we showed that a truncation variant of human ApoAI lacking its 43-residue globular N-terminal domain (hereafter ApoAI*) promoted soluble expression of structurally diverse IMPs, which were recovered from the cytoplasm at high titers (~5–10 mg/L of culture) and in functionally relevant conformations<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Here, we designed chimeras in which the C-terminus of DsbB was genetically fused to ApoAI* while its N-terminus was fused to a highly soluble ‘decoy’ protein, namely the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> maltose-binding protein lacking its N-terminal export signal (cMBP, where c indicates cytoplasmic), to prevent the resulting chimera from becoming inserted in the cytoplasmic membrane (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). Following expression of cMBP-DsbB-ApoAI* (hereafter SIMPLEx-DsbB or SxDsbB) in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3) cells, ~40–50% of the chimera accumulated in the soluble cytoplasmic fraction with the remainder partitioning in the insoluble and detergent-solubilized fractions (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). In stark contrast, wild-type (wt) DsbB or a topologically inverted DsbB variant called H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup> (ref. <sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>), both of which are membrane-bound enzymes, partitioned exclusively in the detergent-soluble fraction (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). A DsbB-ApoAI* chimera lacking the decoy domain accumulated in the detergent-solubilized and insoluble fractions only, while a cMBP-DsbB fusion without the ApoAI* domain was detected primarily in the insoluble fraction with lesser amounts in the detergent-soluble and soluble fractions (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). It should be pointed out that soluble cMBP-DsbB was extensively aggregated as determined by size-exclusion chromatography (SEC), consistent with the soluble aggregates observed for other decoy-IMP fusions lacking the ApoAI* domain<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Structure-guided optimization of soluble DsbB expression</title><p id="P8">Inspection of the DsbB sequence revealed a GxxxA motif (where × represents any amino acid) in the fourth transmembrane (TM) segment that we speculated could be responsible for folding, solubility, and/or stability of the enzyme (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Results</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>). Indeed, GxxxG and GxxxG-like motifs are known to stabilize helix–helix interactions in both membrane and soluble proteins<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. The GxxxA sequence in particular is overrepresented (21% above that expected at random) in all TM sequences identified to date<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. In addition, we predicted that the last 13 amino acids of DsbB, which form a flexible, linker-like segment, could potentially reduce the intimate interaction between the DsbB and ApoAI* domains that appears to be important for IMP solubilization<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Thus, to potentially enhance SxDsbB solubility, we removed the last 13 amino acids of DsbB and added two additional GxxxG motifs along the same face of the fourth transmembrane helix because concatenated GxxxGxxxG motifs known as glycine zippers (GZs) are also overrepresented in TM domains<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. The resulting variant was named DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>). When expressed in the membrane of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells lacking native DsbB, DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> was able to promote disulfide bond formation in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> alkaline phosphatase (PhoA) at a level that was indistinguishable from wt DsbB (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1b</xref>). Having confirmed the activity of DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, this variant was modified with cMBP and ApoAI* to generate a SIMPLEx construct named SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). This new construct exhibited higher levels of soluble cytoplasmic expression compared to SxDsbB (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b and c</xref>), with purified yields reaching nearly 10 mg/L of culture (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1c</xref>). In addition, the GZ motif promoted the formation of soluble SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> tetramers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Soluble DsbB variants function in the cytoplasm</title><p id="P9">Determining the biological activity of the water-soluble DsbB variants required a specific assay to quantify protein oxidation in the cytoplasm. We investigated whether <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PhoA could serve this purpose. The wt PhoA enzyme is secreted by a Sec-specific signal peptide into the periplasmic space where it is rapidly oxidized by the native DsbB-DsbA system to form its two consecutive disulfide bonds that are critical for both stability and phosphatase activity<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> (see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1b</xref>). For these studies, we made use of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DHB4(DE3), a K-12 strain in which the genomic copy of <italic toggle="yes">phoA</italic> is absent and the λDE3 prophage has been site-specifically integrated into the genome, enabling expression of target genes cloned in pET vectors. As expected, expression of periplasmically targeted PhoA (pPhoA) in DHB4(DE3) cells resulted in substantial phosphatase activity in the periplasm and little to no activity in the cytoplasm (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). This activity coincided with the detection of intact PhoA protein in the periplasmic fraction (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). To confirm that this activity was due to the DsbB-DsbA pathway, we performed similar experiments using strain DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic>, a derivative of DHB4(DE3) in which the <italic toggle="yes">dsbA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">dsbB</italic> genes have been insertionally inactivated. When pPhoA was expressed in this strain, the periplasmic phosphatase activity was diminished almost to background levels (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). Next, we created a cytoplasmic PhoA variant (cPhoA) by removal of its native N-terminal signal peptide. Consistent with earlier findings<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>, expression of cPhoA in DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells resulted in no measurable activity above background in either the cytoplasm or periplasm (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>) and no detectable bands in the corresponding immunoblot (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). This result was attributed to the lack of conformational stability of cPhoA in the absence of its structural disulfides, which cannot form in the reducing cytoplasm. As a positive control, cPhoA was expressed in the cytoplasm of SHuffle T7 Express cells (hereafter SHuffle), a strain whose cytoplasmic reductive pathways are diminished, thereby allowing for the formation of disulfide bonds in the cytoplasm<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. As expected, SHuffle cells produced high levels of phosphatase activity in the cytoplasm (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>) and the stability of cPhoA in this compartment was dramatically enhanced (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). Taken together, these results confirmed cPhoA as a reliable reporter of cytoplasmic disulfide bond-forming activity.</p><p id="P10">To evaluate the activity of water-soluble DsbB chimeras, each was co-expressed with the cPhoA reporter and an export-defective version of DsbA in which the N-terminal signal peptide was removed (cDsbA). Importantly, both SxDsbB and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> catalyzed efficient oxidation of cPhoA in the presence of cDsbA in the cytoplasm of DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a,b</xref>). This substantial gain in cPhoA activity and stability was on par with that measured following co-expression of cPhoA, cDsbA and the inverted DsbB variant (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a,3b</xref>), which has its active site located on the cytoplasmic side of the membrane and functions with inverted topology<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Notably, similar results were obtained using a B strain of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, namely BL21(DE3) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>), indicating that the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway can be readily reconstituted in the cytoplasm of an unrelated host strain with retention of activity. Interestingly, when the pathway was transferred to SHuffle cells, the effects on cPhoA activity were not additive but instead inhibitory (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>), suggesting that the two cytoplasmic oxidation mechanisms may negatively interact.</p><p id="P11">To investigate the redox state of cPhoA in these strains, we performed 4-acetamido-4′-maleimidylstilbene-2,2′-disulfonic acid (AMS) alkylation to quantify <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> protein oxidation<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. AMS alkylates any free thiol group found in the side chains of cysteine residues, covalently adding 500 daltons and causing a discernable mobility shift in SDS-PAGE analysis. As expected, cPhoA was completely reduced in the cytoplasm of DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells and completely oxidized in the cytoplasm of SHuffle cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). When expressed in the presence of the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway in DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells, ~90% of cPhoA was oxidized (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). For comparison, DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells equipped with inverted DsbB and cDsbA oxidized ~80% of cPhoA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). These results unequivocally confirm that the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway inserts disulfide bonds into cPhoA with equal or better efficiency than alternative mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Mechanism of water-soluble DsbB</title><p id="P12">The oxidation of cPhoA depended on the presence of solubilized DsbB, as activity was completely abrogated when cPhoA was expressed in the presence of cDsbA only (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). Moreover, cPhoA activity was abolished when essential catalytic residues in either cDsbA or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> were mutated<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>, namely the active-site Cys30-Pro-His-Cys33 motif of cDsbA changed to Ala-Pro-His-Ala, and Cys44 of DsbB substituted with Ala in SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). Given that cPhoA oxidation failed in the presence of the catalytically inactive cDsbA(APHA) construct, we next investigated whether a specific interaction between SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> and cDsbA was a key feature of this activity. In the native DsbB-DsbA system, hetero-dimerization of the DsbB and DsbA components enables thiol–disulfide exchange<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. While the DsbB-DsbA heterodimer exists only transiently as a reaction intermediate, a stable complex that mimics a reaction intermediate can be formed with a Cys130 mutant of DsbB and a Cys33 mutant of DsbA, which are held together by a Cys30 (DsbA)–Cys104 (DsbB) intermolecular disulfide bond<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Accordingly, we produced a C130S mutant of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> and a C33A mutant of cDsbA. When an oxidized mixture of these purified proteins was subjected to an amylose affinity resin, both co-eluted in the same fraction, indicating the formation of a SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S)–cDsbA(C33A) complex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>). When complex formation was interrogated by SEC, an interaction was clearly observed for the oxidized mixture of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and cDsbA(C33A), with the proteins co-eluting in the early fraction and no material eluting in the later fraction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4b,c</xref>).</p><p id="P13">We next determined whether SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> transmitted electrons from cDsbA to components of the membrane electron-transport system, namely ubiquinone (UQ) and menaquinone (MK), as is the case with membrane-bound DsbB<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. To this end, we assayed cPhoA activity in the cytoplasm of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain BL21(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">menA</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">malF::kan…ubiA420</italic>, which is deficient in MK and UQ biosynthesis<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. The topologically inverted DsbB variant previously failed to catalyze disulfide bond formation in a similar strain background<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, and that result was replicated here (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>). When the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway was tested in this quinone-deficient strain, activity was severely attenuated although still above background (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>), suggesting that cPhoA oxidation by solubilized DsbB is primarily catalytic, requiring an intact electron transport chain. Taken together, these results confirm that the catalytic activity and substrate (both DsbA and quinone) specificity of the enzyme is preserved following solubilization.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Structural characterization of water-soluble DsbB</title><p id="P14">To structurally characterize SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> and its complex with cDsbA, we used biological small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS)<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. Reconstructions of the molecular envelopes of cDsbA(C33A) and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) were computed <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> using DAMMIF software<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>, and the average of 20 bead models was determined for each protein and protein complex (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>). No symmetry was imposed in the reconstruction algorithm for cDsbA(C33A), while a p222 symmetry (tetramer) was imposed on SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and its complex with cDsbA(C33A). All 20 models were similar based on mean normalized spatial discrepancy (NSD) values, which were smaller than 0.9 in each case (monomeric DsbA, NSD±SD = 0.551±0.066; dimeric DsbA, NSD±SD = 0.492±0.053; SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S), NSD±SD = 0.799±0.058; and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) crosslinked to cDsbA(C33A), NSD±SD = 0.817±0.099). As expected, the radius of gyration (R<sub>g</sub>), an indicator of how the mass of a particle is distributed around its center of mass, was greater for dimeric cDsbA(C33A) compared to its monomeric counterpart (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>). In support of a complex between solubilized DsbB and DsbA, the R<sub>g</sub> value for crosslinked SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S)–cDsbA(C33A) was greater than that measured for SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) alone (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>). Further analysis of the reconstructed envelopes revealed that both maximum particle size (D<sub>max</sub>) and the volume of the SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S)–cDsbA(C33A) complex were increased relative to the uncomplexed SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>). The “pear” shape of the SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) envelope can be explained by a model whereby the tetrameric SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) proteins are all in a parallel bundle (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>). A similar model for the SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S)–cDsbA(C33A) complex reveals how binding of each cDsbA protein occurs at the top of the pear, effectively increasing envelope height and volume (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Oxidation of diverse substrates by water-soluble DsbB</title><p id="P15">PhoA contains two disulfide bonds that are consecutive in the primary structure. To determine whether more challenging targets could be oxidized by solubilized DsbB, we investigated additional substrate proteins including: (1) phytase (AppA), an <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> periplasmic protein that has similar activity to PhoA but contains four disulfide bonds, one of which is non-consecutive; and (2) murine urokinase-type plasminogen activator (uPA) that contains 12 disulfide bonds, most of which are non-consecutive. The cAppA and c-uPA variants were generated by removing the native N-terminal signal peptides from each. When cAppA was expressed in the cytoplasm of DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells, little to no enzyme activity was detected (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>). The detection of cAppA protein in cell lysates under these conditions (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>) indicated that the lack of activity was attributable to misoxidation/misfolding of the expressed protein. In contrast, expression in the cytoplasm of SHuffle cells resulted in a substantial level of activity (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>) suggesting that an oxidizing cytoplasm was sufficient for proper folding. A similarly high level of activity was observed when cAppA was co-produced with SxDsbB or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, along with an expression-enhanced fusion comprised of cDsbA and glutathione <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-transferase (GST-cDsbA, which was used because unfused cDsbA from pET28a used in these experiments resulted in weak expression). Notably, the expression and activity achieved with water-soluble DsbB was on par with that observed in cells co-expressing inverted DsbB and GST-cDsbA (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a,b</xref>).</p><p id="P16">For both cAppA and cPhoA, a DHB4(DE3) strain background was used because it produces little to no endogenous phosphatase activity owing to knockout of the native <italic toggle="yes">phoA</italic> gene. However, non-phosphatase target substrates do not require a <italic toggle="yes">phoA</italic>-deficient host. Thus, for c-uPA (and all additional targets tested below), we used BL21(DE3) because this strain is capable of high-level protein expression due to the lack of Lon and OmpT proteases. Expression of c-uPA in the cytoplasm of BL21(DE3) cells resulted in no measurable activity above background unless the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway was also co-produced (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c</xref>). As with cAppA, the c-uPA expression and activity was on par with that measured in SHuffle or in BL21(DE3) cells that co-expressed inverted DsbB along with GST-cDsbA (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c,d</xref>).</p><p id="P17">We also investigated whether solubilized DsbB could promote cytoplasmic folding of antibodies including: (1) scFv13, a single-chain Fv (scFv) antibody fragment that specifically binds <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> β-galactosidase (β-gal) and requires 4 disulfide bonds for stability and activity<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>; and (2) anti-HAG cyclonal, a full-length immunoglobulin (IgG) specific for influenza virus hemagglutinin (HAG) that has been engineered for cytoplasmic expression (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, removal of N-terminal signal peptides from both heavy and light chains)<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> and requires 16 disulfide bonds for folding and activity. It is firmly established that full-length antibodies and antibody fragments fail to fold properly when expressed in the cytoplasm of wt <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> because essential disulfide bonds do not form in this reducing environment. Indeed, expression of scFv13 in the cytoplasm of wt BL21(DE3) cells resulted in no measurable antigen-binding activity above background and no detectable accumulation of the protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7a,b</xref>). However, expression of scFv13 in SHuffle cells resulted in a large increase in antigen-binding activity that correlated with substantial accumulation of the protein in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7a,b</xref>). Importantly, when scFv13 was co-expressed with GST-cDsbA and either SxDsbB or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> in the cytoplasm of BL21(DE3) cells, antigen-binding activity and soluble accumulation were nearly identical with the levels observed in SHuffle cells or in BL21(DE3) cells co-expressing GST-cDsbA and inverted DsbB (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7a,b</xref>). Analogously, co-expression of the anti-HAG cyclonal along with SxDsbB or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> in the cytoplasm of BL21(DE3) cells resulted in strong antigen-binding activity that compared favorably to that measured for SHuffle cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8a</xref>). Under the conditions tested here, the topologically inverted DsbB variant was incapable of oxidizing the anti-HAG cyclonal. To determine whether the solubilized DsbB variants catalyzed the formation of fully assembled IgG molecules, SDS-PAGE analysis of Protein A-purified IgGs was performed. The heterotetrameric assembly efficiency of anti-HAG cyclonal produced in the presence of SxDsbB and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> was estimated to be 51 and 57%, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8b</xref>), compared to ~90% for anti-HAG cyclonal assembly in SHuffle cells reported previously<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. This difference is likely due to the fact that SHuffle cells carry a genomic copy of cytoplasmic DsbC, a disulfide bond isomerase that assists in the formation of correctly folded multi-disulfide bonded proteins. Nonetheless, these data reveal that solubilized DsbB is a remarkably flexible biocatalyst that promotes disulfide bond formation in a wide array of structurally diverse substrate proteins.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P18">In this work, we successfully converted membrane-bound DsbB into a water-soluble protein that could be expressed cytoplasmically at relatively high levels and with retention of function. This feat was achieved by leveraging a method called SIMPLEx, which enables <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> solubilization of IMPs in structurally and functionally relevant conformations without the need for potentially inactivating detergents, lipid reconstitutions, or mutations to the IMP itself<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. The SIMPLEx technique was previously shown to be generally useful for solubilizing an array of structurally diverse IMPs, leading to the accumulation of non-aggregated, water-soluble IMPs at high titers (~5–10 mg/L of culture) that retained biological activity, namely ligand binding in the case of EmrE and stimulation of 17,20-lyase activity in the case of human cytochrome <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub> (cyt <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub>)<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Here, we demonstrate for the first time <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> catalysis with a SIMPLEx-solubilized enzyme in the context of a multi-enzyme pathway, opening the door to a wide array of <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> applications involving solubilized IMPs.</p><p id="P19">A catalytic mechanism for solubilized DsbB is supported by the observation that both DsbA and quinone substrate dependence was preserved in the engineered DsbB chimeras. Analogous to the native Dsb pathway, the engineered pathway transferred oxidizing potential to cPhoA in a process that involved known catalytic residues, namely the active-site Cys30-Pro-His-Cys33 motif in cDsbA and the Cys44 residue in solubilized DsbB. In further support of a catalytic mechanism, the water-soluble DsbB-DsbA pathway was extremely efficient with ~90% of cPhoA accumulating in an oxidized state. Further, re-oxidation of solubilized DsbB appeared to involve UQ or MK based on the observation that cPhoA oxidation was severely attenuated in a quinone-deficient strain background. Interestingly, a low level of cPhoA oxidation still occurred in this strain, consistent with the observation that in the absence of quinones, DsbB can oxidize ~40% of DsbA in a 1:1 stoichiometric reaction<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>. However, alternative origins for this low level of quinone-independent activity, such as an unknown cytoplasmic factor reoxidizing solubilized DsbB, cannot be ruled out at this point.</p><p id="P20">Interestingly, the ability of the ApoAI* domain not only to promote solubilization of DsbB but also to accommodate interactions with its biological partner DsbA suggests a remarkable structural plasticity of this unique amphipathic domain. Along similar lines, SIMPLEx-solubilized human cyt <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub> stimulated the 17,20-lyase activity of CYP17A1<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, an activity that is known to involve transmembrane helix–helix interactions between cyt <italic toggle="yes">b</italic><sub>5</sub> and CYP17A1. Hence, these results collectively reveal that the ApoAI* domain is sufficiently flexible to allow protein–protein interactions that are necessary to promote proper function. Additionally, these data justify the use of SIMPLEx as a tool for studying IMPs and their soluble partners.</p><p id="P21">The formation of disulfide bonds in the cytoplasm has long been possible using <italic toggle="yes">trxB gor</italic> suppressor strains such as FÅ113<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> or SHuffle<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. Compared to these mutant strains, an advantage of our engineered pathway is that it can be readily used in any strain background simply by transforming the host of interest with a plasmid encoding the SxDsbB/cDsbA (or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>/cDsbA) genes. Indeed, we showed that the SxDsbB/cDsbA and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>/cDsbA could be directly transferred between unrelated strain backgrounds without loss of function. An alternative approach to cytoplasmic protein oxidation involves inverting the membrane topology of DsbB<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. While this construct can also be readily shuttled between strain backgrounds, a drawback is that it relies on membrane protein expression, which often imposes a burden on the host that is deleterious to cell viability<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. By directing the expression of DsbB to the cytoplasm of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, we take advantage of this compartment’s ability to support recombinant product yields exceeding 50% of the total cellular protein<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> while eliminating the energy-intensive process of membrane integration. In light of these advantages, we envision that our strategy could be used to redirect a wide range of biological pathways involving IMPs to the cytoplasmic compartment. Moreover, the generality of the method could also unlock previously intractable membrane-bound biocatalysts for stand-alone or pathway-mediated applications in cellular, or alternatively, cell-free reaction environments.</p></sec><sec id="S10" specific-use="print-only"><title>Online Methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>Bacterial strains and plasmids</title><p id="P22">The following <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were used in this study: DHB4 (MC1000 Δ<italic toggle="yes">phoA</italic>(PvuII) <italic toggle="yes">phoR</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">malF3</italic> F’[<italic toggle="yes">lac</italic>+(<italic toggle="yes">lacI</italic><sup>Q</sup>) <italic toggle="yes">pro</italic>]), SHuffle T7 Express (New England Biolabs), and BL21(DE3) (Novagen). DHB4 Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> strain was derived from DHB4 by insertional inactivation of the <italic toggle="yes">dsbA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">dsbB</italic> genes with the kanamycin resistance gene as described previously<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Briefly, this was accomplished by P1 phage transduction using the BW25113 <italic toggle="yes">dsbA</italic>::kan and BW25113 <italic toggle="yes">dsbB</italic>::kan strains from the Keio collection as donors and plasmid pCP20 to remove the Kan marker as needed. The DHB4(DE3) and DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> strains were generated using a λDE3 lysogenization kit (Novagen) according to manufacturer’s instructions and positive clones identified based on the ability to produce active GFP from plasmid pET-GFP<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Strain BL21(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">menA</italic> Δ<italic toggle="yes">malF::kan…ubiA420</italic> was constructed exactly as described previously<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>, with the nonessential <italic toggle="yes">menA</italic> gene disrupted by P1 phage transduction and the <italic toggle="yes">ubiA</italic> gene conditionally knocked out by introducing the Δ<italic toggle="yes">malF::kan…ubiA420</italic> allele into the BL21(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">menA</italic> strain. The mutant has a negligible UbiA activity. However, when supplied with 1 mM hydroxybenzoic acid (HBA), this mutant strain can make ~20% amount of the UQ as the wild-type strain; this quinone level is sufficient for the growth of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P23">All plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. Plasmids constructed here were made using standard cloning procedures and all plasmid sequences were confirmed by sequencing. For expression and purification of different DsbB chimeras, the plasmid pET21d (Novagen) was used. Specifically, the ΔspMBP-DsbB-ApoAI* gene fusion (defined here as SxDsbB) was PCR-amplified from pET28-ΔspMBP-DsbB-ApoAI*<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and subsequently cloned in plasmid pET21d. This new plasmid, pET21-SxDsbB, served as the template for creating plasmids pET21-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, pET21-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C44A), and pET21-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S), which were all created by standard site-directed mutagenesis. In addition, removal of the genes encoding cMBP or ApoAI*, or both, from pET21-SxDsbB or pET21-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> gave rise to the following plasmids: pET21-DsbB, pET21-DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, pET21-cMBP-DsbB, pET21-cMBP-DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, pET21-DsbB-ApoAI*, and pET21-DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>-ApoAI*. For cDsbA expression and purification, we used pET39b (Novagen), which carries the full-length <italic toggle="yes">E. coli dsbA</italic> gene. The cDsbA(C33A) mutant was generated using site-directed mutagenesis with pET39b as template. For H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup> expression and purification, plasmid pFH265 was used<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. For PhoA expression in the periplasm, plasmid pBAD-pPhoA was generated by cloning the gene encoding full-length <italic toggle="yes">E. coli phoA</italic> into plasmid pBAD18-Cm<sup><xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. For PhoA expression in the cytoplasm, pFH-cPhoA was constructed by excising the gene encoding cDsbA from plasmid pFH273<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. For co-expression of PhoA and DsbA in the cytoplasm, we used pFH273<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, a pLysSBAD derivative that enables bicistronic expression of the genes encoding mature PhoA lacking its N-terminal signal peptide (cPhoA; residues R22-K471) and mature DsbA lacking its N-terminal signal peptide (cDsbA; residues A20-K208) and also carrying an N-terminal 6x-His tag. Plasmid pFH273mut was generated whereby the active-site Cys30-Pro-His-Cys33 motif of cDsbA was mutated to Ala-Pro-His-Ala, which completely inactivates the enzyme<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Cytoplasmic PhoA expression was also performed using pET24-cPhoA, which was created by cloning mature PhoA (residues R22-K471) in plasmid pET24b. Plasmids for expressing the other substrates, namely cAppA, c-uPA, scFv13, and anti-HAG cyclonal IgG, are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. While working with cAppA, which carried a C-terminal 6x-His tag, we observed conflicting bands in Western blots using the anti-6x-His antibody due to the fact that SxDsbB or SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, which were also 6x-His tagged, migrated similarly. Therefore, we generated a new cAppA expression plasmid in which the C-terminal 6x-His tag was replaced with a FLAG epitope tag in plasmid pHIS. These substrate expression plasmids were each paired with a bicistronic expression plasmid encoding a genetic fusion between <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GST and cDsbA, and one of the DsbB variants. These bicistronic expression plasmids were constructed as follows: first, a genetic fusion between the genes encoding GST and cDsbA was inserted between NheI-XhoI in the bicistronic expression plasmid pET28-BicExp, which has the following multiple cloning site: NcoI-HindIII-RBS2-NheI-XhoI (where RBS = second ribosome binding site). Next, the gene encoding SxDsbB was inserted between NcoI and HindIII, yielding pET28-SxDsbB::GST-cDsbA. Plasmid pET28-H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup>::GST-cDsbA was generated similarly, while plasmids pET28-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>::GST-cDsbA, pET28-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>::GST-cDsbA(APHA), and pET28-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C44A)::GST-cDsbA were generated by site-directed mutagenesis using pET28-SxDsbB::GST-cDsbA as template.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Protein expression and purification</title><p id="P24">For small cultures, single colonies of the strain of interest carrying the plasmid(s) of interest were grown at 30°C in 5 mL of Luria-Bertani (LB; 10 g/L tryptone, 5 g/L yeast extract, 5 g/L NaCl, pH 7.2) supplemented with the corresponding antibiotics, and grown until optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) reached a value of 1.0. At this point isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) or arabinose was added to a final concentration of 1 mM or 0.5 % arabinose, respectively. Protein expression was allowed to proceed overnight at 25°C. For the expression and purification of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S), wt cDsbA, and cDsbA(C33A), a single colony of BL21(DE3) cells carrying the corresponding plasmid was inoculated into 5 mL of LB supplemented with 50 μg/mL of kanamycin and grown overnight at 30°C. The next day, 500 mL of freshly prepared Terrific Broth (TB) supplemented with 100 μg/mL kanamycin was inoculated 1/100 with the overnight culture and cells were grown at 30°C until reaching OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.8. Protein expression was induced by the addition of 0.25 mM IPTG, after which cells were incubated an additional 18 h at 16°C. Cells were harvested by centrifugation before preparation of lysates or purification of protein targets.</p><p id="P25">Protein purification of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) was carried out with amylose resin (New England Biolabs) according to manufacturer’s specifications, followed by SEC using an ÄKTA Explorer FPLC system (GE Healthcare). Ni-NTA purification of wt cDsbA and cDsbA(C33A) was followed by SEC. SEC was performed using a Superdex 200 10/300 GL column. Standards used to calibrate the SEC column were a lyophilized mix of thyroglobulin, bovine γ-globulin, chicken ovalbumin, equine myoglobin and vitamin B12, MW 1,350–670,000, pI 4.5–6.9 (Bio-Rad). Proteins were stored at a final concentration of 1 mg/ml in SEC buffer (20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA pH 8.0) at 4°C. Full-length anti-HAG IgG was purified using Protein-A. Briefly, protein-A agarose resin was equilibrated with 10 ml PBS and then mixed with the filtered soluble lysate fraction. The resin-soluble lysate fraction mixture was incubated at room temperature for 2 h. After settling in a poly-propylene column, the protein-A agarose was washed extensively with PBS. Anti-HAG IgGs were eluted from the column with 0.1 M glycine-HCl (pH 3.0) in 1-ml fractions and immediately neutralized with 100 μl of 1 M Tris (pH 9.0). Purified fractions were resolved by SDS-PAGE under non-reducing conditions and visualized by staining with Coomassie Blue G-250.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Subcellular fractionation</title><p id="P26">Following protein expression, 5 ml of cells expressing the various substrate targets were harvested. Cultures were normalized by OD<sub>600</sub> and culture aliquots were pelleted via centrifugation for 10 min at 4°C and 4,000 × g. Cells were then resuspended in lysis buffer containing 30 mM Tris pH 8.0, 500 mM NaCl, and 40 mM imidazole pH 8.0 and lysed using a sonicator. To separate soluble proteins from membranes, the homogenate was ultracentrifuged (100,000 × g) for 1 h at 4°C and the supernatant was collected as the soluble fraction. Detergent soluble fractions were obtained by treating the pellets resulting from the previous step with 1 ml of lysis buffer containing 2% <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>-dodecyl-β-D-maltoside (DDM; Anatrace). Pellets were resuspended by douncing. Partitioning of membrane proteins into the DDM-containing lysis buffer was achieved by rotating the lysate at 4°C for 2 h. Following centrifugation (50,000 × g) for 30 min at 4°C, the supernatant represented the detergent-solubilized fraction and the pellet represented the insoluble fraction. IMPs in the various fractions were separated by SDS-PAGE using 10% polyacrylamide gels (Bio-Rad) and subsequently detected by Western blotting according to standard protocols using a 1:5,000-diluted monoclonal anti-6x-His horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated antibody (Abcam). For experiments that involved the isolation of periplasmic fractions, cells were initially resuspended in 20% sucrose, 30 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.5, 1 mM EDTA and 1 g/L lysozyme and incubated at room temperature for 10 min. Following centrifugation (10 min at room temperature and 10,000 × g), cell pellets were fractionated according to standard ice-cold osmotic shock. The supernatant resulting from the centrifugation step (10 min at 4°C and 15,000 × g) was taken as the periplasmic fraction, while the remaining pellet was used to prepare the soluble cytoplasmic fraction as described above. IMPs in the various fractions were separated by SDS-PAGE using 10% polyacrylamide gels (Bio-Rad) and subsequently detected by Western blotting according to standard protocols using a 1:5,000-diluted monoclonal anti-6x-His HRP-conjugated antibody (Abcam) or 1:5,000-diluted monoclonal anti-FLAG HRP-conjugated antibody (Abcam) or 1:5,000-diluted monoclonal anti-PhoA-HRP conjugated (New England Biolabs). For loading controls in SDS-PAGE experiments 1:50,000-diluted polyclonal rabbit anti-GroEL (Sigma) and a secondary antibody goat anti-HRP (Abcam) diluted 1:10,000 were used.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Enzyme activity assays</title><p id="P27">For measuring alkaline phosphatase activity, harvested cells were resuspended in subcellular fractionation buffer supplemented with 50 mM <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-ethyl maleimide (Sigma) to prevent the spontaneous oxidation of disulfide bonds. Alkaline phosphatase activity was measured in a continuous assay by monitoring absorbance at 410 nm (Abs<sub>410</sub>) upon the hydrolysis of 4-nitrophenyl phosphate (Sigma) [0.1% (w/v) in 1 M Tris (pH 8.0)] with a plate reader using 5 μl of the fraction to be assayed (periplasmic or cytoplasmic) and 195 μl of substrate in a 96-well plate at room temperature. Measured phosphatase activity was normalized to total protein amount as determined by standard Bradford assay. Phytase activity was quantified as described earlier<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> with slight modifications. Assays were performed in 96-well plates with 20 μl of soluble protein. Reaction was stopped with 50 μl 5 M NaOH. Phytase activity was measured at Abs<sub>410</sub> and normalized to total protein amount as determined by standard Bradford assay. Urokinase activity was quantified using a 96-well plate at room temperature. A 50-μl aliquot of soluble protein was added to wells containing 50 mM Tris pH 8, 60 mM 6-aminohexanoic acid (Sigma), 0.1 mg/ml Bovine Plasminogen (American Diagnostica) and 0.4 mM Spectrozyme PL (American Diagnostica) to a final volume of 150 μl. The plate was incubated at 37°C and Abs<sub>405</sub> was monitored for 2–3 h until reaching plateau. Activity was measured at Abs<sub>405</sub> in a linear range and normalized to total protein amount as determined by standard Bradford assay.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>AMS alkylation</title><p id="P28">Cultures were prepared as described above for the determination of PhoA activity. After induction overnight, 1 mL of culture (normalized by OD<sub>600</sub>) was used to prepare protein samples. Initially, each sample was subjected to trichloroacetic acid (TCA) precipitation at room temperature for 20 min. The supernatant was discarded after centrifuging at 10,000 rpm for 10 min. Pellets were washed with 1 mL of cold acetone, vortexed, centrifuged again at 10,000 rpm for 10 min), and the supernatant discarded. Pellets were air dried for 30 min at room temperature and then resuspended in 80 μl of alkylation buffer (100 mM Tris·Cl, pH 6.8, 1% SDS) with or without freshly dissolved AMS (Molecular Probes). Samples were incubated for 30 min at 37°C. Fully oxidized and reduced controls were generated using aliquots from cells expressing cPhoA. Specifically, pellets washed with acetone and air dried were treated with 50 μL of 3.6 mM (in water) 4,4′-dithiodipyridine (4-DPS) (Sigma) for oxidation or 100 mM dithiothreitol (DTT) (Sigma) for reduction, and incubated at 30°C for an additional 30 min prior to AMS alkylation. For Western blot analysis, samples were boiled and loaded in BioRad 7.5% Mini-PROTEAN TGX Precast Protein Gels. To ensure sufficient separation of the reduced and oxidized cPhoA species, gels were run at 200 mV for 40 min or until the 25-kDa band of the marker exited the gel. The entire AMS alkylation experiment was repeated in triplicate, with all replicates showing similar results.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</title><p id="P29">Cell lysates derived from strains expressing scFv13 or anti-HAG IgG were analyzed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). Costar 96-well ELISA plates (Corning) were coated overnight at 4°C with 50 μl of 4–10 μg/ml antigen in 0.05 M sodium carbonate buffer (pH 9.6). For scFv13, plates were coated with 50 μl of 10 μg/ml β-gal (Sigma) in PBS whereas for anti-HAG, plates were coated with recombinant GST fused to hemagglutinin (GST-HAG) produced in-house<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Following two 5-min washes with PBS, a 3% non-fat milk blocking solution was applied to each well and incubated with shaking for 3 h at room temperature. Subsequently, samples were applied to each well and incubated with shaking for 2 h at room temperature. Extensive washing (four 5-min washes) was performed prior to the addition of one of the following primary antibodies: anti-6x-His HRP-conjugated antibody (Abcam) for scFv13 and anti-human Fc HRP-conjugated antibody (Thermo Scientific) for anti-HAG IgG. Immunodetection was performed by adding 50 μl of blocking solution containing a 1:5,000 dilution of the appropriate antibody to each well followed by incubation for 1 h at 4°C. This was followed by six 5-min washes with cold washing solution (0.5%Tween-20 in PBS). Detection of bound proteins was carried out using SigmaFAST o-phenylenediamine (OPD) tablets followed by monitoring at Abs<sub>492</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Crosslinking of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and cDsbA(C33A)</title><p id="P30">Following purification of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and cDsbA(C33A), as described above, proteins were mixed in an equimolar ratio. The mixture was oxidized on ice for 1 h with 5 mM K<sub>3</sub>[Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>] and stored in SEC buffer for downstream applications.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>SAXS analysis</title><p id="P31">SAXS data were collected at the Cornell High Energy Synchrotron Source (CHESS) G1 station in Ithaca, New York. Protein samples of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S), wt cDsbA and cDsbA(C33A) and crosslinked SEC fractions of SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and cDsbA(C33A) were exposed with a 250 × 250 μm beam of 9.968 keV X-ray. Sample preparation included centrifugation at 30,000 × g for 30 min and filtration to remove any aggregates. Samples (30 μl) in a range of concentrations from 1 to 10 mg/mL were loaded and oscillated in the beam using an automated system with a plastic chip-based sample cell (2-mm path) and polystyrene X-ray transparent windows. The sample cell and X-ray flight path were placed under vacuum to reduce background scattering. Scattering patterns were captured on a Pilatus 100K-S detector (Dectris, Baden, Switzerland) at 1,504-mm distance. The exposure time was 5 s for each image and 10 images were recorded for each sample. All mathematical manipulations of the data (azimuthal integration, normalization, averaging and buffer subtraction) as well as error propagation were carried out using RAW software<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. The range of momentum transfer was calculated to be 0.0068&lt;q=4∏ sin(θ)/λ&lt;0.28 Å–1, where 2θ is the scattering angle and λ=1.257 Å is the X-ray wavelength. Molecular weight estimated from a lysozyme standard (3.5 mg/ml, 50 mM NaOAc, 50 mM NaCl pH 4.0) agreed with our expectations within error. R<sub>g</sub> was calculated using both Guinier approximation<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> and the inverse Fourier transform method as implemented in the GNOM-ATSAS 2.6.1 package by D. Svergun EMBL-Hamburg. The pair distance distribution function P(r) was calculated using the GNOM program<sup><xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. D<sub>max</sub> was estimated based on the goodness of the data fit and smoothness of the decaying tail. The GNOM output file for the dimer was used as input to DAMMIF<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> to perform <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> shape reconstruction without imposing any symmetry. The 20 reconstructed bead models were superimposed and averaged using DAMAVER<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> in the automatic mode. The mean NSD ± SD values were &lt;1 for all envelopes calculated, indicating close agreement between different reconstructed models. The creation of the atomistic models for both SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) crosslinked to cDsbA(C33A) were created using PyMOL and the following crystal structures: ΔspMBP crystal structure (pdb ID: 1NL5), ApoAI lipid-free crystal structure (pdb ID: 2A01), DsbA monomer (pdb ID:1a23), DsbA dimer (pdb ID: 1u3a), monomeric DsbB (pdb ID: 2k74), and DsbB in complex with DsbA (pdb ID: 2zup, 2hi7, 3e9j, 2leg). The computation of SAXS profiles of the models constructed for SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) (NSD=0.799) and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) crosslinked to cDsbA(C33A) and their fit to experimental profiles was carried out using the Fast X-ray scattering web server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://modbase.compbio.ucsf.edu/foxs/">https://modbase.compbio.ucsf.edu/foxs/</ext-link>)<sup><xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="P32">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article (and its supplementary information files).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S20"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS864513-supplement-1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d36e1256" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S21"><p>We thank Professor Lloyd Ruddock (University of Oulu, Finland) for providing plasmids used in this study. We thank Dr. Carolyn Sevier (Cornell University) for helpful discussions of the manuscript. This work is based upon research conducted at the Cornell High Energy Synchrotron Source (CHESS), which is supported by the NSF and the NIH/NIGMS under NSF award DMR-1332208, using the Macromolecular Diffraction at CHESS (MacCHESS) facility, which is supported by award GM-103485 from the NIH/NIGMS. This work also made use of the Cornell Center for Materials Research Shared Facilities, which are supported through the NSF MRSEC program (Grant # DMR-1120296). This work is based upon work supported by NIH Grants # R21DA031409-01 (to M.P.D.), NSF Grants # CBET 1159581 and CBET 1264701 (both to M.P.D.), a Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship (to M.-P.R.), and a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship (to M.-P.R.).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> D.M. designed research, performed all research, analyzed all data and wrote the paper. M.-P.R. performed experiments and analyzed data related to antibody expression. G.R. and N.K. performed experiments and analyzed data related to AMS alkylation, quinone-deficient cPhoA activity, and c-uPA activity. M.B. designed research and analyzed data. M.P.D. designed research, analyzed data and wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN3"><p><bold>Competing Financial Interests</bold>. The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of integral membrane proteins from eubacterial, archaean, and eukaryotic organisms</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pro.5560070420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2143985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Initial sequencing and analysis of the human genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>409</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35057062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gearing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target validation of G-protein coupled receptors</article-title><source>Drug Discov Today</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11839521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1359-6446(01)02131-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groom</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The druggable genome</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrd892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knolker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subcellular targeting strategies for drug design and delivery</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrd2897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane proteins: from sequence to structure</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biophys Biomol Struct</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7919780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.bb.23.060194.001123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rawlings</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane proteins: always an insoluble problem?</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27284043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BST20160025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4900757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loll</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane protein structural biology: the high throughput challenge</article-title><source>J Struct Biol</source><volume>142</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12718926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1047-8477(03)00045-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Gier</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rationalizing membrane protein overexpression</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tibtech.2006.06.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curnow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane proteins in nanotechnology</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19614569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BST0370643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boldog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sligar</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazelbauer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanodiscs separate chemoreceptor oligomeric states and reveal their signaling properties</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>11509</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0604988103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1544200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lipopeptide detergents designed for the structural study of membrane proteins</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tribet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Audebert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popot</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amphipols: polymers that keep membrane proteins soluble in aqueous solutions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>15047</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><year>1996</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8986761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.93.26.15047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC26353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical considerations of membrane protein instability during purification and crystallisation</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><volume>601</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20099147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-60761-344-2_12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slovic</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lear</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saven</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeGrado</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational design of water-soluble analogues of the potassium channel KcsA</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>1828</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0306417101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC357012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizrachi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Making water-soluble integral membrane proteins in vivo using an amphipathic protein fusion strategy</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>6826</fpage><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25851941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncomms7826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4403311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gursky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal unfolding of human high-density apolipoprotein A-1: implications for a lipid-free molten globular state</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>2991</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><year>1996</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8610156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.93.7.2991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC39748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of thiol-redox pathways in bacteria</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11544348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.micro.55.1.21</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the DsbB-DsbA complex reveals a mechanism of disulfide bond generation</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2006.10.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a protein required for disulfide bond formation in vivo</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><year>1991</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1934062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90532-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two cysteines in each periplasmic domain of the membrane protein DsbB are required for its function in protein disulfide bond formation</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>5121</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7957076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1994.tb06841.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC395459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paradoxical redox properties of DsbB and DsbA in the protein disulfide-introducing reaction cascade</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2646</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/21.11.2646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC126043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilhot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that the pathway of disulfide bond formation in Escherichia coli involves interactions between the cysteines of DsbB and DsbA</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>9895</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7568240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.92.21.9895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC40909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatahet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruddock</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topological plasticity of enzymes involved in disulfide bond formation allows catalysis in either the periplasm or the cytoplasm</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>425</volume><fpage>3268</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmb.2013.04.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teese</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langosch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of GxxxG Motifs in Transmembrane Domain Interactions</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>5125</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26244771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GXXXG and AXXXA: common alpha-helical interaction motifs in proteins, particularly in extremophiles</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>5990</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><year>2002</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11993993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi0200763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical analysis of amino acid patterns in transmembrane helices: the GxxxG motif occurs frequently and in association with beta-branched residues at neighboring positions</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jmbi.1999.3488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transmembrane glycine zippers: physiological and pathological roles in membrane proteins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>14278</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16179394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0501234102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1242278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishigami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshihisa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of disulfide bonds in bacterial alkaline phosphatase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>272</volume><fpage>6174</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><year>1997</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9045630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.272.10.6174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SHuffle, a novel Escherichia coli protein expression strain capable of correctly folding disulfide bonded proteins in its cytoplasm</article-title><source>Microb Cell Fact</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>56</fpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22569138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1475-2859-11-56</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3526497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessette</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of sequences of the active-site dipeptides of DsbA and DsbC on in vivo folding of multidisulfide proteins in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>183</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><year>2001</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11208797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/JB.183.3.980-988.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC94966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for Structural and Functional Analyses of Intramembrane Prenyltransferases in the UbiA Superfamily</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>584</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28065269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/bs.mie.2016.10.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5432130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graewert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact and progress in small and wide angle X-ray scattering (SAXS and WAXS)</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23835228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.sbi.2013.06.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petoukhov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applications of small-angle X-ray scattering to biomacromolecular solutions</article-title><source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23142499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2012.10.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>DaS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DAMMIF</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>a program for rapid ab-initio shape determination in small-angle scattering</article-title><source>Journal of Appliedm Crystallography</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1107/S0021889809000338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5023043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27630371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martineau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of an antibody fragment at high levels in the bacterial cytoplasm</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9653035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jmbi.1998.1840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient expression of full-length antibodies in the cytoplasm of engineered bacteria</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>8072</fpage><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26311203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncomms9072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4560801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactivities of quinone-free DsbB from Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>33035</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M506189200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessette</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslund</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient folding of proteins with multiple disulfide bonds in the Escherichia coli cytoplasm</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>13703</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><year>1999</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.96.24.13703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC24128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miroux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Over-production of proteins in Escherichia coli: mutant hosts that allow synthesis of some membrane proteins and globular proteins at high levels</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>260</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><year>1996</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jmbi.1996.0399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baneyx</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mujacic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombinant protein folding and misfolding in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15529165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt1029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Construction of Escherichia coli K-12 in-frame, single-gene knockout mutants: the Keio collection</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><volume>2</volume><issue>2006</issue><fpage>0008</fpage><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16738554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/msb4100050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1681482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras-Martinez</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boock</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostecki</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLisa</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ribosomal exit tunnel as a target for optimizing protein expression in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Biotechnol J</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22076828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/biot.201100198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3382190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tight regulation, modulation, and high-level expression by vectors containing the arabinose PBAD promoter</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>177</volume><fpage>4121</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7608087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.177.14.4121-4130.1995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC177145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkmen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nonconsecutive disulfide bond of Escherichia coli phytase (AppA) renders it dependent on the protein-disulfide isomerase, DsbC</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>11387</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M411774200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><source>PhD thesis</source><publisher-name>Technical University of Denmark</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Kongens Lyngby, Denmark</publisher-loc><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svergun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of the regularization parameter in indirect-transform methods using perceptual criteria</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><year>1992</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneidman-Duhovny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurate SAXS profile computation and its assessment by contrast variation experiments</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>962</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23972848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpj.2013.07.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3752106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneidman-Duhovny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FoXS, FoXSDock and MultiFoXS: Single-state and multi-state structural modeling of proteins and their complexes based on SAXS profiles</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>W424</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27151198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkw389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4987932</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>A water-soluble DsbB variant that catalyzes disulfide bond formation <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic of the native <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> disulfide bond formation pathway, which involves the endogenous transmembrane enzyme DsbB. DsbB is located in the inner membrane and interacts with its soluble periplasmic partner DsbA, which is localized to the periplasmic compartment by virtue of an N-terminal signal peptide specific for the cotranslational signal recognition particle (SRP) pathway. Electron transport is represented by the black arrows. DsbB obtains its electrons directly from quinones (Q). (<bold>b</bold>) Expression of DsbB as a soluble biocatalyst in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cytoplasm is accomplished using the SIMPLEx technology, which renders IMPs water-soluble by introduction of a ‘decoy’ domain (cMBP) and a ‘shield’ domain (ApoAI*). DsbA is redirected to the cytoplasm by removal of its native signal peptide. Following co-expression, solubilized SxDsbB and export-defective DsbA (cDsbA) effectively transform the cytoplasm into a disulfide bond formation compartment. If needed, cDsbA expression can be improved by fusion to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GST, a resident cytoplasmic protein that promotes solubility of its fusion partners.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms864513f1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> solubilization of DsbB using the SIMPLEx strategy</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Molecular architecture of SIMPLEx constructs SxDsbB and SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> used in this study. Each construct included N-terminal cMBP as decoy protein (orange), C-terminal ApoAI* as shield domain (green), and intervening flexible linkers (L, grey) that connected cMBP and ApoAI* to the DsbB domain. The DsbB domains tested were wt DsbB (top) and DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> (bottom), the latter of which is a C-terminally truncated DsbB variant harboring an engineered glycine zipper (GZ, red). (<bold>b</bold>) Western blot analysis of soluble (s), detergent solubilized (d), and insoluble (i) fractions prepared from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain BL21(DE3) carrying pET21-based plasmids encoding one of the following DsbB constructs: topologically inverted DsbB (H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup>), wt DsbB, DsbB-ApoAI*, cMBP-DsbB, and cMBP-DsbB-ApoAI* (SxDsbB) as indicated. Blot was probed with anti-6x-His antibody. Molecular weight (MW) markers are shown on the left. (<bold>c</bold>) Western blot analysis identical to panel (<bold>b</bold>) except with DsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup> in place of wt DsbB in all constructs as indicated. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 9</xref> for uncropped versions of the blot images.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms864513f2.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Solubilized DsbB variants promote folding of alkaline phosphatase</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic showing disulfide bond connectivity for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> alkaline phosphatase, PhoA (2 disulfide bonds depicted by yellow circles connected by yellow lines). Alkaline phosphatase activity measured in periplasmic (white bars) and cytoplasmic (gray bars) fractions derived from the following strains: wt DHB4(DE3) cells (lacking the native <italic toggle="yes">phoA</italic> gene) carrying no plasmid (empty) or pBAD18-pPhoA (pPhoA); DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> cells carrying no plasmid (empty), pBAD18-pPhoA (pPhoA), pFH273 (cPhoA + cDsbA), or pFH273mut (cPhoA + cDsbA(APHA)), along with a pET21d derivative containing SxDsbB, SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>, SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C44A), or H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup> as indicated; and SHuffle cells carrying no plasmid (empty) or pFH-cPhoA (cPhoA). Data is the mean of biological triplicates and the error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM). (<bold>b</bold>) Western blot analysis of the same periplasmic (p) and cytoplasmic (c) fractions assayed in (<bold>a</bold>) as indicated. Blots were probed with anti-PhoA antibody to detect PhoA (top panel) and anti-GroEL antibody to detect GroEL (bottom panel), which served as a cytoplasmic fractionation marker and loading control. Molecular weight (MW) markers are shown on the left. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 10</xref> for uncropped versions of the blot images.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms864513f3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Structural characterization of solubilized DsbB by biological SAXS</title><p>Reconstructed particle envelopes calculated <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> from the SAXS data for cDsbA(C33A) as a monomer (yellow) or dimer (purple) (<bold>a</bold>) and tetrameric SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) (blue) and tetrameric SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>(C130S) crosslinked to cDsbA(C33A) (red) (<bold>b</bold>). Radius of gyration (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>g</sub>) and maximum particle size (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>max</sub>) are reported for each. Below each envelope is the corresponding crystal structure (PDB 1a23 for monomeric DsbA, PDB 1u3a for dimeric DsbA, PDB 2k74 for monomeric DsbB, PDB 2leg for the complex DsbB(C130S) and DsbA(C33A), PDB 2a01 for ApoAI and 1NL5 for MBP). For each construct, the mathematical representation of the fit for the corresponding crystal structure and its calculated envelope (log intensity, I(q), versus q) is plotted in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms864513f4.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Proper folding of complex substrate proteins by solubilized DsbB variants</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Disulfide bond connectivity for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phytase, AppA (4 disulfide bonds depicted by yellow circles connected by yellow lines). Phytase activity (measured as absorbance at 410 nm) in cytoplasmic fractions derived from: <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain DHB4(DE3) Δ<italic toggle="yes">dsbAB</italic> carrying no plasmids (empty) or pHIS-cAppA (cAppA) along with pET28-SxDsbB::GST-cDsbA, pET28-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>::GST-cDsbA, or pET28-H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup>::GST-cDsbA as indicated; and SHuffle cells carrying no plasmid (empty) or pHIS-cAppA (cAppA). (<bold>b</bold>) Western blot analysis of same cytoplasmic fractions assayed in (<bold>a</bold>). (<bold>c</bold>) Disulfide bond connectivity for murine urokinase, uPA (12 disulfide bonds depicted by yellow circles connected by yellow lines). Urokinase activity (measured as absorbance at 405 nm) in cytoplasmic fractions derived from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain BL21(DE3) carrying no plasmids (empty) or pET24b-urokinase along with pET28-SxDsbB::GST-cDsbA, pET28-SxDsbBΔC<sup>GZ</sup>::GST-cDsbA, or pET28-H<sub>0</sub>DsbB<sup>1/9b</sup>::GST-cDsbA as indicated; and SHuffle cells carrying no plasmid (empty) or pET24b-urokinase. (<bold>d</bold>) Western blot analysis of same cytoplasmic fractions assayed in (<bold>c</bold>). Blots were probed with anti-FLAG antibody to detect cAppA and c-uPA (top panels) and anti-GroEL antibody to detect GroEL (bottom panel), which served as a cytoplasmic fractionation marker and loading control. Molecular weight (MW) markers are shown on the left. Activity data is the mean of biological triplicates and the error bars represent the standard error of the mean (SEM). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 11</xref> for uncropped versions of the blot images.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms864513f5.jpg"/></fig></floats-group></article>