
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1558</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101532965</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals, LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5041909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5041909.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5041909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5041909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26992218</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.8129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8129</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ftx non coding RNA-derived miR-545 promotes cell proliferation by targeting RIG-I in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhikui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names initials="C">Changwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names initials="B">Bowen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="M">Meng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="L">Linglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yufeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kangsheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="T">Tao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qingguang</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic toggle="yes">Qingguang Liu,</italic><email>liuqingguang@vip.sina.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><italic toggle="yes">Tao Song,</italic><email>13572431619@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor3"><italic toggle="yes">Kangsheng Tu,</italic><email>tks0912@foxmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>18</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">276162</issue-id><fpage>25350</fpage><lpage>25365</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-20 00:25:28.243"><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2016 Liu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="16" journal-id="Oncotarget" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11837860"><article-title>Retraction: Ftx non coding RNA-derived miR-545 promotes cell proliferation by targeting RIG-I in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><volume>16</volume><date><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><source>Oncotarget</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.28695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11837860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39969212</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the third cause of cancer-related death worldwide. Accumulating studies have demonstrated that aberrant expression of several lncRNAs was found to be involved in the hepatocarcinogenesis. In this study, a lncRNA Ftx was chosen to investigate its effects on HCC cells, and clarify the possible mechanism. We demonstrated that the lncRNA Ftx and Ftx-derived miR-545 were up-regulated in both HCC tissues and cells. MiR-545 was positively correlated with lncRNA Ftx expression. Notably, clinical association analysis revealed that the high expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 was associated with poor prognostic features, and conferred a reduced 5-year overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) of HCC patients. We found that miR-545 was a pivotal mediator in Ftx-induced promotion of HCC cell growth. Subsequently, we identified RIG-I as a direct target of miR-545. The expression of RIG-I was downregulated in HCC tissues and was inversely correlated with miR-545 expression. Our data revealed that ectopic expression of RIG-I abrogated the effects of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 on HCC cells. LncRNA Ftx/miR-545-mediated downregulation of RIG-I led to increased Akt phosphorylation <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Inhibition of Akt phosphorylation abolished the effects of lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 on HCC cells. In conclusion, our study demonstrates that the novel pathway lncRNA Ftx/miR-545/RIG-I promotes HCC development by activating PI3K/Akt signaling, and it may serve as a novel prognostic biomarker and therapeutic target for HCC.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ftx</kwd><kwd>miR-545</kwd><kwd>hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>RIG-I</kwd><kwd>proliferation</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the most common primary malignancy in liver and the third leading cause of cancer-related death worldwide [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Despite the clinical and experimental treatment of HCC were progressed, the long-term survival of HCC remains poor due to lack of the distinct clinical manifestation and late diagnosis [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Currently, the detailed mechanism of hepatocarcinogenesis has not been fully elucidated. Hence, it is urgent to elucidate the underlying molecular mechanisms of HCC, and develop novel tumor markers and therapeutic strategies for the early diagnosis and treatment of HCC.</p><p>In recent years, accumulating studies have demonstrated that a class of long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are involved in various human cancers [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], including HCC [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], gastric cancer [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and colorectal carcinoma [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. LncRNAs are a family of regulatory RNA molecules that are greater than 200 nucleotides in length. Aberrant expression of several lncRNAs play crucial roles in various physiological and pathological processes, such as cell proliferation, apoptosis, differentiation, migration and invasion [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, these lncRNAs could be employed as novel therapeutic targets [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. There have also been reported that the levels of Ftx were predominantly downregulated in breast cancer samples [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Ftx is dispensable for imprinted X-chromosome inactivation (XCI) and is located in the cis-acting regulatory region of the imprinted XCI and expressed from the inactive Xp [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Ftx partially escapes X-inactivation and is upregulated specifically in female ES cells at the onset of X-inactivation [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Ftx is transcribed in different RNA isoforms and contains within intron 12 a cluster of two miRNAs well conserved indifferent mammalian species [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Surprisingly, a related cluster of miRNAs (miR-374a and miR-545) is found within Ftx in most mammalian species [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Studies have shown that Ftx can encode miR-545 and encoding miR-545 might be one of the important roles of Ftx in HCC [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Previous studies show that miR-545 functions as a regulator of cell proliferation, cell cycle and apoptosis in human cancers [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. miR-545 enhanced radiosensitivity via suppressing Ku70 expression and tumor-specific recruitment of regulator T cells in lung carcinoma [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. MiR-545 suppresses DNA damage during the cell cycle by modulating endogenous BRCA1 p200 in breast cancer [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. MiR-545 inhibited pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma growth by targeting RIG-I [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Our previous studies have demonstrated that the low expression of RIG-I contributes to a more aggressive phenotype of HCC [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. RIG-I knockdown promoted tumor cell proliferation, and facilitated migration and invasion of HCC cells by regulating MMP9. However, the expression of miR-545 and its role in HCC initiation and progression, and whether it can exert its function by targeting RIG-I in HCC remain unknown. Moreover, the clinical significance of lncRNA Ftx and its biological functions, and co-expression network of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 are also poorly investigated.</p><p>The aim of the present study was to determine the roles of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in HCC and their relationship with clinicopathological factors. Furthermore, the functions of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in HCC cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle were investigated in <italic toggle="yes">vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Furthermore, RIG-I, a well-known tumor suppressor, was identified as a novel target of miR-545, and mediates Ftx/miR-545-induced HCC cell proliferation. Thus, we suggested a new signaling pathway, Ftx/miR-545/RIG-I, facilitates HCC progression, and it may serve as a potential diagnostic and therapeutic target for HCC.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>LncRNA Ftx was upregulated in HCC tissues and cell lines and correlated with miR-545 expression</title><p>Studies showed that the lncRNA Ftx is proven to be the precursor of miR-545 in both human and mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). We investigate the expression levels of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in one hundred and twenty-six pairs of HCC tissues and matched tumor-adjacent tissues using qRT-PCR. The results showed that the expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in HCC tissues were significantly higher than that in the non-tumor tissues (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B, 1C</xref>) and correlated with each other (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.6455, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.0001, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). Further results confirmed that lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 were upregulated in a panel of HCC cell lines (HepG2, Huh7, Hep3B, SMMC-7721 and Bel-7402) compared with that in non-transformed LO2 hepatic cell line (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>). Moreover, the expression levels of Ftx and miR-545 in five HCC cell lines were correlated with each other (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.9539, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0008, data not shown). These results were consistent with lncRNA Ftx was the primary precursor of miR-545, but also indicated that miR-545 may mediate Ftx-induced HCC progression.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in HCC tissues and cell lines</title><p><bold>A.</bold> Genomic location of the lncRNA Ftx and its mature product miR-545. Relative lncRNA Ftx <bold>B.</bold> and miR-545 <bold>C.</bold> expression levels in HCC tissues and matched adjacent normal tissues were determined by qRT-PCR (n=126). <bold>D.</bold> Positive correlation of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 expression in HCC tissues <bold>E.</bold> The expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in fiveHCC cell lines were significantly increased compared to that in the LO2 cells. U6 snRNA was used as internal control. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>Clinical significance of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 expression in HCC specimens</title><p>We determined the mean level of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 as a cutoff value to investigate the correlation with clinical features and prognosis of HCC patients. As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, the high expression of lncRNA Ftx was prominently associated with a large tumor size (≥5 cm; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>= 0.001), high histological grade (Edmondson–Steiner grade III + IV; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001) and advanced tumor stage (TNM stage III + IV; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>= 0.043). The high expression of miR-545 was prominently associated with a large tumor size (≥5 cm; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> =0.000), venous infiltration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.040), high histological grade (Edmondson–Steiner grade III + IV; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>= 0.037) and advanced tumor stage (TNM stage III + IV; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>= 0.004). These results indicate that aberrant expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 is correlated with poor clinical features of HCC patients. Furthermore, Kaplan-Meier analysis showed that the high lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 expression was closely associated with shorter overall survival (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) and disease-free survival (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>), consistently, the HCC patients with high lncRNA Ftx and high miR-545 had worst OS and DFS (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1A and 1B</xref>), which highlights the potential value of the molecule as a predictive biomarker for the outcome of HCC.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Correlation between the clinicopathologic characteristics and lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 expression in HCC (n = 126)</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinical parameters</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cases</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Expression level</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Expression level</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ftx<sup>high</sup>(n=65)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ftx<sup>low</sup>(n=61)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-545<sup>high</sup>(n=70)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-545<sup>low</sup>(n=56)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age(years)</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 65 years</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.840</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥65 years</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.642</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor size (cm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5cm</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥5cm</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor number</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> solitary</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.577</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.873</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> multiple</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edmondson</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I+II</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III+IV</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNM stage</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I+II</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III+IV</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capsular</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Present</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.708</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Absent</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venous infiltration</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Present</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.716</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Absent</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;400ng/ml</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥400ng/ml</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBsAg</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.822</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; TNM, tumor-node-metastasis.</p><fn id="tfn_001"><label>*</label><p>Statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The prognostic value of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 for HCC patients assessed by Kaplan-Meier analysis</title><p>HCC patients with high expression of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 had worse <bold>A.</bold> overall survival (OS) and <bold>B.</bold> disease-free survival (DFS).<sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Overexpression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 promotes proliferation and cell cycle progression of HCC cell</title><p>To investigate the biological function of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in the development and progression of HCC, we transfected HCC cell line SMMC-7721 with pcDNA-Ftx and miR-545 mimics respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Cell viability was measured using MTT assays and we observed that ectopic expression of lncRNA Ftx had more viability over time compared with NC group (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Consistently, the upregulated expression of lncRNA Ftx markedly enhance the colony formation by the increase in colony number (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). Furthermore, the level of DNA synthesis, examined with BrdU incorporation assay, was significantly elevated in lncRNA Ftx transduced SMMC-7721 cells, whereas the vector control cells displayed relatively lower BrdU incorporation rates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). Cell cycle analysis revealed that overexpression of lncRNA Ftx decreased the number of cells in the G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle while the S-phase population increased in SMMC-7721 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>). Similarly, miR-545overexpression promoted cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression in miR-545-overexpressing SMMC-7721 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, respectively, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B-3E</xref>). Collectively, these results demonstrate that lncRNA Ftx and miR-545functions to enhance proliferation, tumorigenicity and cell cycle progression of HCC cells.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>LncRNA Ftx or miR-545 promotes cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell-cycle progression in SMMC-7721 cells</title><p><bold>A.</bold> The expression of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 was measured in HCC cell SMMC-7721 after transfected by pcDNA-Ftx or miR-545 mimics. <bold>B.</bold> Cell viability was evaluated by the MTT assay at the indicated days. <bold>C.</bold> Representative results for colony formation by the indicated cells. <bold>D.</bold> Representative micrographs (left) and quantification (right) of BrdU incorporating-cells of indicated SMMC-7721 cells. <bold>E.</bold> Effects of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 overexpression on the cell cycle progression of SMMC-7721 cells measured by flow cytometry analysis. Experiments were repeated at least 3 times with similar results, and error bars represent ± SD. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05,<sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01. Scale bar: 100μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Inhibition of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 attenuates proliferation and cell cycle progression of HCC cell</title><p>Loss-of-function studies were further performed to confirm the biological function by Ftx siRNA and anti-miR-545 vector. The expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 was significantly decreased in Hep3B cell (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>, downregulation of lncRNA Ftx led to a significant reduction of cell viability. Furthermore, suppression of lncRNA Ftx significantly inhibited the colony formation ability (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). BrdU incorporation rates were performed to determine the effect of altering lncRNA Ftx level on HCC cell proliferation, we found that downregulation of lncRNA Ftx significantly inhibited the proliferation in Hep3B cell (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). In addition, flow cytometry showed a significant increase in the percentage of cells in G1/G0 phase and a decrease in the percentage of cells in S phase in Hep3B transfected with the lncRNA Ftx siRNA compared with control transfected cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E</xref>). Similarly, miR-545 downregulation inhibited cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression in anti-miR-545Hep3B cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, respectively, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B-4E</xref>). These results demonstrated that lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 regulates the proliferation, tumorigenicity and cell cycle of HCC cells.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Inhibition of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 reduces cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell-cycle progression in Hep3B cells</title><p><bold>A.</bold> The expression of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 was measured in HCC cell Hep3B after transfected by Ftx siRNA or miR-545inhibitor. <bold>B.</bold> Cell viability was evaluated by the MTT assay at the indicated days. <bold>C.</bold> Representative results for colony formation by the indicated cells. <bold>D.</bold> Representative micrographs (left) and quantification (right) of BrdU incorporating-cells of indicated Hep3B cells. <bold>E.</bold> Effects of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545downregulation on the cell cycle progression of Hep3B cells measured by flow cytometry analysis.Experiments were repeated at least 3 times with similar results, and error bars represent ± SD. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05. Scale bar: 100μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>LncRNA Ftx promotes cell proliferation and cell cycle progression which was mediated via miR-545</title><p>Several recent reports have confirmed that lncRNA may function as a competing endogenous RNA (ceRNA) or a molecular sponge in modulating the concentration and biological functions of miRNA [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], suggesting that there might be correlation between expression of lncRNA and miRNA. We found that overexpression of lncRNA Ftx significantly increased miR-545 expression, while, lncRNA Ftx knockdown markedly reduced the expression levels of miR-545(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). By contrast, alterations of miR-545 levels did not influence the expression of lncRNA Ftx (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). To elucidate whether miR-545 plays pivotal roles in Ftx-induced HCC cell proliferation, miR-545 was knocked down bymiR-545 inhibitor in Ftx-overexpressing SMMC-7721 cells and miR-545 was restored by miR-545 mimics in Ftx-suppressive Hep3B cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). Furthermore, miR-545 knockdown markedly abolished the upregulation of Ftx-induced cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D-5G</xref>). Similarly, miR-545 overexpression restored the cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression inhibition of Hep3B cells by Ftx siRNA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, respectively, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D-5G</xref>). These results suggested that lncRNA Ftx regulates the HCC cell proliferation phenotype via miR-545.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>miR-545 mediated the tumor-promoted effects of lnc RNA Ftx on HCC cell lines</title><p><bold>A.</bold> The expression of miR-545 in Ftx knockdown or overexpressed cells validated using qRT-PCR. <bold>B.</bold> The expression of lncRNA Ftx in miR-545 knockdown or overexpressed cells validated using qRT-PCR. <bold>C.</bold> LncRNA Ftx-overexpressing SMMC-7721 that were transfected with miR-545 inhibitor and LncRNA Ftx -suppressive Hep3B cells that were transfected with miR-545 mimics and were subjected to qRT-PCR analysis for miR-545. n = three repeats with similar results. The correlations between lncRNA Ftx effects and miR-545 knockdown or overexpression are shown in the <bold>D.</bold> cell viability, <bold>E.</bold> colony formation, <bold>F.</bold> cell proliferation and <bold>G.</bold> cell cycle progression. miR-545 knockdown abrogated the effects of lncRNA Ftxoverexpression on SMMC-7721 cells. miR-545 overexpression induced effects that were opposite to those stimulated by lncRNA Ftx knockdown in Hep3B cells. n = three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>RIG-I is a direct downstream target of miR-545 in HCC</title><p>Previous study revealed that RIG-I was a direct target of miR-545 in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Our group demonstrated that RIG-I was downregulated in HCC. To confirm that whether RIG-I was a direct target of miR-545 in HCC, we used TargetScan to find that 3′-UTR of RIG-I contained the highly conserved putative miR-545 binding sites (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). qRT-PCR and Western blot analysis showed that ectopic expression of miR-545 dramatically decreased, whereas inhibition of miR-545 increased the mRNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>) and protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>) expression of RIG-I. In addition, when co-transfected with RIG-I-3′-UTR luciferase reporter plasmid, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>, the overexpression of miR-545 prominently reduced the luciferase activity of RIG-I reporter. Whereas, transfection of anti-miR-545 increased the luciferase activity of RIG-I. While the luciferase activity was unaffected by the miR-545-mut (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>). To further validate that RIG-I was a direct downstream target of miR-545, we examined the correlation between miR-545 level and RIG-I expression in HCC tissues. Moreover, we found the expression of RIG-I mRNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>) and protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F</xref>) in the miR-545 high-expressing tumors were significantly lower than those in the miR-545 low-expressing tumors. Notably, an obvious inverse correlation between miR-545 and RIG-I mRNA was revealed by Spearman's correlation analysis in HCC tissues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G</xref>). Collectively, these results strongly suggested that RIG-I is a downstream target of miR-545 in HCC.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>RIG-I is a direct target of miR-545 in HCC cells</title><p><bold>A.</bold> TargetScan was demonstrated that 3′-UTR of RIG-I contained the highly conserved putative miR-545 binding sites. <bold>B.</bold> qRT-PCR analysis of RIG-I mRNA expression in SMMC-7721 cells with miR-545 or negative control (NC) transfection andHep3B cells with anti-miR-545 or anti-miR-NC vector transfection. n = three repeats with similar results. <bold>C.</bold> Overexpression of miR-545 reduced the expression of RIG-I protein in SMMC-7721 cells and knockdown of miR-545 increases the level of RIG-I protein in Hep3B cells. n = three repeats with similar results. <bold>D.</bold> miR-545 significantly suppressed the luciferase activity of RIG-I. Anti-miR-545 led to a notable increase in the luciferase activity of 3′-UTR of RIG-I. MiR-545-mut had no influence on the luciferase activity of RIG-I. n = three repeats with similar results. <bold>E.</bold> The expression of RIG-ImRNA in miR-545 high-expressing tumors was significantly lower than that in miR-545 low-expressing tumors. <bold>F.</bold> A significant inverse correlation between miR-545 and RIG-I protein expression was observed in HCC tissues. Representative immunohistochemical staining showed a weak staining of RIG-I in miR-545 high-expressing HCC tissue and strong staining of RIG-I in the miR-545 low-expressing tumor. <bold>G.</bold> A statistically significant inverse correlation was shown between miR-545 and RIG-I mRNA levels in HCC specimens by Spearman's correlation analysis.<sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01. Scale bar: 100μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title>RIG-I is a critical mediator for the effects of lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis on cell proliferation and cell cycle progression of HCC</title><p>To confirm that the effects of lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 in HCC cells were mediated by RIG-I, we suppressed RIG-I expression by specific siRNA in miR-545-suppressive Hep3B cells and increased RIG-I expression in miR-545-overexpressing SMMC-7721cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). We found that cell viability (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>), colony formation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>) and proliferation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref>) was significantly increased by RIG-I knockdown. Furthermore, RIG-I knockdown markedly rescued the downregulation of miR-545-induced cell cycle (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7E</xref>). Similarly, RIG-I overexpression inhibited cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and promoted G0/G1 phase in miR-545-overexpressing SMMC-7721 cells (respectively, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A-7E</xref>). In consistent, knockdown of RIG-I reverses the effect of lncRNA Ftx siRNA, while ectopic expression of RIG-I counteracts the effect of lncRNA Ftx in Hep3B and SMMC-7721 HCC cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression (respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7F-7J</xref>). These results indicated that RIG-I is an important functional downstream mediator of lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis in HCC.</p><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Alterations of RIG-I partially abolish lncRNA Ftx/miR-545-mediated HCC cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression</title><p><bold>A,F.</bold> LncRNA Ftx/miR-545-suppressive Hep3B cells that were transfected with EV or RIG-I expression plasmid and lncRNA Ftx/miR-545-overexpressing SMMC-7721 that were transfected with control siRNA or RIG-I siRNA were subjected to western blot analysis for RIG-I. n = three repeats with similar results. The correlations between lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 effects and RIG-I knockdown or overexpression are shown in the <bold>B,G.</bold> cell viability, <bold>C,H.</bold> colony formation, <bold>D,I.</bold> cell proliferation and <bold>E,J.</bold> cell cycle progression. RIG-I knockdown abrogated the effects of lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 knockdown on Hep3B cells. RIG-I overexpression induced effects that were opposite to those stimulated by pcDNA-Ftx or miR-545. n = three independent experiments. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_8"><title>LncRNA Ftx-miR-545 axis promoted HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression by activating PI3K/Akt signaling in <italic toggle="yes">vitro</italic></title><p>In cancer cell proliferation and cell cycle progression, the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway has been shown to play an important role and is aberrantly regulated. Previous studies have been demonstrated that the RIG-I expression was associated with the activation of PI3K/Akt signaling [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], so we further investigate that whether dysregulation lncRNA Ftx-miR545 axis alters the activity of PI3K/Akt signaling in HCC cells. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>, overexpressing miR-545 significantly increased, but silencing miR-545 decreased, the Akt activity and the expression of phosphorylated Akt (Ser473) in HCC cells. Consistently, the levels of Cyclin D1 and p27, two downstream effectors of PI3K/Akt signaling, were also significantly altered in the miR-545-deregulated HCC cells. Similarly, lncRNA Ftx overexpression or downregulation exerts the same function (respectively, P&lt;0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A, 8B</xref>). These results indicate that lncRNA Ftx-miR-545 axis activates PI3K/Akt signaling. Furthermore, we examined whether activation of PI3K/Akt signaling contributed to lncRNA Ftx-miR-545-mediated HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression. Inactivation of PI3K/Akt signaling by Akt inhibitor significantly decreased the cell viability (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>), colony formation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>), proliferation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8E</xref>) and promoted the percentage of G0/G1 phase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8F</xref>). Moreover, the Cyclin D1 expression significantly decreased, but p27 increased, in the miR-545-transfected cells or lncRNA Ftx-overexpressing cells treated with Akt inhibitor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8G</xref>). Taken together, our results demonstrate that PI3K/Akt signaling plays essential function during lncRNA Ftx-miR-545-induced HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression.</p><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Activated PI3K/Akt signaling is essential for lncRNA Ftx/miR-545-promoted HCC proliferation and cell cycle progression</title><p><bold>A, B.</bold> Western blotting analysis of p-Akt (Ser473), total Akt, Cyclin D1 and p27 protein levels in indicated cells. GAPDH was used as a loading control. Quantification of cell viability <bold>C.</bold> colony formation <bold>D.</bold> cell proliferation <bold>E.</bold> and cell cycle <bold>F.</bold> in indicated HCC cell treated with Akt inhibitor (0.5 μM). G. The protein expression level of Cyclin D1 and p27 by Western blot analysis in indicated HCC cell treated with Akt inhibitor (0.5 μM). Experiments were repeated at least 3 times with similar results, and error bars represent ± SD. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_9"><title>LncRNA Ftx-miR-545 axis promoted HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression by activating PI3K/Akt signaling <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>Our in <italic toggle="yes">vitro</italic> study has shown lncRNA Ftx-miR-545 axis functions as an oncogene and promotes HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression by activating PI3K/Akt signaling. To determine the function of HCC cell produced-lncRNA Ftx in <italic toggle="yes">vivo</italic>, Hep3B cells with lncRNA Ftx knockdown or control vector were implanted subcutaneously into nude mice. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A-9C</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>, in the lncRNA Ftx knockdown group, the tumor volume and weight were smaller than that in the control group. Furthermore, the downregulation of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in the tumor formation in subcutaneous models (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9D</xref>), inhibited the activation of PI3K/Akt signaling (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9E</xref>). Importantly, the isolated tumor tissues were subjected to immunohistochemistry for Ki67 assays. Our data confirmed that lncRNA Ftx knockdown inhibited cell proliferation in <italic toggle="yes">vivo</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9F</xref>). Taken together, these data strongly suggested that RIG-I-mediated activation of PI3K/Akt by lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis is a key regulatory pathway for HCC initiation and progression.</p><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>LncRNA Ftx promotes HCC growth by activating PI3K/Akt signaling <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p><bold>A.</bold> Representative pictures of HCC xenografts from both Hep3B Vector (left panel) and Hep3B-Ftx siRNA cells (right panel). Tumor volume <bold>B.</bold> and weight <bold>C.</bold> revealed that lncRNA Ftx knockdown significantly inhibited tumor growth <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. <bold>D.</bold> Expression of lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 in siRNA-treated tumors from subcutaneous model. <bold>E.</bold> Expression of RIG-I, p-Akt, Akt, Cyclin D1, p27 were assessed insubcutaneous model by Western blotting. <bold>F.</bold> LncRNA Ftx knockdown inhibited proliferation <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. The photomicrographs for Ki-67 staining were shown. The percentage of Ki-67 positive cells in tumors arisingfrom Hep3B-Ftx siRNA group was signifiantly lower than that arising from Hep3B-control group. n = eight, <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt; 0.01 by t test. Scale bar: 100μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-g009.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) were once neglected and considered to have no function in cells for a long time because they don't encode any proteins [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, recent advances have discovered extensive transcription of ncRNAs by human genome analysis, termed long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Increasing evidences confirmed their various roles in biological processes, such as regulations of gene transcription, posttranscriptional regulation of RNA splicing, and containing information [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, accumulating studies have demonstrated that multiple lncRNAs are dysregulated in HCC and closely related with tumorgenesis, prognosis and diagnosis [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Therefore, identification of specific lncRNAs and their underlying mechanism involved in tumorgenesis may provide promising therapeutic targets for HCC. LncRNA Ftx is the most abundant transcript at the preimplantation embryo stage except for Xist. Chureau [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] et al. proposed that Ftx is a positive regulator of Xist, as deletion of the Ftx promoter leads to decreased Xist expression in male embryonic stem cells. Previous studies identify that chromatin-associated lncRNAs, such as Ftx, were predominantly downregulated in breast tumor samples. Moreover, lncRNA Ftx gives rise to a group of miRNAs, of which miR-545 has been identified in HCC, lung cancer, breast cancer and pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma. In HBV-related HCC, miR-545 in the Ftx lncRNA was overexpressed and promoted tumorigenesis and tumor progression. miR-545 inhibited pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma growth by targeting RIG-I [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Interestingly, our previous studies showed that RIG-I was downregulated and its overexpression inhibited the progression of HCC. So we attempted to address the following question: 1. what is the expression level of lncRNA Ftx and its relationship with clinical characteristics in HCC? 2. Whether lncRNA Ftx can regulate the HCC cell proliferation phenotype via miR-545? 3. Whether LncRNA Ftx-derived miR-545 can modulate cell proliferation of HCC cells by targeting RIG-I? 4. What is the underlying mechanisms of the lncRNA Ftx/miR-545/RIG-I axis in the progression of HCC?</p><p>In the present study, we identified that both lncRNA Ftx and miR-545 were upregulated in HCC tissues compared to matched tumor-adjacent tissues and this was also observed in HCC cells. In addition, the lncRNA Ftx expression was positively correlated with the miR-545 expression. The expression of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 was significantly correlated with clinicopathological features, including tumor size, venous infiltration, high histological grade and TNM stage and the higher lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 had a worse prognosis. Furthermore, ectopic expression of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 promoted cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle progression in HCC cells. Furthermore, the lncRNA Ftx knockdown could downregulated miR-545, while overexpression increased miR-545 in HCC cells. Overexpression of miR-545 restores lncRNA Ftx knockdown-induced inhibition, while knockdown of miR-545 rescues lncRNA Ftx overexpressing-induced promotion HCC cell proliferation and cell cycle progression. Based on the above results, the lncRNA Ftx exerted the tumor-promoted function was mediated, at least in part, via miR-545. However, the functional role of miR-545 in this progress was still unknown. Previous study showed that RIG-I was a target of miR-545. In the study, Results of the present study suggest that miR-545 promoted tumor growth, at least in part, by targeting RIG-I. Firstly, miR-545 was inversely correlated with the levels of both RIG-I mRNA and protein in HCC tissues. Secondly, miR-545 negatively regulated RIG-I abundance in HCC cells. Thirdly, the complementary sequence of miR-545 was identified in the 3′-UTR of RIG-I mRNA. Knockdown of miR-545 increased the luciferase reporter activity of wt 3′-UTR but not mt 3′-UTR of RIG-I. Conversely, the overexpression of miR-545 decreased the luciferase activity of wt 3′-UTR but not mt 3′-UTR of RIG-I. The effects of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 alteration on cell viability, colony formation, proliferation and cell cycle of HCC cells were also abolished by RIG-I modulation. Collectively, our results support RIG-I as a downstream mediator of miR-545 function in HCC. Additionally, we found lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 led to upregulation of cell cycle regulator Cyclin D1 and downregulation of p27 through activation of PI3K/Akt <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">vivo</italic>. Collectively, our results demonstrate that lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis promotes HCC progression through activation of Akt signaling pathway by targeting RIG-I.</p><p>Numerous studies showed that activation of the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway is essential to the development and progression of HCC and associated with malignant phenotype of HCC, such as cell proliferation, invasiveness, angiogenesis and metastasis [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. PI3K/Akt signaling could be activated by RIG-I to promote efficient type I interferon production [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Interestingly, we discovered that the effects of lncRNA Ftx or miR-545 overexpression on HCC cells could be inhibited by Akt inhibitor, which revealed that lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis exerts its function by activating PI3K/Akt signaling. Herein, we discovered that lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 activated PI3K/Akt signaling through targeting RIG-I may represent as a potential therapeutic for HCC therapy.</p><p>In conclusion, we demonstrated that lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 was frequently overexpressed in HCC tissues and cell lines. The lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 axis played a crucial role in the malignant progression of HCC cells through activation of PI3K/Akt by targeting RIG-I. Therefore, lncRNA Ftx/miR-545 has the potential to be a promising diagnostic biomarker, a novel prognostic factor and therapeutic target for HCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4_1"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Written informed consent was obtained from all patients recruited in this study and this study was also approved by the Xi'an Jiaotong University Ethics Committee according to the Declaration of Helsinki. In addition, all experimental protocols were approved by the institutional animal care and use committee of our hospital.</p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title>Tissue specimens and cell lines</title><p>Tumor samples and matched tumor-adjacent tissues were obtained from 126 patients in our hospital from January, 2006 to December, 2009. No patients received preoperative chemo- or radiotherapy before surgery. The human immortalized normal hepatic cell line LO2 and HCC cell lines (HepG2, Hep3B, Huh7, SMMC-7721 and Bel-7402) were obtained from the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China). The cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) at 37°C with 5% CO2.Akt inhibitor MK-2206 (1 μM, Selleck Chemicals, Houston, TX, USA) was used to treat cells according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title>RNA extraction and quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from tissues or cells using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following to the manufacturer's instruction. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed using SYBR Premix Ex Taq II (TaKaRa). TaqMan microRNA assays (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA) were used to quantify the expression levels. Forward and reverse primers were used as follows: RIG-I, TGT GCT CCT ACA GGT TGT GGA and CAC TGG GAT CTG ATT CGC AAA A; miR-545, UCA GCA AAC AUU UAU UGU GUG C and GCG AGC ACA GAA TTA ATA CGA C; Ftx, TAT GCC ACC TAG CCT TTC TAC A and ATC TCT TCA AAA GCG GCA TAA T; U6, CGC TTC GGC AGC ACA TAT ACT A and CGC TTC ACG AAT TTG CGT GTC A; GAPDH, CAA GGT CAT CCA TGA CAA CTT TG and GTC CAC CAC CCT GTT GCT GTA G.</p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Total protein was extracted from whole cells and 40 μg of isolated protein was separated by 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred onto a PVDF membrane (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). The membranes were probed with antibodies: anti-Akt, anti-p-Akt, anti-RIG-I, anti-Cyclin D, and anti-p27 primary antibodies (Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA, USA) for overnight. Then the membranes were incubated with the HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse or anti-rabbit IgG antibody (ZSGB-BIO, China). Protein bands were visualized using an enhanced chemiluminescence kit (Amersham, Little Chalfont, UK).</p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title>Immunohistochemical staining</title><p>Immunohistochemistry was performed on paraformaldehyde-fixed paraffin sections. RIG-I (#3743; Cell Signaling) or Ki-67 (#9027; Cell Signaling) antibody was used in immunohistochemistry using a streptavidin peroxidase-conjugated (SP-IHC) method. Immunohistochemistry was performed as previously reported [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title>Plasmids, oligonucleotides, siRNA and transfection</title><p>The pcDNA-Ftx and Ftx siRNA, miR-545 mimics, scramble and inhibitor and control were obtained by Genepharma (Shanghai, China). RIG-I plasmid and siRNA were synthesized by GeneChem (Shanghai, China) [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Cells were transfected with oligonucleotides using Lipofectamine 2000 Reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies) following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title>MTT and colony formation assays</title><p>Cells (5×10<sup>3</sup>) transfected were seeded into 96-well plates and stained with 0.5 mg/ml sterile MTT (Sigma–Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) for 4 h at 37°C, following which the culture medium was discarded and an extra 150 μl DMSO (Sigma–Aldrich) added. The absorbance at 490 nm was measured at 24, 48 and 72 h after transfection. The colony formation assay was performed as described previously. Briefly, cells were seeded on six-well plates (500 cells/well). After 2 weeks, the colonies were stained with 1% crystal violet and the number of colonies was counted.</p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title>Cell cycle and cell proliferation assays</title><p>For cell cycle analysis, cells were transfected for 48 h and were collected, washed with PBS three times, fixed with 80% ethanol overnight at -20°C, and subsequently treated with RNaseA (Sigma) for 30 min at 37°C, followed by incubation in20 μg/ml of propidium iodide (Sigma) for 20 min at room temperature. After incubation, the cells were subjected to flow cytometry analysis using a FACS Calibur (BD Biosciences, Bedford, MA, USA). For proliferation, bromodeoxyuridine labeling and immunofluorescence was used. Cells grown on coverslips (Fisher, Pittsburgh, PA, USA) were incubated with bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) for 1 h and stained with anti-BrdU antibody (Sigma) according to the manufacturer's instruction. Gray level images were acquired under a laser scanning microscope (Axioskop 2 plus, Carl Zeiss Co. Ltd., Jena, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title>Luciferase reporter assay</title><p>Cells were seeded in triplicate in 24-well plate and allowed to settle for about 12 h. pGL3-RIG-I was co-transfected into HCC cells with TK-Renilla plasmid as control signals using Lipofectamine 2000. Luciferase and control signals were measured at 48h after transfection using the Dual Luciferase Reporter Assay Kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), according to a protocol provided by the manufacturer. Firefly luciferase activity was normalized to the Renilla luciferase activity. Three independent experiments were performed and the data were presented as the mean ± SD.</p></sec><sec id="s4_10"><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> experiments</title><p>4-6 week-old female BALB/c nude mice (Centre of Laboratory Animals, The Medical College of Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, China) were used to establish the nude mouse xenograft model. 5 × 10<sup>6</sup>Hep3B cells transfected with lncRNA Ftx siRNA expressing or control vectors were mixed in 100 uL of Matrigel and were inoculated subcutaneously into the flank of nude mouse. To assess the effects of siRNA therapy on tumor growth, treatment with siRNA (150 μg/kg percutaneous injection twice weekly) was initiated 1 week after injection of tumor cells. Mice were randomized into groups and treated with siRNA incorporated in neutral nanoliposomes (percutaneous administration). Tumor volume was determined by measuring two of its dimensions with calipers every 7 days, and then calculated as tumor volume = length × width × width/2. All mice were sacrificed at 3 weeks after the injection of HCC cells. The xenograft tumor tissues were explanted for pathological examination. All in vivo protocols were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Xi'an Jiaotong University.</p></sec><sec id="s4_11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data are presented as the mean ± SD from at least three independent replicates. SPSS software, 16.0 (SPSS, Inc, Chicago, IL, USA) was used to conduct the analysis, and a two-tailed Student t-test was employed to analyze the differences between two groups. Pearson's correlation analysis was used to analyze the correlation between two indices. Survival curves were plotted by the Kaplan-Meier method and compared by the log-rank test. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY FIGURES</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-25350-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d36e1546" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Scientific Foundation of China (No. 81272645, 81402039 and 81572847), Key Science and Technology Fund of Shaanxi Province (No. 2015SF052).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2011</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.20107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review of outcomes of liver resection for early hepatocellular carcinoma within the Milan criteria</article-title><source>The British journal of surgery</source><year>2012</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1622</fpage><lpage>1629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23023956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bjs.8915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><collab>American Association for the Study of Liver D</collab></person-group><article-title>Management of hepatocellular carcinoma: an update</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2011</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21374666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.24199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3084991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA CASC2 suppresses malignancy in human gliomas by miR-21</article-title><source>Cellular signalling</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25446261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cellsig.2014.11.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNAs: Novel insights into hepatocelluar carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer letters</source><year>2014</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24183851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2013.10.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence of long non-coding RNAs in the tumorigenesis of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer letters</source><year>2015</year><volume>360</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25721084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2015.02.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The long non-coding RNA H19-derived miR-675 modulates human gastric cancer cell proliferation by targeting tumor suppressor RUNX1</article-title><source>Biochemical and biophysical research communications</source><year>2014</year><volume>448</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24388988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2013.12.126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating lncRNAs associated with occurrence of colorectal cancer progression</article-title><source>American journal of cancer research</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2258</fpage><lpage>2265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26328256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4548337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unveiling the hidden function of long non-coding RNA by identifying its major partner-protein</article-title><source>Cell &amp; bioscience</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26500759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13578-015-0050-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4618879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer Specific Long Noncoding RNAs Show Differential Expression Patterns and Competing Endogenous RNA Potential in Hepatocellular Carcinoma</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0141042</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26492393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0141042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4619599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiche</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasack</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luders</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Due</surname><given-names>EU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naume</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borresen-Dale</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hackermuller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumbusch</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNAs differentially expressed between normal versus primary breast tumor tissues disclose converse changes to breast cancer-related protein-coding genes</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e106076</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25264628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0106076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4180073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ftx is dispensable for imprinted X-chromosome inactivation in preimplantation mouse embryos</article-title><source>Scientific reports</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>5181</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24899465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep05181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5381492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Totoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of an imprinted gene cluster in the X-inactivation center</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e71222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23940725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0071222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3735490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chureau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chantalat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougeulle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ftx is a non-coding RNA which affects Xist expression and chromatin structure within the X-inactivation center region</article-title><source>Human molecular genetics</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/ddq516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougeulle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin and evolution of the long non-coding genes in the X-inactivation center</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>2011</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21820484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biochi.2011.07.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The miR-545/374a cluster encoded in the Ftx lncRNA is overexpressed in HBV-related hepatocellular carcinoma and promotes tumorigenesis and tumor progression</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e109782</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25299640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0109782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4192320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-545 suppresses cell proliferation by targeting cyclin D1 and CDK4 in lung cancer cells</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e88022</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0088022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3914893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroR-545 enhanced radiosensitivity via suppressing Ku70 expression in Lewis lung carcinoma xenograft model</article-title><source>Cancer cell international</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26041979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12935-015-0207-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4453103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiotherapy suppressed tumor-specific recruitment of regulator T cells via up-regulating microR-545 in Lewis lung carcinoma cells</article-title><source>International journal of clinical and experimental pathology</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2535</fpage><lpage>2544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4440068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The BRCA1/2-directed miRNA signature predicts a good prognosis in ovarian cancer patients with wild-type BRCA1/2</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2397</fpage><lpage>2406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.2963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25537514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4385859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naetar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathania</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanellopoulou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological modulation of endogenous BRCA1 p220 abundance suppresses DNA damage during the cell cycle</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2274</fpage><lpage>2291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.225045.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3814647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-545 inhibited pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma growth by targeting RIG-I</article-title><source>FEBS letters</source><year>2014</year><volume>588</volume><fpage>4375</fpage><lpage>4381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25315416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.febslet.2014.10.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RIG-I suppresses the migration and invasion of hepatocellular carcinoma cells by regulating MMP9</article-title><source>International journal of oncology</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1710</fpage><lpage>1720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2015.2853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cacchiarelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legnini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sthandier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinappi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tramontano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozzoni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A long noncoding RNA controls muscle differentiation by functioning as a competing endogenous RNA</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22000014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2011.09.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3234495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multilayered complexity of ceRNA crosstalk and competition</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>505</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24429633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature12986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4113481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RIG-I modulates Src-mediated AKT activation to restrain leukemic stemness</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24412064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molcel.2013.12.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase and Akt are required for RIG-I-mediated anti-viral signalling through cross-talk with IPS-1</article-title><source>Immunology</source><year>2015</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25158146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/imm.12373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4298425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of Long Non-Coding RNAs on Tumorigenesis and Glioma Development</article-title><source>Brain tumor research and treatment</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24926466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14791/btrt.2014.2.1.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4049559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA: a new player in cancer</article-title><source>Journal of hematology &amp; oncology</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23725405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1756-8722-6-37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3693878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makunin</surname><suffix>IV</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Non-coding RNA</article-title><source>Human molecular genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>Spec No 1</issue><fpage>R17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16651366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/ddl046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serviss</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grander</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An emerging role for long non-coding RNAs in cancer metastasis</article-title><source>Frontiers in genetics</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25101115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fgene.2014.00234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4103511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging functional and mechanistic paradigms of mammalian long non-coding RNAs</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>6391</fpage><lpage>6400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22492512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gks296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3413108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PI3K pathway as drug target in human cancer</article-title><source>Journal of clinical oncology</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20085938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2009.25.3641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2834432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LIFR functions as a metastasis suppressor in hepatocellular carcinoma by negatively regulating phosphoinositide 3-kinase/AKT pathway</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26249360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/carcin/bgv108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-Regulated NRSN2 Promotes Cell Proliferation and Survival Through PI3K/Akt/mTOR Pathway in Hepatocellular Carcinoma</article-title><source>Digestive diseases and sciences</source><year>2015</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3011</fpage><lpage>3018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10620-015-3736-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>