
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3390</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijip</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8911335</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5806795</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5806795.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5806795</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5806795</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0394632017703274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0394632017703274</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tanshinone inhibits neuronal cell apoptosis and inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="L">Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0394632017703274">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0394632017703274">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="C">Chao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0394632017703274">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiangsan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0394632017703274">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0394632017703274"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-0394632017703274"><label>1</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, Shandong Provincial Hospital Affiliated to Shandong University, Jinan, China</aff><aff id="aff2-0394632017703274"><label>2</label>Department of Massage, Shandong Provincial Hospital Affiliated to Shandong University, Jinan, China</aff><aff id="aff3-0394632017703274"><label>3</label>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, The Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-0394632017703274">Qiangsan Sun, Department of Rehabilitation Medicine, The Second Hospital of Shandong University, No. 247, Beiyuan Road, Jinan 250033, China. Email: <email>sunqiangsan001@126.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">306426</issue-id><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>02</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-07 17:25:15.753"><day>07</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_0394632017703274.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7907936"><article-title>EXPRESSION OF CONCERN: ‘Tanshinone inhibits neuronal cell apoptosis and
inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat model’</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211000803</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211000803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33625269</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="35" elocation-id="20587384211040386" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8422817"><article-title>RETRACTION NOTICE: Tanshinone inhibits neuronal cell apoptosis and inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat model</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211040386</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8422817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34474601</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>We aimed to investigate the effect and mechanisms of tanshinone (TSN) IIA in cerebral infarction. The cerebral infarction rat model was established by middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO). After pretreatment with TSN, cerebral infarct volume, cerebral edema, and neurological deficits score were evaluated, as well as cell apoptosis in hippocampus and cortex of the brain was examined with terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) and the levels of interleukin-6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and C-reactive protein (CRP) were determined by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA). In addition, rat primary neuronal cells were isolated and cultured in oxygen-glucose deprivation (OGD) conditions. After pretreatment with TSN, cell viability and apoptosis were observed by 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay and flow cytometry analysis, respectively. The expressions of Bax and B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2) were detected by quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) and western blotting. Compared with untreated cerebral infarction rat, TSN treatment significantly reduced cerebral infarct volume, cerebral edema, and neurological deficits score (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Cell apoptosis as well as the levels of IL-6, TNF-α, and CRP in hippocampus and cortex of cerebral infarction rat were inhibited after pretreatment with TSN (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, TSN remarkably increased cell viability and inhibited cell apoptosis ratio (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in OGD-induced rat neuronal cells. Besides, TSN significantly downregulated the expression of Bax and upregulated Bcl-2 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). TSN IIA has a preventive effect on cerebral infarction by inhibiting neuronal cell apoptosis and inflammatory response in vitro and in vivo.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cell apoptosis</kwd><kwd>cerebral infarction</kwd><kwd>inflammatory response</kwd><kwd>tanshinone IIA</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Cerebral infarction is a severe cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease, which often occurs due to brain hypoxic-ischemic necrosis, resulting in embolism and thrombosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Although thrombectomy<sup><xref rid="bibr2-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and drug therapy<sup><xref rid="bibr3-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> have been widely applied to clinical therapy of cerebral infarction, the therapeutic effect is still limited. It has been well known that accelerated neuronal cell apoptosis and inflammatory response have been proved to be associated with the cerebral infarction.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Accordingly, drugs target to cell apoptosis and inflammatory response may be an effective treatment strategy in cerebral infarction.</p><p>Tanshinone (TSN) IIA is a lipophilic chemical found in <italic toggle="yes">Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic>.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> TSN has been revealed to be associated with cell lipid peroxidation, methyl guanine transferase activity, cell apoptosis, and anti-inflammatory effects.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Previous study showed that TSN was able to protect against brain injury.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> However, the mechanisms of TSN in cerebral infarction remain to be fully investigated.</p><p>Thus, this study established cerebral infarction rat model and oxygen-glucose deprivation (OGD) neuronal cell model and then evaluated the effects of pretreated TSN on cerebral infarct volume, cerebral edema, neurological deficits, cell apoptosis, and inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat, which aimed to uncover the effects and mechanisms of TSN in cerebral infarction in vitro and in vivo.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section1-0394632017703274"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="section2-0394632017703274"><title>Animal model</title><p>This study was approved by the local Animal Ethics Committee of the Animal Laboratory Center. A total of 45 healthy Sprague-Dawley male rats (250–280 g) were acclimatized under appropriate condition for a week before the experiment and then were randomly and equally assigned to three groups (n = 15 for each group): sham group, middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO) group, and TSN group. Before the MCAO operation, TSN (5 mg/kg) was intraperitoneally injected daily into rats in the TSN group for 7 days. Then, MCAO was performed in rats of MCAO and TSN groups. In brief, the rats were anesthetized using 5% chloral hydrate by intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection, and then an incision was cut in the cervical midline. The exposed external carotid arteries were closed by sterile suture, and the vascular clamp was used to clamp internal carotid artery. Subsequently, an incision in the common carotid artery was made, and then a silicone-coated suture (4-0) was inserted for ligation. After 2 h, the rats underwent reperfusion. Once the symptoms such as left hemiparesis, contralateral forelimb sagging, and standing instability were appeared in rats, the cerebral infarction model rats were considered to be successfully constructed. All the procedures of MCAO were performed in rats of the sham group but without the ligation. All the rats were sacrificed after the cerebral infarction model was induced. The hippocampus and cortex were collected.</p></sec><sec id="section3-0394632017703274"><title>Evaluation of cerebral edema</title><p>The brain water content was measured to evaluate cerebral edema. After reperfusion for 24 h, brain tissue samples were collected from cerebral infarct areas in rats of the MCAO and TSN groups and from corresponding areas in rats of the sham group. The wet weight was obtained from untreated samples and the dry weight was obtained from dried sample using a desiccating oven. Brain water content was measured with (wet weight − dry weight) × 100/wet weight.</p></sec><sec id="section4-0394632017703274"><title>Assay of cerebral infarct volume</title><p>After reperfusion for 6 h, 24 h, 3 days, 7 days, and 14 days, the rats were sacrificed by chloral hydrate and the brains were cut rapidly. Then forebrains were dissected into six sections in coronal plane (2-mm thick), and each section was stained with 2% 2,3,5-triphenyltetrazolium chloride (TTC) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) for 5 min. Image J analysis software (V1.6; NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA) was used to measure the cerebral infarct volume in each slice.</p></sec><sec id="section5-0394632017703274"><title>Neurological evaluation</title><p>After reperfusion for 24 h, neurological deficits were evaluated according to the previously described procedure.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Score was defined as following—0: no neurologic deficit; 1: fail to fully extend left forepaw; 2: circle to the left forepaw; 3: fall to the left forepaw; and 4: fail to walk spontaneously and have a depression.</p></sec><sec id="section6-0394632017703274"><title>TUNEL assay</title><p>The rat hippocampus and cortical tissues were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde and then paraffin-embedded. The sections were then dewaxed and dehydrated. The TUNEL method was used to detect DNA fragmentation in tissue cells by In Situ Cell Death Detection Kit (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). In brief, the sections were reacted with reaction mixture in dark at 37°C for 60 min and fluorescence microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) was used to observe fluorescence. The cells with positive signals in each sample were counted in 10 randomly selected visual fields.</p></sec><sec id="section7-0394632017703274"><title>Detection of inflammatory factor levels</title><p>The cortical tissue was placed in ice-cold homogenization buffer and then supernatants were obtained by centrifugation at 3000 r/min for 15 min. The levels of interleukin-6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and C-reactive protein (CRP) were detected using the corresponding Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) Kits (Shanghai Kexing Biochemical Reagent Co., Ltd, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="section8-0394632017703274"><title>Cell culture and treatment</title><p>Five newborn rats, approximately 1-day old, were used to isolate the primary neuronal cells. Briefly, rats were anesthetized and sacrificed by cervical dislocation. The hippocampal tissues were collected and then digested using 0.05% trypsin. After centrifugation, the cell deposits (neuronal cells) were cultured in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) containing 5% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The neuronal cells were divided into control group, OGD group, and TSN group. Cells in the TSN group were cultured in DMEM with 5 µg/mL TSN for 5 days. Then, OGD was performed in the OGD and TSN groups. In brief, the medium was changed with glucose-free medium to induce the final glucose concentration &lt;1 mM. Both cells in the OGD and TSN groups were cultured under the condition of 95% N<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, while cells in the control group were cultured in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After culturing for 4 h, the medium was changed with the original conditions.</p></sec><sec id="section9-0394632017703274"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>The treated cells (1 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well) were plated on a 96-well plate and incubated for 24, 48, and 72 h. MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) (10 µL, 5 mg/mL) (Shanghai) was added into each well at the same time every day and then the cells were incubated for 4 h. A total of 100 µL dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO, formazan solution, from Beyotime, Shanghai, China) was added. The absorbance (optical density) was read at 570 nm using a microplate reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="section10-0394632017703274"><title>Cell apoptosis assay</title><p>Cell apoptosis was evaluated using Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection kit (BD, San Jose, CA, USA). Briefly, after 72 h of treatment, cells were collected and washed with cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Then, the cells were added into Binding Buffer, and then Annexin V-FITC and propidium iodide (PI) were incubated with cells in dark for 15 min. Cells apoptotic rate was calculated according to flow cytometer (BD).</p></sec><sec id="section11-0394632017703274"><title>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR)</title><p>The cells in the three groups were collected. The total RNA was extracted using Trizol (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and complementary DNA was obtained by reverse transcription. SYBR<sup>®</sup> Premix Ex Taq™ (TaKaRa, Shiga, Japan) was used to perform PCR amplification. The PCR program was as follows: 95°C for 3 min, 39 cycles at 95°C for 10 s, and 55°C for 30 s. Primers for glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH), B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2), and Bax are as follows: Bcl-2 forward: 5′-CATCAGGAAGGCTAGAGTTACC-3′ and Reverse: 5′-CAGACATTCGGAGAC CACAC-3′; Bax Forward: 5′-GAT GCGTCCACCAAGAAG-3′ and Reverse: 5′-AGTTGAAGTTGCCGTCAG-3′; and GAPDH Forward: 5′-AGCTTCGGCACATATTTCATCTG-3′ and Reverse: 5′-CGT TCACTCCCATGACAAACA-3′. The relative messenger RNA (mRNA) levels of Bcl-2 and Bax were calculated by comparative threshold (Ct) cycle method (2<sup>−ΔΔ</sup>Ct).</p></sec><sec id="section12-0394632017703274"><title>Western blotting</title><p>The cells in the three groups were placed on ice for 30 min in lysis buffer (Beyotime). Supernatant was acquired by centrifugation at 12,000 r/min for 20 min at 4°C. Protein sample was separated on sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) gel and then transferred onto polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes. Defatted milk (5%) was used to block the membranes at room temperature for 1 h and then the membranes were incubated with goat anti-rat GAPDH monoclonal antibody (1:1000, Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA, USA), goat anti-rat BCL-2 polyclonal antibody (1:500, Santa Cruz), and goat anti-rat Bax polyclonal antibody (1:500, Santa Cruz) at 4°C overnight. After being washed for three times with PBS, the membranes were incubated with donkey anti-goat IgG (H+L)-horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (1:5000, Santa Cruz) for 2 h at 25°C. Ultimately, the proteins were detected with enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL; Applygen Technologies Inc., Beijing, China).</p></sec><sec id="section13-0394632017703274"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>SPSS 19.0 statistical analysis software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used to analyze data. Continuous variables were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation (SD) and analyzed by t test and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). A value of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section14-0394632017703274"><title>Results</title><sec id="section15-0394632017703274"><title>TSN alleviates cerebral infarction in rat</title><p>To investigate the effect of TSN on cerebral infarction in rat, cerebral infarct volume, cerebral edema, and neurological deficits were evaluated. The results showed that compared with the sham group, brain water content, cerebral infarct volume, and neurological deficits scores were significantly increased in the MCAO group (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0394632017703274">Figure 1(a)–(c)</xref>). Pretreatment with TSN remarkably reduced brain water content (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), cerebral infarct volume (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and neurological deficits scores (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than those in the MCAO group.</p><fig id="fig1-0394632017703274" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>TSN has a preventive role in cerebral infarction rat model. (a) MCAO operation elevates brain water content in cerebral infarction rat model, while TSN reduces brain water content; (b) MCAO increases cerebral infarct volume in cerebral infarction rat model, while TSN reduces cerebral infarct volume; (c) MCAO enhances neurological deficits in cerebral infarction rat model, while TSN improves neurological deficits.</p><p>TSN: tanshinone; MCAO: middle cerebral artery occlusion.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_0394632017703274-fig1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section16-0394632017703274"><title>TSN inhibits neuronal cell apoptosis in brain of cerebral infarction rat</title><p>To investigate the protection mechanism of TSN in cerebral infarction rat, neuronal cell apoptosis in brain was evaluated using TUNEL method. The results revealed that MCAO operation significantly promoted neuronal cell apoptosis in hippocampus and cortical tissues compared with the sham group (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0394632017703274">Figure 2(a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0394632017703274">(b)</xref>), while cell apoptosis was significantly lower in the TSN group than in the MCAO group in hippocampus and cortical tissues (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0394632017703274">Figure 2(c)</xref> shows the representative images of TUNEL assay in cortical tissues.</p><fig id="fig2-0394632017703274" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>TSN inhibits cell apoptosis in hippocampus and cortical tissues of cerebral infarction rat. (a) MCAO operation significantly promotes neuronal cell apoptosis in hippocampus tissues, while TSN inhibits cell apoptosis; (b) the same results are shown in cortical tissues, and (c) representative images of TUNEL assay in cortical tissues.</p><p>TSN: tanshinone; MCAO: middle cerebral artery occlusion.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_0394632017703274-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section17-0394632017703274"><title>TSN inhibits cell apoptosis in primary rat neuronal cells</title><p>In addition to in vivo experiments, OGD cell model was performed to mimic hypoxic-ischemic environment in primary rat neuronal cells. MTT results found that after 24, 48, or 72 h of treatment, cell viability was significantly lower in the OGD group than in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(a)</xref>), while pretreatment with TSN obviously improved cell viability compared with the OGD group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(a)</xref>). Flow cytometry results showed that compared with the control group, cell apoptotic rates were significantly increased in the OGD group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">(c)</xref>), while TSN remarkably inhibited in the TSN group in comparison with the OGD group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">(c)</xref>). In addition, both the mRNA and protein levels of anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2 were significantly inhibited and pro-apoptotic protein Bax was obviously increased in the OGD group compared with the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(d)—(f)</xref>), while TSN remarkably reversed these changes in the expressions of Bcl-2 and Bax compared with the OGD group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0394632017703274">Figure 3(d)–(f)</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3-0394632017703274" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>TSN inhibits rat neuronal cell apoptosis in vitro. (a) MTT assay shows that cell viability is reduced after treatment with OGD for 24, 48, or 72 h, and TSN improves cell viability; (b and c) flow cytometry results show that OGD treatment increases cell apoptotic rate, and TSN suppresses cell apoptotic rate in rat neuronal cells; (d) qRT-PCR reveals that OGD treatment inhibits Bcl-2 mRNA level and increases Bax mRNA level, and TSN reverses these changes; (e and f) Western blotting shows the similar protein levels of Bcl-2 and Bax compared with the mRNA levels.</p><p>TSN: tanshinone; MCAO: middle cerebral artery occlusion; OGD: oxygen-glucose deprivation; Bcl-2: B-cell lymphoma 2.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_0394632017703274-fig3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section18-0394632017703274"><title>TSN inhibits the levels of inflammatory factors in brain of cerebral infarction rat</title><p>Furthermore, we evaluated the effect of TSN on inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat. ELISA results revealed that TNF-α, CRP, and IL-6 levels were all higher in the MCAO group than in the sham group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), while reduced levels of TNF-α, CRP, and IL-6 were found in the TSN group than in the MCAO group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0394632017703274">Figure 4(a)–(c)</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4-0394632017703274" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>TSN inhibits inflammatory response in cerebral infarction rat. (a) ELISA shows that MCAO operation increases TNF-α level, while TSN inhibits TNF-α level; (b and c) CRP and IL-6 levels have similar change trend compared with TNF-α level.</p><p>TSN: tanshinone; MCAO: middle cerebral artery occlusion; IL: interleukin-6; TNF-α: tumor necrosis factor-α; CRP: C-reactive protein; ELISA: Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_0394632017703274-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section19-0394632017703274"><title>Discussion</title><p>Previous studies had shown the neuroprotective effects of TSN on mice focal cerebral ischemia and focal cerebral ischemic/reperfusion injury.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Similarly, in the study, TSN was proved to protect against rat cerebral infarction, including cerebral infarct volume, cerebral edema, and neurological deficits, both in vitro and in vivo in this study.</p><p>It has been well acknowledged that cell apoptosis and inflammation are critical regulators of cerebral infarction. Bcl-2 family plays a vital role in regulating cell apoptosis, which included various cell apoptosis–related factors, such as Bcl-2 and Bax.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> The Bcl-2/Bax ratio is important to regulate cell survival and death.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Our study suggested that the downregulated Bax and upregulated Bcl-2 were consistent with the anti-apoptotic role of TSN in hippocampus and cortex of cerebral infarction rat and OGD neuronal cells. Triterpenoid-enriched extract of <italic toggle="yes">S. miltiorrhiza</italic> also reported to reduce the aortic atherosclerotic lesion, which might be associated with downregulated CRP and monocyte chemotactic protein.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> In addition, TSN could inhibit the expressions of TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 in activated macrophages induced by lipopolysaccharide.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-0394632017703274" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Similarly, our study found that the pretreatment with TSN could inhibit the levels of IL-6, TNF-α, and CRP in hippocampus and cortex of cerebral infarction rat, prompting that the protective role of TSN against cerebral infarction might be closely associated with inflammation reaction. In conclusion, TSN IIA has a preventive effect on cerebral infarction by inhibiting neuronal cell apoptosis and inflammatory response in vitro and in vivo. These data may provide potential therapeutic strategies for cerebral infarction.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81401861) and the Natural Science Foundation of Shandong Province (ZR2014HQ066).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-0394632017703274"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sveinsson</surname><given-names>Ó</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjartansson</surname><given-names>Ó</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valdimarsson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Cerebral ischemia/infarction-diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source>Laeknabladid</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25125437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17992/lbl.2014.0708.553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-0394632017703274"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-b</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A comparison of stent-assisted mechanical thrombectomy and conventional intra-arterial thrombolysis for acute cerebral infarction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Neurology</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23626646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3988/jcn.2013.9.2.91</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3633196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-0394632017703274"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fugate</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabinstein</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Contraindications to intravenous rtPA for acute stroke: A critical reappraisal</article-title>. <source>Neurology: Clinical Practice</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/CPJ.0b013e318296f0a9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5798502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29473642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-0394632017703274"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X-R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Netrin-1 rescues neuron loss by attenuating secondary apoptosis in ipsilateral thalamic nucleus following focal cerebral infarction in hypertensive rats</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>231</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23232257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2012.11.059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-0394632017703274"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danton</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Inflammatory mechanisms after ischemia and stroke</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuropathology &amp; Experimental Neurology</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12578222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnen/62.2.127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-0394632017703274"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fok</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Partial neuroprotective effect of pretreatment with tanshinone IIA on neonatal hypoxia-ischemia brain damage</article-title>. <source>Pediatric Research</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>790</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16189210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1203/01.PDR.0000180550.99162.BC</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-0394632017703274"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Tanshinone IIA protects neonatal rat cardiomyocytes from adriamycin-induced apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Translational Research</source>
<volume>151</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18201675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.trsl.2007.11.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-0394632017703274"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of interleukin-12 and interferon-gamma production in immune cells by tanshinones from Salvia miltiorrhiza</article-title>. <source>Immunopharmacology</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10996033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0162-3109(00)00256-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-0394632017703274"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Resveratrol alleviates nerve injury after cerebral ischemia and reperfusion in mice by inhibiting inflammation and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Clinical and Experimental Medicine</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>3219</fpage>–<lpage>3226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26064211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4443045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-0394632017703274"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotective effects of Tanshinone IIA on permanent focal cerebral ischemia in mice</article-title>. <source>Phytotherapy Research</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18844253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ptr.2615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-0394632017703274"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaux</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Bcl-2 and cell survival</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>335</volume>: <fpage>440</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3262202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/335440a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-0394632017703274"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Formononetin mediates neuroprotection against cerebral ischemia/reperfusion in rats via downregulation of the Bax/Bcl-2 ratio and upregulation PI3K/Akt signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Neurological Sciences</source>
<volume>344</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24996490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jns.2014.06.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-0394632017703274"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Antiatherogenic property of triterpenoids-enriched extract from the aerial parts of Salvia miltiorrhiza</article-title>. <source>Phytotherapy Research</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1045</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ptr.2426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-0394632017703274"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The anti-inflammatory activities of Tanshinone IIA, an active component of TCM, are mediated by estrogen receptor activation and inhibition of iNOS</article-title>. <source>Journal of Steroid Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2009.01.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>