
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1558</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101532965</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals, LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5095048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5095048.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5095048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5095048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27191994</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.9377</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9377</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Methylation-mediated repression of microRNA-129-2 suppresses cell aggressiveness by inhibiting high mobility group box 1 in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhikui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names initials="C">Changwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names initials="B">Bowen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="M">Meng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="L">Linglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yufeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongyong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kangsheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="T">Tao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qingguang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, Shaanxi, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Kangsheng Tu, <email>tks0912@foxmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Tao Song, <email>13572431619@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor3">Qingguang Liu, <email>liuqingguang@vip.sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>24</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">278561</issue-id><fpage>36909</fpage><lpage>36923</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-20 00:25:28.243"><day>20</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2016 Liu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="16" journal-id="Oncotarget" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11837861"><article-title>Retraction: Methylation-mediated repression of microRNA-129-2 suppresses cell aggressiveness by inhibiting high mobility group box 1 in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><volume>16</volume><date><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><source>Oncotarget</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.28694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11837861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39969202</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Aberrant expression of microRNAs (miRNAs) and its dysfunction have been revealed as crucial modulators of cancer initiation and progression. MiR-129-2 has been reported to play a tumor suppressive role in different human malignancies. Here, we demonstrated that miR-129-2 was significantly decreased in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) tissues and cell lines. Furthermore, miR-129-2 was expressed at significant lower levels in aggressive and recurrent tumor tissues. Clinical analysis indicated that miR-129-2 expression was inversely correlated with venous infiltration, high Edmondson-Steiner grading and advanced tumor-node-metastasis (TNM) stage in HCC. Notably, miR-129-2 was an independent prognostic factor for indicating overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) of HCC patients. Ectopic expression of miR-129-2 inhibited cell migration and invasion <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Furthermore, we confirmed that high mobility group box 1 (HMGB1) was a direct target of miR-129-2, and it abrogated the function of miR-129-2 in HCC. Mechanistic investigations showed that miR-129-2 overexpression inhibited AKT phosphorylation at Ser473 and decreased the expression of matrix metalloproteinase2/9 (MMP2/9). Upregulation of p-AKT abolished the decreased cell migration and invasion induced by miR-129-2 in HCC. Whereas inhibition of Akt phosphorylation significantly decreased HMGB1-enhanced HCC cell migration and invasion. Moreover, we found that miR-129-2 was downregulated by DNA methylation, and demethylation of miR-129-2 increased miR-129-2 expression in HCC cells and resulted in significant inhibitory effects on cell migration and invasion. In conclusion, miR-129-2 may serve as a prognostic indicator for HCC patients and exerts tumor suppressive role, at least in part, by inhibiting HMGB1.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>miR-129-2</kwd><kwd>methylation</kwd><kwd>high mobility group box 1</kwd><kwd>invasion</kwd><kwd>hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is one of the most common aggressive malignancies and the third-most common cause of cancer-related death worldwide [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Despite the advances in diagnosis and treatment, the majority of patients with HCC have an extremely dismal prognosis due to the high frequency of tumor recurrence or distant metastasis after surgical resection [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Therefore, a better understanding of the underlying molecular mechanisms involved in the pathogenesis and progression of HCC is extremely important for the development of more effective therapeutic approaches for the treatment of patients with HCC.</p><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are an abundant group of endogenous noncoding RNA molecules of about 22 nucleotides in length [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], which regulate protein-coding gene expression at the post-transcriptional level by base pairing to complementary sites within the 3′-untranslated region (UTR) of target mRNAs and targeting mRNAs for degradation or translational repression [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thus, aberrant expression of miRNAs are involved in tissue morphogenesis, cell processes such as proliferation, cell cycle, apoptosis, migration, invasion and major signaling pathways [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Previous studies have identified the critical role of miRNAs in human cancers and suggest that deregulation of miRNAs is involved in tumor development and progression by modulating the expression of oncogenes or tumor suppressors [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Recently, accumulating evidence demonstrated that epigenetic aberration may contribute to the down-regulation of tumor suppressing miRNAs [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Among which, DNA methylation was frequently observed in the promoter CpG island regions of genes [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. We therefore speculate whether methylation alteration may occur in miRNAs, resulting in deregulation of its target genes in cancer cells.</p><p>MiR-129-2 gene is located in a canonical CpG island on chromosome 11, which was found to be frequently hypermethylated in gastric cancer [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], endometrial cancer [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and HCC [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. It plays a critical role in the progression, such as proliferation, migration, invasion of renal cell carcinoma [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], gastric cancer [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], endometrial cancer [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], esophageal carcinoma [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], glioma cells [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and lung cancer [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Furthermore, miR-129-2 suppresses proliferation and migration of esophageal carcinoma cells through downregulation of SOX4 expression [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and epigenetic repression of miR-129-2 leads to overexpression of SOX4 in gastric cancer [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition, miR-129-2 function as a tumor suppressor in glioma cells by targeting HMGB1 and is downregulated by DNA methylation [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Intriguingly, our studies have demonstrated that HMGB1 was elevated and promoted the migration and invasion of HCC. Moreover, miR-129-2 was methylation-mediated downregulated in HCC [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, the clinical significance and regulatory mechanism between miR-129-2 and HMGB1 are poorly understood.</p><p>In this study, we identify miR-129-2 as downregulated in both HCC tissues and cells and a critical suppressor of HCC cells migration and invasion both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. We demonstrate that miR-129-2 is an independent prognostic factor for predicting both the overall and the disease-free 5-year survival of HCC patients. Furthermore, we revealed that miR-129-2 exerted its biological function, at least in part, by inhibiting HMGB1 expression and additional downstream Akt/MMP2/9 pathways. Moreover, demethylation treatment of miR-129-2 inhibited the migration and invasion of HCC. Taken together, our data suggested that miR-129-2 function as a tumor suppressor in HCC cells by directly targeting HMGB1 and is down-regulated by DNA methylation, which may provide a novel therapeutic strategy for treatment of HCC.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>miR-129-2 is frequently downregulated in HCC tissues and is negatively associated with metastatic potential</title><p>To determine whether miR-129-2 is aberrantly expressed in HCC, we performed qRT-PCR analysis in a 106 pairs of HCC tissues and matched para-tumor tissues. Significantly, there was a remarkable decrease in miR-129-2 expression in approximately 93.4% (99/106) of tumor tissues compared with para-tumor tissues (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A, 1B</xref>). Portal vein tumor thrombus was considered as malignant and aggressive characteristics, as compared with primary tumor tissues, miR-129-2 levels were prominently downregulated in aggressive HCC tissues (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Furthermore, miR-129-2 levels were obviously decreased in tumor tissues arising from patients with tumor recurrence as compared with those without tumor recurrence (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). In addition, we found that well-differentiated HCCs showed higher miR-129-2 expression, as compared with those in poorly differentiated HCCs samples (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>). Similarly, the relative lower expression of miR-129-2 was also observed in a panel of HCC cell lines as compared with a nontransformed hepatic cell line (LO2) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref>). Together, these data indicated that miR-129-2 may play a protective role in the metastasis or invasion of HCC.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>miR-129-2 is frequently downregulated in HCC tissues and is negatively associated with metastatic potential</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) Relative miR-129-2 expression levels in 106 paired HCC tissues and matched adjacent normal tissues were determined by qRT-PCR. (<bold>C</bold>) Comparison of miR-129-2 expression in 20 paired tumor tissues and the corresponding portal vein tumor thrombus (PVTT) by qRT-PCR. (<bold>D</bold>) Comparison of miR-129-2 expression in HCC tissues arising from recurrent and non-recurrent groups by qRT-PCR. (<bold>E</bold>) Comparison of miR-129-2 in differentiated (metastatic potential) HCC tissues was analyzed. (<bold>F</bold>) The expression of miR-129-2 in five HCC cell lines was significantly decreased compared with that in the LO2 cells. U6 snRNA was used as internal control. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>Downregulated expression of miR-129-2 predicts poor prognosis in HCC patients</title><p>We determined the mean level of miR-129-2 as a cutoff value to evaluate the significant contribution in the prognosis of HCC patients. As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, the low expression of miR-129-2 was prominently associated with multiple tumor nodes (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008), venous infiltration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001), high Edmondson–Steiner grading (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014) and advanced tumor-node-metastasis (TNM) tumor stage (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001). Thus, our results indicate that the reduced expression of miR-129-2 is correlated with poor prognostic features of HCC. Furthermore, Kaplan-Meier analysis showed that the higher miR-129-2 expression exhibited better overall survival (OS, median OS time were 53 vs.20 months, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) and disease-free survival (DFS) median DFS time were 31 vs. 18 months, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Moreover, miR-129-2 expression level was an independent risk factor for predicting both 5-year OS and DFS of HCC patients (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004 and 0.001, respectively, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Taken together, these data indicated that the expression level of miR-129-2may be used as an independent factor for predicting the prognosis of HCC.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinical correlation of miR-129-2 expression in HCC</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinical parameters</th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th><th align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Expression level</th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-129-2<sup>low</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 56)</th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-129-2<sup>high</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 65 years</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.982</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 65 years</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.881</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor size (cm)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 5 cm</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 5 cm</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor number</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> solitary</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> multiple</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edmondson</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I + II</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III + IV</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNM stage</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I + II</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III + IV</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venous infiltration</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Present</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Absent</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt; 400 ng/ml</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥ 400 ng/ml</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBsAg</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.485</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The prognostic value of miR-129-2 for HCC patients</title><p>HCC patients with higher expression of miR-129-2 had better (<bold>A</bold>) overall survival (OS) and (<bold>B</bold>) disease-free survival (DFS). **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Multivariate Cox regression analysis of 5-year overall and disease-free survival of 106 HCC patients</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" valign="middle" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Overall survival</th><th align="left" valign="middle" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Disease-free survival</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor number</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.713</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657–4.134</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.064</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218–5.434</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.940</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Venous infiltration</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.057</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986–1.114</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.058</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.506–2.158</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edmondson grade</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.230</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943–5.318</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.967</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814–4.576</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNM stage</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.125</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 003–1.396</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.158</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.039–1.402</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-129-2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.152</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.237–3.685</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.527</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.634–7.753</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn_001"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>TNM, tumor-node-metastasis; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p><fn id="tfn_001"><label>*</label><p>Statistically significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Ectopic expression of miR-129-2 ameliorates HCC migration and invasion, both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>To explore the biologic significance of miR-129-2, we stably overexpressed miR-129-2 in HCC cell lines Hep3B and Huh7 with lentiviruses carrying miR-129-2 and its control. The efficacy of infection was tested by qRT-PCR (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Wound healing assay and Transwell migration assay revealed that exogenous expression of miR-129-2 dramatically inhibited cell migration in comparison with that of control cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B, 3C</xref>). As the invasive capacity is a key step during tumor metastasis, we therefore performed Transwell Matrigel invasion assay with miR-129-2-overexpressing Hep3B and Huh7 cells. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>, forced expression of miR-129-2significantly inhibited cell invasion. In addition, cell growth analyses were also carried out by applying MTT assays and no significant differences were observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Ectopic expression of miR-129-2 ameliorates HCC migration and invasion, both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The expression of miR-129-2 was significantly increased in Hep3B and Huh7 cells infected with miR-129-2 expression or control lentiviruses. Cell migration as measured by wound healing assay (<bold>B</bold>) and Transwell migration assay (<bold>C</bold>) was inhibited by up-regulation of miR-129-2 in Hep3B and Huh7 cells as compared with control cells. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results. (<bold>D</bold>) MiR-129-2 over-expressing Hep3B and Huh7 cells conferred a lower number of invaded cells as compared with control cells. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results.(<bold>E</bold>) Upregulated miR-129-2 had no obvious difference on cell proliferation, as determined by MTT. (<bold>F</bold>) Representative hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) images of metastatic nodules from the mouse lung and liver tissue sections (left) of the Huh7-miR-control group and the Huh7-miR-129-2 group. The number of metastatic nodules in the lungs of each group was presented as the mean SD (right). Experiments were repeated at least 6 times with similar results, and error bars represent ± SD. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>To verify the consequences of ectopic expression of miR-129-2, we subsequently injected Huh7-miR-129-2 and Huh7-miR-control cells into the lateral veins of the nude mice. We observed that up-regulation of miR-129-2 showed fewer and smaller metastatic growth in the lungs and livers of the nude mice with microscopic evaluation (9 vs. 24 nodules per lung in Huh7-miR-129-2 and miR-control cells, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). Collectively, these results indicated that miR-129-2 is capable of manipulating aggressive and metastatic phenotype of HCC both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>HMGB1 was a direct target of miR-129-2 in HCC</title><p>To elucidate the molecular mechanism by which miR-129-2 exerts its inhibitory effect on HCC cells, we predicted potential targets by different miRNA target algorithms and found conserved putative miR-129-2 sites at the 3′-UTR of HMGB1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Our previous studies has demonstrated that HMGB1 was highly expressed in HCC cells and tissues and associated with poor prognosis and aggressive phenotype of HCC. To confirm whether the loss of miR-129-2 is an important factor of HCC malignancy by upregulating HMGB1 expression, we performed that qRT-PCR and Western blot analysis and found that ectopic expression of miR-129-2 dramatically decreased the mRNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>) and protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>) expression of HMGB1. In addition, the overexpression of miR-129-2 prominently reduced the luciferase activity of HMGB1 wild-type reporter but not the mutant type (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). Moreover, we found the expression of HMGB1 mRNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E</xref>) and protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4F, 4G</xref>) in the miR-129-2 high-expressing tumors were significantly lower than those in the miR-129-2 low-expressing tumors. Notably, an obvious inverse correlation between miR-129-2 and HMGB1 mRNA was revealed by Spearman's correlation analysis in HCC tissues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H</xref>). Collectively, these results strongly suggested that HMGB1 is a downstream target of miR-129-2 in HCC.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>HMGB1 is a direct target of miR-129-2 in HCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The putative binding sequence of miR-129-2 in the 3′-UTR of HMGB1. (<bold>B</bold>) qRT-PCR analysis of HMGB1 mRNA expression in Hep3B and Huh7 cells after overexpressing miR-129-2. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results. (<bold>C</bold>) Overexpression of miR-129-2 reduced the expression of HMGB1 protein in Hep3B and Huh7 cells. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results. (<bold>D</bold>) Luciferase reporter assays showing decreased reporter activity after transfection of wild-type HMGB1 3′-UTR reporter construct in the Hep3B and Huh7 cells overexpressing miR-129-2. The HMGB1 3′-UTR mutant constructs had no effect on reporter activity. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results. (<bold>E</bold>) The expression of HMGB1 mRNA in miR-129-2 high-expressing tumors was significantly lower than that in miR-129-2 low-expressing tumors. (<bold>F</bold>) A significantly inverse correlation between miR-129-2 and HMGB1 protein expression was observed in HCC tissues, as determined by Western blot. (<bold>G</bold>) A significant inverse correlation between miR-129-2 and HMGB1 protein expression was observed in HCC tissues. Representative immunohistochemical staining showed a weak staining of HMGB1 in miR-129-2 high-expressing HCC tissue and strong staining of HMGB1 in the miR-129-2 low-expressing tumor. (<bold>H</bold>) A significant inverse correlation between miR-129-2 and HMGB1 was observed in HCC tissues. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>HMGB1 is a downstream mediator of the biological function of miR-129-2 in HCC</title><p>To further validate that miR-129-2 suppressed HCC invasion and metastasis by regulating HMGB1, we performed rescue experiment by transfecting HMGB1 overexpression plasmid or empty vector (EV) in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). We found that HMGB1 overexpression rescued the decreased migration and invasion abilities induced by miR-129-2 overexpressing cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B–5D</xref>, respectively). These data confirm that HMGB1 is an essential and functional downstream mediator of miR-129-2 in HCC.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>HMGB1is the functional mediator downstream of miR-129-2 in HCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) miR-129-2-overexpressingHep3B and Huh7 cells that were transfected with empty vector (EV) or HMGB1 expression plasmid were subjected to western blot analysis for HMGB1. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 repeats with similar results. Altering HMGB1 expression partly abolished the functional effect of miR-129-2 on cell migration (<bold>B</bold>) wound healing assay (<bold>C</bold>) Transwell migration assay and cell invasion (<bold>D</bold>). <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 independent experiments. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>miR-129-2-HMGB1 axis modulates the expression of MMP2 and MMP9 by inhibiting AKT phosphorylation</title><p>To investigate the underlying molecular mechanism of the miR-129-2-mediated attenuation of HCC migration and invasion, we extended the studies on the miR-129-2-HMGB1 module to further downstream, based on reported HMGB1 signaling to AKT and MMPs pathways. Recent studies of MMPs involvement in tumor metastasis such angiogenesis, migration and invasion have received extensive attention that resulted in amounts of experimental data in favor of critical roles of MMPs in these processes [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Expectedly, overexpression of miR-129-2 significantly decreased the AKT activity and the expression of phosphorylated AKT, MMP2 and MMP9 in HCC cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). Moreover, the rescue experiment showed that upregulation of HMGB1 expression in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells led to increased phosphorylation of AKT and the expression of MMP2 and MMP9 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). In addition, we demonstrated that overexpression of HMGB1 induced the AKT phosphorylation, in contrast, HMGB1 knockdown inhibited AKT phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). To further study whether the AKT signaling pathway was necessary for miR-129-2-mediated suppression of HCC migration and invasion, we transfected miR-129-2-overexpressing cells with pmyt-AKT (dominant-active AKT) or pcDNA3.1. We noticed that cell migration and invasion were reversed in couple with the increased expression of MMP2 and MMP9 in the pmyt-AKT transfection group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C–6F</xref>). In addition, the specific AKT inhibitor, MK2206, were applied to further verify whether the rescue experiment are also consistent with previous observations. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G–6I</xref>, the migration and invasion capability were remarkably attenuated upon AKT inhibitor treatment in miR-129-2-overexpressing and HMGB1 overexpression plasmid cotransfection group, and the attenuation effects were also observed in the expression of MMP2 and MMP9 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6J</xref>). Together, these data suggest that intracellular AKT-dependent proteolytic enzyme MMPs signaling pathway may play the key role in the modulation of miR-129-2-involved HCC migration and invasion.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>miR-129-2-HMGB1 axis modulates the expression of MMP2 and MMP9 by inhibiting AKT phosphorylation</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Western blot analysis showing decreased levels of p-AKT, MMP2/9 in miR-129-2–overexpressed Hep3B and Huh7 cells. (<bold>B</bold>) Western blot analysis for AKT/p-AKT, MMP2/9 protein expression in miR-129-2-overexpressing Hep3B and Huh7 cells following transfection with HMGB1 plasmid.(C-F) The miR-129-2-overexpressing Hep3B and Huh7 cells were transiently transfected with pmyt-AKT to increase the expression of p-AKT. The cells were subjected to wound healing assay (<bold>C</bold>) and Transwell migration assay (<bold>D</bold>) and the Matrigel invasion assay (<bold>E</bold>) to detect the functional effect and Western blot (<bold>F</bold>) to investigate the expression of MMP2/9. p-AKT overexpression abrogated the suppressive effects of miR-129-2 overexpressed on HCC cells. (<bold>G</bold>–<bold>J</bold>) The HMGB1 rescue experiment that co-transfection of HMGB1 in miR-129-2-overexpressing Hep3B and Huh7 cells, were treated with AKT inhibitors, MK2206 (2 μmol/L). Then the capacity of cell migration (G, wound healing assay and H, Transwell migration assay) and cell invasion (I, Matrigel invasion assay), the MMP2/9 expression was determined by Western blot (J). p-AKT inhibitor abolished the HMGB1 rescue experiment on the functional effects and the expression of MMP2/9. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 independent experiments. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title>miR-129-2 selectively inhibits AKT phosphorylation at Ser473</title><p>It has been reported that phosphorylation of both Thr308 and Ser473 residues contribute to the full activation of AKT [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore, we tested the change of p-AKT (Ser473) and p-AKT (Thr308) in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells. We found the level of p-AKT (Ser473) significantly decreased, whereas p-AKT (Thr308) revealed no obvious difference in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). Furthermore, we observed that the upstream regulators of p-AKT (Thr308) [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], including P85, PTEN, and PDK1 had no obvious changes in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>), which validated that miR-129-2 selectively inhibited AKT phosphorylation at Ser473, not Thr 308. In addition, to confirm the miR-129-2-mediated inhibition effects of p-AKT (Ser473), we examined the correlation between miR-129-2 and p-AKT (Ser473), MMP2 and MMP9 in serial sections of 106 HCC cases by immunohistochemical study. The expression of p-AKT (Ser473), MMP2 and MMP9 in cancer tissues was significantly higher than those in paired noncancerous tissues. Furthermore, IHC scores were used for semiquantitative analysis, we found a strong inverse correlation between miR-129-2 expression and p-AKT (Ser473), MMP2 and MMP9, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>). These data revealed that miR-129-2 exerts its biological suppressive function through dephosphorylation of AKT on Ser473 and elevated expression of MMP2 and MMP9.</p><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>miR-129-2 selectively inhibits AKT phosphorylation at Ser473</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The total expression of AKT (t-AKT) and phosphorylation levels of AKT, including p-AKT (Ser473) and p-AKT (Thr308), were analyzed by Western blot. (<bold>B</bold>) The major upstream regulators of p-AKT (Thr308) were probed by Western blot. (<bold>C</bold>) Left Panel: the representative picture of immunochemical staining of serial HCC sections for p-AKT (Ser473) and MMP2/9 sections in the different miR-129-2 expression levels tissues. Right Panel: the correlation of miR-129-2 level with those of p-AKT (Ser473) and MMP2/9 in 106 HCC patients. Correlation between two variables was calculated bySpearman rank correlation coefficient. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 independent experiments. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_8"><title>miR-129-2 expression is epigenetically regulated by DNA methylation in HCC</title><p>Our results revealed that miR-129-2 plays an important protective role in HCC migration and invasion by manipulating HMGB1/p-AKT (Ser473)/MMP2/9 signaling pathway, however, the regulatory mechanism of miR-129-2 expression in HCC cells was still unknown. Previous study demonstrated that miR-129-2 downregulation is mediated by epigenetic mechanism, especially DNA methylation. We first detect the promoter methylation level of miR-129-2 in 106 pairs HCC tissues and matched adjacent non-tumor tissues. With threshold set at 10%, we found that the frequency of miR-129-2 gene hypermethylation in tumor tissues was significantly higher than that in matched adjacent non-tumor tissues (50.94% (54/106) in tumor vs. 7.54% (8/106) in para-tumor tissues) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>). Furthermore, we investigate whether miR-129-2 was epigenetically regulated in HCC cells. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>, extremely high methylation was observed in Huh7, Hep3B and SK-Hep-1, while PLC/PRF/5 and SNU-475 were unmethylated, which was inversely correlated with the expression of miR-129-2. To confirm that the DNA methylation participated in the regulation of miR-129-2 expression, we treated Hep3B and Huh7 cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with DNA methytransferase inhibitor 5-Aza-dC. We found miR-129-2 expression was upregulated with 5-Aza-dC compared with the control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). Functional analysis also revealed that demethylation-induced expression of miR-129-2 inhibited cell migration and invasion of Hep3B and Huh7 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D–8F</xref>). These results implicated that epigenetic modification may modulate the miR-129-2 expression in HCC.</p><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>miR-129-2 expression is epigenetically regulated by DNA methylation in HCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The methylation intensity of miR-129-2 promoter in HCC tissues (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 106) and adjacent non-tumor tissues was detected by quantative methylation specific PCR; (<bold>B</bold>) Methylation profiles of 5 HCC cell lines created following methylated DNA quantification analysis. (<bold>C</bold>) Hep3B and Huh7 cells were treated with 4 μmol/L 5-Aza-dC. Relative expression levels of miR-129-2 (normalized by U6 RNA expression) in these cells were determined by Taqman qRT-PCR analysis. (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>F</bold>) Effects of 5-Aza-dC treatment on cell migration and invasion of Hep3B and Huh7 cells, (D) wound healing assay and (E) Transwell migration assay for cell migration and (F) Matrigel invasion assay for cell invasion. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 independent experiments. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Identification of novel and essential molecular biomarkers is imminent to designate alternative strategies to overcome resistance in HCC therapy [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Increasing evidence have demonstrated that miRNAs regulated hepatocarcinogenesis-related gene expression, which indicatesa new insight in the initiation and progression of HCC [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Recently, epigenetic repression of miR-129-2 was identified as a crucial regulator during the progression of human cancers [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Nevertheless, the clinical significance and the underlying molecular mechanismsremain unclear. In our current study, miR-129-2 was found frequently downregulated in aggressive tumors than in nonaggressive tumors. Importantly, our results showed that downregulated miR-129-2 conferred a significant higher recurrence rate for HCC patients. Furthermore, miR-129-2 was reduced in HCC cell lines as compared with a normal hepatic cell line. Clinical analysis revealed that miR-129-2 was expressed at significantly lower levels in HCC patients with multiple tumor nodes, venous infiltration, high Edmondson-Steiner grading and advanced TNM tumor stage. These results suggest that the reduced expression of miR-129-2 is correlated with poor prognostic features in HCC. In addition, our data demonstrated that the reduced expression of miR-129-2 predicted a significant worse 5-year survival for HCC patients. Multivariate Cox repression analysis indicated that miR-129-2 was an independent prognostic factor for predicting survival of HCC patients. Moreover, ectopic expression of miR-129-2 attenuated cell migration and invasion both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">vivo</italic>. These results suggested that miR-129-2 is critical for prognosis determination in HCC patients and plays an important role in the regulation of tumor migration and invasion in HCC.</p><p>It is necessary to identify its downstream functional targets to elucidate its biological effects. HMGB1, the most important member of the high mobility group box protein family [<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], plays multiple roles in cancer progression, angiogenesis, invasion, and metastasis development [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Our previous study identified HMGB1 overexpressed in HCC and associated with poor pathological features. In this study, we confirmed that HMGB1 was a direct downstream target of miR-129-2 and it was implicated in the functional effect of miR-129-2 on HCC. An inverse correlation between the expression of miR-129-2 and HMGB1 mRNA and protein was observed in HCC tissues. Upregulation of miR-129-2 significantly reduced the expression of HMGB1 and decreased the luciferase reporter activity of HMGB1 wt 3′-UTR but not mt 3′-UTR. Importantly, we confirmed that restoration of HMGB1 expression abrogated the functional effect of miR-129-2 on HCC migration and invasion. Taken together, these data provide competent evidences to support that miR-129-2 exerts its suppressive effect on HCC, at least partly, through inhibiting HMGB1.</p><p>It has been well documented that MMPs have been implicated in the aggressiveness of HCC [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In our study, we indicated that miR-129-2 decreased the expression of MMP2/9 by inhibiting AKT phosphorylation. Upregulation of p-AKT rescued the decreased migration and invasion induced by miR-129-2, whereas Akt phosphorylation inhibition significantly decreased HMGB1-enhanced migration and invasion. AKT is an important kinase mediating survival signaling, which is regulated by phosphorylation on Thr308 and Ser473. In present study, we confirmed p-AKT (Ser473) was obviously inactivated in miR-129-2-overexpressing cells, nevertheless, p-AKT (Thr308) presented no significant difference. Consistently, our data indicated that miR-129-2 expression revealed a significantly inverse correlation with p-AKT (Ser473), MMP2 and MMP9, respectively. Taken together, these data revealed that miR-129-2 exerts its physiologic function through inhibiting HMGB1, which in turn results in the dephosphorylation of AKT on Ser473 and decreased expression of MMP2/9.</p><p>Epigenetic modifications are closely associated with gene inactivation. Several studies revealed that promoter hypermethylation induced downregulation of miRNAs closely correlates with carcinogenesis [<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Our data demonstrated that hypermethylation of upstream of miR-129-2 led to the downregulation of miR-129-2 in both HCC tissues and cell lines. Moreover, demethylation of miR-129-2 treatment increased miR-129-2 expression in HCC cells and resulted in significant inhibitory effects on cell migration and invasion. These data suggested that miR-129-2 is downregulated by DNA methylation and functions as a tumor suppressor in HCC cells.</p><p>In conclusion, we find that miR-129-2 is downregulated in HCC and its decreased expression is associated with poor prognostic features. Moreover, miR-129-2 is an independent prognostic factor for OS and DFS of HCC patients. We indicate that miR-129-2 inhibits tumor migration and invasion <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">vivo</italic>. Mechanistically, we suggest that miR-129-2 is downregulated by DNA methylation and functions as a tumor suppressor by targeting HMGB1 in HCC cells, which in turn results in the dephosphorylation of AKT on Ser473 and decreased expression of MMP2/9. Taken together, we consider that miR-129-2 may potentially act as a clinical biomarker and therapeutic target in HCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4_1"><title>Clinical samples</title><p>Tumor samples and matched tumor-adjacent tissues were obtained from 106 patients undergoing curative resection of their primary HCC in the Department of Hepatobiliary Surgery at the First Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University during January, 2006 to December, 2009. Written informed consent was obtained from all patients. None of the patients receive any perioperative chemo- or radiotherapy. The demographic and clinicopathologic data of all enrolled patients were obtained through review of hospital records, and were presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. And disease recurrence and survival information was updated at each follow-up visit. The protocols of this study were approved by the Xi'an Jiaotong University Ethics Committee according to the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title>Cell culture and treatment</title><p>The human immortalized normal hepatic cell line LO2 and HCC cell lines (PLC/PRF/5, SNU-475, SK-Hep-1, Hep3B and Huh7) were obtained from the Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China). The cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, GrandIsland, NY, USA) at 37°C with 5% CO2. Akt inhibitor MK-2206 (1 μM, Selleck Chemicals, Houston, TX, USA), 5-aza-2′-deoxycytidine (5-Aza-dC) (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) was used to treat HCC cells following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title>Real-time quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR)</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from clinical specimens or HCC cells using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following manufacturer's instruction. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed using SYBR Premix Ex Taq II (TaKaRa). TaqMan microRNA assays (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA) were used to quantify the expression levels of miR-129-2. Forward and reverse primers were used as follows: HMGB1, AGA AGT GCT CAG AGA GGT GGA and CCT TTG GGA GGG ATA TAG GTT; miR-129-2, GCG ACT GAC GTC TTT TTG CGG TCT GG and CAG AAC AGT GTC GTG ACA GTG ACG AT; U6, CGC TTC GGC AGC ACA TAT ACT A and CGC TTC ACG AAT TTG CGT GTC A.</p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title>DNA extraction and miR-129-2 methylation assay</title><p>DNA was extracted by digestion of frozen samples and cell pellets with 1% protease K, followed by standard phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. The quantificational methylated DNA analysis was performed by combined DNA methylation-sensitive and methylation-dependent restriction endonuclease digestion, followed by subsequent quantitative PCR assay. The chosen target region for quantificational methylation analysis of miR-129-2 gene is a 190 bp long sequence in CpG island. The Primer sequences were as follows: forward: 5′-GGA CGG TCT GGA GAA ATG GAG A-3′, reverse: 5′-GAT TCG CGA AGG GCA GAA TAT G-3′.</p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Total protein was extracted from HCC cells and 40 μg of isolated protein was separated by 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred onto a PVDF membrane (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). The membranes were probed with the following primary antibodies: Akt (1:1000, Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA, USA), p-Akt (1:1000, Cell Signaling), HMGB1 (1:1000, Cell Signaling), MMP2 (1:1000, Cell Signaling), and MMP9(1:1000, Cell Signaling) for overnight. Then the membranes were incubated with the HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse or anti-rabbit IgG antibody (ZSGB-BIO, China). Protein bands were visualized using an enhanced chemiluminescence kit (Amersham, Little Chalfont, UK).</p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title>Immunohistochemical staining</title><p>Immunohistochemistry was performed on paraformaldehyde-fixed paraffin sections. HMGB1, MMP2, MMP9 (1:100, Cell Signaling) antibody was used in immunohistochemistry using a streptavidin peroxidase-conjugated (SP-IHC) method. Detailed procedure of immunohistochemistry was performed as previously reported [<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title>Plasmids and lentivirus transfection</title><p>Lentiviruses containing vector pGCSIL-GFP and pGCSIL-GFP-miR-129-2 were constructed by Genechem (Shanghai, China) and used to infect Hep3B and Huh7 cells at a multiplicity of infection of 10 or 50, respectively, according to the manufacturer's instructions. HMGB1 expressing vector was synthesized by Sangon Biotech Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). Cells were transfected with oligonucleotides using Lipofectamine 2000 Reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies) following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title>Luciferase assay</title><p>Cells were seeded in triplicate in 24-well plate and allowed to settle for about 12 h. pGL3-HMGB1 was co-transfected into HCC cells with TK-Renilla plasmid as control signals using Lipofectamine 2000. Luciferase and control signals were measured at 48 h after transfection using the Dual Luciferase Reporter Assay Kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), according to a protocol provided by the manufacturer. Three independent experiments were performed and the data were presented as the mean ± SD.</p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title>Wound healing assay</title><p>The cells were seeded in 6-well plates at a high density and allowed to form cell monolayers overnight. A 200 μL sterile plastic tip was used to create a wound line across the surface of plates, and the suspension cells were removed with PBS. Cells were cultured in reduced serum DMEM medium in a humidified 5% CO2 incubator at 37°C for 48 h, and then images were taken with a phase-contrast microscope. Each assay was replicated three times.</p></sec><sec id="s4_10"><title>Transwell migration and invasion assay</title><p>The migration and invasion assays were performed using Transwell chamber (Millipore, Billerica, USA). For migration assay, the transfected cells were seeded into the upper chamber with serum-free medium (2.5 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells), and the bottom of the chamber contained the DMEM medium with 10% FBS. While for invasion assay, the chamber was coated with Matrigel (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA), and the following steps were similar to migration assay. When the cells migrated or invaded for 24 h, the cells were fixed and stained with crystal violet. Migrated and invaded HCC cells were counted under an inverted light microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s4_11"><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> metastasis assay</title><p>4–6 week-old female BALB/c nude mice (Centre of Laboratory Animals, The Medical College of Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, China) were randomized into two groups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5), and either Huh7-miR-129-2 or Huh7-miR-control cells (1 × 10<sup>6</sup>) were injected into the tail veins for the establishments of pulmonary metastatic model. Mice were sacrificed 10 weeks post injection and examined microscopically by H&amp;E staining for the development of lung metastatic foci. Animals were housed in cages under standard conditions. All <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> protocols were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Xi'an Jiaotong University.</p></sec><sec id="s4_12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data are presented as the mean ± SD from at least three independent replicates. SPSS software, 16.0 (SPSS, Inc, Chicago, IL, USA) was used to conduct the analysis, and a two-tailed Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test was employed to analyze the differences between two groups. Pearson's correlation analysis was used to analyze the correlation between two indices. Survival curves were plotted by the Kaplan-Meier method and compared using the log-rank test. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS FIGURES</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-36909-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d36e1437" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND FUNDING</title><p>This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81272645, 81402039, 81502092 and 81572847), the Key Science and Technology Fund of Shaanxi Province (2015SF052), the Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China (LY16H160043) the Natural Science Basic Research Plan in Shaanxi Province of China (No. 2016JQ8047).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>All authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2011</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21296855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.20107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Llovet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Bisceglie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lencioni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>AX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talwalkar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gores</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panel of Experts in</surname><given-names>HCCDCT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and endpoints of clinical trials in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2008</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/djn134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garzon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs in Cancer</article-title><source>Annu Rev Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19630570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.med.59.053006.104707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(04)00045-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The diverse functions of microRNAs in animal development and disease</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17011485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.devcel.2006.09.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: critical regulators of development, cellular physiology and malignancy</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16096373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.4.9.2032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-130b promotes cell aggressiveness by inhibiting peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>20486</fpage><lpage>20499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25387077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms151120486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4264179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-519a promotes tumor growth by targeting PTEN/PI3K/AKT signaling in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2015.3309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4750540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-92a contributes to tumor growth of human hepatocellular carcinoma by targeting FBXW7</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2576</fpage><lpage>2584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26323375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2015.4210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-212 suppresses tumor growth of human hepatocellular carcinoma by targeting FOXA1</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>13216</fpage><lpage>13228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.3916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25965836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4537009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic significance of miR-218 in human hepatocellular carcinoma and its role in cell growth</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1571</fpage><lpage>1577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25110121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2014.3386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs in liver disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23689081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrgastro.2013.87</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4091636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide epigenetic regulation of miRNAs in cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23316035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-3731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epigenomics of cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17320506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2007.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3894624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohm</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic gene silencing in cancer - a mechanism for early oncogenic pathway addiction?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic repression of microRNA-129-2 leads to overexpression of SOX4 in gastric cancer</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2010</year><volume>394</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20331975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2010.03.121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deatherage</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutch</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodfellow</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic repression of microRNA-129-2 leads to overexpression of SOX4 oncogene in endometrial cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>9038</fpage><lpage>9046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19887623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2789184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent DNA methylation of MiR-129-2 and its potential clinical implication in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/gcc.22059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-129–3p, as a diagnostic and prognostic biomarker for renal cell carcinoma, attenuates cell migration and invasion via downregulating multiple metastasis-related genes</article-title><source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24802708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00432-014-1690-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11824026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-129-2 suppresses proliferation and migration of esophageal carcinoma cells through downregulation of SOX4 expression</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23677061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijmm.2013.1384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MiR-129-2 functions as a tumor suppressor in glioma cells by targeting HMGB1 and is down-regulated by DNA methylation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><year>2015</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25772485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11010-015-2382-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4544670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic regulation of miR-129-2 and its effects on the proliferation and invasion in lung cancer cells</article-title><source>J Cell Mol Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2172</fpage><lpage>2180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26081366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jcmm.12597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4568922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methylation-mediated repression of microRNA 129-2 enhances oncogenic SOX4 expression in HCC</article-title><source>Liver Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23402613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/liv.12097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krech</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasemeier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreipe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concordant hypermethylation of intergenic microRNA genes in human hepatocellular carcinoma as new diagnostic and prognostic marker</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23364900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.28068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bufalin inhibits migration and invasion in human hepatocellular carcinoma SK-Hep1 cells through the inhibitions of NF-kB and matrix metalloproteinase-2/−9-signaling pathways</article-title><source>Environ Toxicol</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/tox.21896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-491 is involved in metastasis of hepatocellular carcinoma by inhibitions of matrix metalloproteinase and epithelial to mesenchymal transition</article-title><source>Liver Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1271</fpage><lpage>1280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23725476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/liv.12190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knockdown of MACC1 expression suppressed hepatocellular carcinoma cell migration and invasion and inhibited expression of MMP2 and MMP9</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>376</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23232575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11010-012-1545-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MMP2 promoter polymorphism (C-1306T) and risk of recurrence in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma after transplantation</article-title><source>Clin Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1399-0004.2007.00955.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deryugina</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinases and tumor metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16680569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10555-006-7886-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marignani</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple phosphoinositide 3-kinase-dependent steps in activation of protein kinase B</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>6247</fpage><lpage>6260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.22.17.6247-6260.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC134003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guertin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullholland</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mTOR complex 2 is required for the development of prostate cancer induced by Pten loss in mice</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19185849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2008.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2701381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhayani</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimchi</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staveley-O'Carroll</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusani</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in the Pharmacologic Treatment of Hepatocellular Carcinoma</article-title><source>Curr Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26548906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1574884710666151020100059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cora</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menegon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Migliore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalik</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledda-Columbano</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Columbano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA/gene profiling unveils early molecular changes and nuclear factor erythroid related factor 2 (NRF2) activation in a rat model recapitulating human hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC)</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2014</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23857252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.26616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA and cancer</article-title><source>Mol Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23102669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molonc.2012.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5528350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-mobility group box family of proteins: ligand and sensor for innate immunity</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23116548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.it.2012.10.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tohme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia induced HMGB1 and mitochondrial DNA interactions mediate tumor growth in hepatocellular carcinoma through Toll-like receptor 9</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25681553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhep.2015.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4475488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HMGB1 promotes HCC progression partly by downregulating p21 via ERK/c-Myc pathway and upregulating MMP-2</article-title><source>Tumour Biol</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13277-015-4049-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4844642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26499944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Role of HMGB1 Signaling Pathway in the Development and Progression of Hepatocellular Carcinoma: A Review</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>22527</fpage><lpage>22540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26393575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms160922527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4613322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwarakanath</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pattern Recognition Receptors in Cancer Progression and Metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Growth Metastasis</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26279628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4137/CGM.S24314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4514171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of HMGB1 expression by shRNA constructs inhibits the bioactivity of urothelial carcinoma cell lines via the NF-kappaB pathway</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>12807</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep12807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4523846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epimorphin promotes human hepatocellular carcinoma invasion and metastasis through activation of focal adhesion kinase/extracellular signal-regulated kinase/matrix metalloproteinase-9 axis</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2011</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1808</fpage><lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22045676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/hep.24562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale detection of hypermethylated CpG islands in circulating cell-free DNA of hepatocellular carcinoma patients</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1250</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26516143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cr.2015.126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4650428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highmobility group box 1 has a prognostic role and contributes to epithelial mesenchymal transition in human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>5997</fpage><lpage>6004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26252226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2015.4182</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>