
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Onco Targets Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Onco Targets Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1214</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ott</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101514322</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>OncoTargets and therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6930</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6986254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6986254.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6986254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6986254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32158226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OTT.S236162</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">236162</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hsa_circ_RNA_0011780 Represses the Proliferation and Metastasis of Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer by Decreasing FBXW7 via Targeting miR-544a</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Liu et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Liu et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuanping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names initials="C">Chengsong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names initials="X">Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0004">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0005">5</xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Oncology, Xuzhou Central Hospital, Xuzhou School of Clinical Medicine, Nanjing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xuzhou</addr-line>
<addr-line>221000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Thoracic Surgery, Xuzhou Central Hospital, Xuzhou School of Clinical Medicine, Nanjing Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xuzhou</addr-line>
<addr-line>221000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery/Department of Clinical Nutrition, Beijing Shijitan Hospital, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>
<addr-line>100038</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Oncology, Capital Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>
<addr-line>100069</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0005"><label>5</label><institution>Beijing International Science and Technology Cooperation Base of Tumor Metabolism and Nutrition</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>
<addr-line>100038</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Hanping Shi <fax>Fax +86-0951-6743244</fax> Email shihanpingbj@126.com</corresp><fn id="FT0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">349611</issue-id><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>03</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 Liu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ott-13-745.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="15" journal-id="Onco Targets Ther" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9677507"><article-title>Hsa_circ_RNA_0011780 Represses the Proliferation and Metastasis of Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer by Decreasing FBXW7 via Targeting miR-544a [Retraction]</article-title><volume>15</volume><date><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><fpage>1385</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><source>OncoTargets and Therapy</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OTT.S397666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9677507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36419866</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S2001"><title>Purpose</title><p>Circular RNA (circRNA) is involved in the development of various cancers. However, whether circRNA can inhibit the tumorigenesis of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is still unclear. We aimed to explore the epigenetic function of tumor-suppressive circRNA (hsa_circ_RNA_0011780) and its downstream regulatory factors in NSCLC.</p></sec><sec id="S2002"><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>Quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) was used to evaluate hsa_circ_11780 expression in NSCLC tissues and cell lines. The impact of high hsa_circ_11780 expression on overall survival in patients with NSCLC was tested using the Log rank test. The association between decreased hsa_circ_11780 expression and clinicopathological features in patients with NSCLC was analyzed using the Chi-squared test. In vitro cell proliferation and apoptosis were assayed using the cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8) and flow cytometry, respectively. Mice xenograft models were used to determine the tumor promoting effects of hsa_circ_11780 on NSCLC in vivo. The underlying regulatory mechanism was predicted by bioinformatics and verified by a dual-luciferase reporter assay, RNA transfection, qPCR, and Western blotting. The correlation between miR-544a and hsa_circ_11780 expression was verified using Spearman correlation coefficient.</p></sec><sec id="S2003"><title>Results</title><p>The expression of hsa_circ_11780 in NSCLC tissues and cell lines strongly declined. Low hsa_circ_11780 expression is more likely to present in patients with a large tumor size (&gt;3cm), distant metastasis, and poor overall survival. hsa_circ_11780 overexpression strongly inhibited proliferation, migration, and invasion of NSCLC cells (H226 and A549) in vitro and inhibited tumor growth in vivo. Furthermore, hsa_circ_11780 repressed miR-544a function by competitively binding to the complementary sites of miR-544a. miR-544a released by the declining expression of hsa_circ_11780 reduced the protein concentration of F-Box and WD repeat domain containing 7 (FBXW7) in NSCLC cells.</p></sec><sec id="S2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>FBXW7 expression mediated by the hsa_circ_11780/miR-544a axis is markedly associated with the proliferation, migration, and invasion of NSCLC, resulting in decreased survival. These findings suggest that this regulatory axis may serve as a novel therapeutic target in NSCLC.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>non-small cell lung cancer</kwd><kwd>hsa_circ_11780</kwd><kwd>F-box and WD repeat domain containing 7</kwd><kwd>miR-544a</kwd><kwd>proliferation</kwd><kwd>metastasis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Lung cancer ranks first in both cancer incidence and cancer-related mortality globally.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Two histological subtypes, adenocarcinoma (51%) and squamous cell carcinoma (30%), mainly constitute non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), representing 85% of all lung cancers.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Clinically, NSCLC is usually diagnosed in the late stages of disease development,<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> leading to a lack of treatment options and poor prognosis.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Although approximately 30% of patients with advanced NSCLC initially respond to chemotherapy and radiotherapy, many experience relapse or metastasis occurrence within 6 to 12 months of treatment. Elevated cell proliferation is common in tumorigenesis and is associated with high recurrence rates and treatment resistance in patients with NSCLC. Genetic studies of the aberrant expression underlying NSCLC development will help us fully understand the tumorigenesis of NSCLC, leading to the identification of promising therapeutic targets that may ameliorate the poor survival rates of patients.</p><p>Due to advances in sequencing technology, non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) are being increasingly identified to be involved in the development of disease.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> circRNA is an ncRNA with a covalently closed loop that does not have a 5ʹ cap or 3ʹ polyadenylation tail.<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Studies have shown that circRNA can affect the multiple functions of tumor cells and can be used as a helpful predictor for tumor prognosis.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Chen et al reported that circPTN promoted proliferation and maintained stem cell characteristics of glioma cells by increasing SOX9/ITGA5 concentrations by targeting miR-145-5p.<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The hsa_circ_0035483/miR-335/CCNB1 axis in renal clear cell carcinoma not only promoted autophagy and tumor growth, but also enhanced gemcitabine resistance in tumor cells.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In addition, circDENND4C accelerated glycolysis, migration, and invasion of breast cancer cells under hypoxia by competitively sponging miR-200b/200c.<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Growing evidence suggests that circRNA promotes various biological behaviors in the development of NSCLC, including proliferation,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> invasion,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> migration,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and chemoresistance.<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Therefore, studying the important role of circRNA in tumorigenesis may be effective for identifying novel molecular targets to help inhibit the development of NSCLC.</p><p>An increasing number of circRNAs have been found to be involved in NSCLC, although few have been found to function as tumor-suppressors. In our investigation, we found hsa_circ_11780 (named consistently with that stated in the circBase ID, <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.circbase.org">http://www.circbase.org</ext-link></underline>) was upregulated in the adjacent tissue rather than in the NSCLC cancerous tissue. hsa_circ_11780, located at chromosome 1:39749737–39793025, can transcribe the mRNA of microfilament microtubule cross-link factor 1 (MACF1). The data from our study identified that hsa_circ_11780 inhibited proliferation, migration, and invasion of NSCLC. This indicates that hsa_circ_11780 acts as a tumor suppressor. Developing a molecular intervention targeting hsa_circ_11780 and the relevant downstream pathway, could serve as an effective molecular target for improving the prognosis of patients with NSCLC.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title>Patients, Corresponding Tissues and Follow-Up</title><p>Totally 93 NSCLC patients, who received no radiotherapy or chemotherapy before hospitalization, were enrolled at the Xuzhou Central Hospital (Xuzhou, Jiangsu, China) from April 2014 to October 2014. All patients were diagnosed by pathology. All corresponding tissues were acquired by biopsy (bronchofiberscope and fine-needle aspiration) or surgery. And subsequent tissues were all rapidly frozen at −80 °C. 5-year-follow-up was implemented to attain overall survival. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of XuZhou Central Hospital. Written informed consent was received from all patients before this study.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title>RNA Extraction and Quantitative PCR</title><p>Based on the manufacturer’s protocol, total RNA was extracted from tissues and cultured cells using Trizol solution (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Total RNA was transcribed to cDNA using SuperScript IV Reverse Transcript (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The prepared cDNA was measured by a NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Then, in accordance with the protocol of kit, quantitative PCR for target RNA in tissues and cells was performed using PowerUp™ SYBR™ Green Master Mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) in a 96-well PCR plate on the Applied Biosystems 7500 Sequence Detection system. All expression of target RNA was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔ</sup> Ct method with glyceraldehyde-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) as the endogenous control. All primer sequences this study used are presented in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=236162.docx">Supplementary Table SI</ext-link></underline>.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>RPMI (Roswell Park Memorial Institute) 1640 Medium (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) was used to culture H226, H520, SK-MES-1, A549, H1975, H1299 and normal human bronchial epithelium cell line BEAS-2B. All of them were in an atmosphere with 5% CO<sup>2</sup> at 37 °C, purchased from the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai Institute of Cell Biology, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2004"><title>Gene Overexpression and Cells Transfection</title><p>For gene overexpression, lentiviral vectors (pcD-ciR vector, Geenseed Biotech, Guangzhou, China) were used to construct hsa_circ_11780 expressing particles (oe- hsa_circ_11780, hsa_circ_11780 sequence was shown in <underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=236162.docx">Supplemental Table SI</ext-link></underline>). Hsa_circ_11780-cDNA or NC-cDNA (MOI = 20) with polybrene was transfected into H226 and A549. 24h after transfection, a fresh medium replacement was done to the culture medium. Stably transfected cells were selected by puromycin (1 μg/mL). The Puromycin (1 μg/mL, 2–3 times) selection was done until green fluorescence was shown in all cancer cells via the fluorescence microscope (Olympus IX71, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2005"><title>Proliferation Ability of NSCLC Cells</title><p>NSCLC cells were cultured in 96-well plates (2× 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well) for 5 days. Cell viability was measured every 24h using Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8; Medchembio, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instruction. The tested absorbance at each day was collected to calculate the proliferation curves.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2006"><title>Migration Ability and Invasion Ability in NSCLC Cells</title><p>Transwell inserts with a polycarbonate membrane (8.0μm pores; Corning, New York, NY, USA) were applied for migration assays. Membranes were additionally coated with Matrigel matrix (BD Biosciences, Franklin, NJ, USA) for invasion assays. After NSCLC was transfected with the expression vector or the vector control 24 hrs later, 200μL medium with tumor cells (5 × 10<sup>5</sup>) was seeded into the upper chamber, while 600μL medium supplemented 10% fetal bovine serum was added in the lower chamber. Following incubation for 24h (37 °C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub>), the cells on the upper surface of the polycarbonate membrane were removed. The cells attached to the bottom of the membrane were defined as migrated or invaded. All of those cells were fixed, stained, being counted by the microscope (Leica DM20, Leica Microsystems Inc, Buffalo Grove, IL, USA)</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2007"><title>Apoptosis Assay by Flow Cytometry</title><p>After 48h culture, the apoptosis analysis of NSCLC cells with oe-NC or oe-Circ was analyzed by the Apoptosis Detection Kits (eBiosciences, Waltham, MA, USA). Antibodies with Annexin V/FITC were incubated with tumor cells (5×10<sup>4</sup> cell) for 30 min. Cells were measured by FACS Calibur Flow Cytometry (BD Biosciences, Franklin, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2008"><title>Animal Experiment and Tumor Growth in vivo</title><p>The animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Ethics Committee of Xuzhou Central Hospital. All the procedures of animal experiments were performed in strict accordance with the Laboratory animal protection, welfare and ethics rules of the Institutional Animal Ethics Committee of Xuzhou Central Hospital. 4-week-old BALB/c-nude mice were purchased from the Laboratory Animal Center of Xuzhou School of Clinical Medicine, fed in an atmosphere with a 12h light/dark cycle under specific pathogen-free conditions. NSCLC cells (2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells in 100μL) transfected with an expression vector (oe-hsa_circ_11780) or vector control (oe-NC) were respectively incubated subcutaneously into mice (each group n = 5). The tumor sizes of every mouse were collected every week. In the fifth week, tumor weight was measured after the mice were sacrificed.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2009"><title>Dual-Luciferase Reporter Analysis</title><p>The wildtype target lncRNA or the one containing a mutant miRNA- binding area were constructed (Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA). Both of these lncRNA were cloned with a luciferase gene in reporter vectors (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The synthetic vectors, Renilla luciferase reporter vector, and miRNA mimic were co-transfected into cells using the Lipofectamine 2000 kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) following the protocol provided by the manufacturer, 48h later cells were seeded into 96-well plates. The luciferase activity of Renilla plasmid (as the endogenic control, Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and target gene was assessed via Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay Kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2010"><title>RNA Binding Protein Immunoprecipitation Assay (RIP)</title><p>The Imprint<sup>®</sup> RNA Immunoprecipitation RIP Kit (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was used to analyze the interaction between hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a according to the manufacturer’s instruction. Briefly, H226 and A549 cells transfected with miR-544a mimics or miR-NC were cultured 48 h before anti-AGO2 RIP assay. After the tumor cells were lysed by the lysis buffer (RNase inhibitor and protease inhibitor), the suspension was incubated with magnetic beads (conjugated with Ago2 antibody) (Abcam, San Francisco, CA, USA), or negative control IgG. Finally, the antibody binding RNA was identified by RIP-qPCR assay using the respective target primers.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2011"><title>Western Blotting Assay</title><p>NSCLC cells were resolved by RIPA buffer with 1 mmol/L protease inhibitors. A Bicinchoninic acid (BCA) Protein Assay Kit (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) was applied to measure the concentration of the protein samples in according with the manufacturer’s guidance. The proteins were separated by 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), transfected to a nitrocellulose polyvinylidene Fluoride (PVDF) membrane (Bioss Antibodies, Beijing, China). PVDF membrane with primary antibodies (anti-FBWX7, 1:2000; Abcam, ab109617, San Francisco, CA, USA) was incubated at 4 °C overnight, using GAPDH (1:4000; Abcam, San Francisco, CA, USA) as the endogenous reference. Then the target blot on the membrane was incubated with the secondary antibody with horseradish peroxidase (HRP, 1:8000 dilution, Santa Cruz, CA, USA). The Western blot band was photographed by a chemiluminescence detection system (ECLTM, Pierce, Waltham, MA, USA), quantified by Image J software.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2012"><title>Statistics Analysis</title><p>All data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism 6 software (San Diego, CA, USA), and presented as the mean ± standard deviation. Comparison between two groups was carried out by Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. And the correlation between hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a expression was evaluated via Spearman correlation coefficient. Each experiment was done independently three times. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was defined as a significant difference.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="S0003-S2001"><title>Hsa_circ_11780 Expression Is Highly Related to Superior Survival in NSCLC</title><p>By analyzing a microarray dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE62182">GSE62182</ext-link>) in the Public DataBase (27 pairs of cancer tissues and adjacent normal tissues), we found hsa_circ_11780 declined the most in NSCLC tissues relative to adjacent normal tissues (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). hsa_circ_11780 expression in 93 patients’ tissues (tumor and adjacent normal tissues) was quantified using quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), to verify the critical role of hsa_circ_11780 in NSCLC development. hsa_circ_11780 expression in NSCLC tissues was lower than that in adjacent normal tissues (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Additionally, compared to a normal human bronchial epithelial cell line (BEAS-2B), hsa_circ_11780 expression was significantly decreased in NSCLC cells (H226, H520, SK-MES-1, A549, H1975, and H1299) (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Patients with NSCLC were divided into two groups based on the median expression of hsa_circ_11780 (high group, n = 46; low group, n = 47). Clinicopathological analysis (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) revealed that the decline in hsa_circ_11780 expression was significantly related to large tumor size (&gt; 3 cm) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.026), distant metastasis (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.028), and advanced TNM stage (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.023). Based on Kaplan-Meier analysis, a lower expression of hsa_circ_11780 was associated with inferior overall survival (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, after further stratification, the data showed that NSCLC patients with larger tumor nude (≥3cm) exhibited a higher decrease in hsa_circ_11780 expression than those patients with tumor ≤ 3cm (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Expression of hsa_circ_11780 was lower in patients with M1 stage than in patients with M0 stage NSCLC (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1F</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Altogether, our results indicated that hsa_circ_11780 is downregulated in NSCLC tissues, and it demonstrates a tumor-suppressive role in NSCLC.<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relation Between Hsa_circ_11780 Expression and Clinicopathological Features in NSCLC (n = 93)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total n</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hsa_circ_11780 Expression</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low n = 47</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">High n = 46</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;3 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph node</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distant metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNM stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I+II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III+IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.349</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Squamous carcinoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenocarcinoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Note:</bold> *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 represents statistical difference.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Hsa_circ_11780 expression is highly related to superior survival in NSCLC. (<bold>A</bold>) The heat map for differentially expressing circRNAs in NSCLC tissues compared to corresponding adjacent normal tissues based on circRNA mircoarray from the publish database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE62182">GSE62182</ext-link>). N for adjacent normal tissues; T for NSCLC tissues. (<bold>B</bold>) Expression of hsa_circ_11780 in NSCLC tissues and adjacent normal tissues shown by qPCR. (<bold>C</bold>) Hsa_circ_11780 expression in NSCLC cells (H226, H520, SK-MES-1, A549, H1975, and H1299) and BEAS-2B cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Overall survival of NSCLC patients with high and low Hsa_circ_11780 expression. (<bold>E</bold>) Expression of hsa_circ_11780 in NSCLC tissues with different tumor sizes (Small, n = 39; Large n = 54). (<bold>F</bold>) Expression of hsa_circ_11780 in NSCLC tissues with different M stage (M0, n = 55; M1 n = 38). **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OTT-13-745-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002"><title>Hsa_circ_11780 Restrains NSCLC Cell Proliferation, Migration, and Invasion in vitro</title><p>To confirm the influence of hsa_circ_11780 on the biological behavior of tumor cells, the expression of hsa_circ_11780 in two cell lines (A549 and H226) was increased by a synthesized lentiviral hsa_circ_11780-overexpressing (oe-circ) vector. Quantitative PCR was used to validate overexpression efficiency 48 h after transfection (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Cell proliferation, measured by CCK8 in NSCLC, was repressed in cells overexpressing hsa_circ_11780 (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">C</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, the percentage of apoptotic cells (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) increased, while the migration and invasion of tumor cells (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2E</xref> and <xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">F</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) decreased after the expression of hsa_circ_11780 increased. Therefore, these data suggest that hsa_circ_11780 can mediate the malignant properties (proliferation, migration, and invasion) of NSCLC cells in vitro.<fig id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Hsa_circ_11780 restrains NSCLC cell proliferation, migration, and invasion in vitro. (<bold>A</bold>) Hsa_circ_11780 expression was increased by lentiviral vectors in NSCLC cells. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Proliferative ability of NSCLC cells transfected with overexpressing vector or vector control measured by CCK-8 test. (<bold>D</bold>) Flow cytometry showed the apoptotic rate of NSCLC cells transfected with overexpressing vector or vector control. (<bold>E</bold>) Migration ability of NSCLC cells after hsa_circ_11780 overexpression. (<bold>F</bold>) Invasion ability of NSCLC cells transfected with overexpressing vector or control. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OTT-13-745-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2003"><title>Hsa_circ_11780 Limits NSCLC Tumor Growth in vivo</title><p>A549 and H226 cells transfected with oe-circ or oe-NC were inoculated into immune-deficient mice to induce a xenograft tumor model. The results revealed that increased hsa_circ_11780 limited the growth (tumor size, <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; tumor weight, <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) of NSCLC tumor nodes, compared to that in vector-control mice. The macroscopic observation of tumor nodes is shown in <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">F</xref>. These results suggest that hsa_circ_11780 dysregulation is involved in NSCLC tumor formation in vivo.<fig id="F0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Hsa_circ_11780 limits NSCLC tumor growth in vivo. (<bold>A, B</bold>) Tumor size between hsa_circ_11780 overexpressing mice and the control mice. (<bold>C, D</bold>) Tumor weight of tumor nudes after stable overexpression of hsa_circ_11780. (<bold>E, F</bold>) The macroscopic observation of tumor nudes. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OTT-13-745-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2004"><title>Hsa_circ_11780 Modulates NSCLC Growth by Targeting miR-544a</title><p>circRNAs can upregulate target genes by endogenously competing with microRNA (miRNA). Bioinformatics analyses predicted that complementary base within miR-544a may be the direct target for hsa_circ_11780 (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). Furthermore, assays validated that the luciferase activity of miR-544a was significantly repressed by the wild-type hsa_circ_11780 rather than the mutant form (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref> and <xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01). Based on an immunoprecipitation assay carried out on NSCLC cells, we also verified that hsa_circ_11780 directly targeted miR-544a (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref> and <xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">E</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01). Additionally, the expression of miR-544a declined in NSCLC cells transfected with oe- hsa_circ_11780, compared to the oe-NC treated cells (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4F</xref>, p &lt;0.01). The expression of miR-544a was higher in NSCLC cells (H226, H520, SK-MES-1, A549, H1975, and H1299) than in BEAS-2B (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4G</xref>, p &lt;0.01). Similarly, miR-544a expression in NSCLC tissues was higher than that in adjacent normal tissues (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4H</xref>, p &lt; 0.01). A negative correlation between hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a expression levels was found in human NSCLC tissue (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4I</xref>, R2 = −0.4291, p &lt; 0.0001). Collectively, our data suggested that hsa_circ_11780 interacted with miR-544a as a competing endogenous RNA to inhibit their action.<fig id="F0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Hsa_circ_11780 modulates NSCLC growth by targeting miR-544a. (<bold>A</bold>) The schematic diagram presents the complementary binding sites within hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Luciferase reporter assay confirmed the molecular binding between hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a in H226 (<bold>B</bold>) and A549 (<bold>C</bold>). (<bold>D, E</bold>) The interaction between hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a tested by RIP associated PCR in H226 (<bold>D</bold>) and A549 (<bold>E</bold>). (<bold>F</bold>) qPCR showed the miR-544a expression in NSCLC cells transfected with overexpressing vector or control. (<bold>G</bold>) MiR-544a expression in NSCLC cells (H226, H520, SK-MES-1, A549, H1975, and H1299) and BEAS-2B cells. (<bold>H</bold>) MiR-544a expression in NSCLC tissues and adjacent normal tissues shown by qPCR. (<bold>I</bold>) A negative correlation between the expression of hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a in tumor tissues. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OTT-13-745-g0004.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2005"><title>miR-544a Directly Targets FBWX7 in NSCLC Development</title><p>Based on bioinformatics analysis using TargetScan, we predicted that FBWX7, which exhibited decreased expression in NSCLC, maybe a downstream target for miR-544a. Their complementary binding relationship (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>) was verified by a luciferase reporter assay (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref> and <xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.01). FBWX7 expression was strongly decreased by miR-544a inhibition in cancer cells transfected with oe-circ, compared to that in vector controls (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref> and <xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">E</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.01). Therefore, these results indicate that FBWX7 is an effector protein targeted by the hsa_circ_11780/miR-544a axis in NSCLC.<fig id="F0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>miR-544a directly targets FBWX7 in NSCLC development. (<bold>A</bold>) Bioinformatics tools reveal the complementary binding sites within miR-544a and FBWX7 3ʹ-UTR. (<bold>B, C</bold>) Luciferase reporter assay validated the molecular binding between miR-544a and FBWX7 3ʹ-UTR in H226 (<bold>B</bold>) and A549 (<bold>C</bold>). (<bold>D, E</bold>) Western blot assay showed the FBWX7 protein expression in NSCLC cells transfected with hsa_circ_11780 overexpressing vector or control. **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OTT-13-745-g0005.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>circRNA plays a significant role in numerous physiological processes and pathological progression.<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Accumulating evidence has confirmed that aberrant expression of circRNA is associated with specific diseases. Abnormally high expression often results in malignant behavior of cancer cells, such as proliferation, metastasis, and therapeutic resistance.<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> However, low expression of circRNAs in tumor tissues (compared to adjacent tissues), and its repressing-effect on tumors, has been rarely studied. Researchers have reported that low-expression of circRNA plays a role in tumor suppression, including lung cancer,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> colorectal cancer,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> hepatocellular carcinoma,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and breast cancer.<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> circRNA in these diseases can inhibit various pathological processes involved in cancer development, including apoptosis, proliferation, and invasion.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> In the current study, we identified a novel circRNA named hsa_circ_11780, whose linear-form-mRNA can translate the protein MACF1. We revealed that decreased has_circ_11780 in cancerous tissue, was significantly involved in the proliferation and growth of NSCLC cells both in vitro and in vivo (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In addition, we found that lower hsa_circ_11780 expression was a significant indicator for metastasis and poor prognosis of NSCLC (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> &amp; <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Next, we performed a migration and invasion assay in tumor cells and verified the suppressive effect of hsa_circ_11780 (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Collectively, our results revealed that hsa_circ_11780 is a promising suppressor for distant metastasis and an indicator of poor survival in patients with NSCLC.</p><p>Sponging target miRNAs, for post-transcriptional regulation by competitively binding, is a functional property of circRNAs.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> In our study, we applied bioinformatics analysis to predict the interaction between the hsa_circ_11780 and miR-544a (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). The luciferase activity of the miR-544a was inhibited by wild-type hsa_circ_11780 but was not inhibited by the mutant form, thus demonstrating the direct-binding between them (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref> and C). Furthermore, our results showed that hsa_circ_11780 overexpression suppressed the expression of miR-544a in tumor cells (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>). Therefore, since hsa_circ_11780 displayed a tumor-suppressive role and competitive repression of miR-544a, it is clear that miR- miR-544a acts as a significant oncogene for tumor development. In a previous study, upregulated miR-544a was detected in metastatic tumor samples and cell lines of colorectal cancer.<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p>Homeobox A10 is vital for the regulatory role of miR-544a in migration and invasion.<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> The boosting function of miR-544a on migration and invasion of gastric cancer cells can be mediated by the degradation and the translocation of β-catenin by modulating the expression of cadherin 1 and Axis inhibition protein 2.<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> An investigation by Lu et al found that miR-544a could counteract cadherin 1 activity, leading to migration and invasion of breast cancer.<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Our results represent a novel investigation of the important role of the circRNA-miR-544a-interaction in the tumorigenesis of NSCLC.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">FBXW7</italic>, a tumor-suppressor gene, is a member of the F-box protein family.<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Mutation and allelic loss of FBXW7 result in tumorigenesis in mice with increased FBXW7 and activated p53.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Inactivated FBXW7 often promotes malignant properties in various human cancers. FBXW7 in breast cancer, as an important component of E3 ubiquitin ligase, suppresses cell proliferation by mediating the ubiquitin-regulated degradation of Metadherin.<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Targeting melanoma antigen A (MAGEA1), FBXW7 is involved in the ubiquitination and degradation of the Notch1 intracellular domain (NICD1), resulting in migration and proliferation of breast and ovarian cancercells.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Inactivation of FBXW7 in EGFR-TKI-sensitive cells facilitates gefitinib resistance by strengthening epithelial-mesenchymal transition.<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Increased fbxw7 and decreased skp2, switch stem cells from mitotic division to quiescence in lung adenocarcinoma, by regulating c-myc and p27.<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> miR-367 can maintain the stemness of lung carcinoma by activating the Wnt signal pathway through degradation of FBXW7.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Although FBXW7 is believed to be involved in tumor suppression and superior overall survival of patients with lung cancer,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> few studies have investigated the regulatory upstream function of FBXW7 in NSCLC, particularly the circRNA-miRNA axis. Our study has shown that the hsa_circ_11780-miR-544a axis decreases the intracellular level of NSCLC cells (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). Collectively, our results suggest that FBXW7 acts as a modulator of the malignant properties of NSCLC cells in the circRNA-miRNA-interaction pathway.</p><p>In our study, miR-18a behaved as a functional connection between hsa_circ_11780 and FBXW7 expression. hsa_circ_11780 can mediate the expression of FBXW7 by post-transcriptional regulation. However, the specific molecular feedback from FBXW7 to hsa_circ_11780 has not been discussed in our study, and we recognize this as a limitation. An increasing number of reports state that interfering with the transcription of ncRNAs, by binding to their promotor regions, is the main feedback pattern of the downstream functional protein.<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Zinc finger E-box binding homeobox 1 (ZEB1), which is downstream of the long noncoding RNA (lncRNA) ZEB1 antisense RNA 1(ZEB1-AS)/miR-409-3p, can activate the lncRNA ZEB1-AS expression by binding to its promoter region.<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> lncRNA CASC11 transcription was accelerated when the transcription factor FOXO3 translocated to the promoter of CASC11.<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> A similar positive feedback loop was found in the LINC01296/miR-598/Twist1 axis in NSCLC.<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> These findings indicate that FBXW7 or an FBXW7-related molecule may mediate the transcription of hsa_circ_11780 by functioning as a transcription factor in NSCLC. Nonetheless, this requires further exploration in future studies.</p></sec><sec id="S0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We have demonstrated that a low level of hsa_circ_0011780 expression was associated with the large tumor size, advanced TMN stage, and inferior prognosis of NSCLC. Hsa_circ_0011780 can strongly inhibit the proliferation, migration, and invasion of NSCLC in vitro. Furthermore, FBXW7 expression is mediated by hsa_circ_11780 via complementary binding to miR-544a in NSCLC tumorigenesis. These data suggest that the hsa_circ_0011780/miR-544a/FBXW7 axis may be a promising therapeutic target for NSCLC.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="S0006"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>The datasets analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="S0007"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Yong Liu, Chuanping Yang, Xin Jin, Chengsong Cao, and Qing Li contributed to the acquisition and analysis of data, drafting the article. Hanping Shi and Yong Liu contributed to the conception and design of this study, revising the manuscript. All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting and revising the article, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="S0008" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CA Cancer J Clin</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.v68.6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Moreno</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brambilla</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soria</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Squamous cell carcinoma of the lung: molecular subtypes and therapeutic opportunities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2443</fpage>–<lpage>2451</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-2370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22407829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Crino</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cappuzzo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Present and future treatment of advanced non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3 Suppl 9</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/sonc.2002.34266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12094333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balata</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hendriks</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevention and early detection for NSCLC: advances in thoracic oncology 2018</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Thorac Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1513</fpage>–<lpage>1527</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2019.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31228621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA lncKdm2b is required for ILC3 maintenance by initiation of Zfp292 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.3712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28319097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Takenaka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Analysis of the circular RNA transcriptome in endometrial cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>5786</fpage>–<lpage>5796</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.23534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29464034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5814174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation of circRNA biogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">RNA Biol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2015.1020271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25746834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4615371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kulcheski</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Christoff</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Margis</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circular RNAs are miRNA sponges and can be used as a new class of biomarker</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>238</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2016.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27671698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>circPTN sponges miR-145-5p/miR-330-5p to promote proliferation and stemness in glioma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-019-1376-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31511040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6737709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hsa_circ_0035483 sponges hsa-miR-335 to promote the gemcitabine-resistance of human renal cancer cells by autophagy regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>519</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2019.08.093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31492499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Knockdown of circDENND4C inhibits glycolysis, migration and invasion by up-regulating miR-200b/c in breast cancer under hypoxia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>388</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-019-1398-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31488193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6727545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circular RNA circPIP5K1A promotes non-small cell lung cancer proliferation and metastasis through miR-600/HIF-1alpha regulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>19019</fpage>–<lpage>19030</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.29225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31241217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Circular RNA SMARCA5 inhibits the proliferation, migration, and invasion of non-small cell lung cancer by miR-19b-3p/HOXA9 axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Onco Targets Ther</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>7055</fpage>–<lpage>7065</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OTT.S216320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6722457</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8612164"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>XB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hsa_circ_0001946 inhibits lung cancer progression and mediates cisplatin sensitivity in non-small cell lung cancer via the nucleotide excision repair signaling pathway</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2019.00508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31249811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6582772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Circular RNAs in cancer: an emerging key player</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Hematol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13045-016-0370-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5210264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>CircRNA hsa_circ_100395 regulates miR-1228/TCF21 pathway to inhibit lung cancer progression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Cycle</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>2080</fpage>–<lpage>2090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2018.1515553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30176158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6224268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The circ_0021977/miR-10b-5p/P21 and P53 regulatory axis suppresses proliferation, migration, and invasion in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.29135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31595500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiaotong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jutong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haichao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hsa_circ_0070269 inhibits hepatocellular carcinoma progression through modulating miR-182/NPTX1 axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>109497</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.109497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31606623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>circKDM4C suppresses tumor progression and attenuates doxorubicin resistance by regulating miR-548p/PBLD axis in breast cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncogene</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>42</issue>):<fpage>6850</fpage>–<lpage>6866</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41388-019-0926-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31406252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tumour-suppressive circRNAs: mechanisms underlying their suppression of tumour occurrence and use as therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cas.14211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6890437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31599076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comprehensive circular RNA profiling reveals the regulatory role of the circRNA-000911/miR-449a pathway in breast carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>754</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijo.2018.4265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29431182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5807038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MicroRNA-544a regulates migration and invasion in colorectal cancer cells via regulation of homeobox A10</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Dig Dis Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2535</fpage>–<lpage>2544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-016-4186-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27165435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yanaka</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muramatsu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Uetake</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kozaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Inazawa</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>miR-544a induces epithelial-mesenchymal transition through the activation of WNT signaling pathway in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Carcinogenesis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1363</fpage>–<lpage>1371</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/bgv106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26264654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>miR-544a promotes breast cancer cell migration and invasion reducing cadherin 1 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncol Res</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3727/096504016X14519157902726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27053345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7838652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bellon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nicot</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>FBXW7: a critical tumor suppressor of human cancers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12943-018-0857-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6081812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akhoondi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>von der Lehr</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>FBXW7/hCDC4 is a general tumor suppressor in human cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>9006</fpage>–<lpage>9012</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-1320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17909001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The FBXW7 tumor suppressor inhibits breast cancer proliferation and promotes apoptosis by targeting MTDH for degradation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neoplasma</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4149/neo_2018_170228N149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29534580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MAGEA1 interacts with FBXW7 and regulates ubiquitin ligase-mediated turnover of NICD1 in breast and ovarian cancer cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncogene</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>5023</fpage>–<lpage>5034</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2017.131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28459460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>FBXW7 deletion contributes to lung tumor development and confers resistance to gefitinib therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>895</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1878-0261.12200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29633504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5983212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Fbxw7 and Skp2 regulate stem cell switch between quiescence and mitotic division in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Res Int</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>9648269</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/9648269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31534970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6732578</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10977229"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>miR-367 stimulates Wnt cascade activation through degrading FBXW7 in NSCLC stem cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Cycle</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2374</fpage>–<lpage>2385</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2017.1380136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28949784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5788433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>TINCR suppresses proliferation and invasion through regulating miR-544a/FBXW7 axis in lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.01.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MiR-182 promotes cell proliferation by suppressing FBXW7 and FBXW11 in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Transl Res</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>1142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29736206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5934572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA ZEB1-AS1/miR-409-3p/ZEB1 feedback loop is involved in the progression of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>507</volume>(<issue>1–4</issue>):<fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2018.11.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30448056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The positive feedback loop FOXO3/CASC11/miR-498 promotes the tumorigenesis of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>519</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>518</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2019.08.136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31537383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Positive feedback loop of lncRNA LINC01296/miR-598/Twist1 promotes non-small cell lung cancer tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>234</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>4563</fpage>–<lpage>4571</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.27235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30240003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>