
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1821</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">mtna</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101581621</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6938856</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6938856.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6938856</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6938856</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31877407</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2019.10.041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2162-2531(19)30353-1</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Silencing of Long Non-coding RNA RP1-93H18.6 Acts as a Tumor Suppressor in Cervical Cancer through the Blockade of the PI3K/Akt Axis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="SP">Shu-Ping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names initials="DX">Dan-Xia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="CF">Chun-Fang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="JY">Jian-Ying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="WC">Wen-Cai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="RX">Rui-Xia</given-names></name><email>grxcdxzzu@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Gynecology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou 450052, P.R. China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou 450052, P.R. China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Institute of Medical and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou 450052, P.R. China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author: Rui-Xia Guo, Department of Gynecology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, No. 1, Jianshe East Road, Zhengzhou 450052, Henan Province, P.R. China. <email>grxcdxzzu@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>4</label><p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">347589</issue-id><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 13:25:10.283"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="28" journal-id="Mol Ther Nucleic Acids" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9093014"><article-title>Retraction Notice to: Silencing of Long Non-coding RNA RP1-93H18.6 Acts as a Tumor Suppressor in Cervical Cancer through the Blockade of the PI3K/Akt Axis</article-title><volume>28</volume><date><day>4</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><source>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2022.04.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9093014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35592507</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Cervical cancer (CC) remains a distinct public health stumbling block worldwide. Increasing evidence has highlighted long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) as tumor-associated biological molecules. In this study, by means of altering the expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in CC cells, its ability to influence the biological activities of CC cells was evaluated. Differentially expressed lncRNAs were initially screened from the GEO database. A series of RP1-93H18.6 vectors, small interfering RNA (siRNA) against RP1-93H18.6, and LY294002 (an inhibitor for the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase [PI3K]/Akt [serine/threonine kinase] axis) were introduced in a respective manner to treat the HeLa cells in order to analyze their effects on cellular activities <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Nude mice with xenograft tumors were utilized in order to assess CC tumor growth and metastasis <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 was highly expressed in CC, which could activate the P13K/Akt axis. RP1-93H18.6 vectors exposure increased cell viability, adhesion, migration, and invasion, which resulted in more cells arrested at the S stage and reduced apoptosis, while acting to promote tumor growth and metastasis. The siRNA against RP1-93H18.6 or LY294002 exposure was observed to attenuate the effects induced by RP1-93H18.6 vectors. This study suggests that suppression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 exerts potent inhibitory effects on the development and progression of CC via blockade of the PI3K/Akt axis.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>long non-coding RNA RP1-93H18.6</kwd><kwd>PI3K/Akt axis</kwd><kwd>cervical cancer</kwd><kwd>proliferation</kwd><kwd>adhesion</kwd><kwd>migration</kwd><kwd>invasion</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Cervical cancer (CC) represents one of the most commonly occurring gynecological malignancies,<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> often ranked by studies as a leading cause of cancer-related death on a global scale. Studies have indicated that approximately 528,000 new cases and 266,000 deaths worldwide occur on an annual basis.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Current statistics have implicated human papillomavirus (HPV) integration as a chief risk factor in the greater majority of CC cases.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> In fact, the CC mortality rates have been widely reported to be decreased in an effective manner by means of prophylactic vaccination and organized pap smear screening programs; however, due to the unequal distribution of medical resources and difference in quality of life, women in developing countries are without the same access to certain resources in comparison to their counterparts in the developed world.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Recent years have brought with them radical even fertility-sparing surgical therapies, providing curative remedies for CC at an early stage, while in contrast those of advanced or recurrent carcinomas have limited available treatments and remain largely incurable.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Thus, the urgent need is highlighted for further elucidation regarding the underlying biological mechanism of CC for better treatment.</p><p id="p0015">Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are non-protein coding transcripts longer than 200 nt that have been widely reported to participate in the regulation of cancerous cell proliferation, differentiation, and apoptosis.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> In addition to its involvement in tumorigenesis, functional studies have demonstrated that lncRNAs are capable of serving as prognostic indicators, in addition to playing crucial roles in chromatin modifying, transcription gene regulation, and post-transcriptional management.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> lncRNAs have been reported to exert significant effects on tumorigenesis.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> A previous study suggested that lncRNAs are pathologically linked to CC; for instance, lncRNA MALAT1 is considered as a suppressor of CC cell cycle transition.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> In addition, reports have demonstrated that lncRNA EBIC, an oncogenic lncRNA, contributes to CC cell invasion through binding to EZH2 and suppressing E-cadherin expression.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Furthermore, evidence has been provided indicating that lncRNA ANRIL could be a novel therapeutic approach for CC, and multiple studies have revealed that lncRNAs are significantly involved in the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K)/Akt (serine/threonine kinase) pathway.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The PI3K/Akt/mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway has been previously demonstrated to be upregulated in CC, highlighting its capability as a therapeutic target for CC treatment.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> A previous finding revealed that the antitumorigenesis of baicalein mediated by BDLNR in CC was involved in the activation of the P13K/Akt axis.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p id="p0020">Based on the aforementioned review of literature, we subsequently asserted the hypothesis that the knockdown of RP1-93H18.6 negatively regulates CC cell proliferation, invasion, migration, and adhesion by inactivating the PI3K/Akt axis, shedding new light on potentially novel diagnosis and treatment approaches for CC patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>RP1-93H18.6 Is Upregulated, which May Act to Regulate the PI3K/Akt Axis in CC</title><p id="p0025">In accordance with the analysis of the CC-related chip expression profile data GEO: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE63514" id="intref0010">GSE63514</ext-link>, RP1-93H18.6 was observed to be a significantly upregulated lncRNA in CC (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The differentially expressed lncRNAs from the GEO: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE63514" id="intref0015">GSE63514</ext-link> chip are depicted in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>. RP1-93H18.6 was confirmed to regulate the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway based on the MEM website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://biit.cs.ut.ee/mem/" id="intref0020">https://biit.cs.ut.ee/mem/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>▪▪▪</p><p>RP1-93H18.6 was indicated as an lncRNA highly expressed and regulating the PI3K/Akt axis in CC by GEO: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE63514" id="intref0040">GSE63514</ext-link>. CC, cervical cancer; lncRNA, long non-coding RNA; PI3K, phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase; Akt, serine/threonine kinase.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Higher Positive Rates of Related-Protein Levels Detected in CC Cancerous Tissues</title><p id="p0030">Immunohistochemistry (IHC) was performed to determine the positive rate of the protein levels of PI3K, Akt, as well as the related genes from the PI3K/Akt axis (p53 and mTOR) from the cancerous and paracancerous tissues from which five random fields were selected under high magnification (no less than 200 cells in each filed) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>A and 2B). Regarding the paracancerous tissues, the positive rates of p53, PI3K, Akt, and mTOR were 3.50 ± 1.04, 4.38 ± 1.26, 10.05 ± 1.18, and 6.23 ± 1.37, respectively. In the cancerous tissues, brown or brown-yellowish granules in nucleus were observed in the p53-positive cells, which had a positive rate of 40.31 ± 1.58, while diffuse and deeply stained PI3K, Akt, and mTOR in cytoplasm had positive rates of 44.69 ± 1.87, 50.51 ± 2.49, and 38.44 ± 3.28, respectively. Compared with the paracancerous tissues, the positive rates of p53, P13K, Akt and mTOR in cancerous tissues exhibited distinct elevations (all p &lt;0.05). The results revealed that the related genes were highly expressed in cancerous tissues. Further analysis performed indicated that the association between the positive rates of p53, PI3K, Akt, and mTOR and International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) staging, histological grading, and tumor, node, metastasis (TNM) staging, and the results revealed a significantly correlation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>C–2E).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Positive Rates of Related-Protein Level Were Higher in Cancerous Tissues</p><p>(A) Higher protein expression of P13K, Akt, mTOR, and p53 in cancerous than paracancerous tissues was observed using IHC. Scale bars, 50 um. (B) Positive rates of P13K, Akt, mTOR, and p53 were higher in cancerous tissues than paracancerous tissues (n = 78; data were analyzed by a paired t test). *p &lt; 0.05 versus paracancerous tissues. (C) Relative protein expression of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, and p53 in stage I/II and stage III/IV. (D) Relative protein expression of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, and p53 in well-differentiated and poorly and moderately differentiated cancerous tissues. (E) Relative protein expression of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, and p53 in cancerous tissues with and without lymphatic metastasis. Data in (C)–(E) were analyzed using an independent sample t test. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. PI3K, phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase; Akt, serine/threonine kinase; mTOR, mammalian target of rapamycin.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>RP1-93H18.6 Is Expressed at a High Level in CC Cancerous Tissues</title><p id="p0035">qRT-PCR was subsequently performed in order to determine the mRNA expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6, PI3K, Akt, B cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2), Vimentin, cyclinD1, and β-catenin in paracancerous and cancerous tissues. As illustrated in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A, the mRNA expressions of RP1-93H18.6, PI3K, Akt, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, and β-catenin exhibited higher levels in cancerous tissues than did those of paracancerous tissues, while p53, E-cadherin, and Bcl-2-associated X protein (Bax) were expressed at lower levels when compared to the paracancerous tissues (all p &lt;0.05). Furthermore, in order to determine the protein levels of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, β-catenin, p53, E-cadherin, and Bax in addition to the degree of Akt and mTOR phosphorylation, a western blot analysis was conducted. The results (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B) revealed that when compared with paracancerous tissues, the protein levels of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, and β-catenin were upregulated in cancerous tissues, while those of p53, E-cadherin, and Bax were downregulated with reduced levels of phosphorylated (p-)Akt and p-mTOR. The differences were determined to be statistically significant (all p &lt;0.05). The aforementioned findings revealed that RP1-93H18.6 was highly expressed in cancerous tissues. Furthermore, the correlation between RP1-93H18.6 and FIGO staging, histological grading, and TNM staging was determined, the results of which revealed a distinct correlation (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>C–3E).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>RP1-93H18.6 Expression was Higher in CC Cancerous Tissues</p><p>(A) A qRT-PCR assay was used to determine the relative expression of related genes in cancerous and paracancerous tissues. (B and C) Western blot analysis was used to determine protein level of related genes in cancerous and paracancerous tissues (n = 78; data were analyzed by a paired t test). *p &lt; 0.05 versus paracancerous tissues. (D) Relative expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in squamous cell carcinoma and adenocarcinoma. (E) Relative expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in stage I/II and stage III/IV. (F) Relative protein expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in well-differentiated and poorly and moderately differentiated cancerous tissues. (G) Relative protein expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in cancerous tissues with and without lymphatic metastasis. Data in (D)–(G) were analyzed using an independent sample t test. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. CC, cervical cancer; lncRNA, long non-coding RNA.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>HeLa Cell Line Exhibits the Highest RP1-93H18.6 Expression among the Four CC Cell Lines</title><p id="p0040">The normal cervical epithelial cell line END1/E6E7 and CC cell lines of SiHa, HeLa, CaSki, and C-33A were cultured, after which the RP1-93H18.6 expressions were determined by means of qRT-PCR (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). The results obtained indicated that compared with the END1/E6E7 cell line, RP1-93H18.6 was highly expressed in SiHa, HeLa, CaSki and C-33A cells, whereby HeLa cells exhibited the highest level and as a result were selected for further experimentation.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>HeLa Cell Line Exhibited the Highest RP1-93H18.6 Expression and RP1-93H18.6 Was Localized in the Nucleus</p><p>(A) Relative expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in HeLa, SiHa, CaSki, and C-33A cell lines. *p &lt; 0.05 versus END1/E6E7 cell line; **p &lt; 0.01. (B) Relative expression of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in the HeLa cell line following treatment of si-NC, siRNA#1, siRNA#2, and siRNA#3. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-NC group; **p &lt; 0.01. (C) Subcellular localization of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 detected by RNA FISH. The experiment was repeated three times and data were compared by one-way ANOVA. lncRNA, long-non-coding RNA; NC, negative control; siRNA, small interfering RNA; FISH, fluorescence <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0045">qRT-PCR methods were conducted in order to determine the interference efficiency of small interfering RNA (siRNA). The results revealed that following the siRNA treatment, the RP1-93H18.6 expression was significantly decreased, while siRNA#3 exhibited the highest interference efficiency, and as a result was selected for subsequent experimentation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>B). RNA fluorescence <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) was performed for subcellular localization of RP1-93H18.6, the results of which demonstrated that endogenous RP1-93H18.6 was located within the nucleus. Additionally, after RP1-93H18.6 knockdown, the fluorescence intensity was significantly weakened and then strengthened after RP1-93H18.6 was restored.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Inhibition of RP1-93H18.6 Decreases CC-Related Gene Expression via Blockade of the P13K/Akt Axis</title><p id="p0050">After transfection, qRT-PCR and western blot analysis were conducted in order to determine mRNA and protein expressions, the results of which are displayed in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>. No significant difference was found between the blank and negative control (NC) groups (p &gt; 0.05). Compared with the blank group, RP1-93H18.6 expression and mRNA and protein expressions of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, β-catenin, p53, Bax, and E-cadherin were decreased while the expressions of p-Akt and p-mTOR were decreased in the si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups (p &lt; 0.05). RP1-93H18.6 expression and mRNA and protein expressions of PI3K, Akt, mTOR, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, β-catenin, p-Akt, and p-mTOR increased while mRNA and protein expressions of p53, Bax, and E-cadherin decreased in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (p &lt; 0.05). Compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 group, no difference with regard to the expression of RP1-93H18.6 was detected in the si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group (p &gt; 0.05). When compared with the LY294002 group, the expression of RP1-93H18.6 in the si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group was reduced (p &lt; 0.05); however when compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups, the mRNA and protein expressions of PI3K, Akt, p-Akt, mTOR, p-mTOR, Bcl-2, Vimentin, cyclinD1, and β-catenin together with the levels of p-Akt and p-mTOR were diminished, which was accompanied with higher mRNA and protein expressions of p53, Bax, and E-cadherin (p &lt; 0.05). The above results demonstrated that the HeLa cells and their related gene expressions were decreased by inhibition of RP1-93H18.6 as well as blockade of the P13K/Akt axis.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Suppression of RP1-93H18.6 Decreased CC-Related Gene Expression</p><p>(A) Relative expression of related gene after transfection measured by qRT-PCR. (B and C) Related protein expression of transfected cells determined by western blot analysis. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the blank and NC groups; <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups. The experiment was repeated three times and data were compared by one-way ANOVA. CC, cervical cancer; NC, negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Downregulated RP1-93H18.6 Suppresses HeLa Cell Proliferation and Adhesion</title><p id="p0055">As depicted in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A, the 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-dimethyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay results revealed that the rate of proliferation was significantly accelerated at both the 48 and 72 h time points when compared with the 24 h time point (p &lt; 0.05). There was no significant difference observed in terms of cell proliferation between the blank group and the NC group (p &gt; 0.05). When compared with the blank and NC groups, the optical density (OD) value decreased at 48 and 72 h in the groups of si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 while it was enhanced at the 48 and 72 h time points in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (p &lt; 0.05). No difference in relationship to the OD value was detected at the 48 and 72 h time points among the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups (p &gt; 0.05). In comparison to the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups, the si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group exhibited a reduced OD value at the 48 and 72 h time points (p &lt; 0.05). The above results demonstrated that HeLa cell proliferation was inhibited following the inhibition of lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 and inactivation of the PI3K/Akt axis (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A).<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Suppression of RP1-93H18.6 Suppressed HeLa Cell Proliferation and Adhesion</p><p>(A) MTT assay was employed to measure OD values of HeLa cells at 12, 24, and 48 h to evaluate proliferative ability. (B) Cell adhesion rate in each group of the HeLa cell line at 30, 60, and 90 min post-transfection was determined by adhesion assay. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the blank and NC groups; *p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups. The experiment was repeated three times. Data were compared by repeated-measurement ANOVA in (A) and by one-way ANOVA in (B). MTT, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-dimethyltetrazolium bromide; OD, optical density; NC, negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0060">The cell adhesive rate results were determined using a cell adhesion assay. There was no difference detected in regard to the cell adhesive rate between the NC group and the blank group (p &gt; 0.05). When compared with the blank and NC groups, the cell adhesive rates were reduced in the si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002 and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups (all p &lt;0.05), while enhanced levels were detected in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (p &lt;0.05). The si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 exhibited a diminished cell adhesive rate when compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups (all p &lt;0.05) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>B). These findings provided evidence suggesting that downregulated RP1-93H18.6 inhibited cell adhesion ability.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Downregulated RP1-93H18.6 Suppresses HeLa Cell Migration and Invasion</title><p id="p0065">Scratch testing was performed in order to determine cell migration ability, as illustrated in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7</xref>A and 7B. The area of the wound was speculated to have become smaller due to cell migration ability. Cell wound healing ability at 24 h was strengthened when compared with that at 0 h in each of the transfected groups, with no significant difference detected between the blank and NC groups (p &gt; 0.05). When compared with these two groups, cell migration ability was weakened in the si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups (p &lt; 0.05), while strengthened cell migration ability was observed in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (p &lt; 0.05). The si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group exhibited weakened cell migration ability when compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups (p &lt; 0.05). The above results demonstrated that downregulation of RP1-93H18.6 suppressed cell migration.<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Suppression of RP1-93H18.6 Inhibited HeLa Cell Migration and Invasion</p><p>(A) Effects of lncRNARP1-93H18.6 on CC HeLa cell migration ability in each group post-transfection. (B) Cell wound healing rate of scratch in each group post-transfection. (C) Effects of RP1-93H18.6 on CC HeLa cell invasive ability in each group post-transfection. (D) Invasion number of HeLa cells analyzed by Transwell assay. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the blank and NC groups; <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups. The experiment was repeated three times. Data were compared by one-way ANOVA. CC, cervical cancer; NC, negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0070">The results of Transwell assay are shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7</xref>C and 7D, with the HeLa cell line depicted as the research carrier. No significant difference was found between the blank and NC groups (p &gt; 0.05), while comparisons between the two groups revealed that cell-invasive ability was weakened in the si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups (all p &lt;0.05), in addition to strengthened levels observed in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (p &lt; 0.05). Cell-invasive ability was inhibited in the si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group when compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups (all p &lt;0.05). Based on the above findings, we concluded that cell-invasive potential was weakened when RP1-93H18.6 was downregulated.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title>Downregulated RP1-93H18.6 Weakens HeLa Cell Apoptosis Ability</title><p id="p0075">Flow cytometry was performed, the results of which are shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>. There was no significant difference detected between the blank group and the NC group in relationship to the cell cycle distribution and cell apoptotic rate (all p &gt;0.05). When compared with the blank and NC groups, the cell proportion at the G1 phase was markedly increased, while significant decreases at the S phase with a higher cell apoptotic rate in the si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups were confirmed (all p &lt;0.05). A contrasting trend was detected concerning the above indexes in the RP1-93H18.6 vector group (all p &lt;0.05). No significant differences regarding cell cycle distribution and apoptotic rate in the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups were observed (all p &gt;0.05),while comparisons between the two groups revealed an elevated cell proportion at the G1 phase, reduced S phase, as well as a remarkably higher cell apoptotic rate in the si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 group (all p &lt;0.05). The above results revealed that HeLa cell apoptosis was relieved when RP1-93H18.6 was inhibited and the PI3K/Akt axis was blocked.<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Suppression of RP1-93H18.6 Decreased HeLa Cell Apoptosis</p><p>(A) Cell cycle in each group detected by flow cytometry. (B) Percentage of cells at the G0/G1, S, and G2/M phases. (C) Cell apoptosis detected by flow cytometry. (D) Apoptotic rates in each group post-transfection. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the blank and NC groups; <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups. The experiment was repeated three times. Data were compared by one-way ANOVA. CC, cervical cancer; NC, negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><title>Downregulated RP1-93H18.6 Alleviates Tumor Growth and Metastasis in CC</title><p id="p0080">As depicted in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>, the number of nude mice with xenograft tumor (every 10 mice in six groups) with lymph node metastasis (LNM) and pulmonary tissue metastasis was examined, the results of which demonstrated that the number of nude mice with LNM in the blank, NC, RP1-93H18.6 vector, and si-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups was 6, 8, 10, 5, 4, and 1, respectively, while the number with pulmonary tissue metastasis was 6, 7, 10, 4, 5, and 2, respectively. No difference was observed in relationship to tumor volume, weight, and number of mice with LNM and pulmonary tissue metastasis (p &gt; 0.05). When compared with the blank and NC groups, tumor volume was smaller 10 d after inoculation with fewer nude mice with LNM and pulmonary tissue metastasis, while the RP1-93H18.6 vector group demonstrated an opposite trend regarding the above indexes (p &lt; 0.05). When compared with the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups, increased tumor volume along with elevated tumor weight, and decreased number of nude mice with LNM and pulmonary tissue metastasis were observed in the RP1-93H18.6 vector 10 d after inoculation. These findings suggested that inhibition of RP1-93H18.6 and inactivation of the PI3K/Akt axis alleviated xenograft tumor growth and metastasis in nude mice.<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Suppression of RP1-93H18.6 Alleviated Tumor Growth and Metastasis in CC</p><p>(A) Growth curve of nude mice tumor volume in each group. (B) Tumor weight in each group. (C) The number of transfer units with lymph node metastasis and lung metastasis in each group. n = 10. *p &lt; 0.05 versus the blank and NC groups; <sup>#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 versus the si-RP1-93H18.6 and LY294002 groups. Data were compared by repeated-measurement ANOVA in (A) and by one-way ANOVA in (B) and (C). CC, cervical cancer; NC, negative control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0085">lncRNAs have been found to share a distinct relationship with carcinogenesis and malignancies by binding proteins or mediating short regulatory RNAs, with various reports highlighting their oncogenic RNA properties and contribution to CC cell invasive capability.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> A key study suggested that lncRNA LET could be a prognostic marker and a promising treatment tool for patients suffering from CC.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> High expression of lncRNA CCHE1 has been reported to be an indicator of poor prognosis in CC.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> In addition, overexpression of lncRNA Hox transcript antisense intergenic RNA (HOTAIR) has been strongly linked with the progression of CC.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> More recently, mounting evidence has indicated that knockdown of lncRNAs negatively regulates CC cells. Downregulated lncRNA TUG1 has been confirmed to prevent CC cell growth and metastasis,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> while the knockdown of lncRNA HOTAIR has been shown to result in reduced CC cell proliferation, migration, and invasion.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> These findings were all consistent with those of the current study, whereby the downregulation of RP1-93H18.6 was determined to play a key role in preventing CC cell proliferation, invasion, migration, and adhesion while promoting apoptosis though the inactivation of the P13K/Akt axis. Since RP1-93H18.6 exhibits the highest expression of lncRNA based on the analysis of CC-related chip data, it was employed as our study target. Moreover, RP1-93H18.6 was determined to be expressed at the highest level in HeLa cells and, as a result, HeLa cells were chosen for our experiment.</p><p id="p0090">Activated Akt, or protein kinase B, has been revealed to commonly occur in human carcinomas based on various reports and statistics.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Highly phosphorylated Akt has been detected in cell lines of breast, prostate, and CC and is a contributor to these diseases; additionally, P13K has been judged by multiple studies as the upstream of Akt.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Our study suggested higher expression of Akt phosphorylation in CC along with increased p-mTOR. mTOR is a distal constituent of the PI3K/Akt axis downstream, and through the P13K/Akt/mTOR axis, butein has been highlighted as an effective suppressor of CC cell progression.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Additionally, mTOR is a related gene of the P13K/Akt axis; a prior study concluded that mTOR blocking agents could be potentially significant in treating HPV-positive oral cancer and CC, potentially delaying the process of CC recurrence.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Furthermore, the mTOR axis is upregulated in CC, and the inhibited mTOR axis has served as a potent therapeutic target for CC.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Major investigations have demonstrated that the pathogen of CC is intimately involved in HPV infection and the activated P13K/Akt/mTOR axis.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> The P13K/Akt axis, significantly associated with cancer occurrence and development,<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> has been suggested as a key regulator of multiple cancerous cell proliferation, apoptosis, and metastasis.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Evidence has been presented suggesting that the reduced sensitivity of CC cells to gefitinib by microRNA-221 is associated with the PTEN/PI3K/Akt axis.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> A key observation of the current study revealed that dehydrocostus lactone (DHC) is a negative influencing factor in relation to CC in addition to being involved with various biological events through the P13K/Akt axis.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> By suppression of the P13K/Akt axis in CC, parthenolide has been indicated to promote cell apoptosis and autophagy.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Additionally, an inhibited progranulin (PGRN)/PI3K/Akt/mTOR axis appears to be a potent target for CC treatment.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Current literature has suggested that the PI3K/Akt axis plays a remarkable role in CC progression, with activation of the PI3K/Akt pathway implicated in an incomplete metabolic response in CC.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Additionally, chamaejasmine has been found to promote HeLa cell apoptosis, and its apoptosis-inducing effect is modulated by suppressing the P13K/Akt axis.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Consistent with the above conclusions, our study indicated that knockdown of RP1-93H18.6 or inactivation of P13K/Akt axis inhibits CC cell proliferation, invasion, migration, and adhesion and contributes to apoptosis.</p><p id="p0095">Taken together, our study demonstrated that RP1-93H18.6 is overexpressed in CC tissues when compared with paracancerous tissues. The result of cervical xenograft tumor in nude mice, the RP1-93H18.6 vector group, revealed a significant increase in tumor size, weight, and the number of mice with LNM as well as lung tissue metastasis. The aforementioned key findings were all in accordance with our statements regarding that lncRNA is an oncogenic RNA contributing to tumorigenesis. Our present evidence suggests that the downregulation of RP1-93H18.6 may exert an inhibitory effect on the progression of CC by inhibiting HeLa cell proliferation and the epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) while promoting cell apoptosis via blocking the PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>). These findings may provide a potentially potent and novel therapy for future CC treatment. Nevertheless, certain limitations were faced during our study since the precise molecular mechanism of RP1-93H18.6 inactivating P13K/Akt involved in CC requires further investigation.<fig id="fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Illustration of the Regulatory Mechanism of Silencing lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 in CC</p><p>Silencing lncRNA RP1-93H18.6 can inhibit the progression of CC by inhibiting HeLa cell proliferation and EMT while promoting cell apoptosis through inactivation of the PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway. CC, cervical cancer; lncRNA, long non-coding RNA; EMT, epithelial-mesenchymal transition; PI3K, phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase; Akt, serine/threonine kinase; mTOR, mammalian target of rapamycin.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr10.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p id="p0100">The study was conducted with the approval of the Institutional Review Board of The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University. All participating patients signed informed consent documentation prior to enrollment. This study was conducted in strict accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and with the recommendations in the <italic toggle="yes">Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> of the NIH.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Bioinformatics Analysis</title><p id="p0105">CC-related chip expression profile data GEO: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE63514" id="intref0025">GSE63514</ext-link> and annotated probe file were downloaded from the GEO database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo" id="intref0030">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</ext-link>) and obtained by Affymetrix Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 Array examination. There were 47,000 transcripts included in the chip, representing 38,500 clear human genes. The database was obtained from GenBank, database of expressed sequence tags (dbEST), RefSeq, UniGene database, Washington University EST trace repository, and the NCBI human genome assembly. A total of 24 normal and 28 cancer tissues were then prepared. Background correction and normalization of data in each chip were conducted by the Affy installation package of R software.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Nonspecific filtration was performed using the linear model-empirical Bayes statistics in the Limma installation package combined with application of a traditional t test on the expression profile data in order to prepare differentially expressed lncRNAs.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>Study Subjects</title><p id="p0110">Both CC and paracancerous tissues (2 cm away from the tumor tissues)<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> were collected from 78 patients (mean age, 47.25 ± 7.9 years; range, 28–73 years) who had previously undergone radical resection surgery after being pathologically diagnosed at The First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University between July 2014 and January 2016. All fresh pathological tissue specimens were promptly frozen in liquid nitrogen until the total RNA had been extracted accordingly, during which protein denaturation was cautiously avoided. There were 63 cases of squamous cell carcinoma (SC) and 15 cases of adenocarcinoma. The tumors were categorized into different clinical stages based on the standard established by FIGO as follows: stage I/II, n = 45; stage III/IV, n = 33; well differentiated, n = 13, moderate differentiation, n = 41; poor differentiation n = 24; LNM, n = 37; non-LNM, n = 41 (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>). None of the patients enrolled in our study had received radiotherapy, chemotherapy, or hormone therapy prior to the current study, or had a previous history of digestive system malignancy. All tissue specimens were confirmed by means of pathological diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>IHC</title><p id="p0115">Two to three paraffin-embedded CC tissues and paracancerous tissues were cut into serial sections and then placed in an incubator at 60°C overnight. The sections were dewaxed with xylene and dehydrated using gradient alcohol of 100%, 95%, 80%, and 70% for 5 min separately. After being placed under running water for 5 min, samples were washed three times with PBS (3 min each time). Next, 0.01 M citrate buffer solution (CBS) was employed for antigenic heat repair (10 min), and cooled down to room temperature followed by three additional PBS washes (3 min each time). The sections were then soaked in 0.3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-methanol solution (20 min) to inactivate endogenous peroxidase, after which PBS washing was repeated three times. Specimen blockade was performed using 10% goat serum (36119ES03, Shanghai Yeasen Biotechnology, Shanghai, China) at room temperature (10 min). After the addition of primary antibodies, the samples were incubated at 4°C overnight. PBS was considered as the primary antibody for NC. The specimens were washed with PBS (three times) and subsequently incubated with secondary antibody labeled by the relative primary antibody of horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (0343-10000U, Imunbio, Beijing, China) at room temperature for 30 min. Diaminobenzidine (DAB) (P0203, Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Shanghai, China) was used to develop color (5 min), after which the color degree was regulated under the guidance of a microscope. The sections were then washed under running water (5 min), stained with hematoxylin (3 min), differentiated with 1% hydrochloric acid (5 s), and then soaked in running water to turn blue (10 min). The sections were then mounted with neutral resin and finally viewed and imaged under a microscope. IHC scoring was performed using Image-Pro Plus 7 software (Media Cybernetics).<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The staining intensity was scored as follows: 0 (negative), 1 (weak), 2 (moderate), and 3 (strong). According to the percentage of positively stained cells, the staining extent was scored as 0 (0%), 1 (1%–25%), 2 (26%–50%), 3 (51%–75%), and 4 (76%–100%). The final immunoreactivity score (IRS) = the intensity score × the quantity score. The staining was classified into two categories according to the IRS: negative (0–4) and positive (5–12).<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Immunostaining was independently scored by two pathologists blinded to the clinicopathological characteristics. The relative PI3K/Akt/mTOR antibodies as well as the corresponding secondary antibodies are illustrated in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Construction and Packaging of Lentiviral Plasmid</title><p id="p0120">The pLVX-Puro (Clontech, Palo Alto, CA, USA) lentiviral vector was employed for the following procedure. The restriction sites KpnI and Xhol I were selected. The siRNA-1/2/3 sequences were transformed into short hairpin RNA (shRNA) sequences (sequences were purchased from Shanghai GenePharma, Shanghai, China). The forward primer (100 μM) and reverse primer (100 μM) were mixed at a ratio of 1:1. The mixture was then placed on the PCR instrument with a gradient cooling system from 95°C to 25°C (−0.3°C/cycle, −0.1°C/s). The PCR product was diluted 100 times, 1 μL of which was then permitted to react with linear plv-puro plasmid (200 ng) with the help of T4 DNA ligase (NEB, Hertfordshire, UK) at room temperature (2 h). The ligation product was subject to transformation, amplification, restriction enzyme digestion, and sequencing.</p><p id="p0125">The HEK293-FT cells (Shanghai Branch of Chinese Academy of Science, Shanghai, China) exhibiting logarithmic growth were seeded in a Petri dish. When cells were observed to have adhered to the wall, the serum-free medium (100 μL) was supplemented with psPAX2 (7.5 μg), pMD2.G (2.5 μg; Addgene plasmids 12259 and 12260, respectively, Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA), and pLVX- RP1-93H18.6 (10 μg) for incubation (5 min). The ViaFect transfection agent (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) was subsequently added and mixed with lentiviral plasmid at a ratio of 3:1 for incubation (20 min). Next, the mixture was added dropwise to the cells. The supernatants containing viral particles were harvested 48 h later, followed by centrifugation (4°C, 2,000 × <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>, 10 min), filtration, sub-packing, and cryopreservation (−80°C).</p><p id="p0130">The cells were then seeded in a six-well plate. When cell confluence reached 50% 24 h later, Polybrene (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added until the final concentration was 8 μg/mL, followed by incubation (30 min). Lentivirus (200 μL) was then added to each well. The medium was then replaced by a fresh new medium after 24-h infection. Following a 48-h period of infection, puromycin (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added for selection purposes. Following a 10-day selection period, the HeLa cell line exhibiting stable expression of RP1-93H18.6 was collected, identified, and cryopreserved for further use.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Cell Culture, Grouping, and Transfection</title><p id="p0135">The normal cervical immortalized epithelial cell line END1/E6E7 and CC cell lines SiHa, HeLa, Caski, and C-33A were cultured. The HeLa cells were confirmed to be HPV18 positive and the SiHa and CaSki cells were HPV16 positive, whereas the C-33A cells were noted to be HPV-negative. qRT-PCR was performed in order to determine the mRNA expression of RP1-93H18.6 in each cell line, with the cell line exhibiting the highest expression then selected for subsequent experimentation. The experiment was performed three times. The END1/E6E7 and SiHa cell lines were purchased from the Cell Center of Peking Union Medical College (Beijing, China); the HeLa cell line was from Wuhan Life Science Cell Center (Wuhan, Hubei, China); the Caski cell line was from Wuhan Boster Biological Technology (Wuhan, Hubei China); and the C-33A cell line was from the cell bank of the typical culture preservation of the Committee of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Beijing, China).</p><p id="p0140">The HeLa cells were allocated into the blank (cells without transfection), NC (cells transfected with irrelevant negative sequence), RP1-93H18.6 vector (cells transfected with RP1-93H18.6 vector plasmids), si-RP1-93H18.6 (cells transfected with RP1-93H18.6 interference plasmids), LY294002 (cells treated with LY294002 inhibitors), and si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 (cells transfected with RP1-93H18.6 interference plasmids and treated with LY294002 inhibitors) groups. LY294002 was regarded as a typical inhibitor of the PI3K signaling pathway capable of inactivating the pathway.</p><p id="p0145">The HeLa cells in logarithmic growth phase were seeded in a six-well plate (5 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells per well). After the cells were confirmed to have grown to 70% confluence, transfection was performed in accordance with the instructions on Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Next, 250 μL of serum-free Opti-MEM (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA) was used to dilute 100 pmol of RP1-93H18.6 vector, si-RP1-93H18.6, si-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002, and NC (ultimate concentration of 50 nM). After uniform mixing, HeLa cells were incubated at room temperature (5 min). Next, an additional 250 μL of serum-free Opti-MEM was used to dilute 5 μL of Lipofectamine 2000, followed by mixing and incubation at room temperature for 5 min. The aforementioned solutions were then mixed together, incubated at room temperature (20 min), and then added into the cell culture well. The mixture was then cultured for 6–8 h at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2,</sub> and then cultured for an additional 48 h in a complete medium for subsequent experimentation. The localization of RP1-93H18.6 in HeLa cells was analyzed in connection with the application of FISH.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="p0150">The HeLa cells in each group were collected after a 48-h period of transfection. Total RNA in cells and tissues was extracted in order to determine the RNA concentration and purity using TRIzol (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, Liaoning, China). RNA was reversely transcribed into cDNA with reference to a reverse-transcriptase kit (K1621, Fermentas, Maryland, NY, USA). The reaction conditions were as follows: at 70°C for 5 min, ice bath for 3 min, at 37°C for 60 min, and then at 95°C for 10 min. The cDNA was temporarily kept in a refrigerator at −20°C. The premier sequences of RP1-93H18.6, PI3K, Akt, p53, mTOR, Bcl-2, Bax, Vimentin, E-cadherin, cyclinD1, and β-catenin were designed (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S5</xref>) and synthetized by Shanghai Genechem (Shanghai, China). The mRNA expression was evaluated using a fluorescent qPCR kit (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, Liaoning, China). The reaction system was composed of 5.3 μL of 2× Taq MasterMix, 1 μL of forward premier (5 μM), 1 μL of reverse premier (5 μM), 1 μL of cDNA, and 11.7 μL of RNase-free H<sub>2</sub>O. The reaction conditions were conducted as follows: pre-denaturation at 95°C for 5 min, a total of 35 cycles of denaturation at 94°C for 45 s, annealing at 56°C for 45 s, and extension at 72°C for 45 s. The reaction was examined by qRT-PCR (ABI 7500, Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The relative expression of the target gene was determined based on the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method with GAPDH regarded as the internal control. Each experiment was conducted three times. The formula applied was as follows: ΔCt = Ct (target gene) − Ct (internal control); ΔΔCt = ΔCt (experimental group) − ΔCt (control group). The method was suitable for mRNA expression level measurement in cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p id="p0155">Liquid nitrogen was added to both the CC and paracancerous tissues and then ground into even fine powder. Next, 1 mL of tissue lysate was added, comprised of 50 mmol/L Tris, 150 mmol/L NaCl, 5 mmol/L EDTA, 0.1% serine dehydratase (SDS), 1% Nonidet P (NP)-40, 5 μg/mL aprotinin, and 2 mmol/L phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF). The specimens were then ground into homogenate on an ice bath. Furthermore, the tissues were treated with protein lysate (4°C, 30 min), shaken at regular 10-min intervals, and then centrifuged at 12,000 rpm (4°C, 20 min). After the lipid layer had been aspirated, the supernatant was collected for protein concentration determination of each sample using a bicinchoninic acid (BCA) kit (20201ES76, Shanghai Yeasen Biotechnology, Shanghai, China). Deionized water was used to run a 30-μg sample for the protein lane. Then, 10% SDS separating gel and concentrated gel were prepared, after which the samples and the sample loading buffer were mixed, boiled (100°C, 5 min), ice-bathed, centrifuged, and added equally into each lane for electrophoretic separation purposes using pipettes. Next, the protein on gel was transferred to the nitrocellulose membrane, which was blocked overnight with 5% skim milk powder at 4°C. The membrane was incubated with primary antibodies at 4°C overnight. Tris-buffered saline with Tween 20 (TBST) was used to for washing purposes three times (10 min each time), while the secondary antibodies were added for incubation at room temperature for 2 h. The membrane was then rewashed three times with TBST (10 min each time). DAB was employed for developing, after which a gel imaging instrument (Gel Doc XR, Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) was introduced for image acquisition. The relative protein level was considered to be reflective of the gray value ratio of target protein to that of the internal control, the same method that was also employed in determining the cell protein level. The utilized antibody information is shown in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.9"><title>Cell Viability Detection</title><p id="p0160">The HeLa cells in each group after 24-h transfection were diluted at a certain concentration, paved in a 96-well plate (approximately 5 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells per well), and then incubated (CO<sub>2,</sub> 37°C) for 24, 48, and 72 h, respectively. Each well then received 10 μL of MTT solution (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) under conditions devoid of light during a 4-h period of incubation. The culture medium in each well of the plate was then removed in a careful manner followed by the addition of 100 μL of DMSO (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) under conditions devoid of light, after which the plate was shaken (15 min) for dissolution purposes. The OD at a wavelength at 492 nm was measured using a microplate reader (BioTek Instruments, Winooski, VT, USA). The cell viability curve was drawn with the time points as the abscissa and the OD value as the ordinate. The experiment was repeated three times in an independent fashion.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.10"><title>Cell Adhesion Detection</title><p id="p0165">After the transfected HeLa cells were cultured for 48 h, 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cell suspension was implanted into a 96-well plate coated with Matrigel (50 μg/mg, 354230, Shanghai Qcbio Science &amp; Technologies, Shanghai, China). Three repeated wells were set in each well. The plate was cultured with CO<sub>2</sub> under 37°C conditions and removed at 30-, 60-, and 90-min intervals. The culture medium was aspirated with the non-adhesive cells removed using PBS. The OD value at 492 nm in each well was determined with an MTT assay. The adhesion rate (%) = (OD value of cells adhered on Matrigel/OD value of total cells) × 100%.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.11"><title>Scratch Test</title><p id="p0170">The HeLa cells in each group after a 48-h period of transfection were collected and seeded into a six-well plate at a density of 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well. When cell confluence had reached 90%, a 200-μL sterile pipette tip was applied with equal force to create four horizontal scratches as well as four vertical scratches at the bottom of each well. The previous culture medium was then aspirated followed by the addition of 2 mL of culture medium with 10% serum into each well for culturing purposes. Images were obtained at 0 and 24 h under the guidance of an inverted microscope. The mean value of the cell number from five fields of each sample, as well as the width of each scratch, was calculated accordingly. The scratch healing rate in each group was calculated using the following formula: [(scratch width at 0 h − scratch width at 24 h)/scratch width at 0 h] × 100%. The experiment was repeated three times with the average value then determined. The cell-invasive capability between groups was then compared.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.12"><title>Transwell Assay</title><p id="p0175">Matrigel (354230, Shanghai Qcbio Science &amp; Technologies, Shanghai, China) was dissolved overnight under 4°C conditions and diluted with serum-free RPMI 1640 culture medium at a ratio of 1:3. Then, the 30-μL diluted Matrigel was separately added into the upper chamber at regular 10-min intervals (15, 7.5, and 7.5 μL) in order to evenly extend and cover the entire upper chamber micropores at the bottom. After 48 h of transfection, the HeLa cells in each group were prepared for cell suspension and seeded into the upper Transwell chamber (Corning, Corning, NY, USA). Next, 0.5 mL of RPMI 1640 culture medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) was added to the lower chamber of a 24-well plate, after which it was cultured for 48 h at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, followed by the faint removal of the non-penetrating cells on the Transwell upper chamber. The membrane was then fixed in 95% ethanol for 15–20 min, stained with methyl violet for 10 min, and rinsed. The membrane was finally placed under an inverted microscope for observation and image acquisition, with five fields in every sample being chosen for cell counting. The number of cells invading the Matrigel was considered to be a reflective indicator of cell invasive capacity. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.13"><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p id="p0180">After a 48-h transfection, the medium was aspirated, after which the cells were washed with PBS. The cells were then detached with 0.25% trypsin, collected, and centrifuged (4°C, 1,000 rpm, 5 min) with the supernatant removed. The cells were subsequently washed twice with pre-cooled balanced salt solution (BSS) PBS and centrifuged (1,000 rpm, 5 min), with the supernatant then removed. The cells were then added with pre-cooled 70% ethanol, fixed at 4°C overnight, flushed with BSS PBS, and then centrifuged at 1,000 rpm for 5 min. The cells were then added with 10 μL of RNase enzyme and incubated (37°C, 5 min). The sample was added with 1% propidium iodide (PI) (40710ES03, Shanghai Qcbio Science &amp; Technologies, Shanghai, China) and stained for 30 min under conditions devoid of light. Then the sample then underwent flow cytometry (FACSCalibur, BD Biosciences, FL, NJ, USA) to record cell cycle with red fluorescence at an excitation wavelength of 488 nm. The experiment was repeated three times.</p><p id="p0185">After a 48-h transfection, the HeLa cells were treated with trypsin free of EDTA and collected, after which centrifugation was performed at 4°C (1,000 rpm) for 5 min. After the supernatant had been aspirated, the cells were washed with pre-cooled PBS, centrifuged at 1,000 rpm for 5 min, followed by removal of the supernatant. The apoptosis of cells was examined with an annexin V-fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)/PI kit (CA1020, Solarbio Science and Technology, Beijing, China). The cells were then washed with binding buffer. The mixture of annexin V-FITC and binding buffer was prepared at a ratio of 1:40. The cells were then resuspended and shaken and incubated at room temperature for 30 min. PI and binding buffer were then mixed together at a ratio of 1:40. After the addition of the mixture, the cells were incubated at room temperature for 15 min. Flow cytometry was employed to detect cell apoptosis. The above procedures were repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.14"><title>Xenograft Tumor in Nude Mice</title><p id="p0190">Sixty BALB/c nude mice (age, 4–7 weeks; weight, 18–20 g) purchased from the Animal Center of Sun Yat-sen University (Guangzhou, Guangdong, China) were randomly assigned into the blank, NC, RP1-93H18.6 vector, sh-RP1-93H18.6, LY294002, and sh-RP1-93H18.6 + LY294002 groups (10 mice in each group). The environment was strictly controlled at a pathogen-free constant temperature. The mice were placed under observation for approximately a week prior to tumor inoculation. The transfected cells in each group were centrifuged (1,000 rpm, 5 min), washed with PBS (two times), and then collected. The collected cells were then mixed in an even manner and diluted with high-concentration Matrigel (PBS/Matrigel of 2:1). The nude mice were subcutaneously injected with 5 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells per mouse. Five days later, the nude mice were weighed, and the long and short diameters of the tumor were recorded with vernier calipers. Thirty-five days later, the mice were sacrificed by means of cervical dislocation. Grown tumors were resected and weighed. Tumor weights were compared among groups. The tumor volume (mm<sup>3</sup>) = 1/2 × (L × W<sup>2</sup>), where L indicates the tumor long diameter and W indicates the tumor short diameter. Subaxillary lymph node and lung tissues were resected and sliced (approximately 0.5 cm thick) using a scalpel, and then immediately fixed in 4% polyoxymethylene and 10% formalin separately. Seven days later, subaxillary lymph node and lung tissues were stained with H&amp;E, dehydrated with gradients of alcohol of 70%, 80%, 90%, 95%, and 100% (1 min each time), cleared twice with xylene (5 min each time), immersed in wax, and embedded with paraffin. Then, 4-μm paraffin tissue sections were de-waxed, hydrated, and stained with hematoxylin. Next, the samples were differentiated with 1% hydrochloric acid alcohol, stained with eosin, dehydrated with gradient alcohol, cleared with xylene, and mounted with resin. The number of nude mice with LNM and pulmonary metastasis was determined with five randomly selected views under high magnification.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.15"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0195">The statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 21.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). Measurement data were subject to normal distribution and are expressed as mean ± SD. Comparisons between CC and paracancerous tissues were analyzed using a paired t test, while comparisons between the other two groups were conducted with an independent sample t test. Comparisons among multiple groups were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and tested by a Tukey test afterward. Data at different time points among multiple groups were compared using repeated-measurement ANOVA. p &lt; 0.05 was considered to be indicative of statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="p0200">Q.W., S.-P.Y., and D.-X.C. designed the study. Y.X., C.-F.W., and J.-Y.Z. collated the data, designed and developed the database, carried out data analyses, and produced the initial draft of the manuscript. W.-C.L. and R.-X.G. contributed to drafting the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the final submitted manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p id="p0205">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA MALAT1 modulates radiosensitivity of HR-HPV<sup>+</sup> cervical cancer via sponging miR-145</article-title><source>Tumour Biol.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1683</fpage><lpage>1691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26311052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13277-015-3946-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network</collab><collab>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</collab><collab>Analytical Biological Services</collab><collab>Barretos Cancer Hospital</collab><collab>Baylor College of Medicine</collab><collab>Beckman Research Institute of City of Hope</collab><collab>Buck Institute for Research on Aging</collab><collab>Canada’s Michael Smith Genome Sciences Centre</collab><collab>Harvard Medical School</collab><collab>Helen F. Graham Cancer Center &amp;Research Institute at Christiana Care Health Services</collab><collab>HudsonAlpha Institute for Biotechnology</collab><collab>ILSbio, LLC</collab><collab>Indiana University School of Medicine</collab><collab>Institute of Human Virology</collab><collab>Institute for Systems Biology</collab><collab>International Genomics Consortium</collab><collab>Leidos Biomedical</collab><collab>Massachusetts General Hospital</collab><collab>McDonnell Genome Institute at Washington University</collab><collab>Medical College of Wisconsin</collab><collab>Medical University of South Carolina</collab><collab>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</collab><collab>Montefiore Medical Center</collab><collab>NantOmics</collab><collab>National Cancer Institute</collab><collab>National Hospital, Abuja, Nigeria</collab><collab>National Human Genome Research Institute</collab><collab>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</collab><collab>National Institute on Deafness &amp;Other Communication Disorders</collab><collab>Ontario Tumour Bank, London Health Sciences Centre</collab><collab>Ontario Tumour Bank, Ontario Institute for Cancer Research</collab><collab>Ontario Tumour Bank, The Ottawa Hospital</collab><collab>Oregon Health &amp;Science University</collab><collab>Samuel Oschin Comprehensive Cancer Institute, Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</collab><collab>SRA International</collab><collab>St Joseph’s Candler Health System</collab><collab>Eli &amp;Edythe L. Broad Institute of Massachusetts Institute of Technology &amp;Harvard University</collab><collab>Research Institute at Nationwide Children’s Hospital</collab><collab>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins University</collab><collab>University of Bergen</collab><collab>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</collab><collab>University of Abuja Teaching Hospital</collab><collab>University of Alabama at Birmingham</collab><collab>University of California, Irvine</collab><collab>University of California Santa Cruz</collab><collab>University of Kansas Medical Center</collab><collab>University of Lausanne</collab><collab>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center</collab><collab>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</collab><collab>University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center</collab><collab>University of Pittsburgh</collab><collab>University of São Paulo, Ribeir ão Preto Medical School</collab><collab>University of Southern California</collab><collab>University of Washington</collab><collab>University of Wisconsin School of Medicine &amp;Public Health</collab><collab>Van Andel Research Institute</collab><collab>Washington University in St Louis</collab></person-group><article-title>Integrated genomic and molecular characterization of cervical cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>543</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28112728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature21386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5354998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide profiling of HPV integration in cervical cancer identifies clustered genomic hot spots and a potential microhomology-mediated integration mechanism</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.3178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huchko</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiatt</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukusi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study protocol for a cluster-randomized trial to compare human papillomavirus based cervical cancer screening in community-health campaigns versus health facilities in western Kenya</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>826</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29207966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-017-3818-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5717798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaendler</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing paradigms in the systemic treatment of advanced cervical cancer</article-title><source>Am. J. Obstet. Gynecol.</source><volume>214</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26212178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2015.07.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5613936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA HOTAIR modulates HLA-G expression by absorbing miR-148a in human cervical cancer</article-title><source>Int. J. Oncol.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27574106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.2016.3589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of long non-coding RNA CCAT2 in cervical cancer cell growth and apoptosis</article-title><source>Med. Sci. Monit.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26983975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.897754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4801156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>N.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA-EBIC promotes tumor cell invasion by binding to EZH2 and repressing E-cadherin in cervical cancer</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e100340</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25007342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0100340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4090119</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11781654"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA ANRIL indicates a poor prognosis of cervical cancer and promotes carcinogenesis via PI3K/Akt pathways</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>85</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2016.11.058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahrami</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanian</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ShahidSales</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghayour-Mobarhan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferns</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential value of the PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway for assessing prognosis in cervical cancer and as a target for therapy</article-title><source>J. Cell. Biochem.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>4163</fpage><lpage>4169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28475243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcb.26118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Baicalein inhibits cervical cancer progression via downregulating long noncoding RNA BDLNR and its downstream PI3K/Akt pathway</article-title><source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source><volume>94</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29175387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biocel.2017.11.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>Lde.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sogayar</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating different methods of microarray data normalization</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>7</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>469</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17059609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2105-7-469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1636075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linear models and empirical Bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments</article-title><source>Stat. Appl. Genet. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2004</year><comment>Article3</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2202/1544-6115.1027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16646809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>lncRNA HCP5 promotes the development of cervical cancer by regulating MACC1 via suppression of microRNA-15a</article-title><source>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>4812</fpage><lpage>4819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30070314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26355/eurrev_201808_15616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic distribution and tissue tropism of avian encephalomyelitis virus isolate XY/Q-1410 in experimentally infected Korean quail</article-title><source>Arch. Virol.</source><volume>162</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>3447</fpage><lpage>3458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28795263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00705-017-3504-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackers</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duckett</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Consitt</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malgor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blocking Wnt5a signaling decreases CD36 expression and foam cell formation in atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Cardiovasc. Pathol.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29474941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.carpath.2018.01.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tafazzin (TAZ) promotes the tumorigenicity of cervical cancer cells and inhibits apoptosis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e0177171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28489874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0177171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5425199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunawardane</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niazi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahanbani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valadkhan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel RNA motif mediates the strict nuclear localization of a long noncoding RNA</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>2318</fpage><lpage>2329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24732794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.01673-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4054287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of long non-coding RNA expression profiles in lymph node metastasis of early-stage cervical cancer</article-title><source>Oncol. Rep.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>3185</fpage><lpage>3197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27035672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2016.4715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4869942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low expression of long non-coding RNA LET inhibits carcinogenesis of cervical cancer</article-title><source>Int. J. Clin. Exp. Pathol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25755778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4348863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA CCHE1 overexpression predicts a poor prognosis for cervical cancer</article-title><source>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28239824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of long noncoding RNA HOTAIR predicts a poor prognosis in patients with cervical cancer</article-title><source>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</source><volume>290</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24748337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00404-014-3236-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA TUG1 promotes cervical cancer progression by regulating the miR-138-5p-SIRT1 axis</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>65253</fpage><lpage>65264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29029428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.18224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5630328</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12776624"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activated PI3K/Akt/COX-2 pathway induces resistance to radiation in human cervical cancer HeLa cells</article-title><source>Cancer Biother. Radiopharm.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20578837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/cbr.2009.0707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilja</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated phosphorylation of AKT and Stat3 in prostate, breast, and cervical cancer cells</article-title><source>Int. J. Oncol.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10853013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo.17.1.23</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Butein suppresses cervical cancer growth through the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway</article-title><source>Oncol. Rep.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>3085</fpage><lpage>3092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25962638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2015.3922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molinolo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Dinali</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gangane</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennison</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seiwert</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutkind</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mTOR as a molecular target in HPV-associated oral and cervical squamous carcinomas</article-title><source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2558</fpage><lpage>2568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22409888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-2824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3443560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of mTOR signaling pathway contributes to survival of cervical cancer cells</article-title><source>Gynecol. Oncol.</source><volume>117</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20102778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2009.12.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>URI expression in cervical cancer cells is associated with higher invasion capacity and resistance to cisplatin</article-title><source>Am. J. Cancer Res.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26101702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4473315</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><p id="p0220"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S1. Tables S1–S5</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S2. Article plus Supplemental Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">National Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (grant 31670844), <funding-source id="gs2">Program for Science and Technology Innovation Teams in Universities of Henan Province</funding-source> (grant 17IRTSTHN021), and the <funding-source id="gs3">Major Project of Science and Technology in Henan Province</funding-source> (grant 161100311400). We would like to express our gratitude for the helpful comments received from our reviewers.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0215">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2019.10.041" id="intref0035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2019.10.041</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>