
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3390</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijip</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8911335</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6589964</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6589964.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6589964</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6589964</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31220954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2058738419857537</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2058738419857537</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Skullcapflavone I protects cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused injury through up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenxiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738419857537">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="H">Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738419857537">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="M">Mingyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738419857537">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianshuai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738419857537">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaotian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738419857537">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4646-4017</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuehua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2058738419857537">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2058738419857537"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-2058738419857537"><label>1</label>Department of Emergency, The Affiliated Hospital of Qingdao University, Qingdao, China</aff><aff id="aff2-2058738419857537"><label>2</label>Department of Anesthesiology, The Affiliated Hospital of Qingdao University, Qingdao, China</aff><aff id="aff3-2058738419857537"><label>3</label>Department of Intensive Care Unit, The Affiliated Hospital of Qingdao University, Qingdao, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2058738419857537">Yuehua Chen, Department of Intensive Care Unit, The Affiliated Hospital of Qingdao University, No. 16 Jiangsu Road, Qingdao 266000, China. Email: <email>chen98yh@sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">327275</issue-id><elocation-id>2058738419857537</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-12 13:25:15.480"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7907924"><article-title>EXPRESSION OF CONCERN: ‘Skullcapflavone I protects cardiomyocytes from
hypoxia-caused injury through up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR’</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211000846</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211000846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7907924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33625260</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="35" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8419562"><article-title>RETRACTION NOTICE: Skullcapflavone I protects cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused injury through up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211040397</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211040397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8419562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34472408</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Myocardial infarction (MI) is a serious heart disease in which cardiomyocytes are damaged, caused by hypoxia. This study explored the possible protective activity of Skullcapflavone I (SF I), a flavonoid isolated from the root of <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis Georgi</italic>, on hypoxia-stimulated cardiomyocytes cell injury <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Viability and apoptosis of H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were tested using cell counting kit–8 (CCK-8) assay and Guava Nexin Reagent, respectively. Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was used to measure the long non-coding RNA regulator of reprogramming (lincRNA-ROR) expression. si-ROR was transfected to knockdown lincRNA-ROR. Western blotting was conducted to assess the protein levels of key molecules related to cell proliferation, apoptosis, and mitogen-activated protein kinase/extracellular signal–regulated kinase (MEK/ERK) pathway. We discovered that hypoxia stimulation obviously reduced H9c2 cell and primary cardiomyocytes’ viability and proliferation, but promoted cell apoptosis. SF I treatment mitigated the cell viability and proliferation inhibition, as well as cell apoptosis caused by hypoxia. Moreover, SF I promoted the hypoxia-caused up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Knockdown of lincRNA-ROR reversed the influence of SF I on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Besides, SF I activated MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR. To sum up, our research verified the beneficial activity of SF I on hypoxia-caused cardiomyocytes injury. SF I protected cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused injury through up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR and activation of MEK/ERK pathway.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>flavonoids</kwd><kwd>lincRNA-ROR</kwd><kwd>MEK/ERK pathway</kwd><kwd>myocardial infarction</kwd><kwd>Skullcapflavone I</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-2058738419857537"><title>Introduction</title><p>Myocardial infarction (MI) is a serious heart disease in which blood perfusion to the heart is reduced, resulting in decreased oxygen supplement to cardiomyocytes.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> It is the most common reason for sudden death and characterized by massive cardiomyocytes damage and apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Moreover, the damaged cardiomyocytes will be replaced by fibrous tissue after MI, which cannot carry out normal functions of cardiomyocytes and contributes to the formation and development of chronic ischemic heart diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> The main clinical symptoms of MI include severe and persistent chest pain, which travels from left arm to neck; shortness of breath; abnormal heart beating; sweating; nausea; vomiting; and weakness.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Considering that hypoxia of cardiomyocytes is important to MI, we believe that searching for effective medicines that can protect cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused damage and apoptosis will be beneficial for MI prevention and treatment.</p><p>Phyto-compounds have made great contributions to the prevention and treatment of multiple human diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Flavonoids are a group of plant secondary metabolites widely distributed in plant kingdom with various biological beneficial activities, such as anti-inflammation, anti-oxidation, anti-tumor, cardio-protection, hepatic-protection, and neuro-protection.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="bibr9-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr10-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr11-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Skullcapflavone is the most important flavonoid found and isolated from the root of <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis Georgi</italic>, which can be divided into Skullcapflavone I (SF I, CAS number: 41060-16-6, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419857537">Figure 1</xref>) and Skullcapflavone II (SF II, CAS number: 55084-08-7).<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Park et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> reported that SF I could exert protective effects on liver fibrosis. However, until now, no any literatures are available concerning the effects of SF I on cardiomyocytes damage and apoptosis under hypoxia environment.</p><fig id="fig1-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Chemical skeleton structure of skullcapflavone I.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are RNA transcripts in cells longer than 200 nucleotides without protein-coding activities.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Many lncRNAs are intergenic (long intergenic RNAs, lincRNAs), which are transcribed by RNA pol II, polyadenylated, spliced, and 5′-capped.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> LincRNA regulator of reprogramming (lincRNA-ROR) is a major regulator of stem cell pluripotency, which is highly expressed in pluripotent cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Zhang et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> indicated that lincRNA-ROR was a p53 repressor in response to DNA damage. Wang et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> proved that lincRNA-ROR participated in the self-renewal of human embryonic stem cells via modulating Oct4, Nanog, and Sox2. Moreover, lincRNA-ROR also has been reported to take part in the cell response to hypoxia stress.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>In this study, the rat embryonic ventricular myocardium-derived H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes isolated from neonatal Wistar rats were cultured in hypoxia condition to simulate cardiomyocytes damage in MI. Then, the possible effects of SF I on hypoxia-caused cell viability reduction, proliferation inhibition, and apoptosis enhancement were explored. The potential molecular mechanism related to up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR was also analyzed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-2058738419857537"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="section3-2058738419857537"><title>Cell culture and treatment</title><p>H9c2 cells were obtained from National Infra-structure of Cell Line Resource (Resource No. 3111C0001CCC000219, Beijing, China) and cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium-high glucose (DEME-H, Catalog No. 10566-024, Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA) containing with 10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS, Catalog No. 16140-071, Gibco), 1% (v/v) antibiotic-antimycotic solution (100×, Catalog No. 15240096, Gibco), and 4 mM L-glutamine (Catalog No. G6392, Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) at 37°C in humidity incubator (Sanyo, Jencons, UK) with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 95% air.</p><p>The primary cardiomyocytes were isolated from 3-day-old neonatal Wistar rats (Shandong Laboratory Animal Center, Jinan, China). Briefly, newborn Wistar rats were received anesthetics using pentobarbital sodium. The atria and ventricle were removed prior to isolation. Removed tissues were enzymatically dissociated into a single cell suspension using collagenase I (Catalog No. C0130, Sigma-Aldrich) and isolated cells were cultured in DMEM containing 20% (v/v) FBS and 1% (v/v) antibiotic-antimycotic solution at 37°C in humidity incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 95% air. This study was carried out in accordance with the National Institute of Health’s Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals and was approved by the Ethics Committee of our hospital.</p><p>H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were cultured in hypoxia incubator with 94% N<sub>2</sub>, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 1% O<sub>2</sub> for 24 h to stimulate injury in this research.</p><p>SF I powder was provided by ChemFaces (purity &gt; 98%, Catalog No. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="CFN98643">CFN98643</ext-link>, Wuhan, China) and diluted in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO, Catalog No. ST038, Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, China) to final concentration of 20 mM. H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were treated by SF I at 0.1, 1, 5, or 10 μM for 24 h.</p></sec><sec id="section4-2058738419857537"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>Viabilities of H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were assessed by cell counting kit–8 (CCK-8) assay (Catalog No. HY-K0301, MedChem Express, New Jersey, NJ, USA) or 3-(4,5-Dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay (Catalog No. C0009, Beyotime Biotechnology). For CCK-8 assay, H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were seeded into 96-well plate with 5 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells/well and treated by hypoxia and/or SF I for 24 h. Subsequently, CCK-8 kit solution (10 μL) was added into the culture medium of each well. The plate was placed at 37°C for 1 h. After that, the absorbance of each well at 450 nm was measured using microplate reader (Bio-Tek Instruments, Winooski, VT, USA). Cell viability was expressed as the percentage of control.</p><p>For MTT assay, H9c2 cells were seeded into 96-well plate with 5 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells/well and treated by hypoxia and/or SF I for 24 h. Subsequently, 20 μL MTT solution (2.5 mg/mL) was added into the culture medium of each well. The plate was placed at 37°C for 4 h. After that, the MTT mixture was removed and 150 μL DMSO was added into the each well. Furthermore, the plate was agitated on a shaker for 15 min, and the absorbance of each well at 570 nm was measured using microplate reader.</p></sec><sec id="section5-2058738419857537"><title>Cell apoptosis assay</title><p>Flow cytometry analysis was performed to identify the percentage of apoptotic cells using Guava Nexin Reagent (Catalog No. 4500-0450, Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). In brief, H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were seeded into 24-well plate with 2 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well and treated by hypoxia and/or SF I for 24 h. Subsequently, cells in each group were harvested, washed twice with phosphate buffer saline (PBS), and re-suspended into 100 μL kit buffer at room temperature for 20 min in the dark. After that, the apoptotic cells were recorded using Guava EasyCyte flow cytometer (Guava Technologies, Hayward, CA, USA). Data were analyzed by FCS Express software (De Novo Software, Los Angeles, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="section6-2058738419857537"><title>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR)</title><p>Total RNAs were extracted from H9c2 cells or primary cardiomyocytes using RNAiso Plus kit (Catalog No. 9109, TakaRa Biotechnology, Dalian, China). cDNA was reversely transcribed using PrimeScript<sup>™</sup> II 1<sup>st</sup> Strand cDNA Synthesis kit (Catalog No. 6210, TakaRa Biotechnology). Then, the lincRNA-ROR expression was assessed using TaqMan<sup>™</sup> non-coding RNA assay (Catalog No. 4426961, Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and normalized to β-actin. Data were quantified using 2<sup>–∆∆Ct</sup> method.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section7-2058738419857537"><title>Cell transfection</title><p>si-ROR was used to knockdown lincRNA-ROR in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. In brief, si-ROR and its negative control (si-NC) was designed and synthesized by GenePharma Corporation (Shanghai, China). Cell transfection was performed with the help of Lipofectamine<sup>™</sup> 3000 Transfection Reagent (Catalog No. L3000008, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). qRT-PCR was used for testing transfection efficiency.</p></sec><sec id="section8-2058738419857537"><title>Western blotting</title><p>Total proteins were extracted from H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes using RIPA Lysis Buffer (Catalog No. P0013C, Beyotime Biotechnology) and quantified using BCA Protein Assay kit (Catalog No. P0012S, Beyotime Biotechnology). Western blotting was conducted as previously described.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Following antibodies were used: anti-Cyclin D1 antibody (#2922), anti-p53 antibody (#2524), anti-t-MEK antibody (#4694), anti-p-MEK antibody (#3958), anti-t-ERK antibody (#4695), anti-p-ERK antibody (#4370), anti-β-actin antibody (#4970), anti-rabbit IgG (HRP) antibody (#7074), anti-mouse IgG (HRP) antibody (#7076, Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA, USA), anti-p21 antibody (ab109199), anti-PARP antibody (ab227244), anti-cleaved-PARP antibody (ab32064), anti-Pro-Caspase 3 antibody (ab4051), and anti-Cleaved-Caspase 3 antibody (ab49822, Abcam Biotechnology, Cambridge, MA, USA). Signals of proteins were captured using Bio-Rad ChemiDoc<sup>™</sup> XRS system (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). Intensities of bands were calculated using Image Lab<sup>™</sup> software (Bio-Rad Laboratories).</p></sec><sec id="section9-2058738419857537"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were repeated three times in triplicate. Results were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Graphpad 6.0 software was used for statistical analysis. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were calculated as Student’s t test or one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered to be a statistically significant difference.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section10-2058738419857537"><title>Results</title><sec id="section11-2058738419857537"><title>SF I mitigated Hypoxia caused H9c2 cell proliferation inhibition and apoptosis</title><p>First, the viability, proliferation, and apoptosis of H9c2 cells after SF I and/or hypoxia stimulation were detected. Results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(a)</xref> presented that 0.1–10 μM SF I treatment had no significant influence on H9c2 cell viability (CCK-8 assay). Hypoxia stimulation for 24 h significantly suppressed the viability of H9c2 cells (CCK-8 assay, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(b)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). However, 1, 5, or 10 μM SF I treatment remarkably weakened the hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell viability reduction (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The SF I concentration of 10 μM was chosen for further experiments. The results of MTT assay showed that 10 μM SF I treatment noticeably relived hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell viability loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(c)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(d)</xref> showed that hypoxia stimulation notably lowered the Cylcin D1 protein level in H9c2 cells, but enhanced the p53 and p21 protein levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Relative to hypoxia group, the Cyclin D1 protein level in H9c2 cells was increased, while the p53 and p21 protein levels were decreased in hypoxia + SF I group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, hypoxia stimulation for 24 h remarkably induced H9c2 cell apoptosis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), while 10 μM SF I treatment notably mitigated the hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(e)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). After hypoxia stimulation, the Cleaved-PARP and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in H9c2 cells were both enhanced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419857537">Figure 2(f)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Compared to hypoxia group, the Cleaved-PARP and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in H9c2 cells were both decreased in hypoxia + SF I group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). These above outcomes indicated that SF I could mitigate the hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell viability and proliferation inhibition, as well as cell apoptosis.</p><fig id="fig2-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>SF I mitigated hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell proliferation inhibition and apoptosis. (a) H9c2 cell viability was tested by CCK-8 assay after 0.1, 1, 5, or 10 μM SF I treatment for 24 h. (b) H9c2 cell viability was tested by CCK-8 assay after 0.1, 1, 5, or 10 μM SF I treatment under hypoxia environment for 24 h. After hypoxia stimulation and/or 10 μM SF I treatment for 24 h, (c) H9c2 cell viability was tested by MTT assay; (d) Cyclin D1, p53, and p21 protein levels in H9c2 cells were assessed by western blotting; (e) H9c2 cell apoptosis was evaluated by Guava Nexin assay; and (f) PARP, Cleaved-PARP, Pro-Caspase 3, and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in H9c2 cells were assessed by western blotting. SF I: skullcapflavone I; PARP: poly(ADP-ribose) polymerases. N = 3.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Normoxia group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <sup>##</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Hypoxia group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section12-2058738419857537"><title>SF I promoted hypoxia-caused lincRNA-ROR up-regulation in H9c2 cells</title><p>Then, the lincRNA-ROR expression in H9c2 cells after hypoxia stimulation and/or SF I treatment was measured. Results displayed that hypoxia stimulation noticeably up-regulated the lincRNA-ROR expression in H9c2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738419857537">Figure 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, 10 μM SF I treatment distinctly promoted the hypoxia-caused lincRNA-ROR up-regulation in H9c2 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). These outcomes hinted that up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR might be associated with the protective activity of SF I on hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell viability and proliferation inhibition, as well as apoptosis. Moreover, si-ROR was transfected into H9c2 cells to knockdown lincRNA-ROR expression. The results showed that lincRNA-ROR expression was dramatically reduced in hypoxia + SF I-treated H9c2 cells after si-ROR transfection (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><fig id="fig3-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>SF I promoted hypoxia-caused lincRNA-ROR up-regulation in H9c2 cells. LincRNA-ROR expression in H9c2 cells was measured using qRT-PCR after hypoxia stimulation and/or 10 μM SF I treatment or si-ROR transfection. SF I: skullcapflavone I; lincRNA-ROR: long non-coding RNA regulator of reprogramming. N = 3.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Normoxia group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Hypoxia group; <sup>&amp;&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section13-2058738419857537"><title>Knockdown of lincRNA-ROR reversed the influence of SF I on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells</title><p>Further experiments were performed to confirm whether lincRNA-ROR up-regulation takes part in the protective activity of SF I on hypoxia-treated H9c2 cells. Results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419857537">Figure 4(a)</xref> showed that knockdown of lincRNA-ROR significantly reversed the protective activity of SF I on hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell viability inhibition (CCK-8 assay, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Similar results were found in MTT assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419857537">Figure 4(b)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Cyclin D1 protein level in H9c2 cells was decreased, while the p53 and p21 protein levels were increased in hypoxia + SF I + si-ROR group, relative to hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419857537">Figure 4(c)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, knockdown of lincRNA-ROR also notably reversed the protective activity of SF I on hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419857537">Figure 4(d)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared to hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group, the Cleaved-PARP and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in H9c2 cells were both enhanced in hypoxia + SF I + si-ROR group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419857537">Figure 4(e)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). These above outcomes evidenced that SF I protected H9c2 cells from hypoxia-caused viability and proliferation inhibition, as well as apoptosis, at least by up-regulating lincRNA-ROR.</p><fig id="fig4-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Knockdown of lincRNA-ROR reversed the influence of SF I on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells. After hypoxia stimulation and/or 10 μM SF I treatment or si-ROR transfection, (a and b) H9c2 cell viability was tested by CCK-8 assay and MTT assay; (c) Cyclin D1, p53, and p21 protein levels in H9c2 cells were assessed by western blotting; (d) H9c2 cell apoptosis was evaluated by Guava Nexin assay; and (e) PARP, Cleaved-PARP, Pro-Caspase 3, and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in H9c2 cells were assessed by western blotting. SF I: skullcapflavone I; lincRNA-ROR: long non-coding RNA regulator of reprogramming; PARP: poly(ADP-ribose) polymerases. N = 3.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Normoxia group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Hypoxia group; <sup>&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section14-2058738419857537"><title>SF I also protected primary cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused damage via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR</title><p>The effects of SF I on hypoxia-caused primary cardiomyocytes viability and proliferation inhibition as well as apoptosis were also tested in our study. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419857537">Figure 5(a)</xref> showed that hypoxia stimulation also enhanced the lincRNA-ROR expression in primary cardiomyocytes (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In all, 10 μM SF I treatment distinctly promoted the hypoxia-caused enhancement of lincRNA-ROR expression in primary cardiomyocytes (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, si-ROR transfection lowered the lincRNA-ROR expression (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419857537">Figure 5(b)</xref> displayed that 10 μM SF I treatment also relived the hypoxia-caused primary cardiomyocytes viability loss (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), while si-ROR transfection reversed the effects of SF I (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Cyclin D1 protein level was enhanced, while the p53 and p21 protein levels were reduced in hypoxia + SF I group, relative to hypoxia group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419857537">Figure 5(c)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). si-ROR transfection reversed the SF I-induced Cyclin D1 protein level increase, as well as p53 and p21 protein levels decreases (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419857537">Figure 5(d)</xref> presented that si-ROR transfection reversed the protective effect of SF I on hypoxia-caused primary cardiomyocytes apoptosis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), which accompanied with the increased protein levels of Cleaved-PARP and Cleaved-Caspase 3 in primary cardiomyocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419857537">Figure 5(e)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). These above outcomes evidenced that SF I also protected primary cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused viability and proliferation inhibition, as well as apoptosis, via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR.</p><fig id="fig5-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>SF I also protected primary cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused damage via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR. After hypoxia stimulation and/or 10 μM SF I treatment or si-ROR transfection, (a) lincRNA-ROR expression in primary cardiomyocytes was measured using qRT-PCR; (b) primary cardiomyocytes viability was tested by CCK-8 assay; (c) Cyclin D1, p53, and p21 protein levels in primary cardiomyocytes were assessed by western blotting; (d) primary cardiomyocytes apoptosis was evaluated by Guava Nexin assay; and (e) PARP, Cleaved-PARP, Pro-Caspase 3, and Cleaved-Caspase 3 protein levels in primary cardiomyocytes were assessed by western blotting. SF I: skullcapflavone I; lincRNA-ROR: long non-coding RNA regulator of reprogramming; PARP: poly(ADP-ribose) polymerases. N = 3.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Normoxia group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Hypoxia group; <sup>&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <sup>&amp;&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-2058738419857537"><title>SF I activated MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes through up-regulating lincRNA-ROR</title><p>Finally, the influence of hypoxia stimulation and/or SF I treatment on mitogen-activated protein kinase/extracellular signal–regulated kinase (MEK/ERK) pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyo-cytes was analyzed. Results displayed that hypoxia stimulation obviously inactivated MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes through reducing the expression rates of p/t-MEK and p/t-ERK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419857537">Figure 6(a)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419857537">b</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In all, 10 μM SF I treatment notably reversed the hypoxia-caused inactivation of MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes through enhancing the expression rates of p/t-MEK and p/t-ERK (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). In addition, knockdown of lincRNA-ROR notably reversed the influence of SF I on hypoxia-caused inactivation of MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and in primary cardiomyocytes (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). These outcomes proposed that SF I could activate MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and in primary cardiomyocytes through up-regulating lincRNA-ROR.</p><fig id="fig6-2058738419857537" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>SF I activated MEK/ERK pathway in (a) H9c2 cells and (b) primary cardiomyocytes through up-regulating lincRNA-RoR. After hypoxia stimulation and/or 10 μM SF I treatment or si-ROR transfection, t-MEK, p-MEK, t-ERK, and p-ERK protein levels in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes were assessed by western blotting. SF I: skullcapflavone I; lincRNA-ROR: long non-coding RNA regulator of reprogramming. N = 3.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs Normoxia group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <sup>##</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Hypoxia group; <sup>&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <sup>&amp;&amp;</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs Hypoxia + SF I + si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-fig6.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section16-2058738419857537"><title>Discussion</title><p>Damage of cardiomyocytes caused by acute and persistent hypoxia has been found to play key roles in the occurrence and development of MI<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. Herein, we revealed that SF I, a flavonoid extracted from the root of <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis</italic>, could mitigate rat embryonic ventricular myocardium-derived H9c2 cell and primary cardiomyocytes proliferation inhibition and apoptosis caused by hypoxia. Moreover, we discovered that SF I could promote hypoxia-caused up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR was closely related to the influence of SF I on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Besides, SF I could activate MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes through up-regulating lincRNA-ROR.</p><p>Suitable oxygen supplement is important to maintain normal cardiomyocytes function.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Oxidative stress, along with the insufficient oxygen supplement will cause irreparable injury of cardiomyocytes and lead to the formation of myocardial fibrosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bibr25-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Previous studies demonstrated that hypoxia could inhibit cardiomyocytes viability and proliferation, and promote cell autophagy and apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bibr27-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Inconsistent with the previous studies, we found that hypoxia stimulation obviously reduced the viability of H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. The protein level of Cyclin D1, a critical participator of cell cycle transition,<sup><xref rid="bibr28-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> was decreased in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes after hypoxia stimulation. On the contrary, the protein levels of p53 and p21, which control the initiation of cell cycle,<sup><xref rid="bibr29-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> were increased in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes under hypoxia environment. Moreover, the rate of apoptotic cells and the protein levels of apoptosis-related proteins, Cleaved-PARP and Cleaved-caspase 3, were all enhanced after hypoxia stimulation. These results suggested that cardiomyocytes injury model caused by hypoxia stimulation was established successfully.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> is a well-known and widely used herbal medicine in China, Japan, and Korea.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> As one of the main active ingredients isolated from the <italic toggle="yes">Scutellaria baicalensis</italic>, SF I has been reported to protect liver cells from fibrosis,<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> which implied that SF I might also exert protective activity on cardiomyocytes injury caused by hypoxia. Herein, we found that SF I single treatment had no significant effect on H9c2 cell viability, but remarkably mitigated the hypoxia-caused H9c2 cell and primary cardiomyocytes viability reduction, decrease of Cyclin D1 protein level, and increases of p53 and p21 protein levels. In addition, the enhancement of cell apoptosis and apoptosis-related proteins levels caused by hypoxia stimulation were also reduced after SF I treatment. These findings suggested that SF I could exert protective activities on MI via increasing cardiomyocytes viability and proliferation, as well as decreasing cardiomyocytes apoptosis.</p><p>To date, there is only up to 2% of protein-coding genes that are stably transcribed, whereas the vast majority are non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs).<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> ncRNAs have aroused more and more attentions nowadays, due to their critical regulatory roles in multiple cellular biological processes and pathogenesis of many human diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="bibr32-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> LincRNA-ROR is a typical ncRNA that participates in the regulation of cell reprogramming.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Previous researches demonstrated that lincRNA-ROR played key roles in response to cell hypoxia stress via modulating microRNA-145, hypoxia-inducible factor-1α (HIF-1α), and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF).<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In the current research, we found that hypoxia stimulation up-regulated the lincRNA-ROR expression in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes, which was consistent with the previous study. More importantly, we discovered that SF I treatment dramatically promoted the hypoxia-caused up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR expression in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Besides, knockdown of lincRNA-ROR noticeably reversed the protective effects of SF I on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. These above results implied that SF I exerted protective activity on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes at least partially via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR.</p><p>The inactivation of MEK/ERK pathway in cardiomyocytes has been found to contribute to the occurrence of MI.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bibr34-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> MEK/ERK pathway plays an indispensable role in a number of cellular biological processes in heart, especially cell proliferation, survival, and apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2058738419857537" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> In our research, we found that hypoxia stimulation inactivated MEK/ERK pathway in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. SF I treatment reversed the inactivation of MEK/ERK pathway caused by hypoxia in H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes. Moreover, knockdown of lincRNA-ROR eliminated the influence of SF I on hypoxia-caused inactivation of MEK/ERK pathway. These findings implied that SF I exert protective activity on hypoxia-stimulated H9c2 cells and primary cardiomyocytes might be via up-regulating lincRNA-ROR and then activating MEK/ERK pathway.</p><p>To sum up, this research verified the beneficial activity of SF I on hypoxia-caused cardiomyocytes injury. SF I protected cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-caused injury through up-regulation of lincRNA-ROR and activation of MEK/ERK pathway. We proposed that SF I might be as a potential medicine for MI prevention and treatment, despite the need of further animal and clinical studies.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Yuehua Chen <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419857537-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4646-4017">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4646-4017</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2058738419857537"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vafaie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>State-of-the-art diagnosis of myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Diagnosis</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29536900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/dx-2016-0024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2058738419857537"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngkelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Mast cells regulate myofilament calcium sensitization and heart function after myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source>
<volume>213</volume>: <fpage>1353</fpage>–<lpage>1374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27353089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20160081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4925026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2058738419857537"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Periodic repolarization dynamics—innovative strategies for preventing sudden death</article-title>. <source>Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift (1946)</source>
<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27031208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-0041-108673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2058738419857537"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Myocardial fibrosis in congenital and pediatric heart disease</article-title>. <source>Experimental and Therapeutic Medicine</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1660</fpage>–<lpage>1664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28565750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/etm.2017.4224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5443200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2058738419857537"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Myocardial infarction: Symptoms and treatments</article-title>. <source>Cell Biochemistry and Biophysics</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>867</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25638347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12013-015-0553-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2058738419857537"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundap</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhuvanendran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Plant derived phytocompound, embelin in CNS disorders: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2017.00076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5326771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2058738419857537"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fridlender</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapulnik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koltai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Plant derived substances with anti-cancer activity: From folklore to practice</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpls.2015.00799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4589652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2058738419857537"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terahara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Flavonoids in foods: A review</article-title>. <source>Natural Product Communications</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25924542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-2058738419857537"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Luteolin: A flavonoid that has multiple cardio-protective effects and its molecular mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>692</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29056912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2017.00692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5635727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-2058738419857537"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salaritabar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darvishi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadjiakhoondi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Therapeutic potential of flavonoids in inflammatory bowel disease: A comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>World Journal of Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>23</volume>(<issue>28</issue>): <fpage>5097</fpage>–<lpage>5114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3748/wjg.v23.i28.5097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5537178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-2058738419857537"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abotaleb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Flavonoids in cancer and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Cancers</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>E28</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30597838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers11010028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6357032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-2058738419857537"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Skullcapflavone II attenuates ovalbumin-induced allergic rhinitis through the blocking of Th2 cytokine production and mast cell histamine release</article-title>. <source>International Immunopharmacology</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28886581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2017.08.029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-2058738419857537"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Skullcapflavone I from Scutellaria baicalensis induces apoptosis in activated rat hepatic stellate cells</article-title>. <source>Planta Medica</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>887</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16206047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1055/s-2005-871280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-2058738419857537"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Unique features of long non-coding RNA biogenesis and function</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrg.2015.10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26666209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-2058738419857537"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deniz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Long noncoding RNA (lincRNA), a new paradigm in gene expression control</article-title>. <source>Functional &amp; Integrative Genomics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27681237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10142-016-0524-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-2058738419857537"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eades</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>lincRNA-RoR and miR-145 regulate invasion in triple-negative breast cancer via targeting ARF6</article-title>. <source>Molecular Cancer Research</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25253741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-14-0251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4336811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-2058738419857537"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The human long non-coding RNA-RoR is a p53 repressor in response to DNA damage</article-title>. <source>Cell Research</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23208419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cr.2012.164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3587705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-2058738419857537"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Endogenous miRNA sponge lincRNA-RoR regulates Oct4, Nanog, and Sox2 in human embryonic stem cell self-renewal</article-title>. <source>Developmental Cell</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23541921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.devcel.2013.03.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-2058738419857537"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>The emerging roles of long noncoding RNA ROR (lincRNA-ROR) and its possible mechanisms in human cancers</article-title>. <source>Cellular Physiology and Biochemistry: International Journal of Experimental</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000452539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27855392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-2058738419857537"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ish-Shalom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Analysis of fungal gene expression by real time quantitative PCR</article-title>. <source>Methods in Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>638</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20238263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-60761-611-5_7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-2058738419857537"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Knockdown of ANRIL aggravates H2O2-induced injury in PC-12 cells by targeting microRNA-125a</article-title>. <source>Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28609843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2017.05.122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-2058738419857537"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinstadler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuernau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eitel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Shock index as a predictor of myocardial damage and clinical outcome in ST-elevation myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Circulation Journal</source>
<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26902549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1253/circj.CJ-15-1135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-2058738419857537"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia and heart regeneration: A new paradoxical approach for cardioprotection</article-title>. <source>Archives of Cardiovascular Diseases</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28917832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acvd.2017.06.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-2058738419857537"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Protective effect of tempol against hypoxia-induced oxidative stress and apoptosis in H9c2 cells</article-title>. <source>Medical Science Monitor Basic Research</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSMBR.903764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5408902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-2058738419857537"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Hypoxia-stimulated cardiac fibroblast production of IL-6 promotes myocardial fibrosis via the TGF-beta1 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Laboratory Investigation</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>852</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/labinvest.2016.65</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-2058738419857537"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Knockdown of MicroRNA-122 protects H9c2 cardiomyocytes from hypoxia-induced apoptosis and promotes autophagy</article-title>. <source>Medical Science Monitor: International Medical Journal of Experimental and Clinical Research</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>4284</fpage>–<lpage>4290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28871076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.902936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5597036</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8679544"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-2058738419857537"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Gastrodin protects myocardial cells against hypoxia/reoxygenation injury in neonatal rats by inhibiting cell autophagy through the activation of mTOR signals in PI3K-Akt pathway</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacology</source>
<volume>70</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29148068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jphp.12838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-2058738419857537"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bendris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemmers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Cell cycle, cytoskeleton dynamics and beyond: The many functions of cyclins and CDK inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1786</fpage>–<lpage>1798</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25789852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15384101.2014.998085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4614797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-2058738419857537"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Cell cycle arrest through indirect transcriptional repression by p53: I have a DREAM</article-title>. <source>Cell Death and Differentiation</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29125603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cdd.2017.172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5729532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-2058738419857537"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Skullcapflavone I inhibits proliferation of human colorectal cancer cells via down-regulation of miR-107 expression</article-title>. <source>Neoplasma</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30509103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4149/neo_2018_180427N279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-2058738419857537"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherstyuk</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medvedev</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakian</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Noncoding RNAs in the regulation of pluripotency and reprogramming</article-title>. <source>Stem Cell Reviews</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29143182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12015-017-9782-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-2058738419857537"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>MNDR v2.0: An updated resource of ncRNA-disease associations in mammals</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>46</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>): <fpage>D371</fpage>–<lpage>D374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29106639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkx1025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5753235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-2058738419857537"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>The protective effect of trimetazidine on myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury through activating AMPK and ERK signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Metabolism: Clinical and Experimental</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.metabol.2015.10.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4967934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-2058738419857537"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Filippone</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samidurai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Reperfusion therapy with rapamycin attenuates myocardial infarction through activation of AKT and ERK</article-title>. <source>Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>2017</volume>: <fpage>4619720</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28373901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2017/4619720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5360974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-2058738419857537"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedikaetswe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Evidence that the MEK/ERK but not the PI3K/Akt pathway is required for protection from myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury by 3,’4’-dihydroxyflavonol</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Pharmacology</source>
<volume>758</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25820159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejphar.2015.03.054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>