
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3390</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijip</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8911335</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6668182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6668182.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6668182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6668182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31359794</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2058738419866021</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2058738419866021</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Protective effects of ginsenoside Rb1 on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative injury in human endothelial cell line (EA.hy926) via miR-210</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="F">Fubao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738419866021">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-2058738419866021">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mou</surname><given-names initials="L">Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738419866021">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-2058738419866021">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4598-2509</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2058738419866021">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2058738419866021"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-2058738419866021"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Shanxian Central Hospital, Heze, China</aff><aff id="aff2-2058738419866021"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, Rizhao Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Rizhao, China</aff><aff id="aff3-2058738419866021"><label>3</label>Department of Neurology, The Affiliated Hospital of Northwest University, Xi’an No.3 Hospital, Xi’an, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2058738419866021">Hanming Ge, Department of Neurology, The Affiliated Hospital of Northwest University, Xi’an No.3 Hospital, Xi’an, China. Email: <email>gehanming0006@sina.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-2058738419866021"><label>*</label><p>Co-first authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">327275</issue-id><elocation-id>2058738419866021</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>08</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 12:25:10.757"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted. Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons Licenses</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7925941"><article-title>Expression Of Concern: ‘Protective effects of ginsenoside Rb1 on H2O2-induced oxidative injury in human endothelial cell line (EA.hy926) via miR-210’</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211000848</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211000848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7925941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33641483</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="35" journal-id="Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8419550"><article-title>RETRACTION NOTICE: Protective effects of ginsenoside Rb1 on H2O2-induced oxidative injury in human endothelial cell line (EA.hy926) via miR-210</article-title><volume>35</volume><date><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date><elocation-id>20587384211040399</elocation-id><source>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/20587384211040399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8419550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34472407</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>Ginsenoside Rb1 (Rb1) possesses a cardioprotective effect via mediating microRNAs (miRs), while it is unexplored whether miR-210 is regulated by Rb1 in response to oxidative stress. Human endothelial EA.hy926 cells were stimulated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> before Rb1 treatment. After transfection, cell viability, apoptosis, migration, and invasion assays were conducted. Western blot was applied to quantify protein. BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3 (BNIP3) and miR-210 were analyzed with quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction. Dual luciferase activity assay was performed. Rb1 elevated viability, migration, and invasion of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated cells. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced apoptosis was moderated by Rb1. miR-210 was augmented in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated cells after Rb1 stimulation. miR-210 inhibitor abolished the positive effects of Rb1. BNIP3 was negatively modulated by miR-210 and implicated in modulating viability, apoptosis, and migration and invasion. In addition, BNIP3 modulated phosphorylation of regulators. Rb1 repressed oxidative injury via elevating miR-210. miR-210 negatively mediated BNIP3, which participated in oxidative damage via regulating mammalian targets of rapamycin (mTOR) and nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB).</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>BNIP3</kwd><kwd>ginsenoside Rb1</kwd><kwd>miR-210</kwd><kwd>oxidative stress</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-2058738419866021"><title>Introduction</title><p>The pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases is directly associated with the damage of endothelial cells, which serve as a target for reactive oxygen species (ROS) and consequently are vulnerable to oxidative damage.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Through causing the dysfunction of antioxidant proteins and pro-oxidant enzymes, oxidative stress perturbs mitochondrial properties and subsequently triggers the cleaved progress of caspase-3 and caspase-9 via oxidative stress-mediated signaling pathways.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Once the endothelial cell death is initiated, the endothelial barrier feature is gravely disrupted and the cerebrovascular diseases are therewith contributed since it plays a pivotal role in the development of neurological function.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Numerous pharmaceutical studies have been performed to mitigate the cerebral vascular damage based on account of part antioxidant capability.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p><p>Ginsenoside Rb1 (Rb1), a steroidal saponin compound, is the main bioactive component of ginseng. Extensive evidence have demonstrated that Rb1 alleviates oxidative stress-induced apoptosis and improves cell viability under the stressful environments.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> A previous study has shown that Rb1 substantially maintains the redox homeostasis by scavenging hydroxyl radical and hypochlorous acid.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> A recent study presented a microRNA (miR)-relative mechanism, whereby Rb1 exhibits a cardioprotective effect on hypoxic- and ischemic-damaged cardiomyocytes.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> However, it still remains indistinct whether miR-210 is associated with the protective function of Rb1 against oxidative stress-mediated endothelial cell injury.</p><p>miR-210 is regulated by hypoxia inducible factor (HIF) in response to hypoxia stimulus.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The function of miR-210 has been studied in several physiopathological conditions. A foregone study highlighted that lung adenocarcinoma cells overexpressing miR-210 suggest a specific appearance characterized by abundance of transcripts associated with cell death and mitochondrial dysfunction.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> As for its function in the post-injury neurogenesis, miR-210 participates in mediating the mitochondrial function and modulating apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> The role of miR-210 in cell viability and apoptosis has been elaborated under oxidative stress, which exhibits an anti-oxidative property.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3 (BNIP3), as a crucial mitochondrial redox sensor that mediates cell death in response to oxidative stress,<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> has been reported to be directly modulated by miR-210 to reduce the hypoxia-induced cell death,<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> whereas its downstream cascades are still unexplored in endothelial cells under oxidative stress.</p><p>As a consequence, this study was aimed to investigate the cytoprotective function of Rb1 in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damaged cell model. In addition, we explored the underlying mechanism which might be associated with the miR-210. Considering that BNIP3 is an essential redox sensor, we further studied its modulatory effects on cell viability, migration, invasion and apoptosis as well as the correlative signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-2058738419866021"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="section3-2058738419866021"><title>Cell culture and treatment</title><p>The human endothelial EA.hy926 cells were derived from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Rockville, MD, USA). EA.hy926 cells were cultured in high glucose-Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) containing 10% fetal calf serum (FBS; Gibco, Gaithersburg, MD, USA), 5 mM hypoxanthine (Sigma), 0.02 mM aminopterin (Sigma), and 0.8 mM thymidine (Sigma), in a humidified incubator containing 95% air and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37°C. EA.hy926 cells were stimulated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (Sigma) for 2 h. Before stimulation with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, EA.hy926 cells were pre-incubated with 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h. Rb1 was purchased from Sigma.</p></sec><sec id="section4-2058738419866021"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>EA.hy926 cells (1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) were plated in 24-well plates. After stimulation with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and/or pre-incubation with Rb1, EA.hy926 cells were trypsinized and stained with trypan blue solution (Gibco) and counted with cell-counting chamber under a microscope.</p></sec><sec id="section5-2058738419866021"><title>Apoptosis assay</title><p>A flow cytometry in combination with Annexin V–fluorescein isothiocyanate/propidium iodide (Annexin V-FITC/PI) apoptosis detection kit (Biosea, Beijing, China) were applied to detect apoptotic cells. Briefly, EA.hy926 cells were seeded in six-well plates at a density of 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. After stimulation with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and/or pre-incubation with Rb1, EA.hy926 cells were washed twice with pre-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; Sigma). After staining with Annexin V-FITC/PI, apoptotic cells were distinguished with a flow cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="section6-2058738419866021"><title>Migration and invasion assay</title><p>Cell migration activity was examined with a modified Boyden chamber with 8 μm pores. EA.hy926 cells were supplemented with 200 μL serum-free medium and seeded on the upper compartment. The lower compartment was supplemented with 600 μL complete medium. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or Rb1 was added to both inserts and wells. Cells were fixed with methanol after incubation at 37°C for 8 h. Traversed cells on the lower side of the filter were stained with crystal violet and counted. The invasive behavior of EA.hy926 cells was determined with a BD BioCoat<sup>TM</sup> Matrigel<sup>TM</sup> invasion (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA). Serum-free medium was supplemented into the inserts and the wells. EA.hy926 cells were plated onto the inserts. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or Rb1 was added to both inserts and wells. Chambers were incubated for 24 h at 37°C. After fixation with methanol and staining with crystal violet, the invasive cells were counted.</p></sec><sec id="section7-2058738419866021"><title>Transfection</title><p>miR-210 mimic, miR-210 inhibitor, scramble, and negative control (NC) were provided by GenePharma (Shanghai, China). Lipofectamine 3000 reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) was employed to transfect miR-210 mimic, miR-210 inhibitor, scramble, and NC into EA.hy926 cells by following manufacturer’s instructions.</p><p>Full-length BNIP3 sequence and short hairpin (sh)-BNIP3 directly against BNIP3 were ligated into pEX-3 and pGU6/Neo plasmids (GenePharma) named pEX-BNIP3 and sh-BNIP3, respectively. The empty plasmids served as NCs named pEX and sh-NC. After transfection using lipofectamine 3000, the stably transfected cells cultured in the medium containing 0.5 mg/mL G418 (Sigma) for selecting the G418-resistant cell clones.</p></sec><sec id="section8-2058738419866021"><title>Dual luciferase activity assay</title><p>Fragments of the BNIP3 3′-untranslated region (UTR) containing the putative miR-210 binding site (BNIP3 promoter) or U6 (U6) were generated by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Amplified products were ligated into the pMIR-report vector (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA). EA.hy926 cells were cotransfected with miR-210 mimic or NC and BNIP3 promoter or U6. Renilla luciferase reporter acted as an internal control. The dual-luciferase assay system (Promega, Madison, USA) was used to measure the luciferase activities after transfection for 24 h according to manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="section9-2058738419866021"><title>Quantitative reverse transcription PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from EA.hy926 cells with Trizol reagent (Life Technologies). The expression of miR-210 was quantified with TaqMan MicroRNA Reverse Transcription Kit and TaqMan Universal Master Mix II with the TaqMan MicroRNA Assay of miR-210 and U6 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). U6 served as an internal reference. The mRNA expression of BNIP3 was determined using RNA-to-cDNA Master Mix and TaqMan primers (Applied Biosystems). Its relative expression was normalized with an endogenous control Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) using the Ct method.</p></sec><sec id="section10-2058738419866021"><title>Western blot</title><p>The total proteins were quantified with the BCA<sup>TM</sup> protein assay kit (Pierce, Appleton, WI, USA) after extracting using radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) lysis buffer (Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, China). The Bio-Rad Bis-Tris Gel system was established for Western blot assay according to manufacturer’s protocol. GAPDH served as an internal reference. After separation, proteins were electrophoretically transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane (Invitrogen). Membranes were blocked with 5% bovine serum albumin (BSA; Sigma). Primary antibodies against proteins were used, including Bcl-2 (ab32124; 1:1000), Bax (ab53154; 1:1000), pro caspase-3 (ab32499; 10,000), active caspase-3 (ab32042; 1:500), pro caspase-9 (ab138412; 1:1000), active caspase-9 (ab32042; 1:500), BNIP3 (44060; 1:1000) (all purchased from Abcam, Cambridge, UK), S6 (2217; 1:1000), phospho (p)-S6 (4858; 1:2000), mammalian targets of rapamycin (mTOR) (2983; 1:1000), p-mTOR (5536; 1:1000), inhibitor of nuclear factor κ-B α (IκBα) (4812; 1:1000), p-IκBα (2859; 1:1000), p65 (8242; 1:1000), p-p65 (3033; 1:1000), and GAPDH (5174; 1:1000) (all purchased from Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA). After incubation with primary antibodies for overnight, the PVDF membrane was incubated with a secondary antibody (7074) (Cell Signaling Technology) for 1 h at room temperature. Chemiluminescence was excited by 200 μL Immobilon Western Chemiluminescent horseradish peroxidase (HRP) substrate (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). The protein signals were captured by Image Lab<sup>TM</sup> software (Bio-Rad, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="section11-2058738419866021"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All the experiments were repeated at least for three times. Data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD). The comparison of all results was conducted with Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t-</italic>test and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). The statistical significance was considered when <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> was less than 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section12-2058738419866021"><title>Results</title><sec id="section13-2058738419866021"><title>Rb1-protected EA.hy926 cells against H2O2-induced damage</title><p>In order to investigate whether Rb1 protected EA.hy926 cells against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced damage, we established an oxidative damaged cell model. EA.hy926 cells were overtly injured after treatment with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h, demonstrated by reduction in cell viability (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419866021">Figure 1(a)</xref>), migration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419866021">Figure 1(b)</xref>), invasion (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419866021">Figure 1(c)</xref>), and induction of apoptotic cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419866021">Figure 1(d)</xref>) as well as aberrant expression of apoptosis-related proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738419866021">Figure 1(e)</xref>). Subsequently, we pre-treated EA.hy926 cells with 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h. In contrast to cells in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> group, more EA.hy926 cells pre-treated with Rb1 survived after being exposed to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419866021">Figure 2 (a)</xref>). As for migration and invasion, the distinct induction was achieved in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced EA.hy926 cells pre-incubated with Rb1 in comparison with the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419866021">Figure 2(b)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419866021">c</xref>)). A marked inhibition of apoptosis was observed in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced EA.hy926 cells by Rb1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419866021">Figure 2(d)</xref>). Furthermore, Rb1 upregulated Bcl-2 protein expression, repressed Bax protein expression and the production of active caspase-3 and active caspase-9 in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced EA.hy926 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738419866021">Figure 2(e)</xref>). Collectively, these results suggested that Rb1 protected EA.hy926 cells against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-inudced oxidative injury.</p><fig id="fig1-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Oxidative injury was induced with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in EA.hy926 cells: (a) cell viability was detected after staining with trypan blue. (b) Relative migration was assessed by a modified Boyden chamber. (c) A BD BioCoat Matrigel invasion was performed to analyze the invasive behavior. (d) Apoptotic cells were observed with flow cytometry after staining with Annexin V-FITC/PI. (e) Protein levels were examined with Western blot assay. EA.hy926 cells were treated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h.</p><p>Annexin V-FITC/PI: Annexin V–fluorescein isothiocyanate/propidium iodide.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, or ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 compared to control cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig1.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig2-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-mediated oxidative injury was repressed by Rb1: (a) cell viability was detected after staining with trypan blue. (b) Relative migration was assessed by a modified Boyden chamber. (c) A BD BioCoat Matrigel invasion was performed to analyze the invasive behavior. (d) Apoptotic cells were observed with flow cytometry after staining with Annexin V-FITC/PI. (e) Protein levels were examined with Western blot assay. EA.hy926 cells were treated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h after pre-incubation with/without 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h.</p><p>Annexin V-FITC/PI: Annexin V–fluorescein isothiocyanate/propidium iodide; Rb1: ginsenoside Rb1.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, or ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 compared to control cells; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to H2O2 cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section14-2058738419866021"><title>Rb1 repressed oxidative damage induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> via upregulating miR-210</title><p>A recent research revealed that ROS generation induces miR-210 expression, which mediates proliferation and migration.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> We found that miR-210 expression was evidently augmented in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced cells after stimulation with Rb1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), although it was not significantly mediated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738419866021">Figure 3(a)</xref>). For confirming that Rb1 protected EA.hy926 cells against oxidative injury through upregulating miR-210, we silenced miR-210 by transfecting miR-210 inhibitor into EA.hy926 cells. The transfection efficiency was notable. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738419866021">Figure 3(b)</xref>, miR-210 was upregulated by miR-210 mimc (P &lt; 0.01) while downregulated by miR-210 inhibitor (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Our results indicated that the increment in cell viability, migration, and invasion along with the decrement in apoptotic cells by Rb1 were prominently attenuated by the transfection of miR-210 inhibitor in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced EA.hy926 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419866021">Figure 4(a)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419866021">d</xref>)). In addition, miR-210 silence facilitated apoptosis evidenced by lessened Bcl-2, enhancive Bax, as well as activated caspase-3 and caspase-9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738419866021">Figure 4(e)</xref>). Therefore, we concluded that Rb1 protected EA.hy926 cells against oxidative damage induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> via upregulating miR-210.</p><fig id="fig3-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Rb1 elevated miR-210 expression: (a) miR-210 expression was quantified in EA.hy926 cells after stimulation with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h after pre-incubation with/without 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h. (b) Profile of miR-210 expression was quantified in EA.hy926 cells after transfection with miR-210 mimic, miR-210 inhibitor, scramble, or NC. miR-210 was analyzed with qRT-PCR.</p><p>miR-210: microRNA-210; Rb1: ginsenoside Rb1; NC: negative control; ns: not significant; qRT-PCR: quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</p><p>ns compared to control cells; <sup>##</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to H2O2 cells; <sup>++</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to NC cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>miR-210 inhibitor abrogated the protective effects of Rb1 against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damage: (a) cell viability was detected after staining with trypan blue. (b) Relative migration was assessed by a modified Boyden chamber. (c) A BD BioCoat Matrigel invasion was performed to analyze the invasive behavior. (d) Apoptotic cells were observed with flow cytometry after staining with Annexin V-FITC/PI. (e) Protein levels were examined with Western blot assay. EA.hy926 cells were treated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h and/or pre-incubated with/without 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h after transfection.</p><p>Annexin V-FITC/PI: Annexin V–fluorescein isothiocyanate/propidium iodide; Rb1: ginsenoside Rb1; miR-210: microRNA-210; NC: negative control.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, or ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 compared to control cells; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <sup>##</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared to H2O2 cells; and +P &lt; 0.05 or <sup>++</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to H2O2 + Rb1 + NC cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-2058738419866021"><title>miR-210 negatively regulated BNIP3 expression by targeting BNIP3 3′-UTR</title><p>BNIP3 has been verified as a redox sensor where increased oxidative stress induces homodimerization and activation of BNIP3.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> To investigate the role of miR-210, we artificially promoted and inhibited the expression of miR-210 as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738419866021">Figure 3(b)</xref> (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Our results illustrated that miR-210 negatively regulated BNIP3 expression at mRNA and protein levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419866021">Figure 5(a)</xref>). In addition, our results from dual luciferase activity assay implied that miR-210 mediated BNIP3 expression by targeting BNIP3 3′-UTR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738419866021">Figure 5(b)</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>miR-210 negatively mediated BNIP3 expression by targeting BNIP3 3′-UTR: (a) relative mRNA expression of BNIP3 was quantified with qRT-PCR assay. BNIP3 protein level was evaluated with Western blot method. (b) EA.hy926 cells were co-transfected with miR-210 mimic or NC along with reporter constructs containing BNIP3 promoter or U6. Renilla luciferase reporter acted as an internal control. Relative luciferase activity was normalized with Renilla luciferase activity.</p><p>3′-UTR: 3′-untranslated region; BNIP3: BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3; miR-210: microRNA-210; NC: negative control; ns: not significant; qRT-PCR: quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</p><p>ns compared to control cells; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to scramble cells; <sup>++</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared to NC cells; and *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared to NC cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section16-2058738419866021"><title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induced oxidative damage via upregulating BNIP3</title><p>To confirm that BNIP3 participated in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative injury, we effectually promoted or repressed BNIP3 expression by transfecting pEX-BNIP3 or sh-BNIP3 into EA.hy926 cells, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419866021">Figure 6(a)</xref>). Our results showed that BNIP3 overexpression further promoted H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced decrease in cell viability, migration, invasion, and increment of apoptosis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419866021">Figure 6(b)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419866021">f</xref>)). However, BNIP3 silence reversed the negative effects of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> on cell viability, migration, invasion, and apoptosis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419866021">Figure 6(b)</xref>–(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738419866021">f</xref>)). Taken together, our results demonstrated that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induced oxidative damage via upregulating BNIP3.</p><fig id="fig6-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>BNIP3 modulated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damage: (a) BNIP3 mRNA and protein expression were analyzed by qRT-PCR or Western blot in EA.hy926 cells after transfection. (b) Cell viability was detected with CCK-8 assay. (c) Relative migration was assessed by a modified Boyden chamber. (d) A BD BioCoat Matrigel invasion was performed to analyze the invasive behavior. (e) Apoptotic cells were observed with flow cytometry after staining with Annexin V-FITC/PI. (f) Protein levels were examined with Western blot assay. EA.hy926 cells were treated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h and/or pre-incubated with/without 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h after transfection.</p><p>BNIP3: BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3; sh: short hairpin; NC: negative control; qRT-PCR: quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</p><p><sup>##</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to pEX; <sup>++</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to sh-NC in (a). *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, or ***P &lt; 0.001 compared to control cells; <sup>#</sup>P &lt; 0.05 or <sup>##</sup>P &lt; 0.01 compared to H2O2 + pEX cells; +P &lt; 0.05 compared to H2O2 + sh-BNIP3 cells. n = 3–5.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig6.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section17-2058738419866021"><title>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> blocked mTOR and nuclear factor-κB signaling pathways via upregulating BNIP3</title><p>BNIP3 participates in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced autophagic cell death by suppressing mTOR signaling pathway.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> As for nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) signaling pathway, a study revealed that NF-κB extends to the active transcriptional repression of the death factor BNIP3.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> In this study, we found that the phosphorylation of S6 and mTOR was mitigated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and BNIP3 overexpression further reduced S6 and mTOR phosphorylation. However, BNIP3 silence enhanced the phosphorylated expression of S6 and mTOR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-2058738419866021">Figure 7(a)</xref>). In addition, we also observed that the phosphorylation of IκBα and p65 was inhibited by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and upregulated BNIP3 further relieved the phosphorylation of IκBα and p65, while BNIP3 knockdown restored the phosphorylation of IκBα and p65 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-2058738419866021">Figure 7(b)</xref>). From the aforementioned results, we considered that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> inactivated mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways by upregulating BNIP3.</p><fig id="fig7-2058738419866021" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Depletion of BNIP3 mediated S6, mTOR, IκBα, and p65 phosphorylation: (a) S6, p-S6, mTOR, p-mTOR, (b) IκBα, p-IκBα, p65, and p-p65 were quantified with Western blot assay. EA.hy926 cells were treated with 150 μM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 h and/or pre-incubated with/without 20 μM Rb1 for 1 h after transfection. n = 3.</p><p>mTOR: mammalian targets of rapamycin; IκBα: inhibitor of nuclear factor κ-B α; BNIP3: BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3; NC: negative control; sh: short hairpin; p: phospho.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-fig7.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section18-2058738419866021"><title>Discussion</title><p>Multiple natural compounds, derived from plants, have been excavated for their application in alleviating oxidative injury. The anti-oxidative function of Rb1 has been elaborated in 6-hydroxydopamine-induced oxidative stress.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In this study, we found that Rb1 protected EA.hy926 cells against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative injury by upregulating miR-210. Furthermore, we noticed that miR-210 negatively modulated BNIP3 and consequently mediated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative injury via mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways.</p><p>Previously published research has implied that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> significantly decreased antioxidant enzyme activities.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Another important effect of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> on oxidation is the generation of ROS, which has been validated to mediate apoptosis in an intrinsic manner.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Rb1, containing a tetracyclic triterpene skeleton with an aglycone, is a major component of ginseng. Its antioxidant activity has been proved in rat articular chondrocytes under H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> We found that Rb1 efficaciously restored cell viability, migration, and invasion, meanwhile repressed apoptosis in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated endothelial cells. Furthermore, Rb1 repressed the activation of caspase-3 and caspase-9. It has been proved that oxidative stress induces apoptosis in a caspase-3 or caspase-9-dependent manner.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Collectively, Rb1 protected EA.hy926 against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced apoptosis in a caspase-3 and caspase-9-dependent manner.</p><p>In addition, we found that Rb1-treated EA.hy926 cells showed upregulatory expression of Bcl-2, while downregulatory level of Bax after being treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Bcl-2 family member Bcl-2 protein is the essential modulator of apoptosis, and it has been considered as an effective molecular therapeutic target because of the key role in the pathogenesis of various diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Bax is another member of Bcl-2 family, and its importance has been lighted in executing apoptosis process associated with mitochondrial membrane permeabilization.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> As a consequence, the alteration of Bcl-2 and Bax indicated that the protective role of Rb1 was associated with its anti-apoptotic properties. In addition, its anti-apoptotic activity might be ascribed to its free radical scavenging capacity, which effectively preserves the mitochondrial membrane.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Specifically, a preceding study suggested that Rb1 augments the cellular antioxidant defenses through endoplasmic reticulum-dependent heme oxygenase-1 induction via several signaling pathways.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>Cytoprotection of miR-210 has been studied in several injury cell models. It has been validated that insulin protects H9c2 rat cardiomyoblast cells against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced injury through upregulating the expression of miR-210.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> The potential mechanism is associated with its regulatory function on mitochondrial free radical.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> Furthermore, miR-210 overexpression reduced the apoptosis of mesenchymal stem cells under oxidative stress.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Similarly, we found that low level H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced miR-210 was not significant, while Rb1 obviously aggrandized miR-210 expression. Besides, miR-210 silence abrogated the protective effects of Rb1 in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated cells. As a consequence, we considered that the anti-apoptotic activity of Rb1 was through regulation of miR-210. However, it is still incompletely understood how Rb1 modulated miR-210 expression.</p><p>BNIP3 has been identified as a redox sensor where oxidative stress triggers homodimerization and activation of BNIP3.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The primary function of miRs in protein output is based on the conserved match between miRs and the 3′-UTR of its target genes.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Besides, it has been found that BNIP3 is a target gene of miR-210 in neural progenitor cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> In this study, we further consolidated that miR-210 negatively mediated BNIP3 expression by targeting its 3′-UTR. In addition, BNIP3 silence ameliorated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced injury, whereas BNIP3 overexpression expedited H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced injury. Actually, an anterior study showed that BNIP3 interacts with dynamin Opa1 and consequently leads to mitochondrial fragmentation and apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Consistently, our results suggested that BNIP3 silence blocked the activation of caspase-3 and caspase-9, indicating that BNIP3 knockdown impeded H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced apoptosis.</p><p>Rb1 augmented mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways under inflammatory environment, which exhibited the anti-inflammatory activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr32-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> On the basis of this study, we promoted and inhibited BNIP3 expression via transfection for addressing whether Rb1 triggered mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways via BNIP3. Empirical evidence shows that the apoptosis is induced by mTOR inhibitor.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bibr34-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Moreover, NF-κB has been found to participate in the cell protective process of Rb1. Accordingly, BNIP3, as the mTOR and NF-κB signaling inhibitor, has been demonstrated to promote oxidative injury of endothelial cells in this study.</p><p>The vulnerability of cells to apoptosis is accompanied by the activation of mTOR and NF-κB cascades under multitude adverse stresses.<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="bibr36-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr37-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> A previous study revealed a bidirectional association between mTOR and NF-κB signaling transduction cascades, which renders them indispensable for the regulation of BNIP3 expression.<sup><xref rid="bibr38-2058738419866021" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> As a result, there might be a feedback regulation between BNIP3 and mTOR and NF-κB pathways. Collectively, we concluded that Rb1 might protect endothelial cells against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative injury by activating mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways via downregulating BNIP3.</p><p>According to the aforementioned results, we concluded that the anti-apoptosis property of Rb1 was through inhibition of BNIP3 via upregulating miR-210. Furthermore, BNIP3 was testified to be involved in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced apoptosis via modulating mTOR and NF-κB signaling pathways.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Hanming Ge <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738419866021-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4598-2509">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4598-2509</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2058738419866021"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grammas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cerebral microvascular endothelium and the pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>Expert Reviews in Molecular Medicine</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>e19</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21676288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S1462399411001918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2058738419866021"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Oxidative stress in ischemic brain damage: Mechanisms of cell death and potential molecular targets for neuroprotection</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants &amp; Redox Signaling</source>
<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1505</fpage>–<lpage>1517</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20812869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/ars.2010.3576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3061196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2058738419866021"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Blood-brain barrier breakdown in acute and chronic cerebrovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Stroke</source>
<volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3323</fpage>–<lpage>3328</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21940972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.608257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3584169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2058738419866021"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>The protective role of isorhamnetin on human brain microvascular endothelial cells from cytotoxicity induced by methylglyoxal and oxygen-glucose deprivation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurochemistry</source>
<volume>136</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26578299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jnc.13436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2058738419866021"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Quercetin protects human brain microvascular endothelial cells from fibrillar beta-amyloid1-40-induced toxicity</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharmaceutica Sinica B</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26579424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apsb.2014.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2058738419866021"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Moriano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Burgos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of the adaptogenic potential exerted by ginsenosides Rb1 and Rg1 against oxidative stress-mediated neurotoxicity in an in vitro neuronal model</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>e0182933</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28813475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0182933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5558939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2058738419866021"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotective effects of ginsenosides on neural progenitor cells against oxidative injury</article-title>. <source>Molecular Medicine Reports</source>
<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>3083</fpage>–<lpage>3091</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2016.4914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4805061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2058738419866021"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weakley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ginsenoside Rb1 directly scavenges hydroxyl radical and hypochlorous acid</article-title>. <source>Current Pharmaceutical Design</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>38</issue>): <fpage>6339</fpage>–<lpage>6347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/138161212803832254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-2058738419866021"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Ginsenoside-Rb1 protects hypoxic- and ischemic-damaged cardiomyocytes by regulating expression of miRNAs</article-title>. <source>Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine</source>
<volume>2015</volume>; <fpage>171306</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26074986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2015/171306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4449925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-2058738419866021"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giaccia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MiR-210, micromanager of the hypoxia pathway</article-title>. <source>Trends in Molecular Medicine</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20434954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molmed.2010.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3408219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-2058738419866021"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puissegur</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazure</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertero</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>miR-210 is overexpressed in late stages of lung cancer and mediates mitochondrial alterations associated with modulation of HIF-1 activity</article-title>. <source>Cell Death and Differentiation</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20885442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cdd.2010.119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3131992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-2058738419866021"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voloboueva</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Distinct effects of miR-210 reduction on neurogenesis: Increased neuronal survival of inflammation but reduced proliferation associated with mitochondrial enhancement</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Neuroscience: The Official Journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>
<volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3072</fpage>–<lpage>3084</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28188219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1777-16.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5354339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-2058738419866021"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>miR-210 over-expression enhances mesenchymal stem cell survival in an oxidative stress environment through antioxidation and c-Met pathway activation</article-title>. <source>Science China. Life Sciences</source>
<volume>57</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>989</fpage>–<lpage>997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25168379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11427-014-4725-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-2058738419866021"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinsay</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bnip3 functions as a mitochondrial sensor of oxidative stress during myocardial ischemia and reperfusion</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physiology. Heart and Circulatory Physiology</source>
<volume>295</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>H2025</fpage>–<lpage>H2031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpheart.00552.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2614576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-2058738419866021"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>miR-210 suppresses BNIP3 to protect against the apoptosis of neural progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>Stem Cell Research</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23688833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scr.2013.04.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-2058738419866021"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Reactive oxygen species-responsive miR-210 regulates proliferation and migration of adipose-derived stem cells via PTPN2</article-title>. <source>Cell Death &amp; Disease</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e588</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/cddis.2013.117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3641340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-2058738419866021"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Hydrogen peroxide induces autophagic cell death in C6 glioma cells via BNIP3-mediated suppression of the mTOR pathway</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience Letters</source>
<volume>461</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19539716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neulet.2009.06.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-2058738419866021"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rzeszutek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional silencing of the death gene BNIP3 by cooperative action of NF-kappaB and histone deacetylase 1 in ventricular myocytes</article-title>. <source>Circulation Research</source>
<volume>99</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1347</fpage>–<lpage>1354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.RES.0000251744.06138.50</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-2058738419866021"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ginsenoside Rb1 protects against 6-hydroxydopamine-induced oxidative stress by increasing heme oxygenase-1 expression through an estrogen receptor-related PI3K/Akt/Nrf2-dependent pathway in human dopaminergic cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology</source>
<volume>242</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19781563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.taap.2009.09.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-2058738419866021"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Augusto</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurgueira</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effect of acute vs chronic H2O2-induced oxidative stress on antioxidant enzyme activities</article-title>. <source>Free Radical Research</source>
<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19212855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10715760902751894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-2058738419866021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Redox regulation of the intrinsic pathway in neuronal apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants &amp; Redox Signaling</source>
<volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1437</fpage>–<lpage>1448</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20812874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/ars.2010.3596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3061193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-2058738419866021"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Na</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Protective effect of ginsenoside Rb1 on hydrogen peroxide-induced oxidative stress in rat articular chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ginseng Research</source>
<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5142/jgr.2012.36.2.161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3659580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-2058738419866021"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Oxidative stress inhibits growth and induces apoptotic cell death in human U251 glioma cells via the caspase-3-dependent pathway</article-title>. <source>European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>4068</fpage>–<lpage>4075</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26592828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-2058738419866021"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Hydrogen peroxide induces apoptosis in human dental pulp cells via caspase-9 dependent pathway</article-title>. <source>Journal of Endodontics</source>
<volume>39</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1151</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23953289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joen.2013.06.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-2058738419866021"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahsan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The mystery of BCL2 family: Bcl-2 proteins and apoptosis: An update</article-title>. <source>Archives of Toxicology</source>
<volume>89</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25618543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00204-014-1448-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-2058738419866021"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wurm</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Bax assembles into large ring-like structures remodeling the mitochondrial outer membrane in apoptosis</article-title>. <source>The EMBO Journal</source>
<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26783364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15252/embj.201592789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4755111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-2058738419866021"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The effects of ginsenoside Rb1 on JNK in oxidative injury in cardiomyocytes</article-title>. <source>Archives of Pharmacal Research</source>
<volume>35</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1259</fpage>–<lpage>1267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22864749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12272-012-0717-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3415887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-2058738419866021"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Insulin protects H9c2 rat cardiomyoblast cells against hydrogen peroxide-induced injury through upregulation of microRNA-210</article-title>. <source>Free Radical Research</source>
<volume>49</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1147</fpage>–<lpage>1155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25968948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/10715762.2015.1050588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-2058738419866021"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favaro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-210 regulates mitochondrial free radical response to hypoxia and krebs cycle in cancer cells by targeting iron sulfur cluster protein ISCU</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e10345</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0010345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2859946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-2058738419866021"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidigal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The biological functions of miRNAs: Lessons from in vivo studies</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cell Biology</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25484347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tcb.2014.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4344861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-2058738419866021"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emorine</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Courilleau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The BH3-only Bnip3 binds to the dynamin Opa1 to promote mitochondrial fragmentation and apoptosis by distinct mechanisms</article-title>. <source>EMBO Reports</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/embor.2010.50</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2892319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-2058738419866021"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Ginsenoside Rg1 regulates innate immune responses in macrophages through differentially modulating the NF-kappaB and PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathways</article-title>. <source>International Immunopharmacology</source>
<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25179784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2014.07.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-2058738419866021"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brachmann</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Specific apoptosis induction by the dual PI3K/mTor inhibitor NVP-BEZ235 in HER2 amplified and PIK3CA mutant breast cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>106</volume>(<issue>52</issue>): <fpage>22299</fpage>–<lpage>22304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0905152106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2799764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-2058738419866021"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saiki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasazawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imamichi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Caffeine induces apoptosis by enhancement of autophagy via PI3K/Akt/mTOR/p70S6K inhibition</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21081844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/auto.7.2.14074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3039768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-2058738419866021"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>MAPK and mTOR pathways are involved in cadmium-induced neuronal apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurochemistry</source>
<volume>105</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18021293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2007.05133.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-2058738419866021"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hydrogen peroxide inhibits mTOR signaling by activation of AMPKalpha leading to apoptosis of neuronal cells</article-title>. <source>Laboratory Investigation; A Journal of Technical Methods and Pathology</source>
<volume>90</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>773</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/labinvest.2010.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2861733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-2058738419866021"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingery</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cardiomyocyte NF-kappaB p65 promotes adverse remodelling, apoptosis, and endoplasmic reticulum stress in heart failure</article-title>. <source>Cardiovascular Research</source>
<volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20797985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cvr/cvq274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3002872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-2058738419866021"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhingra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Bidirectional regulation of nuclear factor- κB and mammalian target of rapamycin signaling functionally links Bnip3 gene repression and cell survival of ventricular myocytes</article-title>. <source>Circulation. Heart Failure</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCHEARTFAILURE.112.000061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>