
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">41</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcmi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">100968553</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Medical Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2342</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6554885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6554885.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6554885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6554885</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31170909</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12880-019-0344-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">344</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ultrasound versus temporal artery biopsy in patients with Giant cell arteritis: a prospective cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2944-8717</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names initials="Q">Quan</given-names></name><address><phone>+86 931 862 5200</phone><email>BrigitteFitzpatrickpqi@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="S">Sumei</given-names></name><address><email>sf7k63g@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinghu</given-names></name><address><email>ee9pt15@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412643.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Ultrasound, </institution><institution>the first hospital of Lanzhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>Lanzhou, 730000 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412643.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Cardiology, </institution><institution>the first hospital of Lanzhou University, </institution></institution-wrap>Lanzhou, 730000 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">326939</issue-id><elocation-id>47</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-03 04:25:22.227"><day>03</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12880_2019_Article_344.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="BMC Med Imaging" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7240922"><article-title>Retraction Note: Ultrasound versus temporal artery biopsy in patients with Giant cell arteritis: a prospective cohort study</article-title><volume>20</volume><date><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>54</elocation-id><source>BMC Medical Imaging</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12880-020-00454-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7240922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32438920</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Diagnosis of giant cell arteritis by temporal artery biopsy is time-consuming and visual loss lies in the first week after its diagnosis. The purpose of the study was to test the hypothesis that ultrasound can reduce the risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment in giant cell arteritis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Data regarding physical/ clinical features examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, ultrasound findings, and magnetic resonance imaging examinations of 980 suspected patients for giant cell arteritis were included in the study. Decision curve analysis was applied to get a beneficial score for selected diagnostic modalities. Cost analysis was performed for each patient.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Fewer numbers of false positive giant cell arteritis results were reported under physical/ clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection than physical/clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations (45 vs. 127, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The working area that detects giant cell arteritis at least one time for physical/ clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection and physical/ clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations were 0–91% and 0–86%. No significant difference for true negative results between magnetic resonance imaging and physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007). Physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection were less expensive method than physical/ clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations (14,023 ± 982 ¥/patient vs. 18,551 ± 1231 ¥/patient, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and MRI.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound are recommended for diagnosis of patients with suspected giant cell arteritis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Giant cell arteritis</kwd><kwd>Magnetic resonance imaging</kwd><kwd>Overdiagnosis</kwd><kwd>Overtreatment</kwd><kwd>Temporal artery biopsy</kwd><kwd>Ultrasound</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par9">Giant cell arteritis or temporal arteritis is vasculitis and has been found in more than 50 years age people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] leads to aortitis, stroke, blindness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], or myocardial infarction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Very large populations with giant cell arteritis are found in China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Glucocorticoid treatment after rapid diagnosis is generally recommended in giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The diagnosis of giant cell arteritis is not straightforward but it is made on temporal artery biopsy and the decision is supported by presenting symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] but its sensitivity is varied from 39 to 91%, because of drug intake e.g. glucocorticoid took by patients have effect on the results of temporal artery biopsy means, has large numbers of false negatives results can be found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], which lead to use of a high dose of glucocorticoid as precaution. Moreover, diagnosis by temporal artery biopsy is time-consuming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and visual loss lies in the first week after its diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In short, temporal artery biopsy is considered as ‘gold standard’ for giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] but there are poor associations between the results of temporal artery biopsy and giant cell arteritis especially multi-vessels giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Besides, temporal artery biopsy, ultrasound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] are non-invasive techniques used for diagnosis of giant cell arteritis but MRI has issues of availability and cost [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Additionally, no ionizing radiation involved in ultrasound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Ultrasound has high specificity (100%) but very low (43%) sensitivity was reported for the diagnosis of giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Moreover, glucocorticoid treatment can be started before a formal diagnosis, which leads to weight gain, hypertension, cataract, osteoporosis, and thin skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Overall, giant cell arteritis has problems of overdiagnosis and overtreatment.</p><p id="Par10">The primary aim of the study was to compare sensitivity, specificity, and cost of ultrasound with temporal artery biopsy considering MRI as a reference standard in patients with suspected giant cell arteritis. The secondary endpoint of the study was to test the hypothesis that ultrasound can reduce the risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment in giant cell arteritis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Reagents</title><p id="Par11">Formalin, glycerin, hematoxylin, and eosin were purchased from Mark Specialist Pvt. Ltd., Berlin, Germany. Gadolinium (Omniscan) was purchased from GE Healthcare, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p id="Par12">Patients with recent visual impairment, C-reactive protein level less than 5 mg/dL, jaw or tongue claudication, shoulder girdles (pain and stiffness in the shoulder), pain in the hip (pelvic girdles), abnormal liver functions, or temporal artery tenderness referred by rheumatologists, ophthalmologist, and neurologists (all have minimum 3-years’ experience) to the hospital were included in the study cohort.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par13">Patients with known giant cell arteritis were excluded from the study. Patients who had to receive glucocorticoid treatment (any glucocorticoid treatment less than 6-months prior to study) for the other reason(s) were excluded from enrollment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Physical and clinical features examinations</title><p id="Par14">The evidence of thickening, tenderness, and pulsation of both axillary arteries, scalp, and tongue necrosis were physically examined by neuro physicians (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, ultrasound examinations, and MRI examinations) of the institute. The evidence of posterior or anterior ischemic optic neuropathy, afferent pupillary defect, III/IV/V nerve palsy or bruits on either side were examined by ophthalmologists (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, ultrasound examinations, and MRI examinations) of the institute. The evidence of stroke and aneurysm were examined by a physician (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, ultrasound examinations, and MRI examinations) of the institutes. The sample of blood was collected from each patient and send to a laboratory for examinations of erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), C-reactive protein level, plasma viscosity, blood cell counts, and hemoglobin. All pathological examinations had been made by pathologists (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding physical features, temporal artery biopsy examinations, ultrasound examinations, and MRI examinations) of the institute [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. If age at least 50 years, temporal artery abnormalities, elevated ESR (≥ 50 mm/h), the new type of localized head pain, and claudication of jaw or tongue was reported in the patient then it was considered as giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Temporal artery biopsy examinations</title><p id="Par15">The one-centimeter temporal artery was collected from patients by surgical procedure and send to the laboratory of the institute. The sample was fixed in formalin, embedded in a paraffin block, and slides were stained with hematoxylin and eosin. The prepared slides were observed under a light microscope (Olympus, Beijing, China) in 100 magnifications (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Histopathological examinations had performed by pathologists (minimum 3-years’ experience, (blinded regarding physical features, clinical examinations, ultrasound examinations, and MRI examinations)) of the institute.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Histopathology of the temporal artery (arrow shows giant cell arteritis). Magnification view<italic toggle="yes">: 100; magnification bar: 25</italic> μm</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Ultrasound examinations</title><p id="Par16">Ultrasound examinations of longitudinal and transverse views of both (right and left) temporal arteries, both (right and left) axillary arteries including branches, both (right and left) parietal ramus, both (right and left) proximal frontal ramus, and both (right and left) distal frontal ramus had been taken by ultrasound equipment (Esaote SpA, Genoa, Italy) using an LA 424 linear probe at 13 MHz frequency (Esaote SpA, Genoa, Italy for B-Mode) and 10 MHz frequency (Esaote SpA, Genoa, Italy for color Doppler). The depth of ultrasound was 1.5 cm for temporal arteries, axillary arteries including branches, parietal ramus, and proximal frontal ramus. That for distal frontal ramus was 2.5 cm (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Ultrasound examinations had performed by ultra-sonographers (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding physical features, clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, and MRI examinations) of the institute.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Detailed process flowchart of ultrasound examinations</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>MRI examinations</title><p id="Par17">MRI examinations of longitudinal and transverse views of both (right and left) temporal arteries, both (right and left) axillary arteries including branches, both (right and left) parietal ramus, both (right and left) proximal frontal ramus, and both (right and left) distal frontal ramus had been taken by 3 T Magnetom Skyra MRI equipment (Siemens, Erlangen, Berlin, Germany) with a 20-channel head coil (Siemens, Erlangen, Berlin, Germany). Diffusion-weighted images (a single-shot, spin-echo, and echo-planar), fast saturated T1 W1 (spin-echo sequence), and angiography were recorded before and after administration of 16 mL of gadolinium. Arterial segments were evaluated in cross-sectional views. Axillary arteries including branches and occipital artery were evaluated for 3 cm or more in length (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. MR images had performed by radiologists (minimum 3-years’ experience, blinded regarding physical features, clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, and ultrasound examinations) of the institute.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Detailed process flowchart of magnetic resonance imaging examinations</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Image analysis</title><p id="Par18">Images were uploaded in RadiAnt DICOM Viewer, version 4.9.15 Beta (Mediant, Maciej Frankiewicz, Poznan, Poland).</p><p id="Par19">At least 1.5 mm swelling of the homogeneous wall was considered as vasculitis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). If artery lumen was 50% of the original in color Doppler for non-homogeneous walls, was considered as stenotic (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and if the ultrasound was unable to describe the color of non-homogeneous artery lumen then it was considered as occluded (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). A halo (an eccentric or circumferential hypoechoic ring) around the vessel wall (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), vasculitis, stenotic, or occluded either of temporal arteries, axillary arteries (including branches), parietal ramus, proximal frontal ramus, or distal frontal ramus was considered as giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Ultrasound images were analyzed by ultra-sonographers of the institute with a minimum of 3 years of experiences in ultrasound image analysis (blinded regarding physical features, clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, and MRI examinations).<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Ultrasound image of the temporal artery wall. <bold>a</bold>. Pictorial presentation of the temporal artery wall (normal and swelled). <bold>b</bold>. Color doppler longitudinal view of the swelled temporal artery wall (1.5 cm inflammation)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Pictorial presentation of stenotic (artery lumen was 50% of the original)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Pictorial presentation of the occluded artery (ultrasound was unable to describe the color of the artery lumen)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Ultrasound image of an eccentric or circumferential hypoechoic ring around the temporal artery wall <bold>a</bold>. B-Mode longitudinal view of the temporal artery wall with a halo. <bold>b</bold>. Pictorial presentation of the temporal artery wall with a halo. The arrow shows halo</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO7" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Mural enhancement and mural thickening were used as evaluation criteria for MR images analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). If at least one of ten different MR images either of temporal arteries, axillary arteries (including branches), parietal ramus, proximal frontal ramus, or distal frontal ramus had mural thickening of 0.6 mm or more and significant mural enhancement was considered as giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. MRI was analyzed by radiologists of the institute with a minimum of 3 years of experiences in MR image analysis (blinded regarding physical features, clinical examinations, temporal artery biopsy examinations, and ultrasound examinations).<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Diagnosis of giant cell arteritis by magnetic resonance image <bold>a</bold>. Pictorial presentation of mural thickening. <bold>b</bold>. Magnetic resonance image of a longitudinal view of the temporal artery. The arrow shows mural thickening</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO8" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Beneficial score analysis</title><p id="Par21">Decision curve analysis was applied to get a beneficial score for selected diagnostic modalities as per Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref> and <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Beneficialscore}=\frac{\mathrm{Truepositivegiantcellarteritisdetected}}{\mathrm{Numbersofpatientsenrolled}}-\left(\frac{\mathrm{Falsepositivegiantcellarteritisdetected}}{\mathrm{Numbersofpatientsenrolled}}\times \mathrm{Riskofoverdiagnosisandovertreatment}\right) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Article_Equ1.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Risk}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{overdiagnosis}\ \mathrm{and}\ \mathrm{overteratment}=\frac{\mathrm{Level}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{confidence}\ \mathrm{above}\ \mathrm{which}\ \mathrm{patients}\ \mathrm{were}\ \mathrm{put}\ \mathrm{on}\ \mathrm{glucocorticoid}\ \mathrm{a}\mathrm{s}\ \mathrm{a}\ \mathrm{precaution}\ }{1-\mathrm{Level}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{confidence}\ \mathrm{above}\ \mathrm{which}\ \mathrm{patients}\ \mathrm{were}\ \mathrm{put}\ \mathrm{on}\ \mathrm{glucocorticoid}\ \mathrm{a}\mathrm{s}\ \mathrm{a}\ \mathrm{precaution}\ } $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>Risk of overdiagnosis and overteratment</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Level of confidence above which patients were</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>put</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>on</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>glucocorticoid</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>as</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>precaution</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Level of confidence above which patients were</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>put</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>on</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>glucocorticoid</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>as</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>precaution</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Article_Equ2.gif"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Cost analysis</title><p id="Par22">Physician charges for physical and clinical features examinations, to perform biopsies following histopathology, ultrasound findings, and MRI examinations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] were collected from patients’ record of the institute(s) and pharmacy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">InStat, version Window, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA was used for statistical analysis. The interobserver agreement was derived by Cohen k test (value of k ≥ 0.80 considered as outstanding agreement and a value of 0.8 &gt; k ≥ 0.60 was considered as good agreement) according to Landis and Koch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Constant data were analyzed by the Chi-square test of Independence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Continuous variables were analyzed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) or Wilcoxon’s signed rank test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The results were considered significant at 99% of confidence level.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Characteristics of study participants</title><p id="Par24">During 15 March 2016 to 31 December 2018, a total of 1000 patients were referred to the First Hospital of Lanzhou University, China by rheumatologists, ophthalmologist, and neurologists as a suspected disease of giant cell arteritis. Among them, 5 patients had already diagnosed with giant cell arteritis and 15 patients had received glucocorticoid treatment. Therefore, they were excluded from the analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the analysis</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO9" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">Data of 980 patients were included in the study. Mean age of enrolled patients were 61.12 ± 6.56 years. 48% of patients were females and 52% of patients were males. The other demographic and clinical characteristics of enrolled patients are reported in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Patients had one or more symptoms at the time of enrollment. Therefore, consultants had diagnosed as suspected giant cell arteritis.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The demographic, social, and clinical characteristics of enrolled patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Characters</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Patients enrolled in the cohort</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimum</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximum</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean ± SD</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.12 ± 6.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gender</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">474(48)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">506(52)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fever</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">102(10)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Asthenia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Anorexia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19(2)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Recent visual impairment</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">211(22)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">C-reactive protein level &lt; 5 mg/dL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">245(25)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Jaw or tongue claudication</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">311(32)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Shoulder girdles</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">345(35)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pain in the hip</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">411(42)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Abnormal liver functions</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">245(25)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Temporal artery tenderness</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">311(32)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Weight loss, &gt; 2 kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">189(19)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (mm/h)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.47 ± 5.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ha Chinese</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">978(99.8)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tibetan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">01(0.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mongolian</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">01(0.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">History of smoking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-smokers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">325(33)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Previous smokers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">446(46)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current smokers</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">209(21)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Constant data are represented as a number (percentage) and continuous data are represented as mean ± SD</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Interobserver agreement</title><p id="Par26">A total of seven physicians, five ultra-sonographer, and six radiologists were involved in the interpretations of physical and clinical features, image analysis of ultrasound and MRI respectively. Interobserver agreement for the physical and clinical features interpretations was outstanding (k = 0.83), for image analysis of ultrasound examinations was good (k = 0.62), and for image analysis of MRI examinations was good (k = 0.67) respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Interobserver agreement</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Diagnostic modalities</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical and clinical features</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Temporal artery biopsy</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ultrasound</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Magnetic resonance imaging</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observers involved</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Specialty</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neuro physicians, ophthalmologists, physician, pathologists</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathologists</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ultra-sonographer</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Radiologist</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tools</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Questionaries’ and laboratory tests</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 cores</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-mode and color doppler</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DWI and T1WI</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Criteria for positive giant cell arteritis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">The new type of localized head pain, and claudication of jaw or tongue</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Visualization of giant cell in histopathology</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halo, vasculitis, stenotic, or occluded</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mural thickening ≥0.6 mm and significant mural enhancement</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">k-value</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.67</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>k ≥ 0.80: outstanding agreement, 0.8 &gt; k ≥ 0.60: good agreement</p><p>All observers had minimum 3-years of experience</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Diagnostic parameters</title><p id="Par27">More numbers of true positive giant cell arteritis cases (650 vs. 643) and true negative giant cell arteritis cases (100 vs. 50, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) were reported in case of physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection than physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations. Also, less numbers of false positive giant cell arteritis cases (45 vs. 127, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and false negative giant cell arteritis cases (15 vs. 35, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007) were reported in case of physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection than physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations. Sensitivity was in the order of MRI examinations &gt; physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations &gt; physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection but accuracy were in the order of MRI examinations &gt; physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection &gt; physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations. There was no significant difference for true negative results between MRI and physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection (140 vs. 100, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007, Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Diagnostic parameters of adopted modalities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Parameters of giant cell arteritis</th><th colspan="11" rowspan="1">Diagnostic modalities examinations</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">MRI</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">PC</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">TAB</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">PC + TAB</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Us</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">PC + Us</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients enrolled</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">980</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">True positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">840(86)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">350(36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">400(41)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">643(65)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">385(39)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">650(66)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">True negative</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">140(14)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40(4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50(5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50(5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45(5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100(10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">False positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">290(30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">270(28)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">127(13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46(5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45(5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">False negative</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100(10)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">85(9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35(4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15(2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inconclusive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">200(20)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">175(18)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">125(13)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">489(50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">170(17)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sensitivity</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">MRI</italic> Magnetic resonance imaging</p><p><italic toggle="yes">PC</italic> Physical and clinical features examinations</p><p><italic toggle="yes">TAB</italic> Temporal artery biopsy examinations results</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Us</italic> Ultrasound examinations results</p><p>Continuous variables are represented as mean and constant variables are represented as number (percentage)</p><p>Constant data were analyzed by the Chi-square test of Independence</p><p>The results were considered significant if <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01</p><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value comparison with respect to MRI examinations</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>The risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment</title><p id="Par28">The working area that detects giant cell arteritis at least one time for physical/ clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection and physical/ clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations were 0–91% (high- and medium-risk giant cell arteritis patients) and 0–86% (high-risk giant cell arteritis patients) respectively. Above 91% (for low-risk giant cell arteritis patients) for ultrasound detection and above 86% (for low-and medium-risk giant cell arteritis patients) for temporal artery biopsy had the risk of overdiagnosis and overtreatment respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>).<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Decision curve analysis. a: an area that detects high-risk giant cell arteritis at least one time, b: an area that detects medium-risk giant cell arteritis at least one time, c: an area that detects low-risk giant cell arteritis at least one time. Ultrasound images were analyzed by ultra-sonographers, magnetic resonance images were analyzed by radiologists, the physical and clinical features interpretations were performed by physicians, and the biopsies results were interpreted by pathologists (all evaluators had minimum 3 years of experiences)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO10" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig10_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Cost</title><p id="Par29">Physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection were less expensive method than physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations (14,023 ± 982 ¥/patient vs. 18,551 ± 1231 ¥/patient, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>).<fig id="Fig11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Cost Analysis of adopted diagnostic methods. Patients enrolled were 980 for all analyses. Data are presented as mean ± SD of all. Variables were analyzed by one-way ANOVA. The results were considered significant if <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.<sup>*</sup>less expensive method than physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations and also magnetic resonance imaging method</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO11" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12880_2019_344_Fig11_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par30">The prospective cohort study concluded that physical/ clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection had high accuracy (0.77 respect to MRI) and no risk of the overdiagnosis and overtreatment in the detection of high- and medium-risk giant cell arteritis in the enrolled patients. High accuracy is required in case of suspected giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] because corticosteroid treatment is the only effective treatment currently available for giant cell arteritis and corticosteroid therapy has bruising, cataracts and proximal weakness as treatment-emergent adverse effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The results of the study were in line with available studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, TABUL study enrolled only 381 patients and have used clinical features and physical examinations as ‘gold standard’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], case series study has enrolled only 46 patients and 6-month evaluation of the patients have used as ‘gold standard’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and case-control study also enrolled only 176 patients but without ‘gold standard’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. These available studies are full-filled the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) 1990 criteria for the diagnosis of giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] but do not highlight the overdiagnosis and overtreatment in giant cell arteritis. With respect to the results of the study, low-and medium-risk giant cell arteritis patients can have a risk of side effects due to systemic corticosteroid if they are diagnosed as giant cell arteritis by temporal artery biopsy examinations.</p><p id="Par31">The study reported that ultrasound detection is non-invasive and cost-effective method than temporal artery biopsy examinations. The results of the study were parallel with those of TABUL study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], a retrospective study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], a consecutive case series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], and a case report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Giant cell arteritis has issues of personal, social care, and socioeconomic costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. A biopsy would result in discomfort, bruising, bleeding, or infection at the site of the area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. To overcome the cost factor fast track pathway was introduced in 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Factor fast track pathway reduce the risk of permanent visual impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] but fast track pathway requires high awareness of general practitioners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], which is difficult to achieve in developing countries. Additionally, in China, the cost of fast track pathway is around 16,000 ¥ (greater than ultrasound examinations) to diagnose giant cell arteritis. Also, fast track pathway is also relaid on ultrasound detection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] but in fast track pathway ultrasound examination is carried out by rheumatologist not by specialized ultra-sonographer(s) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In respect to socioeconomic factors of suspected giant cell arteritis patients, conventional ultrasound detection is a suitable diagnostic modality for the detection of giant cell arteritis in Chinese patients.</p><p id="Par32">Large numbers of false negative giant cell arteritis patients were reported by temporal artery biopsy examinations than ultrasound examinations (85 vs. 15, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The results of the study were parallel with those of TABUL study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and prospective multicenter trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The possible justification for the same was that there would be a patchy inflammation in the artery wall, samples of biopsy were taken from the area where no inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], or incidence of the giant cell arteritis in the patients has seasonal variation (an environmental etiology) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. All in all, the diagnosis of giant cell arteritis is clinicians’ challenge.</p><p id="Par33">The study reported that physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection had minimal sensitivity. The results of the study were in line with TABUL study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] but not in line with a consecutive case series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The possible reason for that was ultra-sonographers had difficulties in capturing abnormalities in ultrasound images. Therefore, training is required for ultra-sonographers before scanning the patients. Also, technical standardization of ultrasound equipment, image acquisition, and probe settings are required. Additionally, MRI would be preferred diagnostic modality in patients, whose diagnosis remains disorganized even after ultrasound examination.</p><p id="Par34">With reference to MRI, physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection had fewer sensitivity and accuracy (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 for both) but no significant difference for true negative results (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007) and cost of diagnosis was also low (14,023 ± 982 ¥/per patient vs. 24,221 ± 1545 ¥/per patients, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). MRI has issues of availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Additionally, in physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound do not involve ionizing radiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. MRI has a low field of view and the contrast enhancement of walls of arteries would also be due to atherosclerotic plaques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, ultrasound can successful in discrimination of giant cell arteritis and atherosclerotic plaques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Moreover, for the circle of Willis, the thin-walled intradural arteries do not show any mural enhancement and/or mural thickening under MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The MRI protocol is not specifically adjusted to depict mural inflammation of the superficial cranial arteries and to visualize the intradural arteries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. MRI has no ability to discriminate polyarteritis nodosa, systemic antineutrophilic cytoplasmatic antibody–positive vasculitis, and another inflammatory disease from giant cell arteritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, Ultrasound has advantages of safety, availability, tolerability, and its high resolution of 0.1 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Ultrasound of temporal and extracranial arteries also correlates well with MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Therefore, physical characters and clinical examinations following ultrasound finding is a suitable modality for the diagnosis of giant cell arteritis.</p><p id="Par35">Although the study was the large sample prospective study, there are several limitations of the study have reported, for examples, lack of follow-up data regarding treatment. More numbers of inconclusive results were reported for physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection than physical and clinical features examinations following temporal artery biopsy examinations (170 vs. 125, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005). There are no predefined limits of ultrasound available for the diagnosis of giant cell arteritis in PR China by the ministry of the health department. Lower systemic inflammatory response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], gender [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], and the history of smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] have effects on prevalence of giant cell arteritis but the study did not evaluate such independent parameters in the analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par36">Temporal artery biopsy is a useful technique for the detection of giant cell arteritis but it was a costly and expensive method. Also, it had the chances of overdiagnosis and overtreatment for low-and medium-risk giant cell arteritis. Physical and clinical features examinations following ultrasound detection are non-invasive, economical diagnostic modality, had high specificity, and no chances of overdiagnosis and overtreatment for high and medium-risk giant cell arteritis. The study recommended an ultrasound technique for diagnosis of patients with suspected giant cell arteritis.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p id="Par5">Analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESR</term><def><p id="Par6">Erythrocyte sedimentation rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par7">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STROBE</term><def><p id="Par8">The strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>Authors are thankful to all medical and non-medical staff of the first hospital of Lanzhou University, Lanzhou, China.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>All authors have reviewed and approved the submitted manuscript for publication. SM was the project administrator and contributed to the data curation, design, and literature review of the study. XZ contributed to the conceptualization, software, literature review, and design of the study. QZ contributed to the formal analysis and literature review of the study, draft, review, and edited the manuscript for intellectual content. The author agrees to be accountable for all aspects of work ensuring integrity and accuracy.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>None.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and analyzed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par37">The protocol (FLU/CL/6/2017 dated 3 March 2016) of the study had been approved by the first hospital of Lanzhou University review board. The study had adhered to the law of China, the strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement, and the 2008 Helsinki Declaration. All enrolled patients had been signed an informed consent form regarding examinations, biopsies, pathology, and to have an additional procedure for research purpose only.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par38">All enrolled patients had been signed an informed consent form regarding publication of the study in all formats hard and electronics including personal data and images irrespective of time and language.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par39">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luqmani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradburn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrester-Barker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wailoo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of ultrasound compared to biopsy of temporal arteries in the diagnosis and treatment of giant cell arteritis (TABUL): a diagnostic accuracy and cost-effectiveness study</article-title><source>Health Technol Assess</source><year>2016</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3310/hta20900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5165283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27925577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Giant cell arteritis: a review</article-title><source>Eye Brain</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28539785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/EB.S21825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5432116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ing</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahaie Luna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakpor</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyndel</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnoux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ten Hove</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multivariable prediction model for suspected giant cell arteritis: development and validation</article-title><source>Clin Ophthalmol</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2031</fpage><lpage>2042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OPTH.S151385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29200816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5703153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Sha</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Wenjie</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Xinping</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Xiaofeng</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Retrospective Study of Chinese Patients With Giant Cell Arteritis (GCA)</article-title><source>Medicine</source><year>2016</year><volume>95</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>e3213</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000003213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4998547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barraclough</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fulcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollywood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samanta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BSR and BHPR standards, guidelines and audit working group. BSR and BHPR guidelines for the management of giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>1597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/keq039a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20371504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nesher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The diagnosis and classification of giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>J Autoimmun</source><year>2014</year><volume>48–49</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaut.2014.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24461386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugeberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myklebust</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fast-track ultrasound clinic for early diagnosis of giant cell arteritis significantly reduces permanent visual impairment: towards a more effective strategy to improve clinical outcome in giant cell arteritis?</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/kev289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26286743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danesh-Meyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savino</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poor prognosis of visual outcome after visual loss from giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2005</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2005.01.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15885780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plant</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic and treatment challenges in giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2014</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>2210</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61081-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24976326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunstan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rischmueller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts-Thomson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of biopsy-proven giant cell arteritis in South Australia</article-title><source>Intern Med J</source><year>2014</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imj.12293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24118799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diamantopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugeberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hetland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soldal</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myklebust</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic value of color Doppler ultrasonography of temporal arteries and large vessels in giant cell arteritis: a consecutive case series</article-title><source>Arthritis Care Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.22178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24106211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siemonsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brekenfeld</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufmann-Buehler</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiehler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3T MRI reveals extra- and intracranial involvement in giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3174/ajnr.A4086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25169925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7965928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gromnica-Ihle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natusch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound of proximal upper extremity arteries to increase the diagnostic yield in large-vessel giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/kem322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arida A, Kyprianou M, Kanakis M, Sfikakis PP. The diagnostic value of ultrasonography-derived edema of the temporal artery wall in giant cell arteritis: a second meta-analysis. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2010;11. 10.1186/1471-2474-11-44.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2474-11-44</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2837862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20210989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarpellini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Color duplex ultrasonography findings of temporal arteries in a case of giant cell arteritis: role in diagnosis and follow-up</article-title><source>Open Access Rheumatol</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OARRR.S110585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28352206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5359129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klink</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Both</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ness</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinzelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holl-Ulrich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duwendag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Giant cell arteritis: diagnostic accuracy of MR imaging of superficial cranial arteries in initial diagnosis-results from a multicenter trial</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2014</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.14140056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25102371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saville</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision curve analysis</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seeliger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sznajd</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Craven</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grayson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suppiah</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merkel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luqmani</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are the 1990 American College of Rheumatology vasculitis classification criteria still valid?</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/kex075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28379475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6251621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauenstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warnatz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hetzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of duplex sonography and high-resolution magnetic resonance imaging in the diagnosis of giant cell (temporal) arteritis</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2008</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2574</fpage><lpage>2578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.23699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achilleos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejaco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes and cost-effectiveness analysis of fast track pathway in giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>i5</fpage><lpage>i6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/keu191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26016758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achilleos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsideeg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejaco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast track pathway reduces sight loss in giant cell arteritis: results of a longitudinal observational cohort study</article-title><source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>S</fpage><lpage>103–6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26016758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Laskou F, Coath Fiona C, Aung T, Benerjee S, Dasgupta B. Fast track giant cell arteritis clinic and pathway for early management of suspected giant cell arteritis: an audit. Rheumatology. 2018;57. 10.1093/rheumatology/key075.298.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound in the diagnosis and management of giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2018</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>ii22</fpage><lpage>ii31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/kex461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29982780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Rahman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molteno</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevin</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of giant cell arteritis in Otago, New Zealand: a 9-year analysis</article-title><source>N Z Med J</source><year>2011</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21475359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bas-Lando</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mates</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnenblick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nesher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of giant cell arteritis in Jerusalem over a 25-year period: annual and seasonal fluctuations</article-title><source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>S15</fpage><lpage>S17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17428357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>RHP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lennox</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varcoe</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular treatment of critical lower limb ischemia caused by giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvscit.2018.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30627690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6322075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieben</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grist</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution MRI for assessment of middle meningeal artery involvement in giant cell arteritis</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2008.101816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19605745</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>