
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Manag Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Manag Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1404</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cancmanres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101512700</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMAR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Management and Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6986931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6986931.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6986931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6986931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32158261</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S238373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">238373</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long Noncoding RNA <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Enhances the Malignancy of Cervical Cancer by Functioning as a Molecular Sponge of microRNA-511-3p and Consequently Increasing FGFR2 Expression</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Dai et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Dai et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names initials="R">Rujia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="P">Peihai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0002"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="P">Peishu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University</institution>, <addr-line>Jinan</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shandong</addr-line>
<addr-line>250012</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>School of Life Sciences, Liaocheng University</institution>, <addr-line>Liaocheng</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shandong</addr-line>
<addr-line>252004</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University (Qingdao)</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shandong</addr-line>
<addr-line>266035</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Jun Dai <institution>Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University</institution>, <addr-line>107 Wenhua West Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Jinan</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shandong</addr-line><addr-line>250012</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email daijun_qilu@163.com</corresp><corresp id="AN0002">Peihai Zhang <institution>Department of Gynaecology and Obstetrics, Qilu Hospital of Shandong University (Qingdao)</institution>, <addr-line>758 Hefei Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <addr-line>Shandong</addr-line><addr-line>266035</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email doctorzhang_ph@163.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">349616</issue-id><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>03</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 13:25:10.283"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 Dai et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Dai et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cmar-12-567.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Cancer Manag Res" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7132260"><article-title>Long Noncoding RNA <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Enhances the Malignancy of Cervical Cancer by Functioning as a Molecular Sponge of microRNA-511-3p and Consequently Increasing FGFR2 Expression [Retraction]</article-title><volume>12</volume><date><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><fpage>2367</fpage><lpage>2367</lpage><source>Cancer Management and Research</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S255464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7132260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32308476</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="S2001"><title>Purpose</title><p>A long noncoding RNA called ZFPM2 antisense RNA 1 (<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>) has been verified as a key modulator in multiple human cancer types. Nonetheless, the expression and functions of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer remain poorly understood. Therefore, our purpose was to characterize the expression pattern, clinical value, and detailed roles of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer.</p></sec><sec id="S2002"><title>Methods</title><p>Reverse-transcription quantitative PCR was carried out to measure <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression in cervical cancer. A Cell Counting Kit-8 assay, flow cytometry, Transwell migration and invasion assays, and a tumor xenograft experiment were conducted to determine the influence of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> on cervical cancer cell proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion in vitro and on tumor growth in vivo, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S2003"><title>Results</title><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> was found to be aberrantly upregulated in cervical cancer, and its upregulation was associated with unfavorable values of clinical parameters. A <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown significantly reduced cervical cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion and increased apoptosis in vitro. The <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown decelerated tumor growth of cervical cancer cells in vivo. Molecular investigation indicated that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> acts as a molecular sponge of microRNA-511-3p (miR-511-3p) in cervical cancer cells. Fibroblast growth factor receptor 2 (<italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic>) mRNA was validated as a direct target of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer, and its expression was positively modulated by <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. The effects of the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown on malignant characteristics of cervical cancer cells were greatly attenuated by miR-511-3p inhibition.</p></sec><sec id="S2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> promotes cervical cancer progression through upregulation of miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis output, thereby pointing to possible diagnostics and therapeutics based on the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–miR-511-3p–FGFR2 pathway.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>ZFPM2 antisense RNA 1</kwd><kwd>cervical cancer therapy</kwd><kwd>fibroblast growth factor receptor 2</kwd><kwd>microRNA-511-3p</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><ref-count count="53"/><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cervical cancer ranks the second most frequent cancer among women and the fourth leading cause of gynecological-cancer–related deaths worldwide.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> A total of 569,847 new cervical cancer cases were diagnosed and 311,365 patients died of cervical cancer per year, as estimated by Global Cancer Statistics 2018.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> At present, the major therapeutic approaches to cervical cancer include surgical treatments, radiotherapy, cytotoxic chemotherapy, and adjuvant therapy.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> In addition, natural anti-cancerous drug is also widely used in therapeutic strategies against cervical cancer.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> In spite of tremendous developments in the diagnostic techniques and therapeutic approaches to cervical cancer, long-term prognosis of the patients, especially cases diagnosed at an advanced stage, remains unsatisfactory.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> It is generally believed that human papillomavirus infection is a major but not the only factor causing cervical cancer initiation and progression.<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Accordingly, full characterization of the molecular events of cervical cancer, especially of the pathogenesis, is important for the identification of novel and promising therapeutic techniques.</p><p>Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) are transcripts with length of over 200 nucleotides.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> LncRNAs have no protein-coding capacity but can regulate gene expression at transcriptional, post-transcriptional, and chromosomal levels.<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Recently, lncRNAs received much attention because of their crucial regulatory functions in various biological processes.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Moreover, a growing body of evidence suggests that lncRNAs may play complicated and crucial roles during tumorigenesis and tumor progression.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Many lncRNAs have turned out to be abnormally expressed in cervical cancer. For instance, <italic toggle="yes">TUG1</italic>,<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">PVT1</italic>,<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and <italic toggle="yes">CRNDE</italic><xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> are highly expressed in cervical cancer; on the contrary, <italic toggle="yes">HAND2-AS1</italic>,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">PTCSC3</italic>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and <italic toggle="yes">ZNF667-AS1</italic><xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> are underexpressed in this cancer. Functionally, the aberrantly expressed lncRNAs exert cancer-inhibiting or cancer-promoting actions and thereby serve as critical modulators of cervical carcinogenesis by affecting a number of malignant characteristics.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Therefore, an in-depth understanding of the functions of lncRNAs in cervical cancer is crucial for improving the disease diagnosis, prognosis, and treatments.</p><p>An lncRNA called <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> has been verified as a key modulator in gastric cancer,<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> lung adenocarcinoma,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and renal cell cancer.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Nevertheless, the expression and functions of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer remain poorly understood. Therefore, our purpose was to characterize the expression pattern, clinical value, and detailed roles of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer. Moreover, the molecular mechanisms behind <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–mediated promotion of the aggressive phenotype of cervical cancer cells were explored in detail in vitro and in vivo.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title>Collection of Clinical Samples</title><p>This study was carried out with the approval of Ethics Committees of Qilu Hospital of Shandong University and in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participating patients provided written informed consent. Cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissue samples were collected from 47 patients in Qilu Hospital of Shandong University (Shandong, China). None of the patients had received chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or other antitumor therapies before the surgical operation. The obtained tissue specimens were quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored in liquid nitrogen until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title>Cell Lines</title><p>Four cervical cancer cell lines, HeLa, SiHa, C-33A, and CaSki, were purchased from the Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China), and a normal human cervix epithelial cell line (Ect1/E6E7) from the American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA). All the aforementioned cell lines were maintained in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM; Gibco; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) containing 10% of fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.), 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 μg/mL streptomycin (Gibco; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) at 37 °C in a humidified atmosphere supplied with 5% of CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title>Transient Transfection</title><p>The small interfering RNA (siRNA) specific to <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> (si-ZFPM2-AS1) and negative control siRNA (si-NC) were synthesized by RiboBio (Guangzhou, China). An miR-511-3p mimic, microRNA (miRNA) mimic negative control (miR-NC), an miR-511-3p inhibitor, and its NC were purchased from GeneCopoeia (Guangzhou, China). A plasmid encoding FGFR2 (called pcDNA3.1-FGFR2) and the empty pcDNA3.1 vector were designed and constructed by GenePharma Technology (Shanghai, China). Cells were seeded in 24-well plates and incubated at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24 h. The cells were transfected with the above siRNA, miRNA mimic, miRNA inhibitor, or plasmid by means of Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2004"><title>Isolation of Cytoplasmic and Nuclear RNA</title><p>As described previously,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> the isolation of the cytoplasmic and nuclear fractions of cervical cancer cells was performed with the PARIS Kit (Invitrogen; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2005"><title>Reverse-Transcription Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction (RT-qPCR)</title><p>RT-qPCR was performed as described previously.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> TRIzol (Invitrogen; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) was employed for total-RNA extraction. The concentration and purity of total RNA were evaluated on a NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.). For the quantification of miR-511-3p expression, complementary DNA (cDNA) was synthesized using the miScript Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany). The qPCR was then conducted with the miScript SYBR Green PCR Kit (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany). For the analysis of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA expression, total RNA was reversely transcribed into cDNA by means of the PrimeScript RT-Reagent Kit (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). The cDNA was then subjected to PCR amplification with the SYBR Premix Ex Taq™ Kit (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). U6 small nuclear RNA served as the internal control for miR-511-3p, whereas <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> for other RNAs. Relative gene expression was analyzed with the comparative quantification cycle (2<sup>−ΔΔCq</sup>) method.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2006"><title>Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) Assay</title><p>CCK-8 assay was applied to determine cellular proliferative ability as described previously.<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> At 24 h post-transfection, preparation of cell suspension was performed, and cell concentration was adjusted to 2 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells/mL. In total, 100 μL of the cell suspension was inoculated into wells of 96-well plates. To test cellular proliferation, 10 μL of the CCK-8 reagent (Dojindo Molecular Technologies, Inc.) was added into each well, after which the plates were incubated at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for another 2 h. The absorbance at 450 nm wavelength was measured on a microplate reader (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Benicia, CA, USA). The CCK-8 assay was carried out at 0, 24, 48, and 72 h after cell seeding.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2007"><title>Flow-Cytometric Analysis of Apoptosis</title><p>The apoptosis of transfected cells was evaluated by menas of flow-cytometric analysis.<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> After cultivation for 48 h, transfected cells were harvested using trypsin without EDTA and rinsed with precooled phosphate-buffered saline, followed by quantification of apoptotic cells using the Annexin V–Fluorescein Isothiocyanate (FITC) Apoptosis Detection Kit (BioLegend, San Diego, CA, USA). Namely, the transfected cells were resuspended in 100 μL of Annexin-V-binding buffer prior to double staining with 5 µL of Annexin V–FITC and 5 µL of the propidium iodide solution. After 15 min incubation at room temperature in darkness, a flow cytometer (FACScan; BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) was utilized to quantify the apoptotic cells.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2008"><title>Transwell Migration and Invasion Assays</title><p>The migratory capacity was assessed in 24-well Transwell<sup>®</sup> chambers (pore size: 8 µm; BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) as described by previous studies.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> A total of 5 × 10<sup>4</sup> transfected cells were resuspended in 100 μL of FBS-free DMEM and were seeded in the upper compartments. The complete medium (containing 20% of FBS) was added into the basolateral chambers. After 24 h incubation, nonmigratory cells (those remaining on the upper side of the membranes) were gently wiped off with a cotton-tipped swab, while the migratory cells were fixed in a methanol solution and stained with 0.1% crystal violet. The counting of migratory cells was conducted under an inverted optical microscope (x200 magnification; Olympus Corporation) in five randomly selected fields of view for each chamber. Similar experimental steps were performed for testing the invasive ability, except that the chambers were precoated with Matrigel (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2009"><title>Tumor Xenograft Model</title><p>As described previously,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> tumor xenograft model was utilized to test the influence of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown on tumor growth in vivo. The plasmids encoding a short hairpin RNA (shRNA) specifically targeting <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> (pLKO.1- sh-ZFPM2-AS1) or negative control shRNA (pLKO.1-sh-NC) were designed and manufactured by GenePharma Technology. HeLa cells were transfected with a lentivirus carrying either pLKO.1-sh-ZFPM2-AS1 or pLKO.1-sh-NC and were selected with 2 μg/mL puromycin, resulting in a stable <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown cell line.</p><p>Female BALB/c nude mice (4–6 weeks of age) were acquired from Shanghai SLAC Laboratory Animal Co., Ltd. (Shanghai Laboratory Animal Center of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai, China). HeLa cells stably transfected with either sh-ZFPM2-AS1 or sh-NC were inoculated subcutaneously into a flank of the mice. The size of subcutaneous tumors was determined every 4 days by measurement of their length and width. The volume of tumors was calculated via the following formula: Volume (mm<sup>3</sup>) = width<sup>2</sup> (mm<sup>2</sup>) × length (mm)/2. On Day 28 post-injection, all the mice were euthanized with the method of cervical dislocation. The tumor xenografts were resected for weighing and further experiments. The animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Experimental Animal Review Board of Qilu Hospital of Shandong University, and performed in compliance with the Animal Protection Law of the People’s Republic of China-2009 for experimental animals.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2010"><title>RNA Immunoprecipitation (RIP) Assay</title><p>The binding between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells was examined by the RIP assay based on the Magna RIP RNA-Binding Protein Immunoprecipitation Kit (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA), as described by previous study.<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> Cells were collected and probed in RIPA cell lysis buffer. Following 20 min incubation on ice, each cell lysate was incubated overnight at 4 °C with magnetic beads conjugated with an anti-Argonaute 2 (AGO2) antibody or IgG control (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). The beads were treated with 150 μL proteinase K for digestion of the protein. Finally, RT-qPCR was performed to analyze the purified RNA.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2011"><title>Bioinformatic Prediction</title><p>The miRNA(s) that may interact with <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> was predicted in starBase 3.0 software (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://starbase.sysu.edu.cn/">http://starbase.sysu.edu.cn/</ext-link></underline>).<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Two online miRNA target prediction databases, miRDB<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mirdb.org/">http://mirdb.org/</ext-link></underline>) and TargetScan<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> (<underline><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</ext-link></underline>), were employed for miR-511-3p target prediction.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2012"><title>Luciferase Reporter Assay</title><p>Luciferase reporter assay was conducted to assess the binding between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells.<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> 3′ untranslated region (UTR) fragments containing either the predicted wild-type (WT) miR-511-3p–binding site or a mutant (MUT) binding site were amplified by GenePharma Technology. The amplified fragments were cloned into the pmirGLO luciferase reporter vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) to respectively create luciferase reporter plasmids WT-FGFR2 and MUT-FGFR2. For testing the interaction between miR-511-3p and <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>, the luciferase reporter plasmids WT-ZFPM2-AS1 and MUT-ZFPM2-AS1 were constructed in a similar way. Cotransfection of cervical cancer cells was performed with the combination of either a WT or MUT reporter plasmid and either the miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC. After 48 h, we harvested the transfected cells and detected the luciferase activities via a Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). <italic toggle="yes">Renilla</italic> luciferase activity was utilized as an internal control for normalization.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2013"><title>Western Blotting</title><p>Western blotting was conducted to detect the protein expression.<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Cultured cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline and lysed with radioimmunoprecipitation assay lysis buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) for total-protein isolation. Equal amounts of protein were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate 10% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes, followed by blocking at room temperature for 2 h with 5% nonfat milk diluted in Tris-buffered saline (TBS) supplemented with 0.1% of Tween 20. After overnight incubation at 4 °C with primary antibodies, the membranes were probed with a horseradish peroxidase–conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG antibody (1:5000 dilution; cat. No. ab205719; Abcam) (secondary antibody). The ECL™ Western Blotting Detection Reagent (GE Healthcare) was employed for immunoblot visualization. The following primary antibodies were used in this study: anti-FGFR2 (1:1000 dilution; cat. No. ab58201; Abcam) and anti-GAPDH (1:1000 dilution; cat. No. ab9482; Abcam). GAPDH served as an endogenous control for the quantification of FGFR2 protein expression.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2014"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All results are expressed as the mean ± standard deviation from three independent experiments. The relation between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and clinical parameters of the patients with cervical cancer was tested via the chi-squared test. The Kaplan–Meier method was utilized for survival analysis, and differences between survival curves were assessed by the logrank test. Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was conducted to evaluate differences between two groups. The comparison among multiple groups was made by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) plus the Bonferroni–Dunn test. All statistical analyses were conducted in the SPSS software, version 21.0 (Chicago, IL, USA), and P &lt; 0.05 was assumed to indicate a statistically significant difference.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="S0003-S2001"><title><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Is Upregulated in Cervical Cancer and Is Related to Shorter Survival of Patients with Cervical Cancer</title><p>Cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissue samples were collected from 45 patients and used for the determination of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression by RT-qPCR. The results indicated that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression was higher in the cervical cancer tissue samples than in tumor adjacent tissues (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). The expression status of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in the normal human cervix epithelial cell line (Ect1/E6E7) and four cervical cancer cell lines (HeLa, SiHa, C-33A, and CaSki) was analyzed via RT-qPCR. <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> turned out to be upregulated in all four tested cervical cancer cell lines relative to Ect1/E6E7 cells (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>, P &lt; 0.05).<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is highly expressed in cervical cancer, and this overexpression correlates with a poor prognosis of patients with cervical cancer. (<bold>A</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis was carried out to measure <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression in 45 pairs of cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissues. *P &lt; 0.05 vs tumor adjacent tissue samples. (<bold>B</bold>) The expression of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in the four cervical cancer cell lines (HeLa, SiHa, C-33A, and CaSki) was determined in an RT-qPCR assay. A normal human cervix epithelial cell line (Ect1/E6E7) served as the control. *P &lt; 0.05 vs Ect1/E6E7 cells. (<bold>C</bold>) All 45 participating patients were subdivided into two groups: the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> low-expression group and <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> high-expression group. The overall survival of the two groups was analyzed with the Kaplan–Meier method and compared by the logrank test. P = 0.024.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p><p>We subsequently subdivided all the patients with cervical cancer into either <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> low-expression group or <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> high-expression group, according to the median value of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> among the cervical cancer tissue samples. Analysis the correlation between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression and clinical parameters revealed that increased <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression obviously correlated with tumor size (P = 0.041), FIGO stage (P = 0.020), and lymph node metastasis (P = 0.017) among these 45 patients with cervical cancer (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Furthermore, patients with cervical cancer in the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> high-expression group showed shorter overall survival than did the patients in the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> low-expression group (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>, P = 0.024). Taken together, these results implied that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is overexpressed in cervical cancer and is closely associated with poor clinical outcomes of patients with cervical cancer, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> might be implicated in the malignancy of this disease.<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The relation between ZFPM2-AS1 expression and clinicopathological characteristics in patients with cervical cancer.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">ZFPM2-AS1 expression</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">High (n=24)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low (n=23)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (years)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tumor size (cm)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Histological grade</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderately and Poorly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FIGO stage</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I-II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III-IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lymph node metastasis</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002"><title>Knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Restricts Cervical Cancer Cell Proliferation, Migration, and Invasion and Induces Apoptosis</title><p>Given that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> was more highly expressed in HeLa and SiHa cell lines among the four tested cervical cancer cell lines, the two cell lines were chosen as cell models for further experiments. To evaluate the significance of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer, its expression was silenced in HeLa and SiHa cells using the siRNA specific to <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> (si-ZFPM2-AS1). Obvious downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in HeLa and SiHa cells was verified via RT-qPCR analysis (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). The CCK-8 assay showed that the knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> remarkably suppressed the proliferative ability of HeLa and SiHa cells (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). In addition, the knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> strongly promoted the apoptosis of HeLa and SiHa cells, as evidenced by flow-cytometric analysis (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref> and <xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">D</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). We next conducted Transwell migration and invasion assays to test whether <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is involved in the mobility of cervical cancer cells. According to the results, the knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> significantly reduced the migratory (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2E</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and invasive abilities (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2F</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) of HeLa and SiHa cells. Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> may play a cancer-promoting part in the malignant phenotype of cervical cancer cells.<fig id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown inhibits HeLa and SiHa cell proliferation, migration, and invasion but promotes apoptosis. (<bold>A</bold>) HeLa and SiHa cells were transfected with either si-ZFPM2-AS1 or si-NC. The efficiency of si-ZFPM2-AS1 transfection was evaluated by RT-qPCR. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the si-NC group. (<bold>B</bold>) The CCK-8 assay was applied to determine the proliferative ability of HeLa and SiHa cells after either si-ZFPM2-AS1 or si-NC transfection. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the si-NC group. (<bold>C, D</bold>) The apoptosis of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–deficient HeLa and SiHa cells was determined by flow cytometry. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group si-NC. (<bold>E, F</bold>) The influence of the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown on the migratory and invasive abilities of HeLa and SiHa cells was assessed by Transwell migration and invasion assays (x200 magnification). *P &lt; 0.05 vs the si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0002.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2003"><title><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Directly Targets miR-511-3p in Cervical Cancer Cells</title><p>LncRNA can directly interact with miRNAs to modulate the expression of miRNAs’ targets during carcinogenesis and cancer progression.<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> We first evaluated the expression distribution of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in HeLa and SiHa cells. As indicated in <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> was observed both in the cell nucleus and cytoplasm but was mostly located in the cytoplasm of HeLa and SiHa cells, suggesting that activities of specific miRNAs may be regulated by <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. Some studies have revealed that the roles of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> are dependent on miR-137 in renal cell cancer<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and on miR-18b-5p in lung adenocarcinoma;<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> accordingly, we next determined whether <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> may directly target specific miRNA in cervical cancer. First, bioinformatic prediction was performed to search for the potential miRNA-binding sites in <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. The analysis suggested that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> harbors a potential binding site for miR-511-3p (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). Next, after confirming the efficiency of miR-511-3p mimic transfection (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>, P &lt; 0.05), we conducted the luciferase reporter assay in HeLa and SiHa cells that were cotransfected with either plasmid WT-ZFPM2-AS1 or MUT-ZFPM2-AS1 and either the miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC. Transfection with the miR-511-3p mimic notably reduced the luciferase activity of the plasmid containing the WT miR-511-3p–binding site in HeLa and SiHa cells (P &lt; 0.05), whereas there was no significant alteration in the MUT-ZFPM2-AS1–transfected cell group (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>). After that, the RIP assay revealed that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p were significantly enriched in the AGO2 immunoprecipitation complex (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>, P &lt; 0.05), meaning that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p can associate with AGO2 and that miR-511-3p can directly bind to <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer cells.<fig id="F0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> directly targets miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells. (<bold>A</bold>) The expression distribution of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in the HeLa and SiHa cells was analyzed via isolation of cytoplasmic and nuclear RNA followed by RT-qPCR. (<bold>B</bold>) Bioinformatics analysis uncovered an miR-511-3p–binding site within <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. The mutant binding site is shown too. (<bold>C</bold>) The expression of miR-511-3p in HeLa and SiHa cells was quantified after either miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC introduction. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the miR-NC group. (<bold>D</bold>) Either luciferase reporter plasmid WT-ZFPM2-AS1 or MUT-ZFPM2-AS1 as well as either the miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC were cotransfected into HeLa and SiHa cells. The luciferase reporter assay was conducted at 48 h post-transfection. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group miR-NC. (<bold>E</bold>) The RIP assay was conducted to evaluate the enrichment of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p in AGO2 immunoprecipitates from HeLa and SiHa cell lysates. *P &lt; 0.05 as compared with the IgG group. (<bold>F</bold>) Assessment of miR-511-3p expression in 45 pairs of cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissues was conducted by RT-qPCR. *P &lt; 0.05 vs nontumor tissue samples. (<bold>G</bold>) Spearman correlation analysis was performed to test the expression correlation between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and miR-511-3p in the cervical cancer tissue samples (n = 45). r = −0.6011, P &lt; 0.0001. (<bold>H</bold>) The expression of miR-511-3p was measured in HeLa and SiHa cells after the transfection with either si-ZFPM2-AS1 or si-NC. *P &lt; 0.05 as compared to the si-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0003.jpg"/></fig></p><p>Furthermore, the expression of miR-511-3p was measured in the 45 pairs of cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissue samples. The RT-qPCR data showed that miR-511-3p was weakly expressed in the cervical cancer tissue samples compared with the tumor adjacent tissues (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3F</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). Moreover, the expression of miR-511-3p inversely correlated with <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression in these 45 cervical cancer tissue samples (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3G</xref>; r = –0.6011, P &lt; 0.0001), as evidenced by Spearman correlation analysis. Finally, the miR-511-3p amount in <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–deficient HeLa and SiHa cells was determined, and we investigated whether the expression of miR-511-3p can be sponged by <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. Notably, miR-511-3p expression was increased by the transfection of si-ZFPM2-AS1 in HeLa and SiHa cells (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3H</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). These results collectively indicated that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> may directly interact with miR-511-3p and can act as a molecular sponge of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells.</p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2004"><title>miR-511-3p Suppresses the Malignant Phenotype of Cervical Cancer Cells</title><p>The miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC was introduced into HeLa and SiHa cells, and functional experiments were conducted on the transfected cells to explore the functions of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer progression. The CCK-8 assay and flow cytometry suggested that the ectopic miR-511-3p expression significantly decreased the proliferation (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and increased apoptosis (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) of HeLa and SiHa cells. Additionally, we found that the migration (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and invasiveness (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) of HeLa and SiHa cells were obviously suppressed by miR-511-3p overexpression, as determined by Transwell migration and invasion assays. In summary, these results indicated that miR-511-3p plays a tumor-suppressive role in cervical cancer cells.<fig id="F0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>MiR-511-3p overexpression has an inhibitory influence on the malignant phenotype of HeLa and SiHa cells. (<bold>A, B</bold>) HeLa and SiHa cells were transfected with either the miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC. The proliferation and apoptosis of miR-511-3p–overexpressing HeLa and SiHa cells were respectively examined by the CCK-8 assay and flow-cytometric analysis. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the miR-NC group. (<bold>C, D</bold>) The migration and invasiveness of the aforementioned cells were assessed in Transwell migration and invasion assays (x200 magnification). *P &lt; 0.05 vs the miR-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0004.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2005"><title><italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> Is a Direct Target Gene of miR-511-3p in Cervical Cancer Cells</title><p>To decipher the mechanism underlying the involvement of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer progression, we carried out bioinformatics analysis to find a downstream target of miR-511-3p. The 3′-UTR of <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA was found to contain complementary binding sequences for the seed region of miR-511-3p (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>), and <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> was selected for further experimental verification because this gene is involved in the cervical carcinogenesis and cancer progression<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> in addition to being regulated by multiple miRNAs.<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> The luciferase reporter assay was performed to verify the above prediction. The luciferase activity of HeLa and SiHa cells transfected with WT-FGFR2 was substantially impaired by the miR-511-3p mimic (P &lt; 0.05); however, when the binding sequences of miR-511-3p were mutated in the luciferase reporter plasmid (resulting in plasmid MUT-FGFR2), upregulation of miR-511-3p failed to inhibit the luciferase activity in the transfected HeLa and SiHa cells (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>). In addition, transfection with the miR-511-3p mimic significantly diminished FGFR2 expression in HeLa and SiHa cells at both mRNA (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and protein levels (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). Next, using RT-qPCR, we revealed that the expression of <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA was much higher in cervical cancer tissue samples (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5E</xref>, P &lt; 0.05), manifesting an inverse correlation with miR-511-3p expression (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5F</xref>; r = –0.5810, P &lt; 0.0001). In a word, <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA is a direct target of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells.<fig id="F0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA is a direct target of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the wild-type and mutant binding sites for miR-511-3p in the 3′-UTR of <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA. (<bold>B</bold>) The luciferase reporter assay was carried out in HeLa and SiHa cell lysates after cotransfection with either reporter plasmid WT-FGFR2 or MUT-FGFR2 and the miR-511-3p mimic or miR-NC. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the miR-NC group. (<bold>C, D</bold>) The impact of transfection with the miR-511-3p mimic on FGFR2 expression was examined by RT-qPCR and Western blotting in HeLa and SiHa cells. MiR-NC served as the control. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group miR-NC. (<bold>E</bold>) RT-qPCR analysis was performed to evaluate <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA expression in the 45 pairs of cervical cancer tissue samples and tumor adjacent tissues. *P &lt; 0.05 vs tumor adjacent tissue samples. (<bold>F</bold>) The correlation between <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA and miR-511-3p expression levels in the 45 cervical cancer tissue samples was determined by Spearman correlation analysis. r = −0.5810, P &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0005.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2006"><title>The Oncogenic Actions of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in Cervical Cancer are Dependent on the Enhancement of the miR-511-3p–FGFR2 Axis Output</title><p>To verify the relation between <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and FGFR2 in cervical cancer, the expression of FGFR2 was quantitated in <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–deficient HeLa and SiHa cells. Expression levels of the FGFR2 mRNA (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and protein (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) were lower in the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–deficient HeLa and SiHa cells. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression was found to positively correlate with <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA expression in cervical cancer tissue samples judging by Spearman correlation analysis results (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>; r = 0.5243, P = 0.0002). We subsequently investigated whether <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> controls FGFR2 expression through miR-511-3p sponging. To this end, either the miR-511-3p inhibitor or NC inhibitor as well as si-ZFPM2-AS1 were cotransfected into HeLa and SiHa cells, and the expression of FGFR2 was then determined. MiR-511-3p inhibitor introduction obviously decreased the expression of miR-511-3p in HeLa and SiHa cells (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). The downregulation of FGFR2 mRNA (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6E</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and protein (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6F</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) mediated by the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown was found to be greatly recovered by miR-511-3p inhibition in HeLa and SiHa cells. Therefore, these results proved that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> acts as a competing endogenous RNA (ceRNA) on miR-511-3p and thereby positively regulates FGFR2 expression in cervical cancer.<fig id="F0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis is responsible for the cancer-promoting activities of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer cells. (<bold>A, B</bold>) The mRNA and protein levels of FGFR2 were determined in HeLa and SiHa cells treated with either si-ZFPM2-AS1 or si-NC using RT-qPCR and Western blotting, respectively. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the si-NC group. (<bold>C</bold>) Spearman correlation analysis was applied to demonstrate the positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> mRNA and <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression levels in the cervical cancer tissue samples. r = 0.524., P = 0.0002. (<bold>D</bold>) RT-qPCR was carried out to measure miR-511-3p expression in HeLa and SiHa cells that were transfected with either the miR-511-3p inhibitor or NC inhibitor. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the NC inhibitor group. (<bold>E, F</bold>) Either the miR-511-3p inhibitor or NC inhibitor along with si-ZFPM2-AS1 was introduced into HeLa and SiHa cells. After the transfection, RT-qPCR and Western blotting were carried out to evaluate the change in FGFR2 expression. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group si-NC. <sup>#</sup>P &lt; 0.05 vs group si-ZFPM2-AS1+NC inhibitor. (<bold>G–K</bold>) A series of functional experiments, including the CCK-8 assay, flow-cytometric analysis, and Transwell migration and invasion assays (x200 magnification), was conducted to respectively examine the proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasiveness of HeLa and SiHa cells that were treated as descried above. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the si-NC group. <sup>#</sup>P &lt; 0.05 vs group si-ZFPM2-AS1+NC inhibitor.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0006.jpg"/></fig></p><p>To uncover the importance of the miR-511-3p–FGFR2 pathway for the promotion of cervical cancer progression by <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>, functional experiments were performed on HeLa and SiHa cells that were transfected with either the miR-511-3p inhibitor or NC inhibitor in the presence of si-ZFPM2-AS1. The <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown suppressed HeLa and SiHa cell proliferation (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6G</xref>, P &lt; 0.05), promoted their apoptosis (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6H</xref> and I, P &lt; 0.05), and decreased their migration (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6J</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and invasiveness (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6K</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) in vitro. These phenomena were counteracted by miR-511-3p inhibitor cotransfection. Taken together, these findings revealed that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> contributes to the aggressiveness of cervical cancer in part via upregulation of the output of the miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis.</p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2007"><title>Knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> Reduces the Tumor Growth of Cervical Cancer Cells in vivo</title><p>The in vivo tumor xenograft model was set up to address the impact of the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown on the tumor growth of cervical cancer cells. The results showed that the nude mice injected with the HeLa cells stably transfected with sh-ZFPM2-AS1 manifested slower tumor growth compared with those in the sh-NC group (<xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref> and B, P &lt; 0.05). In addition, the weight of subcutaneous tumors was significantly lower in the sh-<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> group than in the sh-NC group (<xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref>, P &lt; 0.05). The expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>, miR-511-3p, and FGFR2 in the subcutaneous tumors were determined to verify whether the miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis is responsible for the tumor growth inhibition caused by the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown. <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> (<xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7D</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) and FGFR2 protein (<xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7E</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) expression was lower, while miR-511-3p (<xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7F</xref>, P &lt; 0.05) expression was higher in the tumor xenografts derived from HeLa cells stably transfected with sh-ZFPM2-AS1. These results indicated that the reduction in <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression slowed down the tumor growth of cervical cancer cells in vivo, and this effect was mediated by the downregulation of miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis output.<fig id="F0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> restricts cervical cancer cell growth through the miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis. (<bold>A</bold>) HeLa cells stably transfected with either sh-ZFPM2-AS1 or sh-NC were subcutaneously injected into nude mice. The growth curves of groups sh-<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and sh-NC were plotted and analyzed. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the sh-NC group. (<bold>B</bold>) Representative images of tumor xenografts derived from the HeLa cells stably transduced with either sh-<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> or sh-NC. (<bold>C</bold>) Tumor xenografts were excised from the mice and then weighed. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group sh-NC. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression in the tumor xenografts was analyzed via RT-qPCR. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the sh-NC group. (<bold>E</bold>) Western blotting analysis of FGFR2 protein expression in the tumor xenografts derived from HeLa cells stably transfected with either sh-<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> or sh-NC. *P &lt; 0.05 vs group sh-NC. (<bold>F</bold>) The expression of miR-511-3p was estimated in subcutaneous tumors collected in groups sh-<italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> and sh-NC. *P &lt; 0.05 vs the sh-NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-12-567-g0007.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Extensive research has confirmed aberrant expression of lncRNAs in cervical cancer.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> The dysregulation of lncRNAs has been demonstrated to be crucial for cervical carcinogenesis and cervical cancer progression through the control of a wide range of aggressive characteristics of cancer cells.<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Accordingly, lncRNAs may be promising RNAs for the identification of novel chemotherapeutic medications. In this study, we hypothesized that one of cancer-associated lncRNAs, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>, is aberrantly expressed in cervical cancer and is functionally implicated in the malignancy of cervical cancer. Therefore, we employed systematic experimental methods to determine the expression profile of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer and to characterize the role of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is upregulated in gastric cancer, and its upregulation is significantly associated with tumor size, depth of tumor invasion, differentiation grade, and TNM stage.<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Patients with gastric cancer featuring high <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression show shorter overall survival and disease-free survival than do the patients with low <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression.<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Lung adenocarcinoma<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and renal cell cancer<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> also manifest high expression of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. Increased <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression is related to lymph node metastasis, tumor stage, and survival time of patients with renal cell cancer.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> By contrast, the expression profile of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer has been poorly studied until now. Herein, our results suggest that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is strongly expressed in both cervical cancer tissue samples and cell lines. Upregulation of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> highly correlated with tumor size, FIGO stage, lymph node metastasis, and shorter overall survival among the patients with cervical cancer.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> plays tumor-promoting roles in human cancers. For instance, upregulation of ZFPM2-AS increases gastric cancer cell proliferation and reduces apoptosis in vitro and promotes tumor growth in vivo.<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> In lung adenocarcinoma, resumption of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression can increase cancer cell viability and colony-forming ability in vitro.<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> In renal cell cancer, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> overexpression accelerates cancer cell growth and metastasis as well as diminishes cancer cell apoptosis in vitro.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> On the other hand, the functions of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer have not been clarified. In this study, our results showed that a reduction in <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> expression decreased cervical cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion and induced apoptosis in vitro as well as diminished tumor growth in vivo.</p><p>The molecular mechanisms of action of lncRNAs are diverse. LncRNAs can work as ceRNAs by competitively binding to miRNAs through their miRNA response elements, thereby upregulating miRNA target genes.<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Recently, researchers reported that the cancer-promoting activities of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> are mediated by the MIF–p53 signaling pathway in gastric cancer,<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> by the miR-18b-5p–VMA21 axis in lung adenocarcinoma,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and by miR-137 in renal cell cancer.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> After identifying the expression status and roles of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer, we next sought to explore the mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown–mediated suppression of the aggressive phenotype of cervical cancer cells in vitro and in vivo.</p><p>In this study, we demonstrated a network regulating cervical cancer malignancy; this network is composed of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>, miR-511-3p, and FGFR2. First, <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> was found to be mainly located in the cytoplasm of cervical cancer cells. Second, bioinformatic analysis indicated that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> harbors a potential binding site for miR-511-3p. Third, luciferase reporter and RIP assays revealed that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> can directly bind to miR-511-3p and interact with the latter in cervical cancer cells. Fourth, miR-511-3p was found to be only weakly expressed in cervical cancer, showing a negative expression correlation with <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. Fifth, the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown raised endogenous miR-511-3p expression and decreased the expression of miR-511-3p’s target (FGFR2) in cervical cancer cells. Sixth, FGFR2 upregulation was proven in cervical cancer and positively correlated with the expression of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>. Finally, miR-511-3p inhibition abrogated the regulatory effects of the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> knockdown on FGFR2 expression and on the malignant phenotype of cervical cancer cells.</p><p>MiR-511-3p expression is low in prostate cancer and plays an inhibitory part in the aggressiveness of tumor cells in vitro and in vivo.<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Herein, we for the first time showed that miR-511-3p expression is low in cervical cancer tissue samples and cell lines. Further experiments indicated that ectopic miR-511-3p expression slowed the proliferation of cervical cancer cells, induced their apoptosis, and impaired their migratory and invasive abilities in vitro. Further molecular investigation identified <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> as a direct target gene of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer cells. <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic>, located in human chromosomal region 10q26, is upregulated in cervical cancer tissue samples and cell lines, with an obvious correlation with lymph node metastasis, disease-free survival, and overall survival.<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Functionally, <italic toggle="yes">FGFR2</italic> is believed to serve as an oncogene enhancing the malignant characteristics of cervical cancer.<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Here, our results confirmed that <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> can positively regulate FGFR2 expression by functioning as a ceRNA of miR-511-3p in cervical cancer, thereby pointing to possible diagnostics and therapeutics based on the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–miR-511-3p–FGFR2 axis.</p></sec><sec id="S0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Thus, we validated an oncogenic function of lncRNA <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical cancer. The regulation of miR-511-3p and FGFR2 expression by <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> is a mechanism behind the oncogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic> in cervical carcinogenesis and cervical cancer progression. Hence, the <italic toggle="yes">ZFPM2-AS1</italic>–miR-511-3p–FGFR2 regulatory pathway might be a therapeutic target in cervical cancer.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="S0006"><title>Ethics Approval and Informed Consent</title><p>This study was carried out with the approval of Ethics Committees of Qilu Hospital of Shandong University and in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. All participating patients provided written informed consent. The animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Experimental Animal Review Board of Qilu Hospital of Shandong University.</p></sec><sec id="S0007"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the present study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="S0008"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the Analysis of Cervical Cancer Screening in Women of the Shandong Province (2017ws302).</p></sec><sec id="S0009" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lortet-Tieulent</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2012</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CA Cancer J Clin</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CA Cancer J Clin</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ananth</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Influence of treatment center and hospital volume on survival for locally advanced cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gynecol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>506</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2015.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26177552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4679418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>YL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Methyl protodioscin from Polygonatum sibiricum inhibits cervical cancer through cell cycle arrest and apoptosis induction</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Food Chem Toxicol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>110655</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2019.110655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31271762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Handler</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rankin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Issel</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Illinois breast and cervical cancer program: implementing effective public-private partnerships to assure population health</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Public Health Manage Pract</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000000191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25470661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banister</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pirisi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Creek</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buckhaults</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identification and characterization of HPV-independent cervical cancers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>13375</fpage>–<lpage>13386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.v8i8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5355105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A human papillomavirus-independent cervical cancer animal model reveals unconventional mechanisms of cervical carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2636</fpage>–<lpage>2650 e2635</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30840887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6812687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dinger</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mattick</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long non-coding RNAs: insights into functions</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Rev Genet</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fullwood</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Roles, functions, and mechanisms of long non-coding RNAs in cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gpb.2015.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26883671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4792843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>ZX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>LX</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long noncoding RNAs, emerging and versatile regulators of tumor-induced angiogenesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31392075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6682713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lecerf</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bourhis</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adriaenssens</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The long non-coding RNA H19: an active player with multiple facets to sustain the hallmarks of cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Mol Life Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>4673</fpage>–<lpage>4687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-019-03240-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31338555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11105575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The prognostic value and mechanisms of lncRNA UCA1 in human cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Manag Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>7685</fpage>–<lpage>7696</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S200436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31616184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6698587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Progress in the study of long noncoding RNA in tongue squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oooo.2019.08.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31611036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Role of non-coding RNA in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncol Lett</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>3963</fpage>–<lpage>3973</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2019.10758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31579086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6757267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nian</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>NN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA TUG1 aggravates the progression of cervical cancer by binding PUM2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>8211</fpage>–<lpage>8218</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_201910_19128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31646551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>QQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA PVT1 promotes proliferation and invasion through enhancing Smad3 expression by sponging miR-140-5p in cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Radiol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/raon-2019-0048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31626590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6884931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>LncRNA CRNDE acts as an oncogene in cervical cancer through sponging miR-183 to regulate CCNB1 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Carcinogenesis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/bgz166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31605132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>lncRNA HAND2-AS1 inhibits cancer cell proliferation, migration and invasion by downregulating ROCK1 in HPV-positive and negative cervical squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Ther Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2512</fpage>–<lpage>2518</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2019.7830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31555362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6755406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA PTCSC3 inhibits the proliferation, invasion and migration of cervical cancer cells via sponging miR-574-5p</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1440-1681.13186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31587336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA ZNF667-AS1 reduces tumor invasion and metastasis in cervical cancer by counteracting microRNA-93-3p-dependent PEG3 downregulation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2375</fpage>–<lpage>2392</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mol2.v13.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31420931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6822248</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11705813"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA LINC00958 regulates cell sensitivity to radiotherapy through RRM2 by binding to microRNA-5095 in cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>234</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>23349</fpage>–<lpage>23359</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.28902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31169309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA CRNDE enhances cervical cancer progression by suppressing PUMA expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>108726</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.108726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31202167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA STXBP5-AS1 suppressed cervical cancer progression via targeting miR-96-5p/PTEN axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>109082</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2019.109082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31212131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ZFPM2-AS1, a novel lncRNA, attenuates the p53 pathway and promotes gastric carcinogenesis by stabilizing MIF</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncogene</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>45</issue>):<fpage>5982</fpage>–<lpage>5996</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41388-018-0387-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29985481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6226322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>lncRNA ZFPM2-AS1 promotes proliferation via miR-18b-5p/VMA21 axis in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jcb.29176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31297866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>MZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>XJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA ZFPM2-AS1 promotes the tumorigenesis of renal cell cancer via targeting miR-137</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>5675</fpage>–<lpage>5681</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_201907_18304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31298319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA LINC00052 regulates miR-608/EGFR axis to promote progression of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Mol Pathol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>104321</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexmp.2019.104321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA NR2F1-AS1 enhances the malignant properties of osteosarcoma by increasing forkhead box A1 expression via sponging of microRNA-483-3p</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aging</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<fpage>11</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/aging.102563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6932892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31801112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA LINC01111 suppresses pancreatic cancer aggressiveness by regulating DUSP1 expression via microRNA-3924</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Death Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>883</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-019-2123-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31767833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6877515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SNHG8 is upregulated in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma and directly sponges microRNA-411 to increase oncogenicity by upregulating KPNA2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Onco Targets Ther</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6991</fpage>–<lpage>7004</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/OTT.S214881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31695414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6717851</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8500503"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA LOC554202 modulates chordoma cell proliferation and invasion by recruiting EZH2 and regulating miR-31 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Prolif</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cpr.12388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6529120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28963737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA EPB41L4A-AS2 suppresses progression of ovarian cancer by sequestering microRNA-103a to upregulate transcription factor RUNX1T1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1113/EP087847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA PXN-AS1 suppresses pancreatic cancer progression by acting as a competing endogenous RNA of miR-3064 to upregulate PIP4K2B expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>390</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-019-1379-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31488171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6727519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA NEAT1 enhances the resistance of anaplastic thyroid carcinoma cells to cisplatin by sponging miR95p and regulating SPAG9 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>988</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijo.2019.4868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31485599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>S</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>starBase v2.0: decoding miRNA-ceRNA, miRNA-ncRNA and protein-RNA interaction networks from large-scale CLIP-Seq data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>Database issue</issue>):<fpage>D92</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3964941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>miRDB: an online resource for microRNA target prediction and functional annotations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>Database issue</issue>):<fpage>D146</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25378301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4383922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname>
<given-names>IH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones-Rhoades</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burge</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prediction of mammalian microRNA targets</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>798</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)01018-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14697198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Long noncoding RNA SNHG16 silencing inhibits the aggressiveness of gastric cancer via upregulation of microRNA-628-3p and consequent decrease of NRP1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Manag Res</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>7263</fpage>–<lpage>7277</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S211856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31447585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6682761</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8487261"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Downregulation of long noncoding RNA CRNDE suppresses drug resistance of liver cancer cells by increasing microRNA-33a expression and decreasing HMGA2 expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cell Cycle</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>2524</fpage>–<lpage>2537</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2019.1652035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31416393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6738913</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10446803"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bayoumi</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Broskova</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Crosstalk between long noncoding RNAs and MicroRNAs in health and disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms17030356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26978351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4813217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expression of fibroblast growth factor receptor family members is associated with prognosis in early stage cervical cancer patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Transl Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>124</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-016-0874-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27154171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4859953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kawase</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ishiwata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuda</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Expression of fibroblast growth factor receptor 2 IIIc in human uterine cervical intraepithelial neoplasia and cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MicroRNA-889-3p targets FGFR2 to inhibit cervical cancer cell viability and invasion</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Ther Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1440</fpage>–<lpage>1448</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2019.7675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31316631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6601145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>DQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MicroRNA-1266 suppresses papillary thyroid carcinoma cell metastasis and growth via targeting FGFR2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3430</fpage>–<lpage>3438</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26355/eurrev_201806_15166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29917195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>MiR-628-5p decreases the tumorigenicity of epithelial ovarian cancer cells by targeting at FGFR2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>495</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>2085</fpage>–<lpage>2091</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2017.12.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29229394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>miR-381-3p suppresses the proliferation of oral squamous cell carcinoma cells by directly targeting FGFR2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>922</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28469963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5411798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>WW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname>
<given-names>QZ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LINC00511 knockdown prevents cervical cancer cell proliferation and reduces resistance to paclitaxel</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biosci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31180057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>YG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Expression of the lncRNA ZFAS1 in cervical cancer and its correlation with prognosis and chemosensitivity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gene</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>696</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2019.01.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30738960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long non-coding RNA RP11-552M11.4 favors tumorigenesis and development of cervical cancer via modulating miR-3941/ATF1 signaling</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biol Macromol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.02.083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30790638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>SP1-induced up-regulation of lncRNA LUCAT1 promotes proliferation, migration and invasion of cervical cancer by sponging miR-181a</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Artif Cells Nanomed Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21691401.2019.1575840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30831032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>LncRNA SBF2-AS1 promotes the progression of cervical cancer by regulating miR-361-5p/FOXM1 axis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Artif Cells Nanomed Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>776</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21691401.2019.1577883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30856345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tay</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Noncoding RNA: RNA regulatory networks in cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19051310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5983611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29702599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Significantly altered expression of miR-511-3p and its target AKT3 has negative prognostic value in human prostate cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochimie</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2017.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28624527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>