
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1524</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101548923</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pharmacol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-9812</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6137241</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6137241.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6137241</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6137241</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30245628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00987</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CuO and CeO<sub>2</sub> Nanostructures Green Synthesized Using Olive Leaf Extract Inhibits the Growth of Highly Virulent Multidrug Resistant Bacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qaisar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/358845/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names initials="M">Mudassar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/358905/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names initials="A">Ayesha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pervez</surname><given-names initials="MT">Muhammad T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names initials="N">Nyla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/422443/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names initials="T">Talib</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/359267/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names initials="G">Gregory</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/267143/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Integrative Plant Biology, Institute of Plant Genetics of the Polish Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Poznan</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biotechnology, Virtual University of Pakistan</institution>, <addr-line>Lahore</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>National Institute of Vacuum Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Islamabad</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Molecular Biology, Virtual University of Pakistan</institution>, <addr-line>Lahore</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology, Virtual University of Pakistan</institution>, <addr-line>Lahore</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Applied Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering Lab, Department of Bioinformatics and Biotechnology, International Islamic University, Islamabad</institution>, <addr-line>Islamabad</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Karl Tsim, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Hong Kong</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Souaibou Yaouba, University of Nairobi, Kenya; Shuai Ji, Xuzhou Medical University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Qaisar Maqbool, <email>qaisar.vu@gmail.com</email> Ayesha Maqbool, <email>ayesha.maqbool@vu.edu.pk</email> Gregory Franklin, <email>fgre@igr.poznan.pl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Ethnopharmacology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">305167</issue-id><elocation-id>987</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>09</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>09</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 Maqbool, Nazar, Maqbool, Pervez, Jabeen, Hussain and Franklin.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Maqbool, Nazar, Maqbool, Pervez, Jabeen, Hussain and Franklin</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Front Pharmacol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6375058"><article-title>Retraction: CuO and CeO<sub>2</sub> Nanostructures Green Synthesized Using Olive Leaf Extract Inhibits the Growth of Highly Virulent Multidrug Resistant Bacteria</article-title><volume>10</volume><date><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><elocation-id>135</elocation-id><source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30792660</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>One of the major challenges of nano-biotechnology is to engineer potent antimicrobial nanostructures (NS) with high biocompatibility. Keeping this in view, we have performed aqueous olive leaf extract mediated one pot facile synthesis of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS. Prepared NS were homogenous, less than 26 nm in size, and small crystallite units as revealed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and X-ray diffraction (XRD) analyses. Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS showed typical Cu-O prints around 592–660 cm<sup>-1</sup> and Ce-O bond vibrations at 453 cm<sup>-1</sup>. The successful capping of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS by compounds present in the plant extract was further validated by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) and thermal gravimetric analysis (TGA). Active phyto-chemicals from the leaf extract simultaneously acted as strong reducing as well as capping agent in the NS synthesis. NS engineered in the present study showed antibacterial potential at extremely low concentration against highly virulent multidrug-resistant (MDR) gram-negative strains (<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>), alarmed by World Health Organization (WHO). Furthermore, CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS did not show any cytotoxicity on HEK-293 cell lines and Brine shrimp larvae indicating that the NS green synthesized in the present study are biocompatible.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>green synthesis</kwd><kwd>CuO-nanostructures</kwd><kwd>CeO<sub>2</sub>-nanostructures</kwd><kwd>multidrug-resistant bacteria</kwd><kwd>cytotoxicity</kwd><kwd>biocompatibility</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Narodowym Centrum Nauki<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004442</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">UMO-2016/21/B/NZ9/01980</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">UMO-2016/23/B/NZ902677</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">W26/7.PR/2015 [GA 3413/7.PR/2015/2]</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="37"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="0"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Bacterial epidemiology, microbial invasions, drug resistance, and random mutations are the hot topics under discussion today. There is a race between drug development and bacterial resistance (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Puzyn et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Saravanakumar et al., 2017</xref>). The loss of efficiency to cure microbial infections is persistently observed for several drugs (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Puzyn et al., 2011</xref>). Many antimicrobial agents that revolutionized treatment against infections in the past have now lost their bactericidal capabilities (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Zaman et al., 2017</xref>). The potential threat to mankind gets higher when WHO issued the list of multi-drug-resistant (MDR) pathogen in 2017, which includes <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic>. According to WHO observations, these bacteria are resistant even to the strongest third generation antibiotics (cephalosporin group). It is strongly predicted that death toll due to drug resistant pathogens may rise up (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Rather et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Zaman et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Grzelak et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>Due to multiple modes of action, nanostructures (NS) have been successfully used against MDR bacterial pathogens. The ability to fine-tune the morphological, optical, magnetic, and physical properties of metal oxide NS makes them suitable agents for biomedical and biotechnological applications (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Wang X. et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Caballero-Calero and D’Agosta, 2017</xref>). Due to extremely small size and high reactivity, these NS could target the surface envelop and even the genomic content of bacterial pathogens. Maximum penetration of the bacterial cell wall by NS has been observed due to opposite charges of attraction. These unique properties of multimode of actions and maximum invasion are quite helpful in developing NS as broad-spectrum antibiotics in the future (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ni et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Among metal oxide NS experimented so far, the performance of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS was found extremely effective in biological applications (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Anwaar et al., 2016</xref>). CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS exhibits variable oxidation states, stable crystal structure, greater surface energy, high surface to charge ratio, visible light activation, and greater stability making it as an ideal candidate for biomedical applications (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Charbgoo et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kamila and Venugopal, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Stephen Inbaraj, 2018</xref>). All these characteristics are directly linked to variable oxidation states of Ce (Ce<sup>3+</sup>, Ce<sup>4+</sup>) and photoexcitaion at room temperature through which the NS can generate lethal reactive oxygen species (ROS) (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Maria Magdalane et al., 2017</xref>). When tested against lethal strains like <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, CuO-NS showed moderate antibacterial behavior (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Although a variety of metal oxide NS have been tested for advanced biomedical applications, the extensive use of synthetic reagents during their chemical synthesis makes these NS least biocompatible. Green synthesis of NS using plant extract has gained a lot of importance because of the bio-safety and economy of NS prepared by this method. Olive leaf aqueous extract contains a variety of phyto-reductants for tailoring NS. The biomedical potential of olive is well known primarily due to the presence of antioxidants like oleuropein, oleuroside and apigenin-7-O-glucoside (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Maalej et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Marslin et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we report on the comparative analysis of green synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS for their biocompatibility, cytotoxicity and most importantly antimicrobial potential. Results presented here will help us to understand the performance of green synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS in future biomedical applications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Green Synthesis of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS Using Olive Leaf Extract</title><p>Olive leaves (<italic toggle="yes">Olea europaea</italic>) were collected and washed three times with ddH<sub>2</sub>O. To avoid any damage to light sensitive bioactive compounds, collected leaves were dried under shade. Later on, they were ground in to fine powder. To prepare the extract, 30 g of leaf powder was added to an Erlenmeyer flask containing 300 mL of ddH<sub>2</sub>O and shaken at 50 rpm at 50°C in an incubator. After 2 h, the mixture was filtered through a Whatmann No. 1 filter paper and the filtrate was stored in a refrigerator at 15°C.</p><p>For the green synthesis of CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS, 13.02 g of (CeNO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>. 6H<sub>2</sub>O was added to 300 mL of plant extract in an Erlenmeyer flask. The reaction mixture was stirred at 1,500 rpm at 50°C on a magnetic plate. After 2.5 h of stirring, the reaction mixture was centrifuged at 10,000 rpm (GR Bio-Tek centrifuge, Orpington, England) for 10 min to pellet the synthesized CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS. Dark brown color CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS pellets were obtained. The pellets were washed three times with ddH<sub>2</sub>O. In the next step, all of the washed CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS pellets were placed in Hot-Air-Oven setup to 60°C for 6.5 h. In order to achieve greater crystallinity, CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS were further calcined inside a Gallenkamp furnace (Apeldoorn, Netherlands) at 500°C for 2.5 h. A similar procedure was adopted for CuO-NS synthesis by using 5.43 g of Cu(CO<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> in 300 mL of olive leaf extract. Prepared NS were stored in airtight containers under ambient conditions. The step-by-step process of facile green synthesis of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS is illustrated in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Scheme showingfacile green synthesis of NS using olive leaf extract.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>High Performance Liquid Chromatography (HPLC) Analysis of Plant Extract</title><p>For the identification of active bio-molecules present in the olive leaf extract used in the green synthesis, it was subjected to HPLC analysis as described before (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Miller, 2017</xref>). Briefly, 5 g of olive leaf powder was added to 30 mL of aqueous methanol (60%) and thoroughly mixed in a blender. The resulting mixture was centrifuged at 3,000 rpm for 5 min. The supernatant was collected and filtered through 0.22 μm micro-filter. Separation of compounds was performed in an HPLC (Agilent 1100 Technologies, Ireland) using water-acetic acid (99.5–0.5) as mobile phase-A and acetonitrile as mobile phase-B. The flow rate of the column was set at 1 mL/min along with temperature set at 25°C. Compounds were examined based on retention time (t<sub>R</sub>) and elution time (t<sub>o</sub>) for unretained peak. Moreover, polyphenolic compounds from olive extract were identified using two systems of liquid chromatography hyphenated to mass spectrometers following the method of <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Piasecka et al. (2015)</xref>. The first system consisted of HPLC Agilent 1100 coupled to Esquire 3000 (Bruker Daltonics) ion trap mass spectrometer and the second was UPLC (Acquity Waters) hyphenated to QExactive hybrid MS/MS quadrupole-Orbitrap instrument (Thermo). Compounds were identified according to exact masse of their [M+H]+ and [M-H]- ions; their fragmentation patterns and chromatographic retention times by comparison with standard compounds (Sigma-Aldrich).</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><sec><title>Thermal Gravimetric Analysis (TGA) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>The thermal stability and bio-molecular capping action around green synthesized NS were evaluated using PerkinElmer-Diamond-TGA (Llantrisant, United Kingdom). The temperature increment was set between 25.00 and 800.00°C with increase of 10.00°C/min.</p></sec><sec><title>Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy (FTIR) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>Vibrational bond energies and molecular nature of NS were examined by FTIR spectroscopy (SHIMADZU FTIR) with wave number set between 400 and 4,000 cm<sup>-1</sup> following KBr pellet method.</p></sec><sec><title>X-ray Diffraction (XRD) Analysis</title><p>Crystallographic parameters of green synthesized NS were checked with PANalyticalX′Pert<sup>3</sup> powder machine (Royston, United Kingdom) powered with Ni-Monochromator, and machine diffraction angel (2𝜃) specific for crystalline materials (20–80°). In XRD analysis, Cu_Kα radiation of specific wavelength 1.5406 Å was used. In order to determine the crystallite size value of bio-fabricated NS, Scherer’s equation [<italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = 0.9λ/βcos𝜃] was applied. From the values of equation, D is the average crystalline domain size perpendicular to the reflecting planes, λ is showing the X-ray wavelength (1.5406 Å), ß is the angular full width at half maximum (FWHM) in radians and 𝜃 is the diffraction angle [2𝜃 (degree) is the calculated angle of diffraction in degree] or also known as Bragg’s angle.</p></sec><sec><title>Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>Measurement of NS size and surface morphology is important for NS based biological applications. Hence, the size and surface structure of fabricated CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS were analyzed using JOEL-JSM-6490LA-SEM (Tokyo, Japan) setup at 20 kV with counting-rate of 2838.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Activity of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>To screen the antibacterial potential of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922), <italic toggle="yes">E. cloacae</italic> (ATCC 23373), <italic toggle="yes">A. baumanni</italic> (ATCC 19606), and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">aeruginosa (ATCC</italic> 27853) strains were tested via disc diffusion method as we reported before (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2016</xref>). In detail, bacterial strains were cultured in nutrient broth culture (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37°C until reaching 1.5 × 10<sup>8</sup> colony forming unit (CFU) per mL. Bacteria were carefully spread on Petri dishes containing semi-solid culture medium. Sterilized filter paper discs loaded with 5 μL solution containing 20 μg/μL of NS. Discs loaded with 5 μL roxithromycin (4 mg/mL) were considered as positive control, while discs loaded with deionized H<sub>2</sub>O was used as negative control. All of the inoculated plates were placed in the incubator set for 37°C and the zone of inhibition (ZOI) was measured after 24 h.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytotoxicity Assay of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS on HEK-293 Cells</title><p>Cell viability assay was performed following the method as described previously (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbas et al., 2017a</xref>). HEK-293 cells (Sigma-Aldrich) were seeded in a 96-well plate at a concentration of 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well and incubated at 37°C under 5% CO<sub>2</sub> environment to allow cell adhesion. After 24 h of incubation, the wells were added with different concentrations of the CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS (0.01, 0.05, and 0.1 mg/mL). The cell viability was examined via CCK-8 analyzer and OD was recorded at 450 nm by Multi Scan MK3 after 24 h of NS treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Examination of Biocompatibility of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS (Using Brine Shrimp Larvae)</title><p>The biocompatibility of green synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>NS was tested via Brine shrimp (<italic toggle="yes">Artimia salina</italic>) lethality assay. Brine shrimp eggs procured from Ocean-Star-International (Coral Springs, United States). They were maintained in 3.8% (w/v) saline water (Coral Springs, United States) at 37°C for 2 days for hatching. 48 h after hatching, the larvae were collected using Pasteur pipette. To each vial containing different concentrations (5, 10, and 15 mg/mL) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>NS in saline water was transferred with 10 larvae. Larvae transferred to vials containing doxorubicin dissolved saline water (10 μg/mL<italic toggle="yes">)</italic> and to vials containing only saline water served as negative and positive controls, respectively. All the vials with larvae were incubated at 28°C. After 24 h of incubation, the number of live and dead larvae was counted manually with the aid of a magnifying glass to calculate the LD<sub>50</sub> value of NS.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All the experiments were repeated at least three times and the values are presented as the mean ± SD. Statistical investigation of the results was done by student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests using SPSS software. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>HPLC and TGA Findings</title><p>HPLC analysis of olive leaf extract revealed the presence of several secondary metabolites (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). They were oleuroside (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 33.8), oleuropein (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 23.6), isoquercetin (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 12.5), apigenin-7-O-glucoside (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 16.2), luteolin-7-glucoside (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 8.9), verbascoside (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 7.9), rutin (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 6.7), and hydroxytyrosol (<italic toggle="yes">t<sub>R</sub></italic> = 2.5).</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>HPLC chromatogram showing major compounds present in the olive leaf extract <bold>(top)</bold> with hypothesized capping action around NS <bold>(bottom)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Capping action around CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS was evaluated through TGA analysis. When the green synthesized NS were subjected to progressively increasing temperature, the loss of weight in NS was observed in three phases. In the first phase from 50 to 100°C, the loss of weight was due to surface absorbed H<sub>2</sub>O. In the second phase from 100 to 200°C, there was the breakdown of capping agent, which resulted in combustion of capping agent attached to the surface of NS, which might be connected with oleuropein originated organic compound (C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>10</sub>O<sub>3</sub>). The thermal decomposition of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS observed in the third phase at 600°C was due to high temperature oxygen decay. TGA findings are shown in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Graphical presentation of thermal gravimetric analysis (TGA) of the green fabricated NS showing the progressive decomposition of capping agent with increasing temperature.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Characterization of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><sec><title>FTIR Studies of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>FTIR analysis revealed the successful reduction of precursor ionic complexes of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>. The reading around 2,800 cm<sup>-1</sup> represents the presence of surface adsorbed H-O-H molecules. The vibration modes from 2,500 to 4,000 cm<sup>-1</sup> are showing C-O, O-H and H-H bond order frequencies. Cu-O identification peaks were traced at 592, 607, and 665 cm<sup>-1</sup>. While Ce-O stretching bond frequencies were found at 453 cm<sup>-1</sup>.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>FTIR spectra of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS green-synthesized using olive leaf extract.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>XRD Studies of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>XRD results are important to predict the crystallite size, crystal shape, grain boundaries, phase purity, doping results, and total surface area of engineered NS. <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold> represents the typical XRD spectrum of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS prepared after calcination. Both of the samples reflect absolute pure crystalline phase with no additional peaks indicating that there are no other impurities. In case of CuO-NS, all of the Braggs peaks are well corresponding to JCPDS-05-0661 (Card-No.), while the Braggs peaks of CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS are similar to JCPDS-340394 (Card No.). This similarity index clearly indicates the pure crystalline morphology of green synthesized NS. CuO-NS crystallite size calibrated through Scherer approximation is 5 nm while CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS crystallite size is found 6 nm. Crystallographic design validates that each Ce atom in a crystallite is surrounded by eight oxygen atoms showing face-centered cubic geometry.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>XRD analysis of prepared CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SEM Analysis of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>As revealed by the SEM imaging (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold>), all the prepared NS were spherical and highly homogenous and the average size of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS was 22 ± 02 and 24 ± 04 nm, respectively.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>SEM images of <bold>(A)</bold> CuO-NS <bold>(B)</bold> CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Activity of Green-Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p><bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref></bold> shows the ZOI exhibited by CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS treatment against the tested MDR pathogens. All the strains were successfully inhibited by both CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS. The maximum ZOI against <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was 18.3 mm and 21.2 mm, respectively, for CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS. Moreover, due to the divergent physio-chemical characteristics of Cu and Ce, both of them have shown differential inhibitory behavior. Olive leaf extract has also shown mild inhibitory action with maximum ZOI of 8 mm against <italic toggle="yes">E. cloacae</italic>.</p><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>Graph showing the zone of inhibition recorded for various MDR pathogens against CuO-NS, CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS, plant extract, roxithromycin (positive control) and deionized water (negative control).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cytotoxicity and Biocompatibility Testing of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS on HEK-293 Cells and Brine Shrimp Larvae</title><p><bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref></bold> represents the effect of different concentrations (0.01, 0.05, and 0.1 mg/mL) of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS on HEK-293 cell lines. It is quite obvious from the findings that both of the NS show no or mild cytotoxicity to the HEK-293 cells even at relatively high concentration of 0.1 mg/mL. Mild cytotoxicity was observed for green synthesized NS at very high concentration of 0.05 mg/mL.</p><fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 8</label><caption><p>Effect of green synthesized NS on HEK-293 cell viability.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g008.jpg"/></fig><p>We have selected Brine shrimps, as their early developmental stages are very sensitive to toxic agents, and the toxicity symptoms could be easily observed. Biocompatibility assay with Brine shrimps larvae shows that both CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS are non-toxic to them up to 10 mg/mL. When increasing the concentration of to 15 mg/mL, CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS caused 20 and 30% mortality, respectively (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>). At this concentration, 100% mortality of larvae was observed in doxorubicin treatment.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Analysis of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS, toxicity to Brine shrimp larvae.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Different concentration of NS applied<hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">5 mg/mL</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">10 mg/mL</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">15 mg/mL</th></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% M</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% M</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% M</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CuO-NS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Olive</italic> extract</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Negative) control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxorubicin (positive control)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic toggle="yes">T, no. of A. salina added; L, alive A. salina after 24 h; %M, % mortality.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Role of Phyto-Reductants and Capping Agents for Tailoring CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>The abundance of oleuropein over other phenolic compounds was observed in HPLC chromatogram of olive leaf extract (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>), as reported in previous studies (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Maalej et al., 2017</xref>). Oleuropein is highly unstable molecule and will rapidly breakdown into more polarizable hydroxytyrosol (C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>10</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) usually in organic solvents (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2016</xref>). This molecule might have been involved in the capping action around high-energy planes (atoms) in tailoring CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS in the present study. It could simultaneously act as phyto-reducing and phyto-capping agent during the NS synthesis. TGA findings (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref></bold>) supplement the HPLC observations. When the green synthesized NS were subjected to increasingly high temperature, there was a breakdown of surface capping agent (hydroxytyrosol), which resulted in the combustion of bio-capping agent attached to the surface of NS. The thermal decomposition of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS around at 600°C was due to high temperature oxygen decay (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">El-Nahhal et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool, 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of Green-Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>FTIR was used to analyze the chemical composition and surface chemical coordinates of the CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS (<bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). The vibration modes from 2,500 to 4,000 cm<sup>-1</sup> are showing C-O, O-H, and H-H bond order frequencies (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool, 2017</xref>). Cu-O identification peaks were traced at 592, 607, and 665 cm<sup>-1</sup>. While Ce-O stretching bond frequencies were found at 453 cm<sup>-1</sup>. Corresponding findings related to Cu-O and Ce-O are well indexed to previously reported studies (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Zayyoun et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Crystallite size, crystal shape, grain boundaries, phase purity, doping results, and total surface area of engineered NS are important factors for antibacterial performance. Smaller crystallite size will provide greater penetration capabilities with maximum absorption rate (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al., 2018</xref>). Smaller will be the crystallite size, greater will be the value of quantum confinement effect, which is responsible for the overall reactivity and surface activation of the electron during the reaction (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Thanh et al., 2014</xref>). NS synthesized in the present study possess ideal reduction in crystallite size (see <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref></bold>) with an overall homogenous morphology which augmented greater reactivity to their structure for antimicrobial applications.</p><p>Since the size and shape of NS will define their reactivity, surface area, rate of absorption into microbial cell, cell surface interaction, protein binding etc. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Adhikari et al., 2018</xref>), these parameters are of prime importance for antimicrobial applications. SEM findings as presented in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref></bold> supports green synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS behavior for greater penetration to tissue.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Potential of Green-Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS</title><p>Due to the divergent physio-chemical characteristics of Cu and Ce, both of them have shown differential inhibitory behavior. Phyto-reductants from olive leaf extract have also shown mild inhibitory actions and these bactericidal properties of olive plant extract are well known in literature (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Maalej et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>The observed difference in the ZOI between bacterial strains may be due to unique bacterial cell wall morphology that assists pathogens to oppose against applied antimicrobial NS. In addition to this, other characteristics like the rate of NS diffusion across bacterial envelop, chemical properties, binding activation energy, ionic discharge and surface charge attraction also play the key role against a range of bacterial pathogens (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Wang L. et al., 2017</xref>). Gram negative pathogens also possess structural differences in cell wall like the deposition of lipopolysaccharide material which augments more virulence to them. Furthermore, it has been commonly observed that green synthesized NS own low level of genotoxic and cytotoxic nature for normal somatic cells with proven efficiency as compare to NS produced by other physical or chemical methods (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Devipriya and Roopan, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2017</xref>). Doped or undoped CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS engineered by various chemical procedures also showed cytotoxicity to healthy cells (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbas et al., 2017a</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dekkers et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Current findings explore that green-synthesized NS are of extremely small size, homogenous morphology, smaller crystallite size, enhanced surface area, and are of pure chemical nature. All these properties cumulatively contributed toward supreme antibacterial action. Smaller size and positively charged NS can easily be attracted by negatively charged bacterial surface. This electrostatic force of attraction is quite helpful in auto-phagocytosis of NS inside the bacterial cellular environment (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Maqbool et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Normally, it has been observed that due to the presence of additional mucus layer (lipopolysaccharide), it is a tough task for any drug molecule to penetrate across it. But due to the optimized charged surface, NS probably can penetrate through cellular covering. In some of the previously observed bactericidal activities, thiol (-SH) group present in the bacterial cell surface protein also have shown strong affection for metal oxide NS, due to which NS may also involve in denaturation of bacterial surface proteins (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">El-Nahhal et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Cu possesses variable oxidation state between Cu<sup>+</sup> and Cu<sup>2+</sup>. This is primarily because most of the transition metals can involve either 3 d or 4 s shells for electron shuffling (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Wang S. et al., 2017</xref>). It is commonly observed that variable oxidation states of metal ions can produce lethal ROS when exposed to the cellular environment. Ce also own variable oxidation state of Ce<sup>3+</sup> and Ce<sup>4+</sup>, which also supports ROS burst and activation of redox process during antibacterial action (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Charbgoo et al., 2017</xref>). Metal ions from NS are even more reactive and highly responsible for ROS generation. In our study, the antibacterial activity might also be strongly linked to the photo-activation of ROS by NS on bacterial growth as hypothesized in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref></bold>. Lethal ROS species (OH<sup>-</sup>, <sub>1</sub>O<sup>2-</sup>, <sup>∗</sup>O<sub>2</sub>) interact with the cellular environment and produce greater oxidative stress. Increase in oxidative stress causes direct genome destruction, plasmid and cell protein denaturation, ROS-induced mitochondrial damage and partial or absolute loss of cell wall permeability (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Kung et al., 2017</xref>). The multimode of actions performed by green fabricated CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS causes complete growth inhibition of all of the MDR bacterial strains.</p><fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>FIGURE 9</label><caption><p>Biocompatibility of green synthesized NS (ROS generation in bacterial cell causes lethal effects, while NS applied on Brine Shrimp are shown non-toxic).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fphar-09-00987-g009.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Bio-Compatibility Testing of Green Synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS on HEK-293 Cells and Brine Shrimp Larvae</title><p>It is very important that while targeting the pathogen, NS must not harm the somatic cell environment. NS synthesized from the physical or chemical methods are found toxic to healthy cells (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Asharani et al., 2008</xref>). This is probably due to the extensive use of hazardous acid base synthetic reagents in NS preparation by these methods (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dekkers et al., 2017</xref>). On the other hand, green chemistry proves to be an efficient and most reliable method to engineer highly biocompatible NS (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Abbas et al., 2017b</xref>). Moreover, mild cytotoxicity activities of green-synthesized NS are probably due to high concentration metal ion intoleration, NS sedimentation, loss of NS-homeostasis, genotoxicity, or lethal ROS induction (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016</xref>). Overall testing concludes that CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS are differentially cytotoxic toward gram-negative bacteria as compared to normal body cells.</p><p>Cytotoxic assay (<bold>Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></bold>) evidently demonstrated that both CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS are not toxic to Brine shrimp larvae. In order to achieve efficient drug development, it is vital to have the understanding of the toxicity of synthesized NS. Normally it has been observed that metal oxide NS show differential cytotoxicity when applied on healthy cells (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Abbas et al., 2016</xref>). In the current study, olive leaf extract mediated synthesis of NS demonstrates greater biocompatibility with the least lethal effect on Brine shrimps larvae as shown in <bold>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref></bold>. Even at higher dosage, minor lethality was reported. This mild lethal effect shown by CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS (30% with 15 mg/mL) is probably due to sedimentation of heavy Ce-metal ions, alteration in cellular metabolism and lethal ROS production (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gliga et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We have successfully fabricated the CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS using bio-reductants from olive leaf extract and have achieved the following outcomes:</p><list list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple"><list-item><label>•</label><p>HPLC analysis of plant extract and TGA findings of CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS confirms the successful capping action performed by phytochemicals around NS. The NS are of extremely small size (SEM results) and homogenous.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>XRD findings validate the pure chemistry of green-synthesized CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS with small crystallite size.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>FTIR spectrum demonstrates single phase and pure chemical nature of chemically bonded Cu-O and Ce-O in prepared CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS, respectively.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>Although the green fabricated CuO-NS and CeO<sub>2</sub>-NS could completely inhibit the growth of MDR bacterial strains, they are not toxic to healthy HEK-293 cells and Brine shrimp larvae.</p></list-item></list><p>So, green synthesis proves to be the most reliable method for achieving biocompatible NS. We believe that NS reported in the present study might have the potential to fight against antibiotic resistant pathogenic bacteria in the near future.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>QM and MN contributed to major part of the research work. GF provided his expert opinion and technical expertise related to the accomplishment of biomedical application part. The remaining authors contributed equally.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work has received funding from Narodowe Centrum Nauki (NCN), Poland, Grant No. UMO-2016/21/B/NZ9/01980. QM is supported by Ph.D. grant from the NCN Project No. UMO-2016/23/B/NZ902677. GF is supported by European Union’s 7th Framework Program for research, technological development, and demonstration under grant agreement no. 621321 and co-financed by funds allocated for education through project no. W26/7.PR/2015 (GA 3413/7.PR/2015/2) for the years 2015–2019.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>M. O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017a</year>). <article-title>ROS mediated malignancy cure performance of morphological, optical, and electrically tuned Sn doped CeO<sub>2</sub> nanostructures.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">AIP Adv.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>095205</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4990790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S. Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwaar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>Green synthesised zinc oxide nanostructures through Periploca aphylla extract shows tremendous antibacterial potential against multidrug resistant pathogens.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">IET Nanobiotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2016.0238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29155392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8676301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider Naqvi</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Inhibition of Neuroblastoma cancer cells viability by ferromagnetic Mn doped CeO2 monodisperse nanoparticles mediated through reactive oxygen species.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mater. Chem. Phys.</italic></source>
<volume>173</volume>
<fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.MATCHEMPHYS.2016.01.042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>“Impact of copper oxide nanoparticles on growth of different bacterial species,” in</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Energy and Environment. Water Science and Technology Library</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadava</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-10-5798-4_5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anwaar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The effect of green synthesized CuO nanoparticles on callogenesis and regeneration of <italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>1330</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5005396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27630655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asharani</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valiyaveettil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Toxicity of silver nanoparticles in zebrafish models.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nanotechnology</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>:<issue>255102</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0957-4484/19/25/255102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21828644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caballero-Calero</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Agosta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Review—towards the next generation of thermoelectric materials: tailoring electronic and phononic properties of nanomaterials.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">ECS J. Solid State Sci. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>N3065</fpage>–<lpage>N3079</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1149/2.0111703jss</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charbgoo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darroudi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Cerium oxide nanoparticles: green synthesis and biological applications.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Nanomedicine</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1401</fpage>–<lpage>1413</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S124855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28260887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5325136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephen Inbaraj</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Various physicochemical and surface properties controlling the bioactivity of cerium oxide nanoparticles.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Crit. Rev. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07388551.2018.1426555</pub-id> [Epub ahead of print].<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29402135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekkers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schins</surname><given-names>R. P. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Römer</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandebriel</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The effect of zirconium doping of cerium dioxide nanoparticles on pulmonary and cardiovascular toxicity and biodistribution in mice after inhalation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nanotoxicology</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17435390.2017.1357214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28741972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devipriya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roopan</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Cissus quadrangularis</italic> mediated ecofriendly synthesis of copper oxide nanoparticles and its antifungal studies against <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus niger</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus flavus</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Mater. Sci. Eng. C</italic></source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.MSEC.2017.05.130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28866178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Nahhal</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammad</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hempelmann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Bhaisi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and characterization of silica-, meso-silica- and their functionalized silica-coated copper oxide nanomaterials.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Sol Gel Sci. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10971-016-4034-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gliga</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edoff</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Källman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Cerium oxide nanoparticles inhibit differentiation of neural stem cells.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>9284</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-09430-9438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5570910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28839176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzelak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojewódzka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meczynska-Wielgosz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuberek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojciechowska</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruszewski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Crucial role of chelatable iron in silver nanoparticles induced DNA damage and cytotoxicity.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Redox Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.REDOX.2018.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29351884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5975067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venugopal</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Synthesis and structural analysis of different CuO nano particles.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Appl. Sci. Eng.</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6703/IJASE.2017.14(3).133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P.-Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.-J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>B.-W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Silver decorated copper oxide (Ag@CuO) nanocomposite enhances ROS-mediated bacterial architecture collapse.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Colloids Surf. B Biointerfaces</italic></source>
<volume>155</volume>
<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.COLSURFB.2017.04.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28460302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Influence of dissolved organic matter on photogenerated reactive oxygen species and metal-oxide nanoparticle toxicity.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Water Res.</italic></source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.WATRES.2016.03.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27064207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subhan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jazayeri</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanniasinkam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obied</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Plant phenols as antibiotic boosters: in vitro interaction of olive leaf phenols with ampicillin.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Phyther. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.5562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26931616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C. V. H.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prud’homme</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Nanoparticle targeting of Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria for magnetic-based separations of bacterial pathogens.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Nanosci.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13204-017-0548-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maalej</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouallagui</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadrich</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isoda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Assessment of <italic toggle="yes">Olea europaea</italic> L. fruit extracts: phytochemical characterization and anticancer pathway investigation.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed. Pharmacother.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.BIOPHA.2017.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28360012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Green-synthesised cerium oxide nanostructures (CeO<sub>2</sub> NS) show excellent biocompatibility for phyto-cultures as compared to silver nanostructures (Ag-NS).</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">RSC Adv.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>56575</fpage>–<lpage>56585</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c7ra12082f</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9264114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35876755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iftikhar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Green fabricated CuO nanobullets via <italic toggle="yes">Olea europaea</italic> leaf extract shows auspicious antimicrobial potential.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">IET Nanobiotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1049/iet-nbt.2016.0125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28530197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8676164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kausar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial potential of green synthesized CeO<sub>2</sub> nanoparticles from <italic toggle="yes">Olea europaea</italic> leaf extract.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Nanomedicine</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>5015</fpage>–<lpage>5025</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S113508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27785011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5063554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maria Magdalane</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaviyarasu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Judith Vijaya</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddhardha</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeyaraj</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Facile synthesis of heterostructured cerium oxide/yttrium oxide nanocomposite in UV light induced photocatalytic degradation and catalytic reduction: synergistic effect of antimicrobial studies.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Photochem. Photobiol. B Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>173</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.JPHOTOBIOL.2017.05.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28554073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marslin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siram</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvakesavan</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruszka</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachlicki</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Secondary metabolites in the green synthesis of metallic nanoparticles.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Materials</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>940</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma11060940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6024997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29865278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Production of dihydrochalcone-rich green rooibos (<italic toggle="yes">Aspalathus linearis</italic>) extract taking into account seasonal and batch-to-batch variation in phenolic composition of plant material.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">S. Afr. J. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.SAJB.2016.02.198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Antibiotic resistance determinant-focused <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> vaccine designed using reverse vaccinology.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Mol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>:<issue>458</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms18020458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5343991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28230771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piasecka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawikowska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachlicki</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Combined mass spectrometric and chromatographic methods for in-depth analysis of phenolic secondary metabolites in barley leaves.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J. Mass Spectrom.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jms.3557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25800187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puzyn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasulev</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajewicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasari</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michalkova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Using nano-QSAR to predict the cytotoxicity of metal oxide nanoparticles.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nat. Nanotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2011.10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rather</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bajpai</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Self-medication and antibiotic resistance: crisis, current challenges, and prevention.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Saudi J. Biol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.SJBS.2017.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28490950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5415144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saravanakumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaprakash</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohankumar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Low-cost and eco-friendly green synthesis of silver nanoparticles using <italic toggle="yes">Prunus japonica</italic> (Rosaceae) leaf extract and their antibacterial, antioxidant properties.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Artif. Cells Nanomed. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>1165</fpage>–<lpage>1171</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21691401.2016.1203795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27396523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanh</surname><given-names>N. T. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahiddine</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Mechanisms of nucleation and growth of nanoparticles in solution.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chem. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>7610</fpage>–<lpage>7630</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr400544s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25003956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The antimicrobial activity of nanoparticles: present situation and prospects for the future.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Nanomedicine</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1227</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S121956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28243086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5317269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cazelles</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>W.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vázquez-González</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoabi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Reziq</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Mimicking horseradish peroxidase and NADH peroxidase by heterogeneous Cu <sup>2+</sup> -modified graphene oxide nanoparticles.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Nano Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>2043</fpage>–<lpage>2048</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.7b00093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28183178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Synthesis, properties, and applications of hollow micro-/nanostructures.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chem. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>116</volume>
<fpage>10983</fpage>–<lpage>11060</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.5b00731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27156483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamun</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A review on antibiotic resistance: alarm bells are ringing.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Cureus</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>e1403</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.1403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5573035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28852600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zayyoun</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahmad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laânab</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaber</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The effect of pH on the synthesis of stable Cu2O/CuO nanoparticles by sol–gel method in a glycolic medium.</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Appl. Phys. A</italic></source>
<volume>122</volume>:<issue>488</issue>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00339-016-0024-29</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>