
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci. Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BSR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6499500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6499500.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6499500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6499500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30962271</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20181196</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>21</subject><subject>39</subject><subject>47</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>miR-517a is up-regulated in glioma and promotes glioma tumorigenesis <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0128-9606</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names initials="CL">Cheng-li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names initials="F">Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="KQ">Ke-qin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Neurosurgery, Nanxishan Hospital of Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, Chongxin Road No. 46, Guilin 541002, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Cheng-li Du (<email>duchengli6688@sina.com</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>08</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">334154</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20181196</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9620486"><article-title>Expression of Concern: miR-517a is upregulated in glioma and promotes glioma tumorigenesis in vitro and in vivo</article-title><volume>42</volume><issue>10</issue><date><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-2018-1196_EOC</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-2018-1196_EOC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9620486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36287110</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="43" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9842945"><article-title>Retraction: miR-517a is upregulated in glioma and promotes glioma tumorigenesis in vitro and in vivo</article-title><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><date><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-2018-1196_RET</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-2018-1196_RET</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9842945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36645304</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>miR-517a has been reported to act as an oncogenic miRNA in human hepatocellular carcinoma and lung cancer. However, the roles and underlying molecular mechanism of miR-517a in glioma remain unclear. In the present study, the expression of miR-517a in clinical glioma tissues and glioma cell lines was examined by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). Transfected with knockdown or forced expression of miR-517a, the effects of miR-517a on cell proliferation, migration, and invasion were detected through <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> tumorigenesis assays. Here, we report that miR-517a expression was up-regulated in glioma tissues when compared with normal brain tissues, and up-regulation of miR-517a level is tightly correlated with the status of pathology classification of glioma. A functional assay found that overexpression of miR-517a in glioma cells markedly promoted or suppressed cell proliferation, colony formation, migration and invasion, respectively. Moreover, we revealed that the knockdown of miR-517a dramatically suppressed glioma cell growth, migration, and invasion <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Furthermore, we found that knockdown of miR-517a significantly induced apoptosis. Therefore, miR–517a acts an oncogenic miRNA that promotes tumor progression in glioma, and thus may become a promising therapeutic candidate for glioma.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>apoptosis</kwd><kwd>glioma</kwd><kwd>invasion</kwd><kwd>migration</kwd><kwd>miR-517a</kwd><kwd>proliferation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Malignant gliomas are the most common primary tumors of the central nervous system. They are characterized by high invasion, migration, and proliferation abilities [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref>]. Despite recent advances in our understanding of the molecular mechanisms of the disease – and improvement in therapeutic strategies – the median survival of GBM patients still remains dismal, with less than 1 year after diagnosis [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thus, it is quite urgent to understand the molecular mechanisms by which glioma initiates, progresses, invades, and recurs in order to develop effective prognostic biomarkers and novel therapies.</p><p>miRNAs are endogenous, small, non-coding RNAs that regulate gene expression by antisense complementarity to specific mRNA. MiRNAs are short non-coding RNAs that interfere with target gene expression through either inhibition of mRNA translation or promotion of mRNA degradation [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Recent works have suggested that deregulation of a group of small non-coding RNAs called miRNAs is involved in initiation and progression of gliomas, including miR-335 [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], miR-218 [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], miR-15b, miR-152 [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], miR-92b [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], miR-145 [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and miR-124 [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. miR-517a is considered to be a novel oncomiR and was observed to be elevated in human hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; expression of miR-517a increased proliferation, migration, and invasion of HCC cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A recent study reported that miR-517a accelerated lung cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion through inhibiting forkhead box J3 (FOXJ3) expression [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, the regulatory mechanism of miR-517a in glioma remains largely unclear.</p><p>In the present study, we investigated the putative role of miR–517a in the progression of glioma. We found that the expression of miR–517a was frequently increased in clinical glioma tissue samples compared with normal brain tissues, and up-regulation of miR–517a level is tightly correlated with the status of pathology classification. Furthermore, through <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and in mouse xenograft model, we investigated the function of miR-517a in glioma, including the proliferation, migration, invasion, and apoptosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Clinical samples</title><p>We obtained 60 snap-frozen glioma and 20 normal brain samples from Nanxishan Hospital of Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, including 20 grade II tumors, 20 grade III tumors, and 20 grade IV tumors according to the WHO classification. All specimens had confirmed pathological diagnosis and were classified according to the WHO criteria (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These glioma cases were from 38 males and 22 females with age ranging from 19 to 72 years. The purpose and content of the present study were explained fully to all subjects, whose signed informed consent was obtained prior to enrollment. Written informed consent was obtained from each patient. Our study was conducted in accordance with the World Medical Association’s Helsinki guidelines and was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Nanxishan Hospital of Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, China.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinicopathological data of the patients included in the present study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>All patients</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Male</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Female</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;65 year old</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>≥65 year old</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Grade</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>I</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>II</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>III</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Cell lines</title><p>The LN18, U87, and U118 glioma cell lines and primary normal human astrocytes (NHAs) were purchased from the Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China). Cells were cultured in DMEM (GIBCO-BRL) medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 mg/ml streptomycin (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, U.S.A.) at 37°C/5% CO<sub>2</sub>. All cell lines were authenticated by short tandem repeat DNA profiling.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>RNA isolation, reverse transcription, and qRT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Total RNA (500 ng) was reverse transcribed in a final volume of 10 μl using random primers under standard conditions for the PrimeScript RT reagent Kit (TaKaRa, Dalian, China). We used the SYBR Premix Ex Taq (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) to determine ANRIL expression levels, following the manufacturer’s instructions. For miR-517a, RNA was transcribed into complementary DNA and amplified with specific sense, 5′ -ATTGGGGCTCGCGT-3′, according to the manufacturer’s instructions (Takara Bio, Inc.). U6 (sense primer: 5′-CTCGCTTCGG CAGCACATATA-3′) genes were used as miRNA and gene internal controls, respectively. Cycling conditions were 95°C for 10 min to activate DNA polymerase, followed by 45 cycles of 95 °C for 15 s, 58 °C for 15 s, and 72 °C for 10 s. Specificity of amplification products was confirmed by melting curve analysis. PCR reactions for each gene were repeated three times. Independent experiments were done in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Stable expression or knockdown of miR-517a in glioma cell lines</title><p>Lentiviral vectors which overexpressed or knockdown miR-517a were purchased from GenePharma (Shanghai, China). A lentiviral vector expressing scrambled RNA was used as the control and the sequence was 5′-TTAACGTCGATGTCCGT-3′. Glioma cell lines were infected with lentiviral vector. Total RNA from these cell clones was isolated, and levels of miR-517a were quantified using RT-qPCR.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Western blot assay and antibodies</title><p>Cells were lysed using mammalian protein extraction reagent RIPA (Beyotime) supplemented with protease inhibitors cocktail (Roche) and phenylmethylsulfonyl-fluoride (Roche). Fifty micrograms of protein extractions were separated by 10% SDS–PAGE, transferred to 0.22 mm nitrocellulose (NC) membranes (Sigma) and incubated with specific antibodies. Autoradiograms were quantified by densitometry (Quantity One software; Bio-Rad). Information on the antibodies is provided: Bad (1:1000 dilution CST- 9292); Bax (1:1000 dilution CST- 2772); Bcl-2 (1:1000 dilution CST- 15071); Cleaved Caspase-3 (1:1000 dilution CST- 9661), and β-actin (1:1000 dilution CST-4970).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>MTT assay</title><p>A cell proliferation assay was conducted with MTT kit according to the manufacturer’s instruction. Triplicate wells were measured in each treatment group.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Colony formation assay</title><p>For the cells to form colonies, a total of 600 LN18 or U118 cells transfected with miR–517a mimic or scramble mi-RNA were placed onto a fresh six-well plate and maintained in media containing 10% FBS, replacing the medium every 4 days. After 2 weeks, the colonies were fixed with methanol and stained with 0.1 % crystal violet (Sigma, St. Louis, MO). The visible colonies were manually counted. Triplicate wells were assessed for each treatment group.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Transwell assay</title><p>Matrigel-coated invasion chambers (8 μm, BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, U.S.A.) were prepared according the manufacturer’s instructions. Transfected GBM cells were seeded in the upper compartment and allowed to migrate for 24 h in an incubator. Cells were seeded in 1% FBS DMEM medium in the upper chamber and 10% FBS medium in the well below the insert. The cells that had invaded the lower surface were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and stained with 0.1% crystal violet. The number of cells that had invaded through the Matrigel was counted in six random fields for triplicate membranes under the microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Flow-cytometric analysis</title><p>After the double staining with FITC-Annexin V and propidium iodide (PI) was done using the FITC Annexin V Apoptosis Detection Kit (BD Biosciences) according to the manufacturer’s recommendations, the cells were analyzed with a flow cytometry (FACScan®; BD Biosciences) equipped with a CellQuest software (BD Biosciences). Cells were discriminated into viable cells, dead cells, early apoptotic cells and apoptotic cells, and then the relative ratio of early apoptotic cells were compared with control transfectant from each experiment. Cells for cell cycle analysis were stained with PI using the CycleTEST™ PLUS DNA Reagent Kit (BD Biosciences) following the protocol and analyzed by FACScan.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Tumor formation assay in a nude mouse model</title><p>Female athymic BALB/c nude mice (4-week-old) were maintained under pathogen-free conditions and manipulated according to protocols approved by the Shanghai Medical Experimental Animal Care Commission. U87 cells were stably transfected with sh-miR-517a and empty vector and harvested from 6-well cell culture plates. A total of 100 μl of suspended cells was subcutaneously injected into a single side of the posterior flank of each mouse. Tumor growth was examined every 3 days, and tumor volumes were calculated using the equation V = 0.5 × D × d2 (V, volume; D, longitudinal diameter; d, latitudinal diameter). At 18 days post-injection, mice were killed, and the subcutaneous growth of each tumor was examined.</p><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (two-tailed), one-way ANOVA, and Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test were conducted to analyze the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> data by SPSS 20.0 software. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec4"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec4-1"><title>Up-regulation of miR-517a in human glioma tissues and cell lines</title><p>To explore the expression and significance of miR-517a in glioma, we first examined the expression level of miR-517a in 60 snap-frozen glioma tissues and 20 normal brain tissues by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). Compared with normal brain tissues, significant increase of miR-517a was observed in glioma tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Meanwhile, we also observed that increased levels of miR-517a in glioma patients were positively correlated with the status of pathology classification (WHO II vs WHO IV; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01). A gradually increased miR-517a expression was found from grade II to IV samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). In addition, qRT-PCR was performed on a panel of three human glioma cell lines (LN18, U87, and U118) and primary NHA. Up-regulation of miR-517a could also be observed in glioma cell lines than that of NHA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). These results suggested that miR-517a could be closely related to human glioma and up-regulation of miR-517a might be related to glioma oncogenesis and progression.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>miR-517a expression is up-regulated in glioma tissue samples and cell lines</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The expression levels of miR-517a in glioma tissues and normal brain tissues were determined by qRT-PCR. U6 was used as a loading control. Increased levels of miR-517a was positively correlated with the status of pathology classification by qRT-PCR. The unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>test was used for this assay. (<bold>B</bold>) Expression levels of miR-517a in three glioma cell lines (LN18, U87, and U118) and primary NHAs were determined by qRT-PCR. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 vs NHAs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-2"><title>Overexpression of miR-517a promotes growth of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>To further explore its biological roles in glioma, miR-517a overexpression lentiviral vector (Lv-miR-517a) and lentiviral empty vector (miR-NC) were transfected into human glioma LN18 and U118 cells. After transfection, the expression level of miR-517a was significantly up-regulated compared with the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). We then performed colony formation assay to determine the cell proliferation in each group, and showed that up-regulation of miR-517a significantly increased LN18 and U118 cells proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B,C). Additionally, MTT assay indicated that up-regulation of miR-517a also substantially promoted the proliferation ability in LN18 and U251 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D). These results demonstrated that miR-517a could promote the proliferation phenotype of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>miR-517a promotes glioma cell growth <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Real-time RT-PCR was conducted to determine the relative miR–517a level in glioma LN18 and U118 cells transfected with miR–517a mimic or scramble miR-NC. (<bold>B,C</bold>) <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> proliferative ability of glioma cells was significantly decreased in overexpressed miR-517a cells compared with miR-NC cells by colony formation assay in LN18 (upper) and U118 (lower) cells. (<bold>D</bold>) MTT assay was performed to determine cell proliferation in LN18 (upper) and U118 (lower) cells. Non-transfected LN18 and U118 cells were used as control. Absorbance was read at 490 nm with averages from triplicate wells. Data are presented as mean ± SD from three independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 and ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.005 vs miR-NC.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-3"><title>Overexpression of miR-517a induced the invasion and migration of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>Next, we examined the effects of miR-517a on the ability of LN18 and U118 cells to invade and migrate. Cell migration and invasion abilities were determined in the LN18 and U251 cells transfected with the Lv-miR-517a or miR-NC by a transwell chamber or a Boyden chamber, respectively. Transwell assays with Matrigel demonstrated that LN18 and U118 cells-overexpressing miR-517a were found to have significantly increased migration and invasion abilities than control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Together, these data suggest that miR-517a is critical for glioma cells invasion and migration <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>miR-517a promotes migration and invasion of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Representative images of transwell invasion assay using LN18 and U118 cells stably expressing miR-517a or mi-NC. (<bold>B</bold>) Stably up-regulating miR-517a increased the migration and invasiveness ability of LN18 and U118 cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro.</italic> Data are presented as mean ± SD from three independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 and ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.005 vs miR-NC.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-4"><title>Knockdown of miR-517a inhibits glioma cell proliferation, migration, and invasion</title><p>To determine whether miR-517a had an effect on the malignant phenotype of glioma cells, we constructed lentiviral-mediated knockdown of miR-517a in the U87 cell line, which exhibited the highest miR-517a expression level among cell lines in our study. The miR-517a expression levels were knocked down more than 70% in U87 cell line relative to the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). Colony formation assay and MTT assay showed that knockdown of miR-517a decreased the proliferation ability in U87 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B,C). In addition, the transwell assays demonstrated that LN18 cells knockdown of miR-517a were found to have significantly reduced the migration and invasion abilities than control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effects of knockdown of miR-517a on the growth, migration, and invasion of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) U87 cells were transduced with anti-miR-517a or control. (<bold>B</bold>) Colony-forming assays were conducted to determine the proliferation of anti-miR-517a-transfected U87 cells. (<bold>C</bold>) MTT assays were used to determine the cell viability of anti-miR-517a-transfected U87 cells. Values represented the mean ± SD from three independent experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative images of transwell invasion assay using U87 cells transduced with anti-miR-517a or mi-NC. (B) Knockdown of miR-517a decreased the migration and invasiveness ability of U87 cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Data are presented as mean ± SD from three independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 and ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.005 vs miR-NC.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-5"><title>Knockdown of miR-517a induces apoptosis <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>To illustrate the mechanisms of how miR-517a modulates glioma cell growth, flow cytometry was applied to detect the effects of miR-517a on cell apoptosis. Annexin V/PI double staining demonstrated that the proportion of apoptosis LN18 cells transfected with anti-miR-184 was significantly higher than that in the anti-miR-NC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). Concordantly, the expression of caspase-3 cleavage and Bad were activated, the expression of Bax and Bcl-2 were markedly reduced in LN18 cells transfected with anti-miR-517a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B).</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>miR-517a knockdown induces apoptosis in U87 cell</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Apoptosis in U87 cell transduced with anti-miR-517a and control was performed by flow cytometry and the apoptotic index was defined as the percentage of apoptotic cells. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01. (<bold>B</bold>) Cleaved caspase-3, Bax, Bad2, and Bcl-2 were evaluated by Western blotting. The data represent the mean ± SD from three independent experiments. **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01 vs miR-NC.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-6"><title>Down-regulation of miR-517a inhibits glioma cell tumorigenesis <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>To explore whether the level of miR-517a expression could affect tumorigenesis, LN18 cells stably transfected with lentiviral-mediated anti-miR-517a or empty vector were inoculated into female nude mice. Eighteen days after the injection, the tumors formed in the anti-miR-517a group were substantially smaller than those in the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A,B). Moreover, the mean tumor weight at the end of the experiment was markedly lower in the anti-miR-517a group compared with the empty vector group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). Tumors formed from lentiviral anti-miR-517a-transfected LN18 cells exhibited decreased positivity for Ki67 than those from control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D). These findings indicate that knockdown of miR-517a inhibits tumor growth <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effects of down-regulation of miR-517a on tumor growth <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The tumor volume was calculated once every 3 days after injection of U87 cells stably transfected with sh-miR-517a or empty vector. Points, mean (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=7); bars indicate SD. (<bold>B</bold>) Tumor weights are represented as means of tumor weights ± SD. (<bold>C</bold>) Tumor growth curves are summarized. The error bars indicate the SD. (<bold>D</bold>) Tumors developed from sh-miR-517a-transfected U87 cells showed lower Ki67 protein levels than tumors developed by control cells. Upper: H&amp;E staining; Lower: immunostaining. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01, and N.S. not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20181196-g6.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p>Gliomas are well-known for not only rapid proliferation but also invading the surrounding brain tissue, leading to extremely poor prognosis. Similar to other tumors, some environmental carcinogenic factors may also be associated with the occurrence of glioma [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. miRNAs have emerged as key factors involved in several biological processes, including development, differentiation, cell proliferation, and tumorigenesis [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, it is possible that miRNAs may shed light on the potential mechanism of glioma. In the present study, our data provided the first evidences that expression of miR-517a was increased in glioma tissues compared with normal brain tissues. We further found that miR-517a expression was positively correlated with the status of pathology classification. These results suggest that miR-517a may promote the progression of glioma.</p><p>Chromosome 19 miRNA cluster (C19MC) on 19q13.41 have been considered so far to be the largest human miRNA gene cluster, which harbor 43 miRNA genes and extends over 100 kb long region [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Recent miRNA-related studies show that miR–517a has been proposed to be promoted in tumor metastasis of HCC and lung cancer [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Whereas, in bladder cancer miR-517a was down-regulated, and ectopic restoration of miR-517a significantly inhibited cell proliferation by promoting apoptosis [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. These studies suggest that miR–517a may have have different roles in different cancers. To comprehensively understand the effect of miR-517a on glioma cancer cells, we performed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> proliferation and invasion assays to identify the migration and invasion ability of glioma cells. Importantly, our study showed that knockdown of miR–517a significantly inhibited tumorigenesis as well as the tumor growth of glioma cells <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. These data further indicate that miR-517a indeed acts as a novel oncogenic miRNA in glioma cells.</p><p>Apoptosis, a fundamental process essential for development and maintenance of tissue homeostasis, is a major mechanism to eliminate cancer cells [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Thus, an effective strategy for cancer treatment seems to target signaling intermediates in the apoptosis-inducing pathways [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Here, we showed that knockdown of miR-517a induces apoptosis in LN18 cells. Consistently, the expression of caspase-3 cleavage and Bad were up-regulated, the expression of Bax and Bcl-2 were markedly down-regulated in LN18 cells transfected with anti-miR-517a, which is consistent with apoptosis induction. These data add further evidence for the oncogenesis role of miR-517a in glioma.</p><p>In summary, our results showed that miR-517a expression was frequently up-regulated in glioma specimens and cell lines, and increased levels of of miR–517a level was tightly correlated with the malignant progression. Our study <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> suggested that miR–517a acts as a novel oncogenic miRNA that promotes tumor cell proliferation, migration, and invasion of glioma cells by inducing apoptosis. The present study provides novel insights into the mechanism underlying the development and progression of glioma, and suggests that miR–517a may become a promising therapeutic candidate for glioma.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="sec6" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that there are no sources of funding to be acknowledged.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>Conception and design: C.D.; Administrative support: C.D. and F.P.; Provision of study materials or patients: C.D. and F.P.; Collection and assembly of data: K.L.; Data analysis and interpretation: K.L. and F.P.; Manuscript writing: All authors; Final approval of manuscript: All authors.</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term>Bad</term><def><p>Bcl-2-associated death promoter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Bax</term><def><p>Bcl-2-associated X protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Bcl-2</term><def><p>B-cell lymphoma-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBS</term><def><p>fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GBM</term><def><p>glioblastoma multiforme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCC</term><def><p>hepatocellular carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTT</term><def><p>Methylthiazolyldiphenyl-tetrazolium bromide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NHA</term><def><p>normal human astrocyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>propidium iodide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p>quantitative real-time PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIPA</term><def><p>Radio-Immunoprecipitation Assay</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furnari</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bachoo</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowitch</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavenee</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Malignant glioma: genetics and biology of a grave matter</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.891601</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emdad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Future approaches for the therapy of malignant glioma: targeting genes mediating invasion</article-title>. <source>Future Oncol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fon.12.16</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22515436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefranc</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brotchi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Possible future issues in the treatment of glioblastomas: special emphasis on cell migration and the resistance of migrating glioblastoma cells to apoptosis</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Oncol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2411</fpage>–<lpage>2422</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2005.03.089</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stupp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegi</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bent</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taphoorn</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janzer</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effects of radiotherapy with concomitant and adjuvant temozolomide versus radiotherapy alone on survival in glioblastoma in a randomised phase III study: 5-year analysis of the EORTC-NCIC trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70025-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19269895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>281e297</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(04)00045-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Targeting oncogenic miR-335 inhibits growth and invasion of malignant astrocytoma cell</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cancer</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-10-59</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21592405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3129318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>D.X.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-218 inhibits glioma invasion, migration, proliferation, and cancer stem-like cell self-renewal by targeting the polycomb group gene Bmi1</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>6046</fpage>–<lpage>6055</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-13-0358</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23950210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MiR-15b and miR- 152 reduce glioma cell invasion and angiogenesis via NRP-2 and MMP-3</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source>
<volume>329</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2012.10.026</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23142217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3553580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MiR-92b controls glioma proliferation and invasion through regulating Wnt/beta- catenin signaling via Nemo-like kinase</article-title>. <source>Neuro-oncology</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>588</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/neuonc/not004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3635522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MiR-145 reduces ADAM17 expression and inhibits in vitro migration and invasion of glioma cells</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Rep.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2012.2084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23076445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3540808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-124 inhibits migration and invasion by down-regulating ROCK1 in glioma</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e69478</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069478</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23936026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3720724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toffanin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoshida</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lachenmayer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabellos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minguez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-based classification of hepatocellular carcinoma and oncogenic role of miR-517a</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>140</volume>, <fpage>1618</fpage>–<lpage>1628</lpage>, <comment>e16</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21324318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3680790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MiR-517a-3p accelerates lung cancer cell proliferation and invasion through inhibiting FOXJ3 expression</article-title>. <source>Life Sci.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2014.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karsy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murali</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jhanwar-Uniyal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Involvement of mTORC1 and mTORC2 in regulation of glioblastoma multiforme growth and motility</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Oncol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>731</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19724909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijo_00000386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lando</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitelaw</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruick</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>FIH-1 is an asparaginyl hydroxylase enzyme that regulates the transcriptional activity of hypoxia-inducible factor</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1466</fpage>–<lpage>1471</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.991402</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12080085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC186346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Targeting HIF-1 for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc1187</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13130303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolin-Cavaillé</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dance</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavaillé</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>C19MC microRNAs are processed from introns of large Pol-II, non-protein-coding transcripts</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>3464</fpage>–<lpage>3473</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp205</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19339516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2691840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshitomi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enokida</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiyomaru</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kagara</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatarano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Restoration of miR-517a expression induces cell apoptosis in bladder cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Rep.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1661</fpage>–<lpage>1668</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21479368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2011.1253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniani</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derakhshan</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Baradaran</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of apoptosis and roles in cancer development and treatment.</article-title>
<source>Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2129</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25824729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7314/apjcp.2015.16.6.2129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Involvement of apoptotic pathways in docosahexaenoic acid-induced benefit in prostate cancer: Pathway-focused gene expression analysis using RT<sup>2</sup> Profile PCR Array System.</article-title>
<source>Lipids Health Dis</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-017-0442-5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28330470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5363041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>