
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Signal Transduct Target Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3308</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sigtrans</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101676423</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-9907</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2059-3635</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6895114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6895114.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6895114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6895114</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-019-0082-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">82</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RETRACTED ARTICLE: Dickkopf-1 contributes to hepatocellular carcinoma tumorigenesis by activating the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hao-Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broering</surname><given-names initials="R">Ruth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="XD">Xiang-de</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="XH">Xian-huan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="LB">Lei-bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="WR">Wen-rui</given-names></name><address><email>doctorrui@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="C">Chao</given-names></name><address><email>mdliuchao@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2360 039X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12981.33</institution-id><institution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Epigenetics and Gene Regulation and Department of Hepato-Pancreato-Biliary Surgery, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, </institution><institution>Sun Yat-sen University, </institution></institution-wrap>510120 Guangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2187 5445</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5718.b</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine, Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, </institution><institution>University Duisburg-Essen, </institution></institution-wrap>45147 Essen, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">327433</issue-id><elocation-id>54</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41392_2019_Article_82.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Signal Transduct Target Ther" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10162956"><article-title>Retraction Note: Dickkopf-1 contributes to hepatocellular carcinoma tumorigenesis by activating the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway</article-title><volume>8</volume><date><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>181</elocation-id><source>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10162956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37147281</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Dysregulation of dickkopf-related protein 1 (DKK1) expression has been reported in a variety of human cancers. We previously reported that DKK1 was upregulated in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). However, the role of DKK1 in HCC remains unclear. This study aimed to investigate the clinical significance and biological functions of DKK1 in HCC. The expression of DKK1 was examined in cirrhotic and HCC tissues by immunohistochemistry and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR). DKK1 was silenced or overexpressed in HCC cell lines, and in vitro and in vivo studies were performed. Immunohistochemistry revealed that DKK1 was weakly expressed in cirrhotic tissues (8/22, 36.4%) but upregulated in HCC tissues (48/53, 90.6%, cohort 1). Significant upregulation of DKK1 was observed in 57.6% (19/33, cohort 2) of HCC tissues by qRT-PCR, and the expression of DKK1 was associated with tumor size (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024) and tumor number (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.019). Genetic depletion of DKK1 impaired the proliferation, colony-forming ability, invasion, and tumor formation of HCC cells (HepG2 and HUH-7). Conversely, forced expression of DKK1 increased the proliferation, colony-forming ability, and invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro and enhanced tumor formation in vivo. Subsequent investigation revealed that the DKK1-mediated proliferation and tumorigenicity of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells is dependent on the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway. These findings indicate that DKK1 plays an oncogenic role in HCC by activating the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Oncogenes</kwd><kwd>Cancer genetics</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the most frequent cause of cancer-related death worldwide.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> Curative procedures such as hepatectomy and liver transplantation can only be offered to approximately 1/3 of HCC patients and are associated with high recurrence rates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> It is crucial to elucidate the underlying mechanism of HCC progression in order to develop therapeutic agents effective against HCC. Molecules that might be used as diagnostic/prognostic biomarkers or that inhibit HCC progression must be identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup></p><p id="Par3">Dickkopf-related protein 1 (DKK1) is a secreted protein that has been clearly identified as a direct inhibitor of Wnt/β-catenin signaling via the LRP5/6 coreceptor of Frizzled proteins.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> Accumulating evidence supports the involvement of DKK1 in human cancers. However, the role of DKK1 in tumor biology remains unclear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> The expression of DKK1 was reported to be downregulated in colorectal carcinoma and lung cancer cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> Accumulation of Musashi RNA-binding protein 1 (MRP-1) in HCC cells significantly promotes proliferation, tumor formation, and cell cycle progression via silencing of DKK1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> In contrast, upregulation of DKK1 has been found in a variety of human cancers, such as cholangiocarcinoma and pancreatic, esophageal, breast and kidney cancers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> In the liver, the expression of DKK1 is downregulated in human HCC, and upregulation of DKK1 in HCC was able to inhibit the invasion of HCC cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> However, Chen and his colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> reported that DKK1 enhances HCC cell invasion via the MMP-7 signaling pathway. Overexpression of DKK1 is associated with a poor prognosis in human HCC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> In addition, DKK1 can be used as a serum biomarker for the diagnosis of HCC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> It has been reported that HCC develops with increased frequency in hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg) transgenic mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> We previously reported that DKK1 was upregulated in HBsAg mouse liver tissues and in human HCC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> Ultimately, the specific role of DKK1 in HCC remains controversial. In this study, the expression of DKK1 was examined in cirrhotic and HCC tissues by immunohistochemistry and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR). The biological function of DKK1 was investigated in HCC cell lines (HepG2 and HUH-7) using proliferation, invasion, cell cycle, colony formation, and xenograft tumor formation assays.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par4">Patient characteristics, immunohistochemistry, cell line establishment and cell culture, quantitative RT-PCR, western blot analysis, cell proliferation analyses, cell colony analyses, cell cycle analyses, cell invasion analyses, and subcutaneous xenograft assays in nude mice were performed as described in the Supplementary Materials and Methods.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</title><p id="Par5">Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) was performed to investigate the expression of DKK1 in the supernatant of HCC cells with a Human DKK1 ELISA Kit (Elabscience, China). Briefly, a 96-well plate was precoated with anti-human DKK1 antibodies, and supernatant samples were diluted with sample dilution buffer and added to the wells. The plate was incubated for 90 min at 37 °C. After DKK1 was bound to the wells by the immobilized antibody, the liquid was removed from each well, and biotinylated anti-human DKK1 antibody was immediately added to the wells and incubated at 37 °C for 1 h. After washing three times, HRP-conjugated streptavidin was added after removal of unbound biotinylated antibody. The wells were washed again, and TMB substrate solution was added. Finally, the absorbance was measured at 450 nm by using an ELISA plate reader. According to the standard curve generated by serial dilution of recombinant human DKK1, the level of soluble DKK1 in each supernatant sample was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Virus production and transduction</title><p id="Par6">Lentiviral vectors (pGLV3/H1/GFP/Puro, pGHGV) expressing shRNA targeting human DKK1 or β-catenin or a negative control shRNA (listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>) were purchased from GenePharma (Shanghai, China). All shRNA sequences were subjected to Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) analysis to confirm the absence of homology to any additional known coding sequences. Full-length human DKK1 cDNA was PCR amplified, HA tagged, and inserted into the lentiviral vectors (pCDH/CMV/GFP/Puro, pCMGV) upstream of the internal ribosome entry (IRES) site. The DKK1 fragment was then isolated by <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic>I digestion and inserted into a DKK1 retroviral vector (pCMGV/DKK1). HepG2 and HUH-7 cells were infected with the pGHGV/shRNA-DKK1, pGHGV/shRNA-β-catenin, pCMGV/DKK1, or pCMGV vectors after 10 population doublings, as previously described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> After puromycin selection, loss or gain of DKK1 or β-catenin were confirmed by qRT-PCR and western blot analysis, and stable cell lines were established.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Confocal microscopy assay</title><p id="Par7">HepG2 and HUH-7 cells were grown to 50% confluence on glass coverslips in a 24-well plate. Following treatment, cells were fixed with 4% PFA, washed twice with PBS, and blocked for 30 min in PBS containing 10% goat serum and 0.1% saponin (DSP). Primary antibodies specific for DKK1 and β-catenin in DSP were added simultaneously for 2 h at room temperature. After washing three times with PBS, secondary antibodies in DSP were added for 2 h at room temperature. Coverslips were washed again three times with PBS and were then mounted on slides with DAPI Slow Fade. Representative images were acquired on a Leica TCS SP5 confocal microscope with an oil immersion objective at ×60magnification. Representative images are shown as enhanced using ImageJ software. The primary antibodies and secondary antibodies are listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>TCF/LEF reporter assay</title><p id="Par8">HepG2 and HUH-7 cells were plated at a density of 2 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well in 48-well plates and transfected with pGL3-blast or pGL3-LEF/TCF (purchased from MssBio, Guangzhou) using Lipofectamine<sup>TM</sup> 3000 according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Luciferase activity was assessed using a Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay system (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The primer sequences used for amplification of TCF/LEF are shown in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par9">All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS for Windows (version 17.0; SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). All experiments with cultured cells were carried out independently at least three times in experimental triplicate. All data are expressed as the means ± standard deviations (SDs) unless otherwise indicated. We determined the significance of differences in the human HCC data using Fisher’s exact test, in the in vitro data using Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, and in the in vivo data using the Mann–Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test. In all cases, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values of &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>DKK1 expression is upregulated in human HCC tissues</title><p id="Par10">Immunohistochemistry revealed positive staining for the DKK1 protein in the cytoplasm of tumor cells. In general, DKK1 was weakly expressed (DKK1−, 14/22, 63.6%; DKK1+, 8/22, 36.4%) in 22 human cirrhotic tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>). In contrast, upregulated DKK1 expression (DKK1++ or +++) was observed in 48 of 53 human HCC tumor samples (90.6%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c, d</xref>), while weak DKK1 expression (DKK1− or +) was found in the other five human HCC tumor samples (9.4%). qRT-PCR was performed to investigate the expression of DKK1 in 33 paired HCC and corresponding peritumoral tissues. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>, significant upregulation of DKK1 was found in 57.6% (19/33, cohort 2) of the HCC tissue specimens compared with the corresponding peritumoral tissue specimens. These findings indicate that DKK1 may participate in human HCC progression.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>DKK1 expression is increased in HCC tissues. The expression of DKK1 in human liver tissues was evaluated by immunohistochemistry and qRT-PCR. The results revealed weak expression (DKK1− or +) in 22 of 22 human cirrhotic tissue samples (<bold>a, b</bold>). Upregulated DKK1 expression (DKK1++ or +++) was observed in 48 of 53 human HCC tumor samples (<bold>c, d</bold>). Scale bar = 100 μm. Thirty-three pairs of fresh HCC and corresponding peritumoral liver tissues were used for qRT-PCR analysis (<bold>e</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e480" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>HCC-related DKK1 expression is associated with tumor size and number</title><p id="Par11">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, qRT-PCR revealed that upregulated DKK1 expression was correlated with tumor size (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024) and tumor number (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.019). However, DKK1 expression was not correlated with age (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.116), sex (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.142), capsular invasion (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.292), portal vein tumor thrombi (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 1.000), bile duct tumor thrombi (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.424), lymphatic metastasis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 1.000), tumor stage (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.238), histological grade (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.531), serum alpha fetoprotein level (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 1.000), serum CA19-9 level (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.698), serum CA125 level (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.707), or extrahepatic metastasis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.620).<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinicopathologic data of 33 Hepatocellular carcinoma patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Group</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">DKK1<break/>up</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">DKK1<break/>down</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.166</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt;50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capsular invasion</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.296</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Portal vein tumor thrombi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bile duct tumor thrombi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.424</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lymphatic metastasis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metastasis</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.620</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Yes</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> No</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor size (cm)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt;5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor number</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Single</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Multiple</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tumor stage (UICC, 2010)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.238</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> I + II</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> III + IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Histological grade</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.531</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> G1 + G2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> G3 + G4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HBsAg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Negative</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serum AFP (ng/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt;25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CA199 (μl/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.698</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt;35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CA125 (μl/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.707</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt;35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≤35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Compared via the chi-square test (Fisher’s exact test)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Transfection of DKK1-shRNA inhibits the proliferation, colony-forming ability, cell cycle progression, and invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro</title><p id="Par12">qRT-PCR and western blotting were performed to analyze the expression levels of DKK1 in DKK1-short hairpin RNA (shRNA) HCC cells (HepG2 and HUH-7). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>, DKK1 was effectively and functionally suppressed by DKK1-shRNA in the evaluated HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. To verify that DKK1 was functionally silenced by the shRNA, we utilized ELISA to measure the expression levels of DKK1 in the supernatant of HCC cells. The ELISA results revealed that the DKK1 level was decreased in the supernatant of cultured stable DKK1-shRNA HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a, b</xref>). We further examined whether decreased DKK1 expression affected the biological activities of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. The CCK-8 (Cell Counting Kit-8) assay results revealed that downregulation of DKK1 by DKK1-shRNA significantly inhibited the proliferation of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). The colony formation assay results revealed that fewer colonies were found in DKK1-shRNA-treated HepG2 and HUH-7 cells than in the corresponding control cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). In addition, the FACS analysis-based cell cycle progression assay results revealed that DKK1 suppression decreased the number of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in the S phase (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). The cell invasion assay results showed that the number of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells that migrated through the Transwell filter was markedly lower in the DKK1-shRNA group than in the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). Collectively, these data indicate that suppression of DKK1 not only inhibits the proliferation but also decreases the invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Transfection of DKK1-shRNA suppresses the proliferation, colony-forming ability, cell cycle progression, and invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro. Short hairpin RNA (shRNA)-DKK1 was transfected into HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. The stable cell lines were established after puromycin selection. Changes in DKK1 mRNA expression were determined by qRT-PCR (<bold>a</bold>). The levels of DKK1 were determined by western blot analysis (<bold>b</bold>). Transfection of DKK1-shRNA suppressed the proliferation (<bold>c</bold>), colony-forming ability (<bold>d</bold>), cell cycle progression (<bold>e</bold>), and invasion (<bold>f</bold>) of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1212" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Forced expression of DKK1 increases the proliferation, colony-forming ability, cell cycle progression, and invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro</title><p id="Par13">To investigate the effects of DKK1 on HCC cells, pCMGV/DKK1-derived retroviruses were used to transduce HepG2 and HUH-7 cells to establish HCC cell lines with stable forced expression of DKK1. The qRT-PCR and western blot analysis results revealed that DKK1 expression was effectively and functionally induced in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells compared with control cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, b</xref>). In addition, the ELISA results showed that the DKK1 level was increased in the supernatants of cultured HepG2 and HUH-7 cells with stable forced expression of DKK1 (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a, b</xref>). The results of CCK-8 and colony formation assays revealed that forced expression of DKK1 significantly increased the proliferation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>) and colony-forming ability (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>) of both HepG2 and HUH-7 cells compared with the corresponding control cells. Furthermore, the cell cycle distribution analysis results showed a significant increase in the number of cells in the S phase after forced expression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). Moreover, the number of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells that migrated through the Transwell filter was markedly higher in the forced DKK1 expression group than in the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f</xref>). Taken together, these data suggest that forced expression of DKK1 enhances the proliferative and invasive properties of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro.<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Stable forced expression of DKK1 enhances the proliferation, colony-forming ability, cell cycle progression, and invasion of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro. HepG2 and HUH-7 cells with forced expression of DKK1 were established via a DKK1 lentiviral vector (LV-DKK1). Changes in DKK1 mRNA expression were determined by qRT-PCR (<bold>a</bold>). The protein levels of DKK1 were determined by western blot analysis (<bold>b</bold>). Forced expression of DKK1 enhanced the proliferation (<bold>c</bold>), colony-forming ability (<bold>d</bold>), cell cycle progression (<bold>e</bold>), and invasion (<bold>f</bold>) of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vitro. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1270" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Forced expression of DKK1 enhances the tumorigenicity of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vivo</title><p id="Par14">Because the in vitro studies suggested that DKK1 plays a regulatory role in HepG2 and HUH-7 cell proliferation and invasion, the biological significance of these results was further evaluated in an in vivo model of HCC. To this end, a xenograft tumor formation assay was performed to investigate the effect of DKK1. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, downregulation of DKK1 impaired the tumorigenicity of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in nude mice. Scrambled shRNA-treated HepG2 and HUH-7 cells generated large tumors on the right flanks of the nude mice (green arrow). Smaller tumors were observed on the left flanks of mice injected with DKK1-shRNA-treated HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (red arrow). Forced expression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells led to significantly enhanced in vivo growth of the tumors on the left flanks of the nude mice (red arrow) compared with the growth of the tumors from control cells on the right flanks of the nude mice (green arrow) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). These data corroborate the in vitro observations and support the idea that forced expression of DKK1 enhances the tumorigenicity of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vivo, indicating that DKK1 might function as an oncogene.<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Forced expression of DKK1 promotes tumor formation by HepG2 and HUH-7 cells in vivo. Compared with control conditions, downregulation of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells significantly diminished in vivo tumor formation. Control HepG2 and HUH-7 cells transfected with scrambled shRNA generated large tumors on the right flanks of nude mice (green arrow), while smaller tumors were observed on the left flanks of mice injected with DKK1-shRNA-transfected HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (red arrow) (<bold>a</bold>, left panel). The volumes of tumors in the recipient mice are shown (<bold>a</bold>, right panel). Forced expression of DKK1 in HCC cells produced significantly enhanced in vivo growth of tumors on the left flanks of the nude mice (red arrow) compared with tumors on the right flanks of mice injected with control cells (green arrow) (<bold>b</bold>, left panel); the volumes of tumors in the recipient mice are shown (<bold>b</bold>, right panel). *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1305" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>The Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is activated by DKK1 in HCC cell lines</title><p id="Par15">Next, we investigated a potential mechanism underlying the effects of DKK1 on HCC cell proliferation and tumor formation. DKK1 is well established as a key regulator of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> Increased expression of DKK1 is associated with cytoplasmic/nuclear β-catenin accumulation in HCC patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> Therefore, we investigated whether DKK1 can activate the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway. Fluorescently labeled anti-DKK1 and anti-β-catenin antibodies were used for confocal microscopy analysis. Confocal microscopy revealed that forced expression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells increased the nuclear expression of β-catenin (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, d</xref>) in vitro. In contrast, downregulation of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells impaired the nuclear expression of β-catenin (Figs. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and 2c, f) in vitro. To detect the activity of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway, we used a luciferase reporter assay. HCC cells were transfected with pGL3-TCF/LEF for the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway assessment. As shown in Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a,b</xref>, suppression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells decreased the luciferase activity, and vice versa. Additionally, the western blot analysis results revealed that suppression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells decreased the protein expression of WNT1 and β-catenin (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Moreover, forced expression of DKK1 enhanced WNT1 and β-catenin expression in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells compared with the corresponding control cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Subsequent investigation revealed that forced expression of DKK1 enhanced the nuclear expression of β-catenin (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c, d</xref>). These findings indicated that DKK1 promotes β-catenin nuclear translocation and that the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is activated by DKK1 in human HCC cell lines. WNT1 and β-catenin may be important downstream targets of the DKK1 cascade.<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is activated by DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. The expression of DKK1 and β-catenin in HCC cells was investigated by confocal microscopy. Overexpression of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells increased the nuclear accumulation of β-catenin (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, white arrows) compared with that in the corresponding control cells (<bold>b</bold>). However, downregulation of DKK1 in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells did not obviously inhibit the nuclear accumulation of β-catenin (<bold>c</bold>, <bold>f</bold>) compared with that in the corresponding control cells (<bold>e</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1365" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig><fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>DKK1-mediated proliferation and tumor formation are dependent on the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway in human HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. The protein levels of WNT1, β-catenin, and nuclear β-catenin in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells were measured by western blot analysis. Suppression of DKK1 in these cells decreased the expression of WNT1 and β-catenin (<bold>a</bold>) and the accumulation of nuclear β-catenin (<bold>c</bold>). Forced expression of DKK1 enhanced the expression of WNT1 and β-catenin (<bold>b</bold>) and the accumulation of nuclear β-catenin (<bold>d</bold>) in these cells compared with the corresponding control cells. β-Catenin-shRNA lentiviral vectors were used to deplete β-catenin in DKK1-overexpressing HCC cells, and β-catenin depletion was then confirmed by western blotting (<bold>e</bold>). Knockdown of β-catenin significantly inhibited the proliferation (<bold>f</bold>) and tumorigenicity (<bold>g</bold>, left panel) of DKK1-overexpressing HCC cells. The volumes of tumors in the recipient mice are shown (<bold>g</bold>, right panel). *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1402" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Downregulation of β-catenin impaired the proliferation and tumorigenicity of HCC cells with forced expression of DKK1</title><p id="Par16">Deregulation of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is a hallmark of cancers, including HCC. β-Catenin is a major functional protein in the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> However, whether β-catenin is involved in formation of tumors by HCC cells with forced expression of DKK1 (DKK1<sup>High</sup> HCC cells) remains unclear. To investigate the role of β-catenin, β-catenin-shRNA lentiviral vectors were used to deplete β-catenin expression in DKK1<sup>High</sup> HepG2 and HUH-7 cells and establish stable β-catenin<sup>Low</sup>DKK1<sup>High</sup> HepG2 and HUH-7 cell lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f</xref>, β-catenin knockdown in DKK1<sup>High</sup> HCC cells markedly inhibited proliferation compared with that under control conditions in vitro. Consistent with this result, β-catenin<sup>Low</sup>DKK1<sup>High</sup> HepG2 and HUH-7 cells exhibited significantly diminished in vivo tumor formation (red arrow) compared with DKK1-DKK1<sup>High</sup> HepG2 and HUH-7 cells (green arrow) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6g</xref>) in vivo. These findings indicate that DKK1 enhances proliferation and tumor formation through β-catenin in HCC cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par17">We previously reported that DKK1 was overexpressed in HCC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> However, the specific role of DKK1 in HCC remains to be ascertained. It has been reported that DKK1 promotes HCC cell invasion and that increased expression of DKK1 is associated with poor prognosis in HCC patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> These data suggest that DKK1 may be involved in the progression of HCC. Herein, we demonstrated that DKK1 is upregulated in HCC tissues and is associated with larger tumor sizes and multiple tumors in patients with HCC. These findings indicate that DKK1 may participate in the progression of HCC. Additionally, depletion of DKK1 in HCC cells impaired cell proliferation, colony formation, cell cycle progression, and cell invasion abilities in vitro. In contrast, forced expression of DKK1 dramatically enhanced the proliferation, colony-forming ability, cell cycle progression, and invasion of HCC cells. Taken together, these data suggest that DKK1 plays a vital role in the proliferation and invasion of HCC cells in vitro.</p><p id="Par18">The function of DKK1 in HCC tumor formation, has not been examined to date. Here, the results of the in vivo assays provide the first evidence that implantation of HepG2 and HUH-7 cells with forced expression of DKK1 into nude mice results in enhanced tumor formation, indicating that DKK1 plays a significant role in the tumorigenicity of HCC cells in vivo. Collectively, these results indicate that DKK1 functions as a tumor oncogene in HCC. In the present study, the possible mechanism by which DKK1 mediates proliferation and tumor formation in HCC was investigated. WNT-induced signaling, which is frequently involved in cancer progression, can be suppressed by DKK1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> In addition, DKK1 has been shown to be activated during the progression of multiple tumors, including HCCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> Moreover, Yu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> reported that increased expression of DKK1 is associated with cytoplasmic/nuclear β-catenin accumulation in HCC patients. It seems likely that DKK1 is involved in the regulation of Wnt/β-catenin in HCC cells. Here, we found that the expression levels of WNT1 and β-catenin were dramatically increased in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells with forced expression of DKK1. Knockdown of DKK1 in HCC cells by DKK1-shRNA dramatically impaired the protein expression of WNT1 and β-catenin. Moreover, deletion of DKK1 decreased TCF/LEF activity. Most importantly, the findings from confocal microscopy and western blot analysis also revealed that forced expression of DKK1 promotes β-catenin nuclear translocation in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells. Taken together, these data suggest that the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is activated by DKK1 in HCC cells in vitro. WNT1 and β-catenin may be important downstream targets of DKK1.</p><p id="Par19">β-Catenin is the key functional protein in the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> It has been reported that β-catenin translocates from the cytoplasm to the nucleus and is essential for tumorigenesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> However, whether DKK1 is involved in the regulation of β-catenin in HCC cells is unclear. Thus, β-catenin-shRNA lentiviral vectors were used to deplete β-catenin expression in HepG2 and HUH-7 cells with forced expression of DKK1. We found that knockdown of β-catenin markedly inhibited the in vitro proliferation and in vivo tumorigenicity of HCC cells with forced expression of DKK1 compared with the corresponding control cells. These findings imply that DKK1 may enhance the proliferation and tumorigenicity of HCC cells through β-catenin.</p><p id="Par20">In conclusion, DKK1 contributes to HCC tumorigenesis by activating the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway, thus providing us with a potential therapeutic option for HCC in clinical practice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41392_2019_82_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary date</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This article has been retracted. Please see the retraction notice for more detail:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-023-01475-8">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-023-01475-8</ext-link></p></fn><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Rui Zhang, Hao-Ming Lin, Ruth Broering</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>5/5/2023</p><p>This article has been retracted. Please see the Retraction Notice for more detail: 10.1038/s41392-023-01475-8</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1038/s41392-019-0082-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by The Special Research Foundation of the National Nature Science Foundation of China (81972262, 81972255, 81772597, 81702904), the Guangdong Natural Science Foundation (2018A030313645, 2017A030311002, 2015A030313101); the Guangdong Science and Technology Foundation (2016A020215199, 2017A020215196); the Science and Technology Program of Guangzhou, China (201607010111); the Pearl River S&amp;T Nova Program of Guangzhou, China (201610010022); the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (17ykpy44, 18ykpy22); Grant [2013]163 from the Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Molecular Mechanism and Translational Medicine of the Guangzhou Bureau of Science and Information Technology; Grant KLB09001 from the Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Gene Regulation and Target Therapy of Guangdong Higher Education Institutes; and grants from the Guangdong Science and Technology Department (2015B050501004, 2017B030314026).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>R.Z., H.-M.L. and C.L. designed this research. R.Z. and W.-R.W. conducted the experiments and analyzed the data; W.-R.W., L.-B.X., X.-D.S., X.-H.Y. and R.B. interpreted the results; R.Z., C.L. and R.B. drafted the manuscript with contributions from all authors; and R. Z. and W.-R.W revised the paper.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par21">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangiovanni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased survival of cirrhotic patients with a hepatocellular carcinoma detected during surveillance</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2003.12.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Llovet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burroughs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2003</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>1907</fpage><lpage>1917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)14964-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimhofer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and metabonomic biomarkers for hepatocellular carcinoma: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Br. J. Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2015.38</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25826224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4385954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling networks guiding epithelial-mesenchymal transitions during embryogenesis and cancer progression</article-title><source>Cancer Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2007.00550.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11158989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glinka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dickkopf-1 is a member of a new family of secreted proteins and functions in head induction</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/34848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Head inducer Dickkopf-1 is a ligand for Wnt coreceptor LRP6</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00290-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11448771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dickkopf1: a tumor suppressor or metastasis promoter?</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1477</fpage><lpage>1483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.26449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21953410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3253198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dickkopf-1 expression is down-regulated during the colorectal adenoma-carcinoma sequence and correlates with reduced microvessel density and VEGF expression</article-title><source>Histopathology</source><year>2015</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/his.12474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24916146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dickkopf-1 inhibits epithelial-mesenchymal transition of colon cancer cells and contributes to colon cancer suppression</article-title><source>Cancer Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2012.02222.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22321022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7659378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of Dickkopf-1 among non-small cell lung cancer cells</article-title><source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2015.3654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25901391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Musashi1 regulates survival of hepatoma cell lines by activation of Wnt signalling pathway</article-title><source>Liver Int.</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/liv.12458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decreased expression of Dkk1 and Dkk3 in human clear cell renal cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2367</fpage><lpage>2373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2014.2077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24676838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum dickkopf-1 is a novel serological biomarker for the diagnosis and prognosis of pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>19907</fpage><lpage>19917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.4529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26101916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4637329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rachner</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dickkopf-1 is regulated by the mevalonate pathway in breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>R20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/bcr3616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24528599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3979025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High expression of Dickkopf-related protein 1 is related to lymphatic metastasis and indicates poor prognosis in intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma patients after surgery</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.27788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23132676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamabuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dikkopf-1 as a novel serologic and prognostic biomarker for lung and esophageal carcinomas</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>2517</fpage><lpage>2525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-3369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17363569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forget</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Wnt pathway regulator DKK1 is preferentially expressed in hormone-resistant breast tumours and in some common cancer types</article-title><source>Br. J. Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6603579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17245340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2360041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proliferation and migration mediated by Dkk-1/Wnt/beta-catenin cascade in a model of hepatocellular carcinoma cells</article-title><source>Transl. Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trsl.2007.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17964517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DKK1 promotes hepatocellular carcinoma cell migration and invasion through beta-catenin/MMP7 signaling pathway</article-title><source>Mol. Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-12-157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24325363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4029244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated expression of DKK1 is associated with cytoplasmic/nuclear beta-catenin accumulation and poor prognosis in hepatocellular carcinomas</article-title><source>J. Hepatol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2008.11.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19303159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum DKK1 as a protein biomarker for the diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma: a large-scale, multicentre study</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70233-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22738799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic values of alpha-fetoprotein, dickkopf-1, and osteopontin for hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Med. Oncol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12032-014-0367-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25652109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisari</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular pathogenesis of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B virus transgenic mice</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1145</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(89)90770-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2598264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatic expression of oncogenes Bmi1 and Dkk1 is up-regulated in hepatitis B virus surface antigen-transgenic mice and can be induced by treatment with HBV particles or lipopolysaccharides in vitro</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.30742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28419472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation of Bmi1 promotes malignant transformation of hepatic progenitor cells</article-title><source>Oncogenesis</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/oncsis.2016.6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26926789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5154353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>AX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of signaling pathways in the development and treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>4989</fpage><lpage>5005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2010.236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20639898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation of Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in gastrointestinal cancers</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2012</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22155636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3285553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monga</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WNT/beta-catenin signaling in liver health and disease</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1298</fpage><lpage>1305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.21651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17464972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Sancho</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Wnt antagonist DICKKOPF-1 gene is a downstream target of beta-catenin/TCF and is downregulated in human colon cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1208303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15592505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikandar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The class I HDAC inhibitor MGCD0103 induces cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in colon cancer initiating cells by upregulating Dickkopf-1 and non-canonical Wnt signaling</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3093052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birchmeier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt signalling and its impact on development and cancer</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc2389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18432252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCubrey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GSK-3 as potential target for therapeutic intervention in cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2881</fpage><lpage>2911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.2037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24931005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4102778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FoxM1 promotes beta-catenin nuclear localization and controls Wnt target-gene expression and glioma tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2011.08.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22014570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3199318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>eta-catenin nuclear translocation in colorectal cancer cells is suppressed by PDE10A inhibition, cGMP elevation, and activation of PKG</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5353</fpage><lpage>5365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.6705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26713600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4868691</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>