
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1754</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontimmu</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101560960</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6333053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6333053.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6333053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6333053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30671063</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.03102</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Plumbagin Ameliorates Collagen-Induced Arthritis by Regulating Treg/Th17 Cell Imbalances and Suppressing Osteoclastogenesis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/574430/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names initials="H">Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/459736/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zanjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>†</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/456075/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jinwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names initials="N">Niandong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="H">Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="E">Eryi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c003"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/508769/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Pharmacy, Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital, Shanghai JiaoTong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Shanghai Key Laboratory of Orthopaedic Implants, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Surgical Oncology, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line>Houston, TX</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Bone Research Program, ANZAC Research Institute, University of Sydney</institution>, <addr-line>Sydney, NSW</addr-line>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Stomatology, Shanghai Renji Hospital, Shanghai JiaoTong University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Shanghai Institute of Traumatology and Orthopaedics</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Kottarappat N. Dileepan, University of Kansas Medical Center Research Institute, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Rui Li, University of Pennsylvania, United States; Hua Wang, Anhui Medical University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Tingyu Wang <email>drtywang@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Eryi Lu <email>lueryi222@126.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Tingting Tang <email>ttt@sjtu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Inflammation, a section of the journal Frontiers in Immunology</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>†These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">305241</issue-id><elocation-id>3102</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>01</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 12:25:10.757"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2019 Wang, Qiao, Zhai, Zhang, Tu, Zheng, Qian, Zhou, Lu and Tang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Qiao, Zhai, Zhang, Tu, Zheng, Qian, Zhou, Lu and Tang</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Front Immunol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6990429"><article-title>Retraction: Plumbagin Ameliorates Collagen-Induced Arthritis by Regulating Treg/Th17 Cell Imbalances and Suppressing Osteoclastogenesis</article-title><volume>11</volume><date><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>112</elocation-id><source>Frontiers in Immunology</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6990429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32038665</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p><bold>Objective:</bold> Plumbago zeylanica L. (with plumbagin as its active ingredients) has been used for centuries to treat conditions such as joint swelling, fractures, and bacterial infections, suggesting that it possesses anti-inflammatory and immunosuppressive properties. In the present study, we evaluated the potential anti-arthritic activity and related mechanisms of plumbagin.</p><p><bold>Methods:</bold> Collagen-induced arthritis (CIA) was initiated in Wistar rats with collagen type II. Plumbagin (2 and 6 mg/kg) was orally administered to rats with CIA from day 12 to day 32 post immunization. The effects of plumbagin on arthritis progression were assessed by paw swelling, clinical scoring, and histologic analysis. The percentage of Treg and Th17 were defined by flow cytometry or immunofluorescence (IF) staining. Bone erosion and resorption were assessed by micro-CT and histomorphometric analysis. Osteoclast differentiation was further determined by <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> osteoclastogenesis assay. The molecular docking assay was used to determine the potential binding site of plumbagin.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> Treatment with plumbagin significantly inhibited arthritis development, as well as suppressed the local and systemic inflammation. Plumbagin reciprocally regulated pro-inflammatory Th17 cell and immunosuppressive Treg cell populations. In addition, plumbagin protected inflammation-induced bone loss by inhibiting osteoclast formation and activity. Plumbagin markedly suppressed RANKL-stimulated osteoclast-specific gene expression by repressing NF-κB signaling activation and MAP kinase phosphorylation. Further study via molecular docking assay demonstrated that plumbagin bound to MET169 of JNK kinase and LYS138 and SER183 of p38 kinase.</p><p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> Plumbagin not only attenuates the immune-induced arthritis by inhibiting inflammation, but also protects bone erosion by directly inhibiting osteoclast formation and activity. These data suggest plumbagin is a promising new candidate drug for treating inflammatory joint diseases.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>plumbagin</kwd><kwd>arthritis</kwd><kwd>Th17 cells</kwd><kwd>osteoclast</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="7289"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a systematic autoimmune polyarthritis that leads to joint swelling and deformity. Persistent inflammation in RA leads to synovial hyperplasia, articular cartilage degradation, and bone erosion (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Recent studies have found that Th17 and regulatory T cells (Tregs) play important roles in the pathogenesis of RA (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Th17 cells are pro-inflammatory T helper cells that play a dominant role in the production of the pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-17 (IL-17), which serves as a marker of inflammation (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Tregs, in contrast, are immunosuppressive cells that participate in the regulation of RA progression (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). In most cases, the balance between Th17 and Tregs characterized by low Th17/Treg ratio may be compromised in RA disease. The imbalance of Th17/Treg has been also reported in several inflammatory disorders, such as primary biliary cirrhosis and inflammatory bowel disease (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, Th17 cells may induce osteoclast formation and regulate bone resorption in RA by upregulating receptor activation of nuclear factor-κB ligand (RANKL) (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Furthermore, IL-17 mediates bone resorption and proteoglycan loss, which cause joint degradation (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Therefore, adjusting Th17 cell and Treg levels in RA patients enables us to control the inflammatory process and simultaneously inhibit osteoclastogenesis.</p><p>Plumbagin (5-hydroxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone) is a small molecular weight compound derived from the roots of Plumbago zeylanica L, a traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). It has been used for centuries in China as an effective medicine to treat conditions such as joint swelling, fractures, and bacterial infections, suggesting that it possesses anti-inflammatory and immune-suppressive properties (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). There have been several recent studies focusing on the anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, and immune-suppressive properties of plumbagin (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Our previous studies have shown that plumbagin inhibits the growth, invasion, and migration while induces the apoptosis of human breast cancer cells (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). We also found that the combination of plumbagin and zoledronic acid (ZA) significantly and synergistically suppressed tumorigenesis (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>On top of all the above mentioned features, the anti-inflammatory properties of plumbagin are especially noteworthy and have been reported by various studies. In our previous study, we found that plumbagin effectively downregulated expression of pro-inflammatory mediators by inhibiting NF-κB and MAPK signaling in LPS-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Checker et al. reported that plumbagin has anti-inflammatory effects on lymphocytes (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Sheeja demonstrated that plumbagin can inhibit carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats by prolonging hotplate reaction time and shortening pain response durations in formalin-induced nociception (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Luo suggested that plumbagin can effectively decrease the expression of the pro-inflammatory cytokines including interleukin 1 (IL-1), interleukin 6 (IL-6), and tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) and can also inhibit the phosphorylation of NF-κB in carrageenan-induced edema (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, Poosarla et al. reported that plumbagin has inhibitory effects on T cells (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). However, there have been no reports regarding the therapeutic effect of plumbagin on RA and the mechanism underlying the effects of plumbagin. Thus, in this study, we aimed to further evaluating the effects and the mechanisms of plumbagin on inflammation and inflammation-induced bone destruction in a rat RA model.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Collagen-Induced Arthritis Induction</title><p>Male Wistar rats (6–8 weeks old) were maintained for collagen-induced arthritis (CIA) modeling, as described previously (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Briefly, the rats were intradermally immunized on the backs of their tails with 100 μl of bovine collagen type II (CII, 2 mg/ml) in Incomplete Freund's adjuvant (IFA) on day 0, which was repeated on day 7 for booster immunization. To assess the influence of plumbagin (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) on CIA, plumbagin (2 mg/kg in the low group and 6 mg/kg in the high group) was administered intra-gastrically to CIA rats from day 12 to day 32 after first CII immunization. CIA rats treated with PEG 2,000 served as vehicle group. Arthritis severity scores (expressed as the sum of the scores of the four limbs) and paw swelling (expressed as the average volume increase of the two hind paws) were assessed every other day by two independent observers (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). All animal experiments were performed in accordance with the guidelines of the Ethics Committee of Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine.</p></sec><sec><title>Micro-CT and Histologic Examination</title><p>Rats were harvested on day 32 after the first CII immunization. The right hind limb of rats were dissected and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde/PBS and analyzed by micro-CT using an Inveon Micro PET/CT system (Siemens Co., Knoxville, TN). Scanning was performed at 60 keV, 167 μA, and 1,475 ms without using a filter. In total, ~100 slices were collected at a resolution of 20 μm per pixel. The 3-dimensional (3D) structure and morphometry were reconstructed and analyzed in a double-blinded manner. Following micro-CT scan, the right hind limbs were fixed in 10% NB-formalin for 3 days and decalcified for 14 days in 14% EDTA and then paraffin-embedded. Three micrometer sections were cut and Alcian blue/H&amp;E Orange G or TRAP staining were performed. For immunofluorescence (IF) staining, the sections were blocked with blocking solution (Thermo Scientific) and incubated with anti-RORγ (Novus Biologicals) or anti-Foxp3 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) antibodies at 4°C overnight. The sections were then washed with PBS and incubated in the presence of Alexa fluorescence 594 or Alexa fluorescence 488 labeled secondary antibodies. The nucleus was visualized with DAPI (Vector Laboratories). All sections were analyzed by a Olympus BX43 fluorescence microscopy with cellSens Standard software.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Spleens were isolated from each group on day 32 after the first CII immunization, and minced in PBS to form cell suspensions. After lysing the red blood cells with 0.83% ammonium chloride, we filtered the splenocytes through a 70 μm cell strainer. The splenocytes were then incubated with FITC-conjugated CD4 monoclonal antibodies (mAb, Thermo Fisher Scientific Co., United States), and then sorted by FACSCalibur flow cytometry sorting (BD PharMingen), to obtain CD4+ T cells. Purified CD4+ T cells then incubated with or without plumbagin for 3 days under Th17 cell polarization conditions as described in the literature (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Murine RAW264.7 cells (American Type Culture Collection, Rockville, MD, United States) and osteoblastic MC3T3-E1 and Kusao cells were cultured in α-MEM (Hyclone, Logan, UT, United States) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Hyclone, Logan, UT, United States) and penicillin/streptomycin (Gibco-BRL, Gaithersburg, MD, United States). RANKL and M-CSF (Rocky Hill, NJ, United States) were added in the culture to induce osteoclast formation in RAW264.7 cells. MC3T3-E1 and Kusao cells incubated with or without plumbagin in osteogenic media were used to determine the effects of plumbagin on osteoblast activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>The splenocytes were stimulated for 4 h with phorbol myristate acetate (PMA) and ionomycin (Sigma-Aldrich), as well as GolgiStop (BD Biosciences). Then the cells were surface labeled with FITC-conjugated CD4 mAb. After being permeabilized with Cytofix/Cytoperm solution (BD PharMingen), the cells were intracellularly stained with PE-Cy 5-conjugated Foxp3 or APC-conjugated IL-17 (R&amp;D). All data were acquired and analyzed using the Accuri C6 (BD Biosciences) software included with the instrument.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Alkaline Phosphatase (ALP) and Alizarin Red (ARS) Assay</title><p>To induce osteogenic differentiation, murine MC3T3-E1 and Kusao cells were cultured in osteogenic media (α-MEM supplemented with 10% FBS, 50 μg/ml ascorbic acid, 10 mM glycerophosphate, 100 nM dexamethasone, and 1% penicillin/streptomycin) with the indicated plumbagin concentrations. After the cells were incubated for 3 and 7 days, respectively, ALP staining was performed with the staining kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Chemical Industrial Co. Ltd., Nanjing, China), according to the manufacturer's instructions. After the cells were incubated for 21 days, ARS staining was conducted for 45 min at room temperature using 1% alizarin-red solution (pH 4.2; Sigma-Aldrich). Then, the cells were washed twice with deionized water until the orange color disappeared. ARS quantification was subsequently carried out using 10% cetylpyridinium chloride (Sigma-Aldrich) in 10 ml of sodium phosphate (pH 7.0; Sigma-Aldrich) to resolve the previous orange dye, and optical density (OD) values were measured at 620 nm with a microplate reader (Thermo Electron Corp., Waltham, MA, USA). These experiments were repeated independently for at least three times.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Viability Assay</title><p>Cell viability was measured using the Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) method. RAW264.7 cells were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 8,000 cells/well and then treated with complete α-MEM containing M-CSF (30 ng/ml) for 24 h. After that, the RAW264.7 cells were treated with various plumbagin concentrations for an additional 24, 48, 72, or 96 h. Ten microliters of CCK-8 solution was added into each well at 37°C for 2 h, and OD values were determined with a microplate reader. IC<sub>50</sub> (half maximal inhibitory concentration) values were also calculated after 48 h and 72 h. These experiments were repeated independently for at least three times.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Osteoclastogenesis Assay</title><p>Murine osteoclast precursor RAW264.7 cells were treated with or without plumbagin at the indicated concentrations in complete α-MEM containing 30 ng/ml M-CSF and 50 ng/ml RANKL. The osteoclast differentiation medium was replaced every 2 days until mature multinucleated osteoclasts were formed, followed by tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP) staining. TRAP-positive multinucleated cells containing at least three nuclei were classified as mature osteoclasts. These experiments were repeated independently for at least three times.</p></sec><sec><title>ELISA</title><p>The left hind paws were harvested from each group and suspended in PBS. TNF-α and IL-1β levels in tissue homogenate supernatant as well as serum were measured with ELISA kits (Jiayuan Biotechnology, Inc. PRC; Boster Biotechnology Co., Ltd. PRC). IL-17 and TGF-β levels in the culture supernatants were also determined using ELISA kits (Neobioscience Technology Co., Ltd, PRC), according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Extraction and Real-Time PCR</title><p>RNA was extracted using TRIzol. Gene expression levels of RORγt, Foxp3, ACP5, ATP6V0D2, CTSK, DCSTAMP, and NFATc-1 induced by RANKL in RAW264.7 cells were measured via real-time PCR (ABI 7500, Applied Biosystems Inc., United States), according to the manufacturer's protocols. GAPDH was used as a quantitative control gene, and all reactions were run in triplicates. The sequences for the relevant primers were as follows: RORγt (F): 5′-CGCCTGGAGGACCTTCTACG-3′ and (R): 5′-ACAGCTCCATGAAGCCTGAG-3′; Foxp3 (F): 5′-TGAGCTGGCTGCAA TTCTGG-3′ and (R): 5′-ATCTAGCTGCTCTGCATGAGGTGA-3′; ACP5 (F): 5′-TC CTGGCTCAAAAAGCAGTTF-3′ and (R) 5′-ACATAGCCCACACCGTTCTC-3′; ATP6V0D2(F): 5′-GCCTCAGGGGAAGGCCAGATCG-3′ and (R): 5′-GGCCACCTCTTCACTCCGGAA-3′; CTSK (F): 5′-GGACCCATCTCTGTGTCCAT-3′ and (R): 5′-CCGAGCCAAGAGAGCATATC-3′; DCSTAMP (F): 5′-AAAACCCTTGG GCTGTTCTT-3′ and (R): 5′-AATCATGGACGACTCCTTGG-3′; NFATc-1 (F): 5′-GGGTCAGTGTGACCGAAGAT-3′ and (R): 5′-GGAAGTCAGAAGTGGG TGGA-3′; and GAPDH (F): 5′-TGGAGAAACCTGCCAAGTATGA-3′ and (R): 5′-CTCTCAGCTGTGGTGGTGAA-3′.</p></sec><sec><title>Western Blotting</title><p>Murine osteoclast precursor RAW264.7 cells were pretreated with 5 μM plumbagin for 6 h, followed by stimulation with 50 ng/ml RANKL for 0, 5, 10, 20, 30, or 60 min. Cells were then lysed with RIPA buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) for protein extraction. Equal volumes of protein lysates were resolved using SDS-PAGE and then transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, United States). These membranes were incubated with the appropriate primary antibodies (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, United States) at 4°C overnight before secondary antibody incubation (Abcam, Cambridge, United Kingdom) for 2 h at room temperature. The results were detected with an Odyssey V3.0 image scanner (Li-COR. Inc., Lincoln, NE, United States). The experiments were repeated independently for at least three times.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular Docking</title><p>Three-dimensional homology models of mouse JNK/p38 kinase domains were established with Modeler 9.12 using human JNK and p38 architecture as templates. The JNK/p38 stereo-chemical constructs were confirmed using PROCHECK. MolConverter and MarvinSketch were used to generate and refine the spatial coordinates of plumbagin, which was linked to the ATP docking pockets of JNK and p38 using the Lamarckian genetic algorithm based on AutoDock and AutoDock Vina. The resulting molecular model figures depicting binding activity were prepared using PyMOL visualization software.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All data are expressed as the mean ± SEM and were analyzed using Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test (comparisons between two groups) or ANOVA followed by LSD and S-N-K test. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Plumbagin Ameliorates the Progression of Inflammatory Arthritis</title><p>Paw swelling of all the rats were measured and scored every other day from day 12 until day 32 post type II collagen (Col-II) immunization. As shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref>, arthritis developed in CIA rats treated with vehicle since day 12, which continued to increase and peaked approximately on days 24–26 after Col-II immunization. Low dose (2 mg/kg) and high dose (6 mg/kg) of plumbagin were orally administered to rats with CIA from day 12 to day 32. Compared with CIA rats treated with vehicle, plumbagin-treated CIA rats exhibited significantly attenuated arthritis, as determined by hind paw volume measurement, and arthritis scores (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A,B</xref>). The attenuated paw swelling in plumbagin-treated CIA rats was displayed by the representative images of the hind paws from rats of different groups taken on day 32 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Plumbagin (PL) treatment suppresses inflammatory arthritis in rats with collagen-induced arthritis (CIA). <bold>(A,B)</bold> Hind paw swelling measurement and time course of clinical arthritis in non-arthritic control rats (Ctrl), vehicle-treated CIA (CIA+Veh) rats, and CIA rats treated with low and high doses of plumbagin [CIA+PL(low) and CIA+PL(high)]. <bold>(C)</bold> Representative images of paw swelling. <bold>(D,E)</bold> Representative images of Alcian blue/H&amp;E Orange G stained knee sections from different groups (original magnification ×50). Yellow arrowheads indicate sites of synovitis <bold>(D)</bold> and cartilage degradation <bold>(E)</bold>. <bold>(F,G)</bold> Protein levels of TNF-α and IL-1β in the supernatant of hind paw joint homogenate as measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) on day 32. <bold>(H,I)</bold> Protein levels of TNF-α and IL-1β in rat plasma as measured by ELISA on day 32. Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10/group. ##<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. non-arthritic control rats. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. vehicle-treated CIA rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>Compared to non-arthritic rats, histological examination of joints from CIA rats demonstrated severe synovial proliferation and inflammatory cell infiltration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>), as well as cartilage destruction (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>). Plumbagin-treated CIA rats exhibited significantly alleviated inflammation and cartilage degradation when compared with the vehicle-treated CIA rats (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D,E</xref>). In consistence with the measurement and score of paw swelling, the supernatant of ankle joint tissue homogenate exhibited a down-regulation of the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-α and IL-1β in plumbagin-treated CIA rats when compared to CIA-vehicle rats (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F,G</xref>). In addition, there was also a systemic reduction of TNF-α and IL-1β levels resulted from plumbagin treatment as measured in plasma (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1H,I</xref>). These results indicate that plumbagin inhibits joint inflammation, and suppresses pro-inflammatory cytokines both locally and systemically.</p></sec><sec><title>Plumbagin Reciprocally Regulates Th17 Cells and Tregs <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p>Th17 cell/Treg imbalances play a pivotal role in RA pathology. To determine whether the Th17 and Treg cell populations were altered in plumbagin-treated CIA rats, the ratio of CD4<sup>+</sup>IL-17<sup>+</sup> cells (Th17 cells) and CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> cells (Tregs) in the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells of spleen was assessed by flow cytometry. Compared to non-arthritic control rats, vehicle-treated CIA rats exhibited up-regulated CD4<sup>+</sup>IL-17<sup>+</sup> cells which indicated increased Th17 cell population, as well as down-regulated CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> cells, which suggested decreased Treg cell population (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">D</xref>). This Th17 cell/Treg imbalances associated with arthritis was rescued by plumbagin treatment. CIA rats treated with both low and high doses of plumbagin displayed decreased Th17 cell population and increased Treg cell population compared to vehicle-treated CIA rats (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">D</xref>). Compared to non-arthritic control rats, the absolute number of Th17 cells was much higher and the absolute number of Treg cells was much lower in spleens of vehicle-treated CIA rats (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G,H</xref>). Plumbagin treatment significantly decreased the absolute numbers of Th17 cells and increased the absolute numbers of Treg cells in spleen of CIA rats (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G,H</xref>). In addition to cell population and absolute number evaluations, the gene expression levels of RORγt and Foxp3 as Th17 and Treg specific transcription factors were also measured in isolated splenocytes. In consistence with the flow cytometry results, RORγt mRNA levels were lower in plumbagin-treated CIA rats than in vehicle-treated CIA rats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). Conversely, Foxp3 mRNA levels were significantly higher in plumbagin-treated CIA rats than that in vehicle-treated CIA model in rats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>). To examine whether plumbagin regulates Th17 cells and Tregs in inflamed joint, we performed immunofluorescence (IF) staining to measure RORγt and Foxp3 expression in the joint tissues from CIA rats treated with vehicle or plumbagin. As shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2I</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">K</xref>, plumbagin treatment significantly decreased the numbers of Th17 cells and increased the number of Tregs in knee joint of CIA rats.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Plumbagin reciprocally regulates Th17 cells and Tregs in rats with CIA. <bold>(A)</bold> Representative flow cytometry profile of IL-17+ cell frequencies among CD4+ T cells in spleens collected from Ctrl, CIA+Veh, CIA+PL(low), and CIA+PL(high) rats on day 32. <bold>(B)</bold> Representative flow cytometry profile of Fopx3+ cell frequencies among CD4+ T cells in spleens collected from rats of different groups on day 32. <bold>(C,D)</bold> Quantitative analysis of IL-17+ and Fopx3+ cell populations in splenic CD4+ T cells from rats of different groups on day 32. <bold>(G,H)</bold> Th17 cells and Treg cells were counted in the spleens of different groups on day 32. <bold>(E,F)</bold> Gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ROR</italic>γ<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Foxp3</italic> as assessed by qRT-PCR of splenocytes isolated from rats of different groups. <bold>(I)</bold> Immunofluorescence micrographs of RORγt (red) or Foxp3 (green) in the knee joint of the vehicle and plumbagin-treated CIA rats. DAPI (blue) was used to counterstain the nuclei. <bold>(J,K)</bold> Quantitative analysis of RORγt and Foxp3 cell numbers in joint tissues from CIA rats treated with vehicle or plumbagin (high dose). Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5/group. ##<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. normal control rats. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. vehicle-treated CIA rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>To further confirm the regulatory effects of plumbagin on Th17 and Treg cell imbalances, we investigated the effects of plumbagin on Th17 cell differentiation and Foxp3 induction <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from CIA rats were cultured under conditions favoring Th17 cell development with or without plumbagin. Consistent with <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> results, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> treatment with plumbagin at the doses as low as 2.5 μM already significantly decreased Th17 cell population and increased Treg cell population (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">D</xref>). Plumbagin treatments also resulted in decreased RORγt and increased Foxp3 mRNA expression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E,F</xref>). In addition, as the main cytokines mediating Th17 and Treg activities, respectively, the protein levels of IL-17 and TGF-β in the supernatants of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell cultures were measured by ELISA. The results demonstrated that plumbagin (2.5 to 7.5 μM) treatment decreased IL-17 levels and increased TGF-β levels under the conditions favoring Th17 cell development (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G,H</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Reciprocal effects of plumbagin treatment on Th 17 and Treg cell differentiation <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Representative flow cytometry profile <bold>(A,B)</bold> and quantification <bold>(C,D)</bold> of IL-17+ and Fopx3+ cells in splenic CD4+ T cells isolated from CIA rats, which were cultured under Th17-polarizing conditions for 72 h with or without plumbagin in different concentrations. <bold>(E,F)</bold> Gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ROR</italic>γ<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Foxp3</italic> as assessed by qRT-PCR of splenic CD4+ T cells isolated from CIA rats with different treatments. <bold>(G,H)</bold> Protein levels of IL-17 and TGF-β as measured by ELISA in the supernatants of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell cultures under different conditions. Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5/group. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. vehicle-treated CIA rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Plumbagin Attenuated Joint Bone Erosion and Proximal Tibial Bone Loss in CIA Rats</title><p>In addition to joint inflammation and cartilage degradation, the μCT analysis revealed significant severer bone erosions in the knee and hind paw joints of CIA-vehicle rats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, red arrowheads). In contrast, the bone erosions were mild in plumbagin-treated CIA rats. In order to detect whether plumbagin protected bone loss, we further determined changes in bone microarchitecture in the proximal tibiae. In comparison to non-arthritic rats, the tibial trabecular bone volume (%, BV/TV) was significantly reduced in CIA rats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). The reduction of trabecular bone mass in CIA animals was largely due to a reduction in trabecular thickness (Tb.Th, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>) and an increasing in trabecular separation (Tb.Sp, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). In contrast, this trabecular bone reduction was effectively protected by plumbagin treatment as shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">D</xref>. In addition to trabecular bone, tibial cortical bone volume, and thickness were also reduced in CIA rats. Again, this cortical bone loss was protected by plumbagin treatments (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4E,F</xref>). Taken together, these data suggest that plumbagin exerts significant protective effects against bone destructions in CIA rats.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Plumbagin suppresses joint bone erosion and tibial bone loss in rats with CIA. <bold>(A)</bold> Representative reconstructed 3D micro-CT images of knee and hind paw joints of Ctrl, CIA+Veh, CIA+PL(low), and CIA+PL(high) rats to show joint bone erosion. Red arrowheads indicate sites of joint bone erosion. <bold>(B–F)</bold> Micro-CT parameters of trabecular bone mass and cortical bone mass are shown in <bold>(B)</bold>, trabecular bone volume (BV/TV), <bold>(C)</bold> trabecular thickness, <bold>(D)</bold> trabecular separation, <bold>(E)</bold> corticol bone volume, <bold>(F)</bold> corticol thinkness. <bold>(G)</bold> Representative histological images of tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP) staining for osteoclasts (red) at a region distant to the site of inflammation in the proximal tibia of rats from different groups. Histomophometric quantification of <bold>(H)</bold> osteoclast number/bone surface (N.Oc/BS), and <bold>(I)</bold> osteoblast surface/bone surface (Ob.S/BS) in rats from different groups. Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5/group. #<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ##<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. normal control rats. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. vehicle-treated CIA rats.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>Joint destruction is caused by decreased bone formation and increased bone resorption, therefore, we examined whether plumbagin affected osteoblast and osteoclast activities that controls the balance of bone formation and resorption. Histomorphometric analysis revealed that osteoclast numbers were increased in CIA rats compared with non-arthritic normal rats, which was significantly reduced by plumbagin treatment (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4G</xref>). In contrast, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H</xref>, CIA rats displayed the significantly decreased osteoblast surface compared to non-arthritic control rats, however, there was no significant difference of osteoblast surface between vehicle-treated CIA rats and plumbagin-treated CIA rats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I</xref>). These findings suggest that plumbagin has protective effects on bone resorption in CIA rats, without affecting bone formation.</p></sec><sec><title>Plumbagin Inhibits Bone Damage by Decreasing Osteoclast Formation</title><p>The effects of plumbagin on osteoblast differentiation were further evaluated in MC3T3 and Kusao cells. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> showed that osteogenic media significantly increased ALP activity in MC3T3 cells, with no apparent effects on ALP activity in Kusao cells after 3 days incubation. Plumbagin treatment at different concentrations (0.15–1.25 μM) did not affect ALP activity in either MC3T3 or Kusao cells after 3 or 7 days incubation (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">C</xref>). ARS staining also confirmed that no significant effects on mineralized bone matrix formation in either MC3T3 or Kusao cells resulted from plumbagin treatment (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D,E</xref>). These data suggested that there was no significant effects of plumbagin on osteoblast activity.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Plumbagin inhibits osteoclastogenesis via suppressing osteoclast formation. <bold>(A,B)</bold> Representative images of ALP stained osteoblastic 3T3 and Kusao cells treated with or without plumbagin in different concentrations (0.15 −1.25 μM) for 3 and 7 days. <bold>(C)</bold> Quantitative analysis of 3T3 and Kusao cells positive for ALP staining. <bold>(D)</bold> Representative images of ARS stained osteoblastic 3T3 and Kusao cells treated with or without plumbagin in different concentrations (0.15–1.25 μM) for 21 days. <bold>(E)</bold> Quantitative analysis of 3T3 and Kusao cells positive for ARS staining. <bold>(F)</bold> Representative TRAP staining image of RAW264.7 cells under RANKL/M-CSF stimulation with or without plumbagin (1.25–5 μM). <bold>(G,H)</bold> Quantification of TRAP-positive multinucleated osteoclasts numbers and resorption areas. <bold>(I,J)</bold> Cell viability assessment of RAW264.7 cells treated with plumbagin (2.5–20 μM) for 48 h and 72 h. The IC50 values in RAW264.7 cells treated with plumbagin for 48 h and 72 h is 11.22 and 9.22 μM, respectively. Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5/group. <sup><italic toggle="yes">##</italic></sup>, <sup>**</sup>, <sup>&amp;&amp;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 versus control in <bold>(C)</bold> and <bold>(E)</bold>. <sup>**</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 versus plumbagin 0 μM group in <bold>(G)</bold> and <bold>(H)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>To further determine the effect of plumbagin on bone resorption, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> osteoclast formation assay was performed. Plumbagin at 2.5 and 5 μM concentrations for 5 days significantly inhibited RANKL/M-CSF-induced osteoclast formation in RAW264.7 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Quantification of TRAP-positive multinucleated osteoclasts numbers and areas confirmed a reduction of osteoclast activity resulted from plumbagin treatment as shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5G,H</xref>. In addition, after 48 and 72 h incubation, plumbagin (0.25–1.25 μM) inhibited osteoclast formation in RAW264.7 cells, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 11.22 and 9.22 μM, respectively (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5I,J</xref>). Taken together, these findings indicate that plumbagin significantly inhibits osteoclast formation with no effect on osteoblast differentiation.</p></sec><sec><title>Plumbagin Suppresses Osteoclast Activity by Repressing NF-κB Signaling Activation and MAP Kinase Phosphorylation</title><p>Since plumbagin exerted inhibitory effect on osteoclast formation and activity, we further investigated the underlying mechanisms by examining the expression of osteoclast-specific genes. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">E</xref> showed that plumbagin at the concentration of 1.25 and 2.5 μM (or 2.5 μM only) significantly inhibited the expression of <italic toggle="yes">ACP5, ATP6V0D2, CTSK, DCSTAMP</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">NFATc-1</italic> induced by RANKL in RAW264.7 cells. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F</xref> showed that administration of RANKL stimulated pI-κBα and pP65 expression and decreased total I-κBα expression, which were significantly abrogated by the treatment of plumbagin (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G</xref> showed that RANKL induced pERK, pJNK and pP38 expression levels without affecting t-ERK, t-JNK, and t-P38 expression levels. However, administration of plumbagin inhibited RANKL-induced pJNK and pP38 expression without affecting pERK expression, demonstrating that pJNK, and pP38 kinases are more likely to be the targets of plumbagin. This was further confirmed by the molecular docking assay, which demonstrated that plumbagin bound to MET169 of JNK kinase and LYS138 and SER183 of P38 kinase, providing potential inhibition sites at which plumbagin functioned against MAPK pathway (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6H,I</xref>). Additionally, the expression levels of downstream c-Fos and NFATc-1, which are activated following JNK/P38 phosphorylation, were significantly inhibited by plumbagin (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6J</xref>). These results indicate that plumbagin is able to target kinases and abrogate phosphorylation of these kinases, thereby decreasing expression levels of downstream functional proteins which are important in the development of arthritis.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Plumbagin downregulates RANKL-activated NF-κB and MAPK signaling during osteoclastogenesis. <bold>(A–E)</bold> Gene expression of osteoclast-specific genes (<italic toggle="yes">ACP5, ATP6V0D2, CTSK, DCSTAMP</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">NFATc-1</italic>) as assessed by qRT-PCR of RAW264.7 cells under RANKL/M-CSF stimulation with or without plumbagin (1.25–5 μM) for 24 h. <bold>(F)</bold> Protein level of NF-κB signaling in RAW264.7 cells treated with RANKL and plumbagin for up to 60 min evaluated by Western blotting. <bold>(G)</bold> Protein level of MAPK signaling in RAW264.7 cells treated with RANKL and plumbagin for up to 60 min evaluated by Western blotting. <bold>(H,I)</bold> The potential binding sites of plumbagin against JNK and P38 kinase displayed by molecular docking assay. <bold>(J)</bold> Downstream osteoclastic protein (c-fos and NFATc-1) levels in RAW264.7 cells treated with RANKL and plumbagin for up to 5d evaluated by Western blotting. Quantitative results are presented as mean ± SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3/group.<sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. plumbagin 0 μM group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fimmu-09-03102-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the current study, we used the well-established CIA model to investigate effects of plumbagin on inflammation and inflammation-mediated bone damage in arthritis. Plumbagin significantly inhibited arthritis development by alleviating paw swelling and histological changes, as well as suppressing the joint tissue expression of TNF-α and IL-1β and their serum levels. This anti-inflammatory effects of plumbagin appeared through its reciprocally regulation of the populations of Th17, the inflammatory cell, and Treg, the immunosuppressive cells, indicating that plumbagin has the ability to reduce systemic and local inflammation. Plumbagin also protected inflammation-induced bone loss through its direct inhibition effects on osteoclast formation and activity via NF-κB pathway signaling activation and MAP kinase phosphorylation.</p><p>Th17 cells are a subgroup of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells that are capable of producing high levels of IL-17 and possess the specific transcription factor RAR-related orphan receptor gamma t (RORγt). In recent years, the role of Th17 in RA has been studied extensively. IL-17 levels are much higher in the synovial fluid of RA patients than in the synovial fluid of osteoarthritis patients (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In RA synovial fibroblasts cultures, IL-17 induces the production of inflammatory cytokines (such as IL-6, IL-8, PGE2, and G-CSF) in a dose-dependent manner, and these effects can be blocked with the anti-IL-17 antibody (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Blocking IL-17 using different methods including anti- IL-17 antibody, transgenic IL-17 knockout, transgenic <italic toggle="yes">IL-17RA</italic> knockout, and soluble IL-17 receptor protein alleviated arthritis in various models (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). On the other hand, both systemic and local (intra-articular) adenoviral IL-17 gene transfer exacerbated CIA (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>+</sup> T regulatory cells (Tregs) possess the specific transcription factor Foxp3 and play pivotal roles in immunological tolerance and immune homeostasis. Treg levels and functions are decreased and impaired, respectively, in both RA patients and in CIA animal models (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In the present studies, Th17-Treg cell imbalance was observed in CIA rats with increased Th17 cell population and decreased Treg cell population, which was consistent with the clinic data of RA patients (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) Moreover, compared with non-arthritic control rats, the absolute number of Th17 cell was much higher and the absolute number of Treg cell was much lower in the spleen of vehicle-treated CIA rats. This imbalance was rescued by plumbagin, associated with decreasing RORγt mRNA levels and upregulating Foxp3 levels in the splenocytes of CIA rats, resulting in less server inflammation. Furthermore, plumbagin-mediated Foxp3 expression under Th17-polarizing conditions facilitated the conversion of Th17 cells to Tregs. The mechanisms of converting Th17 cells into Treg cells by plumbagin should be investigated in details in the future.</p><p>Bone erosion on the surface of inflammatory knee-joints and bone loss in proximal tibiae associated with joint inflammation were clearly demonstrated in CIA rats. Both micro-CT and histomorphometric analyses showed that plumbagin exerts protective effects against those CIA-related bone destruction. During RA progression, bone damage hinges on the balance between osteoblast and osteoclast cells. Our data strongly suggest that plumbagin exerts the direct effects on osteoclastogenesis through RANKL pathway. RANKL binds to RANK, expressed in the surface of osteoclast precursor cells, and then stimulates NF-κB and MAPK pathways (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) NF-κB activation begins with I-κBα phosphorylation, which increases downstream p65 translocation and phosphorylation, contributing to NF-κB signaling activation (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In the RANKL-stimulated <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> system, pretreatment of cells with plumbagin significantly decreased multinucleated osteoclast formation. In addition, plumbagin reduced RANKL-induced NF-κB p65 phosphorylation and I-κBα phosphorylation, suggesting that plumbagin influences NF-κB activation via these upstream effects. Plumbagin also affected MAPK pathway by attenuating JNK and p38 phosphorylation without impacting ERK phosphorylation. It was confirmed by molecular docking assay which revealed that plumbagin was able to target JNK and p38 kinase binding sites, thus inhibiting the subsequent phosphorylation and downstream activation of functional proteins, such as c-Fos and NFATc-1. The transcriptional factor NFATc1 is considered a trigger for osteoclast terminal differentiation, as NFATc1 deficient bone marrow macrophages cannot differentiate into multinucleated osteoclasts, even with RANKL stimulation (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Upon activation, NFATc1 is translocated from the cytoplasm to the nucleus via a calcineurin-dependent mechanism and triggers the transcription of genes required for osteoclast differentiation, as well as bone resorption (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Furthermore, it has been reported that NFATc1 directly binds to the ACP5, ATP6V0D2, CTSK, and DCSTAMP promoters. Interestingly, Western blotting and real-time PCR results in our study indicated that plumbagin decreases NFATc1 protein expression in osteoclasts through a transcription-dependent mechanism, resulting in the subsequent downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">ACP5, ATP6V0D2, CTSK</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">DCSTAMP</italic> mRNA expression.</p><p>Of note, IL-17 have been shown to promoted osteoclast formation from CD14<sup>+</sup> osteoclast precursor cells acquired from healthy donors by upregulating receptor activator of NF-κB (RANK) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) Another study also reported that bone erosion and destruction in CIA is driven by Th17 cells by regulating RANKL-mediated osteoclast formation (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In our study, plumbagin treatment significantly decreased the numbers of Th17 cells, and increased the number of Tregs in the inflamed joint of CIA rats. These indicated that the bone protection effects of plumbagin shown in the current study may be also resulted from its regulation of Th17 cells, however, more evidence is required in future investigations.</p><p>In conclusion, the findings of the current study have important implications regarding the potential application of plumbagin as a treatment of RA, as our data suggest that this therapy can not only alleviate inflammatory response which results in mitigating inflammation-associated bone destruction, but also protect bone loss directly.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors were involved in drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content, and all authors approved the final version to be published. TW, EL, and TT designed the research. TW, HQ, and ZZ performed experiments and had full access to all of the data in the study. TW, HQ, ZZ, and JZ analyzed data. TW, HQ, XZ, NQ, EL, JT, HZ, and TT wrote the manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) (grant # 81874011, 81572104, and 81301531) to TW. This work was also partially supported by the Innovation Grant from Shanghai Municipal Science and Commission (grant #18140903502) to TW.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Picerno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adinolfi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alunno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>One year in review: the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Rheumatol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26203933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh-hora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenic conversion of Foxp3+ T cells into TH17 cells in autoimmune arthritis</article-title>. <source>Nat Med.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.3432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24362934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rebamipide suppresses collagen-induced arthritis through reciprocal regulation of th17/treg cell differentiation and heme oxygenase 1 induction</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheumatol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>874</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.38310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24757140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwakura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Suppression of immune induction of collagen-induced arthritis in IL-17-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>171</volume>:<fpage>6173</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.171.11.6173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14634133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vollenhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trollmo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmström</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CD25<sup>bright</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells are enriched in inflamed joints of patients with chronic rheumatic disease</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar1192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC464877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastaff-Leung</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabarrack</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Foxp3+ regulatory T cells, Th17 effector cells, and cytokine environment in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Immunol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10875-009-9345-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pöllinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyndall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Th17 cells, not IL-17+ γδ T cells, drive arthritic bone destruction in mice and humans</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>2602</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1003370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamopoulos</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laface</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenschein</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwakura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Interleukin-17A upregulates receptor activator of NF-kappaB on osteoclast precursors</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>R29</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20167120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2875663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plumbagin (5-hydroxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone) suppresses NF-κB activation and NF-κB-regulated gene products through modulation of p65 and IκBα kinase activation, leading to potentiation of apoptosis induced by cytokine and chemotherapeutic agents</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>17023</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M601595200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16624823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somasundaram</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemalatha</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sengodan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased sensitivity of BRCA defective triple negative breast tumors to plumbagin through induction of DNA Double Strand Breaks (DSB)</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>26631</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep26631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27220670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4879579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Plumbagin exerts an immunosuppressive effect on human T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia MOLT-4 cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2016.03.092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27018383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plumbagin attenuates cancer cell growth and osteoclast formation in the bone microenvironment of mice</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharmacol Sin.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/aps.2013.152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24384612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4075744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Suppressive effects of plumbagin on invasion and migration of breast cancer cells via the inhibition of STAT3 signaling and down-regulation of inflammatory cytokine expressions</article-title>. <source>Bone Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4248/BR201304007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26273514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4472116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Synergistic suppression of human breast cancer cells by combination of plumbagin and zoledronic acid <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Acta Pharmacol Sin.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/aps.2015.42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26235741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4561967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Structural simulation of adenosine phosphate via plumbagin and zoledronic acid competitively targets JNK/Erk to synergistically attenuate osteoclastogenesis in a breast cancer model</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e2094</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2016.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26866274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4849151</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC6506481"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plumbagin inhibits LPS-induced inflammation through the inactivation of the nuclear factor-kappa B and mitogen activated protein kinase signaling pathways in RAW 264</article-title>.7 cells. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2013.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24296134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Checker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poduval</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of plumbagin are mediated by inhibition of NF-kappaB activation in lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2009.03.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19374955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Checker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subrahmanyam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poduval</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plumbagin inhibits proliferative and inflammatory responses of T cells independent of ROS generation but by modulating intracellular thiols</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>1082</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.22620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20564204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3065107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheeja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioassay-guided isolation of anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive compound from Plumbago zeylanica leaf</article-title>. <source>Pharm Biol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13880200903156424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20645715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Antiinflammatory and analgesic effect of plumbagin through inhibition of nuclear factor-κB activation</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>335</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.110.170852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20858709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poosarla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D</surname><given-names>N R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Athota</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunkara</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of T cell proliferation and cytokine response by Plumbagin, extracted from Plumbago zeylanica in collagen induced arthritis</article-title>. <source>BMC Complement Altern Med.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-11-114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22085488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3248848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamontain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber-Steffens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenei-Lanzl</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wajant</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Stimulation of TNF receptor type 2 expands regulatory T cells and ameliorates established collagen-induced arthritis in mice</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cmi.2017.138</pub-id>. [Epub ahead of print].<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29375132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6318277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic frequency of blood CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells in rats with collagen-induced arthritis</article-title>. <source>Korean J Physiol Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4196/kjpp.2015.19.2.83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25729268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4342740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metawi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serum and synovial fluid levels of interleukin-17 in correlation with disease activity in patients with RA</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-011-1737-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchs</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fossiez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frappart</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human interleukin-17: A T cell-derived proinflammatory cytokine produced by the rheumatoid synovium</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1529-0131(199905)42:5&lt;963::AID-ANR15&gt;3.0.CO;2-E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10323452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umesaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gut-residing segmented filamentous bacteria drive autoimmune arthritis via T helper 17 cells</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2010.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20620945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2904693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshifuji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neutrophils are essential as a source of IL-17 in the effector phase of arthritis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e62231</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23671588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3646022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadik</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alekseeva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luster</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>IL-17RA signaling amplifies antibody-induced arthritis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e26342</fpage>. (<year>2011</year>) <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3197623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubberts</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Den Berg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miossec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>IL-17 derived from juxta-articular bone and synovium contributes to joint degradation in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11299057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC30709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooles</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaacs</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treg cells in rheumatoid arthritis: an update</article-title>. <source>Curr Rheumatol Rep.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11926-013-0352-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23888361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felcenloben</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piasecki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancyr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atamaniuk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adoptively transferred Tregs accumulate in a site-specific manner and ameliorate signs of less advanced collagen-induced arthritis progress in rats</article-title>. <source>Immunotherapy</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/imt.14.121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25804475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TXNDC5 synergizes with HSC70 to exacerbate the inflammatory phenotype of synovial fibroblasts in rheumatoid arthritis through NF-κB signaling</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Immunol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cmi.2017.20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28603283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6123406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Geraniin suppresses RANKL-induced osteoclastogenesis <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and ameliorates wear particle-induced osteolysis in mouse model</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>330</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2014.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25016282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isshiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Induction and activation of the transcription factor NFATc1 (NFAT2) integrate RANKL signaling in terminal differentiation of osteoclasts</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00369-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12479813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asagiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autoamplification of NFATc1 expression determines its essential role in bone homeostasis</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>202</volume>:<fpage>1261</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20051150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16275763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2213228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliprantis</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of bone and joint remodeling by NFAT</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>233</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0105-2896.2009.00849.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20193006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2904911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>