
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Technol Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Technol. Cancer Res. Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3299</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tct</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101140941</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1533-0346</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1533-0338</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6131299</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6131299.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6131299</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6131299</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30198403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1533033818797587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1533033818797587</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Study on Attenuating Angiogenesis and Epithelial–Mesenchymal Transition (EMT) of Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma (NSCLC) by Regulating <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="S">Sicong</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033818797587">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xi</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1533033818797587">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="D">Daojing</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1533033818797587">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="M">Meiying</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1533033818797587">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names initials="C">Cheng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1533033818797587">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1533033818797587">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5595-7422</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="F">Feng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1533033818797587">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1533033818797587"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1533033818797587">
<label>1</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, Medical College of Nanchang University, Nanchang, Jiangxi, China</aff><aff id="aff2-1533033818797587">
<label>2</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, Jiangxi Province Tumor Hospital, Nanchang, Jiangxi, China</aff><aff id="aff3-1533033818797587">
<label>3</label>Department of Oncology, Medical College of Nanchang University, Nanchang, Jiangxi, China</aff><aff id="aff4-1533033818797587">
<label>4</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, The Third Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University, Nanchang, Jiangxi, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1533033818797587">Feng Jiang, MD, Department of Thoracic Surgery, Jiangxi Province Tumor Hospital, No 519 Beijing East Road, Nanchang 330006, Jiangxi, China. Email: <email>wxqwgb@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">305491</issue-id><elocation-id>1533033818797587</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>09</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-18 12:25:26.937"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="22" elocation-id="15330338231218448" journal-id="Technol Cancer Res Treat" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10734323"><article-title>Retraction Notice</article-title><volume>22</volume><date><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>15330338231218448</elocation-id><source>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10734323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38111166</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>To investigate the role of MAGE family member C2 in angiogenesis and epithelial–mesenchymal transition of non-small cell lung carcinoma.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The Cancer Genome Atlas data set was analyzed to filter the highly expressed gene melanoma antigen family C2 in non-small cell lung carcinoma. Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction was performed to verify the overexpression of melanoma antigen family C2 in non-small cell lung carcinoma cell lines. Melanoma antigen family C2 complementary DNA and short hairpin RNA (shRNA) were transfected into SK-MES-1 cells to regulate melanoma antigen family C2 expression. Cell Counting Kit-8 assay, flow cytometry, wound healing assay, and Transwell assay were performed to investigate the effect of melanoma antigen family C2 on proliferation, apoptosis, migration, and invasion of SK-MES-1 cell line. Western blot was used to detect the expression of epithelial–mesenchymal transition markers. Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay was performed to investigate the secretion of vascular endothelial growth factor, and tube formation assay was conducted to explore the effect of melanoma antigen family C2 on angiogenesis ability of the tumor. Tumor xenograft on nude mice and immunohistochemical/hematoxylin and eosin staining were also performed to detect the influence of melanoma antigen family C2 on growth and metastasis of non-small cell lung carcinoma cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 was highly expressed in non-small cell lung carcinoma cells; melanoma antigen family C2 promoted the expression of epithelial–mesenchymal transition-related proteins as well as enhance the secretion of vascular endothelial growth factor and promote angiogenesis; melanoma antigen family C2 promoted proliferation, migration, and invasion and suppressed apoptosis of non-small cell lung carcinoma cells. It could also facilitate growth and metastasis of non-small cell lung carcinoma <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 was a critical factor of angiogenesis and epithelial–mesenchymal transition in non-small cell lung carcinoma.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic></kwd><kwd>angiogenesis</kwd><kwd>VEGF</kwd><kwd>EMT</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>edited-state</meta-name><meta-value>corrected-proof</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-1533033818797587"><title>Introduction</title><p>Lung carcinoma is the leading cause of carcinoma-related death around the world.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="bibr2-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr3-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> According to the risk assessment given by International Agency for Research on Cancer at 2012, over 1.8 million patients are diagnosed with lung carcinoma (12.9% of the total) and about 1.6 million patients are killed by it (19.4% of the total) per year.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Generally, over 80% of lung carcinoma cases are classified as non-small cell lung carcinoma (NSCLC).<sup><xref rid="bibr5-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="bibr6-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr7-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Treatments including chemotherapy and surgery have been widely used to cope with NSCLC, but 5-year overall survival rate is only 16% for patients with NSCLC of all stages.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr9-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The grim situation of NSCLC therapy makes it seriously necessary to further explore the mechanism of NSCLC and build new therapeutic strategies.</p><p>Initiation and development of NSCLC is partly attributed to the aberrant expression of proto-oncogenes, which lead to tumor proliferation, metastasis, and other tumor progressions.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> With the development of bioinformatics, increasing oncogenes have been detected and explored in different kinds of carcinomas. Cancer–testis antigens (CTAs) are a group of carcinoma-associated antigens that have extremely low expression in normal tissues except adult testis but aberrant high expression in many kinds of tumors, particularly advanced carcinomas with stem cell–like characteristics.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Cancer–testis antigen melanoma antigen family C2 (<italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>), a member of type I melanoma antigen (MAGE) family, is a widely explored gene for that it is one of the most immunogenic CTAs.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> It has been identified as the oncogene in many carcinomas, including melanoma,<sup><xref rid="bibr14-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> prostate cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr15-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> breast cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr16-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and multiple myeloma.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>
</p><p>Epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT) and angiogenesis are 2 critical factors influencing tumor growth and metastasis. Epithelial–mesenchymal transition is a complex multistep event, which is characterized by the loss of E-cadherin and occludins, downregulation of epithelial maker cytokeratin, upregulation of mesenchymal marker vimentin and fibronectin, and acquisition of fibroblast-like morphology with cytoskeleton reorganization.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> The motility, invasiveness, and metastatic ability of tumor cells are closely related to EMT.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Angiogenesis in tumors promotes the tumor growth and metastasis in the vascular phase,<sup><xref rid="bibr20-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> which is the main reason for the failure of antitumor therapy.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> The process of angiogenesis is actually the proliferation of vascular endothelial cells arranged by vessels,<sup><xref rid="bibr22-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> and the vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) actively participates in the angiogenesis, lymphangiogenesis, and tube formation.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Many anti-VEGF medicines like endostatin have been widely used as the therapeutic strategy against the carcinomas, but they are impressionable to the tumor microenvironment.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> For that both EMT and angiogenesis play crucial roles in the tumor progression, their correlation with oncogenes is of great research value.</p><p>Given that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could promote the tumor growth and metastasis, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> may function through facilitating EMT and angiogenesis in NSCLC. In our study, we regulated the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> and investigated the effects of differentially expressed <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> on the progress of EMT and angiogenesis in NSCLC. It will further improve the cognition about the function of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> and provide a new potential target for NSCLC treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-1533033818797587"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section3-1533033818797587"><title>Bioinformatic Analysis</title><p>The clinical data of patients with NSCLC were obtained from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) data set. R 3.4.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org">https://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) containing DESeq2 was used to analyze the data and draw the volcano plot and heatmap. Screening conditions were | log<sub>2</sub>(Foldchange) | &gt;2 and adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001. All the differentially expressed genes were showed in the volcano plot, and top 10 differentially expressed genes were showed in the heatmap.</p></sec><sec id="section4-1533033818797587"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Human embryo kidney cell line HEK-293T, human NSCLC cell line SK-MES-1 (with TP53 and EGFR mutation), A549, and HCC827, human normal lung epithelial cell line BEAS-2B, and human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were purchased from BeNa Culture Collection (Beijing, China). HEK-293T and SK-MES-1 cells were cultured with Dulbecco modified Eagle medium (DMEM; Gibco, Grand Island, New York) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco), BEAS-2B and HCC827 cells were cultured with RPMI-1640 medium (Gibco) containing 10% FBS, A549 cells and HUVEC were cultured with Ham F12K medium (Gibco) containing 10% FBS. All the cells were incubated at 37°C in a humidified chamber containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="section5-1533033818797587"><title>Lentivirus Transfection</title><p>Lentivirus vectors containing <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> complementary DNA (cDNA) and shRNA were customized from GenePharma (Shanghai, China). Lentiviral packaging mixtures (containing lentivirus vectors, pMDLg/pRRE, pRSV-Rev, and pMD2.G) were cotransfected into HEK-293T cells to get lentivirus particles. SK-MES-1 cells were seeded onto 24-well plates (10<sup>5</sup>/well) and incubated for 24 hours, then the culture medium was replaced with fresh DMEM containing 5μg/mL polybrene, and the virus suspension was added into the medium (multiplicity of infection [MOI] = 20). After 24-hour incubation, the culture medium was replaced with fresh DMEM in order to remove the lentivirus and polybrene. Cells with <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> upregulated or downregulated were then available after 48-hour incubation.</p></sec><sec id="section6-1533033818797587"><title>Quantitative Reverse Transcription-Polymerase Chain Reaction</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Beyotime, Shanghai, China), then DNA Reverse Transcription Kit (#4368814; Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California) was used to perform the reverse transcription, and quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was performed using SYBR Select Master Mix on ABI Prism 7000 Sequence Detection system (Applied Biosystems). Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (<italic toggle="yes">GAPDH)</italic> was chosen as the internal reference, and the relative expressions of messenger RNAs (mRNAs) were calculated using 2<sup>−△△CT</sup> method. Experiments were repeated in triplicate for accuracy. Primer sequences are shown in <xref rid="table1-1533033818797587" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table1-1533033818797587" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Primers for qRT-PCR.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer Sequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAGEC2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-ACTTCGTCTATGGGGAGCCT-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-TGCGGTATCAATTGTGGCCT-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">VEGF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CTTGCCTTGCTGCTCTACCT-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GCAGTAGCTGCGCTGATAGA-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">GAPDH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-TGGAGAAAATCTGGCACCAC-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1533033818797587"><p>Abbreviations: MAGEC2, melanoma antigen family C2; qRT-PCR, quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section7-1533033818797587"><title>Western Blot</title><p>The cell proteins were extracted through The Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act (RIPA) lysis buffer (Beyotime) and quantified using bicinchoninic acid (BCA) kit (Beyotime), then 20 μg of proteins were treated by Sodium Dodecyl Sulphate - PolyAcrylamide Gel Electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and transferred onto polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes (Invitrogen, Eugene, Oregon). Electrochemiluminescent detection system (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts) was used for blot signal detection. Specific proteins were detected by primary antibody rabbit anti-<italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">MAGEE1</italic>; #ab209667, 1:5000; Abcam, Cambridge, Massachusetts). Anti-<italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> (#ab9485, 1:2500; Abcam) was used as the internal reference, and HRP-conjugated goat-anti-rabbit IgG (#ab6721, 1:10000; Abcam) was used as secondary antibody.</p></sec><sec id="section8-1533033818797587"><title>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</title><p>The cells were seeded onto 96-well plates and incubated at 37°C in humid air with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24 hours. Culture supernatant was collected, and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) was performed using Human VEGF Quantikine ELISA Kit (#DVE00; R&amp;D Systems, Abingdon, United Kingdom) according to the manufacturer’s protocol.</p></sec><sec id="section9-1533033818797587"><title>Cell Counting Kit-8 Assay</title><p>Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8; #CK04; Dojindo, Kumamoto, Japan) was used to detect the cell viability. The cells were digested, then the cell suspension was planted into 96-well plates (10<sup>4</sup>/well). After 24-/48-/72-/96-hour incubation, CCK-8 solution was added (10 µL/well), and the optical density at 450 nm wavelength was detected using the microplate reader (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="section10-1533033818797587"><title>Tube Formation Assay</title><p>Each well of the 96-well plates was coated with 50 μL diluted Matrigel (BD Biosciences, San Jose, California), then the mixture of 2 × 10<sup>4</sup> HUVEC and transfected SK-MES-1 cells (1:1) was seeded onto the layer of Matrigel in 100 μL DMEM containing 10% FBS. Positive control group was additionally treated with 50 ng/mL VEGF (Beyotime). After 8-hour incubation, endothelial cell tube formation was observed. The ability of endothelial cells to form tubular structures in the different conditions was assessed using the optical microscope (Nikon, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="section11-1533033818797587"><title>Flow Cytometry</title><p>SK-MES-1 cell apoptosis was detected using Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (#APOAF; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, Missouri), according to the manufacturer’s protocol. After digested by 0.25% trypsin for 24 hours, the cells were collected into flow tubes and washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 3 times. Then each tube was added with 150 μL binding buffer and 1 μL Annexin V-FITC and incubated for 15 minutes in dark at room temperature. The cells were then treated by 100 μL propidium iodide, and the cell apoptosis was determined using FACSCanto II Flow Cytometer (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="section12-1533033818797587"><title>Wound Healing Assay</title><p>The cells were seeded in 6-well plate with 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells in each to grow to 80% confluence. The wounds were scratched with pipette tip gently across the center of the well. After washed 3 times with serum-free medium, the cells were incubated in humid atmosphere, 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The migrated cells were observed with the optical microscope at 0 and 24 hours, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="section13-1533033818797587"><title>Transwell Invasion Assay</title><p>Matrigel was diluted with 100 μL serum-free DMEM and mixed, then the Transwell chambers were coated with diluted Matrigel (200 mg/mL) at the density of 50 μL/well and placed into a 24-well plate. Then each chamber was filled with 250 μL cell suspension (containing 4 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells), and the 24-well plate was filled with DMEM containing 10% FBS. After 24-hour incubation, methyl alcohol and 0.1% crystal violet (Sigma-Aldrich) were respectively used for the fixation and staining of the invaded cells. The number of invaded cells was counted under the optical microscope.</p></sec><sec id="section14-1533033818797587"><title>Tumor Xenograft</title><p>BALB/c nude mice (4-5 weeks old, weighing 18-22 g) were purchased from SLACCAS (Shanghai, China). Suspension of SK-MES-1 cells transfected with <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA or shRNA was injected into the armpit of the mice (10<sup>7</sup>/0.1 mL). Size of the tumors was measured with a vernier caliper per 5 days. All the mice were decapitated after 30-day feeding, then the tumors were excised and weighed, and tissues were taken out, then formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded for immunohistochemical (IHC) or hematoxylin and eosin (HE) staining. All the experiments involving laboratory animals have been approved by the ethic committee of Jiangxi Province Tumor Hospital.</p></sec><sec id="section15-1533033818797587"><title>Immunohistochemical Staining</title><p>Sections of tumor tissues were dewaxed at 67°C and then 3% hydrogen peroxide–methanol solution was used to inactivate endogenous peroxidase. Nonspecific antigens were blocked by 10% goat serum at 37°C for 1 hour. After washed with PBS, the sections were incubated with primary antibody rabbit anti-VEGFA (1:100, ab52917; Abcam) at 37°C for 1.5 hour and with secondary antibody HRP-labeled goat anti-rabbit IgG (1:2000, ab205718; Abcam) for 1 hour at room temperature. Then the sections were washed with PBS and incubated with Diaminobenzidine (DAB) (#<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="D12384">D12384</ext-link>; Sigma-Aldrich) for 3 minutes in a dark room. After the coloration, the sections were washed with DDH<sub>2</sub>O for 20 minutes and then counterstained with hematoxylin for 1 minute. Finally, the sections were washed and mounted with rhamsan gum.</p></sec><sec id="section16-1533033818797587"><title>Hematoxylin and Eosin Staining</title><p>Lung tissues of the mice were first dewaxed using xylene and placed in 4% paraformaldehyde, immersed and fixed for 24 hours. After that, the tissues were washed using distilled water for 3 minutes, followed by staining with hematoxylin for 15 minutes. The stained tissues were disposed in 1% hydrochloric acid (acid ethanol) for color separation for 10 seconds and then soaked in warm water for 5 minutes. Eosin dye solution 0.25% was subsequently added to counterstain the tissues for 5 minutes. Hematoxylin and eosin staining results were detected with the optical microscope.</p></sec><sec id="section17-1533033818797587"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All the data were analyzed with GraphPad Prism 6 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, California) and presented as mean (standard deviation). Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used to detect differences between groups; Pearson rank correlation coefficient was performed to assess the correlations between 2 factors. All the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments were repeated 3 times and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments were repeated 5 times to ensure the accuracy. The differences were considered to be statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section18-1533033818797587"><title>Results</title><sec id="section19-1533033818797587"><title>Melanoma antigen family C2 Was Highly Expressed in NSCLC</title><p>The Cancer Genome Atlas data set was used to screen the differentially expressed mRNAs in NSCLC. The result of bioinformatic analysis showed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> was one of the top 10 upregulated genes in NSCLC (log<sub>2</sub>(Foldchange) = 6.52; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033818797587">Figure 1A and B</xref>). Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction and Western blot were then used to detect the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> in 3 NSCLC cell lines SK-MES-1, A549, and HCC827, and the result conformed to the bioinformatics analysis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033818797587">Figure 1C and D</xref>), indicating that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> was an extremely highly expressed gene in NSCLC.</p><fig id="fig1-1533033818797587" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 was highly expressed in non-small cell lung carcinoma. A, Volcano plot of differentially expressed messenger RNAs in NSCLC based on the data of The Cancer Genome Atlas (log2(Foldchange) &gt; 2, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.001). B, Heatmap of top 10 highly expressed mRNAs in NSCLC (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.001). C, Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction: MAGEC2 mRNA was extremely highly expressed in SK-MES-1, A549, and HCC827 cell lines compared with normal lung epithelial cells BEAS-2B. D, Western blot: <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> protein was extremely highly expressed in SK-MES-1, A549, and HCC827 cell lines compared with normal lung epithelial cells BEAS-2B (**<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.001). MAGEC2 indicates melanoma antigen family C2; NSCLC, non-small cell lung carcinoma; mRNAs, messenger RNAs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-fig1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section20-1533033818797587"><title>Melanoma antigen family C2 Promoted Proliferation, Migration, and Invasion and Suppressed Apoptosis of NSCLC</title><p>To further explore the influence of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> on NSCLC, we used lentiviral vectors to transfect <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA or shRNA into SK-MES-1 cells, and qRT-PCR was performed to verify the regulation of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>. Three designed shRNAs were respectively transfected into SK-MES-1 cells, and shRNA2 showed the best silencing efficiency (the lowest <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> mRNA expression compared with NC; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2A</xref>). Therefore, shRNA2 was selected for performing following experiments and labeled as <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA. The <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> expression was significantly enhanced after transfecting <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA, while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> expression was significantly declined after transfecting <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2-1533033818797587" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 promoted proliferation, migration, invasion, and EMT, while suppressed apoptosis of NSCLC cells. A, Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction: Silencing efficiency of 3 designed shRNAs on MAGEC2 mRNA. shRNA2 was selected for following experiments and labeled as MAGEC2 shRNA. B, Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction: MAGEC2 was significantly upregulated after MAGEC2 cDNA transfection, while MAGEC2 was significantly downregulated after MAGEC2 shRNA transfection. C, Cell Counting Kit-8 assay: Cell proliferation of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly enhanced while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly suppressed, compared to negative control group. D, Flow cytometry: Basal cell apoptosis of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly reduced while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly ascended, compared with NC group. E, Wound healing assay: Closed wound area of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group at 24 hours was significantly bigger, while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly smaller, compared with NC group. F, Transwell assay: Invasive cell number of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly bigger while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly smaller, compared with NC group. G, Western blot: Expressions of E-cadherin and cytokeratin were significantly declined after <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA transfection or induced after <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA transfection; expressions of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>, vimentin, and fibronectin were significantly induced after <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA transfection or declined after <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA transfection (*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01). cDNA indicates complementary DNA; EMT, epithelial–mesenchymal transition; MAGEC2, melanoma antigen family C2; mRNA, messenger RNA; NSCLC, non-small cell lung carcinoma; NC, negative control; qRT-PCR, quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-fig2.jpg"/></fig><p>Cell function experiments were then conducted to investigate the effect of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> on viability of NSCLC cells. Cell Counting Kit-8 assay showed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could positively regulate proliferation of SK-MES-1 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2C</xref>); flow cytometry revealed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could significantly suppress basal apoptosis of SK-MES-1 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2D</xref>); wound healing assay and Transwell assay indicated that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could positively regulate migration and invasion ability of SK-MES-1 cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2E and F</xref>). All the results revealed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> might be a key factor of NSCLC progress.</p></sec><sec id="section21-1533033818797587"><title>Melanoma antigen family C2 Promoted the Progression of EMT</title><p>Given that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could positively affect migration and invasion of NSCLC cells, which was strongly associated with EMT, we conducted Western blot to detect the differential expression of EMT marker proteins after regulating <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>. The result showed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could negatively regulate the expression of E-cadherin and cytokeratin and positively regulate the expression of vimentin and fibronectin (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033818797587">Figure 2G</xref>). These results confirmed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could promote the progression of EMT in NSCLC cells.</p></sec><sec id="section22-1533033818797587"><title>Melanoma antigen family C2 Facilitated Angiogenesis Ability of NSCLC</title><p>Since that angiogenesis was one of the critical factor of tumor growth, we performed ELISA and tube formation assay to explore the potential relationship between <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> and angiogenesis. Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction indicated that <italic toggle="yes">VEGF</italic> mRNA expression was positively regulated by the expression of MAGEC2 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033818797587">Figure 3A</xref>); similarly, ELISA showed that the VEGF concentration in supernatant of culture medium was positively regulated by the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033818797587">Figure 3B</xref>). Tube formation assay revealed that HUVEC cells mixed with <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>-overexpressed SK-MES-1 cells had better angiogenesis, while HUVEC cells mixed with <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>-knockdown SK-MES-1 cells had poorer angiogenesis, compared to HUVEC cells alone. Human umbilical vein endothelial cells with exogenous VEGF had similar angiogenesis with those mixed with <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>-overexpressed SK-MES-1 cells and were diagnosed as the positive control (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033818797587">Figure 3C</xref>). These results indicated that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could promote the expression of VEGF and facilitate angiogenesis in NSCLC.</p><fig id="fig3-1533033818797587" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 promoted angiogenesis of non-small cell lung carcinoma. A, Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction: VEGF mRNA expression was significantly upregulated after MAGEC2 cDNA transfection or downregulated after MAGEC2 shRNA transfection. B, Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay: VEGF secretion was significantly induced after MAGEC2 cDNA transfection or reduced after <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA transfection. C, Tube formation assay: Tube formation of VEGF (positive control) or <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly more intensive while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was less intensive, compared with NC group. (*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.01). cDNA indicates complementary DNA; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; MAGEC2, melanoma antigen family C2; mRNA, messenger RNA; NC, negative control; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-fig3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section23-1533033818797587"><title>Melanoma antigen family C2 Facilitated the Growth, Angiogenesis, and Metastasis of NSCLC <italic toggle="yes">In Vivo</italic>
</title><p>Tumor xenograft on nude mice was performed to explore the influence of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> on the growth and metastasis of NSCLC <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Tumor volume of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly higher compared to the control group among the 30-day feeding, while which of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033818797587">Figure 4A and B</xref>). Similar to tumor volume, tumor weight of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was also significantly higher, while which of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was notably lower, compared to control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033818797587">Figure 4C</xref>). Serum of all the nude mice was extracted for ELISA, and the result showed that the concentration of serum VEGF of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly higher, while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033818797587">Figure 4D</xref>). Vascular endothelial growth factor IHC staining of tumor tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033818797587">Figure 4E</xref>) provided the similar result that VEGF-positive rate of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly higher while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was lower compared to NC group. Hematoxylin and eosin staining of mice lung tissues revealed that the tumor of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group had a severer pulmonary metastasis, while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group had a slighter metastasis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033818797587">Figure 4F</xref>). All these results indicated that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could facilitate the growth, angiogenesis, and metastasis of NSCLC <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="fig4-1533033818797587" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Melanoma antigen family C2 promoted tumor growth, angiogenesis, and metastasis of NSCLC <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. A, Photograph of tumors taken from the mice. B, Tumor volume of MAGEC2 cDNA group was significantly bigger while MAGEC2 shRNA group was significantly smaller, compared with NC group. C, Tumor weight of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly bigger while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly smaller, compared with NC group. D, Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay: Mice serum VEGF concentration of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group was significantly higher while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group was significantly lower, compared with NC group. E, Vascular endothelial growth factor immunohistochemical staining of the tumor tissues (100× magnified): <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group had a higher VEGF positive rate while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group had a lower positive rate, compared with NC group. F, Hematoxylin and eosin staining of lung tissues (200× magnified) of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> cDNA group had more pulmonary nodules while <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> shRNA group had less, compared with NC group (**<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01). cDNA indicates complementary DNA; MAGEC2, melanoma antigen family C2; NC, negative control; NSCLC, non-small cell lung carcinoma; NC, negative control; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section24-1533033818797587"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> was a positive regulator of the growth and metastasis of NSCLC. According to the analysis result of TCGA data set, <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> was an extremely highly expressed gene in NSCLC tissues and it was barely expressed in adjacent tissues. Although the aberrant expression of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> and its promotion to the tumor progression have been confirmed in many kinds of carcinomas, its role in NSCLC has not been clearly explored before. Firstly, we preformed both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments to confirm that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> worked as an oncogene in NSCLC, which was corresponded with previous studies<sup><xref rid="bibr14-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="bibr15-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr16-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr17-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>; moreover, our study paid attention on the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> and critical physiological process of NSCLC. The results substantiated our hypothesis that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could promote the EMT and angiogenesis of NSCLC.</p><p>Epithelial–mesenchymal transition and angiogenesis are 2 crucial tumor progressions. For that most carcinomas are originated from the mutation of epithelial cells, EMT is a necessary progression for tumor cells. It is not a simple process to acquire migration and invasion ability, but a complicated reprogramming involved in metabolism, epigenetics, and differentiation, through which differentiated epithelial cancer cells express semblable characteristics, such as expressing stem cell markers and then acquiring stem cell-like functions.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Numerous researches have revealed the relationship between EMT and its upstream genes. For example, an oncogene <italic toggle="yes">ZEB1</italic> has been widely recognized as an EMT inducer<sup><xref rid="bibr25-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>; the effect of transforming growth factor-β on regulating EMT was also investigated by many researches<sup><xref rid="bibr26-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>; <italic toggle="yes">SNAI2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TWIST1</italic> were reported to regulate EMT progression in thyroid carcinomas.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> The gene involved in our study, <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>, has been considered as an EMT inducer in breast cancer (PMID: 24687377). Our study confirmed that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could also promote EMT in NSCLC, which would improve the understanding about NSCLC progression.</p><p>Angiogenesis is an important part of the vascular phase in tumor growth and metastasis. Extensive researches have demonstrated the effectiveness of tumor therapy targeting vascular endothelial cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="bibr29-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr30-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> For that there is a natural synergy between targeting vascular endothelial cells and tumor cells, it is urgent to determine gene regulation of tumor angiogenesis and develop new angiogenic inhibitors. In tumors, VEGF is a regulator of endothelial cell proliferation, migration, invasion, and survival by mediating angiogenesis and vascular tube formation.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="bibr32-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Vascular endothelial growth factor overexpression is related to intratumoral microvessel density and a poor prognosis in varieties of cancers.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Downregulation of VEGF could inhibit cell proliferation and lead to tumor cell apoptosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr34-1533033818797587" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> In our study, we found that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could enhance the expression and secretion of VEGF, and silencing <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could significantly suppress the expression of VEGF and the progression of angiogenesis, indicating that <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could positively regulate VEGF activation and it might be a potential target for antiangiogenesis therapy.</p><p>In summary, activation of <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> in NSCLC functions as an important part in EMT and angiogenesis. Melanoma antigen family C2 promotes EMT progression and VEGF-induced vascular endothelial cell growth, migration, and tube formation, then facilitates angiogenesis and tumor development. Our findings also showed that silencing <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> could suppress NSCLC cell proliferation, migration, and tube formation as well as accelerate NSCLC cell apoptosis. Taken together, targeting <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic> might be a potential gene therapy for NSCLC treatment. However, the specific relationship among <italic toggle="yes">MAGEC2</italic>, EMT, and angiogenesis was not intensively studied in our research for some restrictions. We believe that there are several signaling pathways participating in these progressions and that will be the target of our further study.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1533033818797587"><p><bold>Authors’ Note:</bold> Sicong Jiang and Xi Liu contributed equally to this work, they are co-first authors. All the experiments involving laboratory animals have been approved by the ethic committee of Jiangxi Province Tumor Hospital and the approval number is JXPTH-201706-233.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2-1533033818797587"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1533033818797587"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1533033818797587"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Feng Jiang, MD<inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033818797587-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5595-7422">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5595-7422</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><glossary content-type="abbr"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1-1533033818797587">CTAs</term><def><p>cancer–testis antigens;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2-1533033818797587">cDNA</term><def><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3-1533033818797587">DMEM</term><def><p>Dulbecco Modified Eagle Medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4-1533033818797587">ELISA</term><def><p>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5-1533033818797587">EMT</term><def><p>epithelial–mesenchymal transition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6-1533033818797587">FBS</term><def><p>fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7-1533033818797587">HUVECs</term><def><p>human umbilical vein endothelial cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8-1533033818797587">IHC/HE</term><def><p>immunohistochemical/hematoxylin and eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9-1533033818797587">MAGE</term><def><p>melanoma antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10-1533033818797587">MAGEC2</term><def><p>melanoma antigen family C2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11-1533033818797587">mRNAs</term><def><p>messenger RNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term12-1533033818797587">NSLCLC</term><def><p>non-small cell lung carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term13-1533033818797587">PBS</term><def><p>phosphate-buffered saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term14-1533033818797587">qRT-PCR</term><def><p>quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term15-1533033818797587">TCGA</term><def><p>The Cancer Genome Atlas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term16-1533033818797587">VEGF</term><def><p>vascular endothelial growth factor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1533033818797587"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNA-346 facilitates cell growth and metastasis, and suppresses cell apoptosis in human non-small cell lung cancer by regulation of XPC/ERK/Snail/E-cadherin pathway</article-title>. <source>Aging (Albany NY)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2509</fpage>–<lpage>2524</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27777383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/aging.101080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5115903</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11386926"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1533033818797587"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hsa-miR-134 suppresses non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) development through down-regulation of CCND1</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>35960</fpage>–<lpage>35978</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27166267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.8482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5094975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1533033818797587"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iaboni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Aptamer-miRNA-212 conjugate sensitizes NSCLC cells to TRAIL</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e289</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27111415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mtna.2016.5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5014461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1533033818797587"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hsa-miR-329 exerts tumor suppressor function through down-regulation of MET in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>21510</fpage>–<lpage>21526</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26909600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.7517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5008302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1533033818797587"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Long intergenic noncoding RNA 00511 acts as an oncogene in non-small-cell lung cancer by binding to EZH2 and suppressing p57</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e385</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27845772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mtna.2016.94</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5155326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1533033818797587"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hsa-miR-326 targets CCND1 and inhibits non-small cell lung cancer development</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>8341</fpage>–<lpage>8359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26840018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.7071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4884997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1533033818797587"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Down-regulation of c-Met and Bcl2 by microRNA-206, activates apoptosis, and inhibits tumor cell proliferation, migration and colony formation</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>25533</fpage>–<lpage>25574</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26325180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.4575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4694850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1533033818797587"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Novel miR-9600 suppresses tumor progression and promotes paclitaxel sensitivity in non-small-cell lung cancer through altering STAT3 expression</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e387</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27845771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mtna.2016.96</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5155328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1533033818797587"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Long non-coding RNA NEAT1 promotes non-small cell lung cancer progression through regulation of miR-377-3p-E2F3 pathway</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>32</issue>):<fpage>51784</fpage>–<lpage>51814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27351135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.10108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5239515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1533033818797587"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNA-187-3p mitigates non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) development through down-regulation of BCL6</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>471</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26845350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2016.01.175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1533033818797587"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hsa-miR-139-5p inhibits proliferation and causes apoptosis associated with down-regulation of c-Met</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>37</issue>):<fpage>39756</fpage>–<lpage>39792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26497851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.5476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4741860</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9882992"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1533033818797587"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Combined cancer testis antigens enhanced prediction accuracy for prognosis of patients with hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>3513</fpage>–<lpage>3528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26097535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4466922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1533033818797587"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cancer-testis antigen MAGE-C2 binds Rbx1 and inhibits ubiquitin ligase-mediated turnover of cyclin E</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>39</issue>):<fpage>42028</fpage>–<lpage>42039</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26540345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.5973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4747207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1533033818797587"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MAGE-C2 promotes growth and tumorigenicity of melanoma cells, phosphorylation of KAP1, and DNA damage repair</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>759</fpage>–<lpage>767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23096706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/jid.2012.355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3570725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1533033818797587"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortezavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MAGE-C2/CT10 protein expression is an independent predictor of recurrence in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e21366</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21754986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0021366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3130772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1533033818797587"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalieer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pilot study on MAGE-C2 as a potential biomarker for triple-negative breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Dis Markers</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>2325987</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27843173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2016/2325987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5098074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1533033818797587"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lajmi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luetkens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yousef</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cancer-testis antigen MAGEC2 promotes proliferation and resistance to apoptosis in multiple myeloma</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>762</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26456863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bjh.13762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1533033818797587"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamouille</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular mechanisms of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm3758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4240281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1533033818797587"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition in human cancer: comprehensive reprogramming of metabolism, epigenetics, and differentiation</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25595324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2015.01.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-1533033818797587"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tumor angiogenesis and therapy</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>S340</fpage>–<lpage>S343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0753-3322(05)80070-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-1533033818797587"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphoproteomics and lung cancer research</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>12287</fpage>–<lpage>12314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23202899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms131012287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3497273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-1533033818797587"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silvestre</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tedgui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of angiogenesis and remodelling of the microvasculature</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18339645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cvr/cvn070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-1533033818797587"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>JAK2/STAT3 signaling pathway activation mediates tumor angiogenesis by upregulation of VEGF and bFGF in non-small-cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Lung Cancer</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21333372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2011.01.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-1533033818797587"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alahuhta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aikio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayrynen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Endostatin induces proliferation of oral carcinoma cells but its effect on invasion is modified by the tumor microenvironment</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>336</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26112215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yexcr.2015.06.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-1533033818797587"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preca</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bajdak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A self-enforcing CD44s/ZEB1 feedback loop maintains EMT and stemness properties in cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2566</fpage>–<lpage>2577</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26077342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.29642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-1533033818797587"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>TGFbeta and matrix-regulated epithelial to mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1840</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2621</fpage>–<lpage>2634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24561266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbagen.2014.02.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-1533033818797587"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buehler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of epithelial-mesenchymal transition regulators SNAI2 and TWIST1 in thyroid carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Mod Pathol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/modpathol.2012.137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3559085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-1533033818797587"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ocak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callison</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massion</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of focal adhesion kinase in small-cell lung carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>1301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21800286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.26382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3673887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-1533033818797587"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kallergi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markomanolaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannoukaraki</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hypoxia-inducible factor-1alpha and vascular endothelial growth factor expression in circulating tumor cells of breast cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>R84</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19919679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/bcr2452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2815547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-1533033818797587"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Therapeutic efficacy of a novel focal adhesion kinase inhibitor TAE226 in ovarian carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>10976</fpage>–<lpage>10983</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-07-2667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-1533033818797587"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demicco</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Histologic variability in solitary fibrous tumors reflects angiogenic and growth factor signaling pathway alterations</article-title>. <source>Hum Pathol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1015</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25976141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.humpath.2015.03.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-1533033818797587"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claesson-Welsh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>VEGFA and tumour angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>273</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23216836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/joim.12019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-1533033818797587"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Antitumor effect and antiangiogenic potential of the mTOR inhibitor temsirolimus against malignant pleural mesothelioma</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24378576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2013.2948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-1533033818797587"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A novel synthetic small molecule YF-452 inhibits tumor growth through antiangiogenesis by suppressing VEGF receptor 2 signaling</article-title>. <source>Sci China Life Sci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28194552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11427-016-0369-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>