
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci. Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BSR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6747000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6747000.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6747000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6747000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31439759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20182193</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>25</subject><subject>21</subject><subject>39</subject><subject>13</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MUC1 gene silencing inhibits proliferation, invasion, and migration while promoting apoptosis of oral squamous cell carcinoma cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="AM">Ai-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names initials="XH">Xiao-Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bo</surname><given-names initials="ZQ">Zu-Qiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="XF">Xiao-Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3887-7492</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Stomatology, Dongying City People’s Hospital, Dongying 257091, P.R. China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Jin Zhang (<email>zhangjin201811@163.com</email>)</corresp><fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p>Authors contributed equally</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">341281</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20182193</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>16</day><month>09</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>09</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 13:25:10.283"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7316175"><article-title>Expression of Concern: MUC1 gene silencing inhibits proliferation, invasion and migration while promoting apoptosis of oral squamous cell carcinoma cells</article-title><volume>40</volume><issue>6</issue><date><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-20182193_EOC</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-20182193_EOC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7316175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32579205</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7403949"><article-title>Retraction: MUC1 gene silencing inhibits proliferation, invasion and migration while promoting apoptosis of oral squamous cell carcinoma cells</article-title><volume>40</volume><issue>8</issue><date><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-20182193_RET</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-20182193_RET</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7403949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32743651</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The aim of the present study is to investigate the role of RNA interference in the inhibition of MUC1 gene expression in occurrence and metastasis of oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) and its in-depth mechanisms. The OSCC and normal oral mucosa tissues, as well as normal oral epithelial cell line HOK and OSCC cell line SCC-4, Cal-27, TSCCA, Tca8113 were obtained to detect the expression of MUC1. Slug expression in OSCC and normal oral mucosa tissues was also determined. The OSCC cells were grouped to investigate the role of MUC1 gene silencing on proliferation, DNA replication, cell cycle distribution, apoptosis, colony formation ability, epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT), invasion, and migration of OSCC cells. We first found higher positive rate of MUC1 and Slug expression in OSCC tissues. Next, it was determined that higher expression of MUC1 was found in OSCC tissues and cells. Furthermore, silencing of MUC1 declined Slug expression, inhibited the proliferation, DNA replication, cell cycle progression, and EMT while inducing apoptosis of OSCC cells. Our study suggests that overexpression of MUC1 is found in OSCC, and MUC1 gene silencing could inhibit the proliferation, invasion, and migration while inducing apoptosis of OSCC cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Apoptosis</kwd><kwd>Invasion</kwd><kwd>Migration</kwd><kwd>MUC1 gene silencing</kwd><kwd>Oral squamous cell carcinoma</kwd><kwd>Proliferation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) is involved in the oral tongue, lower gingival and alveolus, upper gingival, floor of the mouth, retromolar triangle, buccal mucosa, lip mucosa, and hard palate [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. OSCC accounts for nearly 3% of all malignant tumors around the world, with 550,000 new cases every year worldwide in recent years [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Smoking and alcohol consumption are regarded as the major risks for OSCC, but only a small part of people develop oral cancer with these habits, which suggests that other genetic factors also result in the pathogenesis of the disease [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Until now, the main therapy for OSCC is the surgical resection accompanied by radiotherapy and chemotherapy [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Great advances have been achieved in general patient care, surgical techniques, as well as local and systemic adjuvant therapies, while the mortality rate of OSCC still high and the 5-year overall survival rate remains less than 50% [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Based on this, it is of great importance to find potential targets for the treatment of patients suffering from OSCC [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Mucins, as high molecular weight glycoproteins, exert function in cell growth, differentiation and cell signaling, and the gene expression of mucin is highest in the system of respiratory, digestive, and reproductive systems [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref>]. Mucin 1 (MUC1) is a membrane-bound protein, and it is a member of the mucin family [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. MUC1 possesses a core protein mass of 120–225 kDa, which increases to 250–500 kDa with glycosylation [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14–16</xref>]. MUC1 consists of two subunits, namely an N-terminal extracellular subunit (MUC1-N) together with a C-terminal transmembrane subunit (MUC1-C) [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It is reported that overexpression of MUC1 is able to induce anchorage independent growth and tumorigenicity [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Meanwhile, an aberrant expression of MUC1 has highlighted its role in the pathogenesis of various human cancers [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Recent article has described that MUC1 might serve as a regulator engaging in several interactions that could contribute to enhance migration and invasion, as well as survival [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. It is also reported that MUC1 is presented on the majority of cancers with glandular epithelial origin, which acts as a potential target for therapeutic interventions in these cancers [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A recent study has demonstrated that MUC1 expression might be a useful diagnostic target for prediction and treatment of the invasive/metastatic potential of OSCC [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Slug (Snail2) plays essential roles in controlling the epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) during disease development [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Evidence has shown that MUC1 may up-regulate EMT-related genes such as Snail and Slug [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, no study focussed on the silencing of MUC1 on the biological functions of OSCC cells. Based on this, we conducted the present study to investigate the role of RNA interference in the inhibition of MUC1 expression in occurrence and metastasis of OSCC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Study subjects</title><p>The samples were collected from 90 cases of OSCC who were surgically resected from the Dongying City People’s Hospital from 2016 to 2017. Case selection was based on availability organization and tracking data. Of these patients, 46 were males and 44 were females, aged 32–74 years, with an average age of 55.21 ± 0.29 years. Patients received no preoperative radiotherapy, chemotherapy, biotherapy, or other specific treatment for cancer. According to World Health Organization (WHO) pathological classification amongst those 90 OSCC patients, there were 30 cases of well differentiation, 30 cases of moderate differentiation, and 30 cases of poor differentiation. According to the TNM staging of the International Union Against Cancer (UICC) in 2009 [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], there were 60 cases in N0 phase, 27 cases in N1 phase, and three cases in N2 phase. The OSCC tissues were selected as an experimental group. Additionally, 35 cases of normal oral mucosa tissues (patients with traumatic or orthodontic extraction without smoking and drinking history) were used as a control group. All tumor cases were reassessed and histologically classified by the same pathologist. Histological identification was based on WHO standards. The Medical Ethics Survey Association of Dongying City People’s Hospital authorized the study and the patient informed consent was obtained.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Immunohistochemical staining</title><p>The specimens were embedded in paraffin wax and sliced. The slices dehydrated with gradient ethanol, inactivated endogenous enzyme with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and rinsed with phosphate buffer saline (PBS) three times 5 min each time. The slices were incubated with normal goat serum at room temperature for 15 min, added with the primary antibody of 20–30 μl PBS diluted MUC1 (1:100, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.) and Slug (1:100, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.) for incubation at 4°C overnight. The PBS replaced the primary antibody as a negative control. After that, the slices were rinsed with PBS three times, incubated with biotin labeled secondary antibody for 20 min, incubated with horseradish enzyme labeled streptomyces ovalbumin working fluid for 20 min and developed with diaminobenzidine (DAB) for 3–5 min (Beijing Zhongshan Golden Bridge Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China). Next, the slices were washed with running water, counterstained with hematoxylin for 5 min, dehydrated, cleared by xylene, and sealed. The PBS replaced the primary antibody as a blank control. Five high-power visual fields were randomly selected to observe the positive expression of MUC1 and Slug.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Cell culture</title><p>Normal oral epithelial cell line HOK and OSCC cell line SCC-4, Cal-27, TSCCA, and Tca8113 were purchased from American Type Culture Collection. Normal oral epithelial cell line HOK was cultured in HOK cell culture medium (Scien Cell, U.S.A.), SCC-4 and Cal-27 OSCC cells were cultured in DMEM (with 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 μg/ml streptomycin) containing 10% FBS, and TSCCA and Tca8113 OSCC cells were cultured in RPMI-1460 medium (with 10% FBS, 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 μg/ml streptomycin). All the cells were cultured in an incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 95% relative humidity at 37°C. The cells in logarithmic growth phase were collected and subcultured every 2 days.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Preparation of recombinant expression plasmid, cell transfection, and grouping</title><p>Two siRNA oligonucleotide sequence for MUC1 gene were designed: MUC1 siRNA-1 sequence: 5′-AAGGTACCATCAATGTCCACG-3′, MUC1 siRNA-2 sequence: 5′-AAGTTCAGTGCCCAGCTCTAC-3′. At the same time, a NC sequence (siRNA-NC) was designed: 5′-CGCTTACCGATTCAGAATGG-3′. Two siRNA recombinant expression plasmids pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-1 and pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2 were constructed using lentiviral plasmid pGC-LV. The recombinant plasmid was successfully digested and sequenced to confirm the successful recombination. The siRNA sequence was synthesized by Shanghai Genechem Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). TSCCA cells were inoculated into a cell culture plate at a density of 1 × 10<sup>9</sup> cells/l. The multiplicity of infection of viral plasmid was set as 50, and the cell transfection and grouping of TSCCA cells were based on transfection kit steps: (1) blank group: no virus infection; (2) con-siRNA group: infected with empty pGC-LV; (3) siRNA-NC group: infected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC; and (4) MUC1 siRNA-2 group: infected with pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>MTT assay</title><p>When the transfected TSCCA cells reached about 80%, the cells were washed with PBS twice. The cells were detached by trypsin, and the single cell suspension was made by trituration through the straw. The inoculated cells were inoculated in a 96-well plate at density of 3 × 10<sup>3</sup> – 6 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells in each well (200 μl/well), and six parallel wells were set. After incubated in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator at 37°C for 24–72 h, MTT solution (5 mg/ml, Sigma–Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.) was added to each well. The MTT solution (250 mg) was put it in a beaker, added with 50 ml of PBS (0.01 mol/l, pH 7.4), and stirred for 30 min on an electromagnetic mixer in in normal environment. The microporous filtering film (0.22 μm) was used for degerming, packaged and reserved at 4°C for further use. Next, after incubating in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator at 37°C for 4 h, and the culture medium was abandoned. Each well was added with 150 μl DMSO, shaking gently for 10 min to dissolve crystal. The optical density (OD) value of every well was determined with a microplate reader at 0, 24, 48, and 72 h, respectively. The OD value was set as ordinate, and the interval time was set as horizontal ordinate to plot MTT curve. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>EdU assay</title><p>The DNA replication of the cells was measured using a Cell-light EdU Luminescence Assay Kit (RiboBio, Guangzhou, China). Each group of cells was routinely detached, resuspended and counted, and seeded in a 96-well plate at 1.0 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well, with three replicate wells in each group. After incubating for 2 h with 100 μl of 50 μM EdU, cells were rinsed with PBS and fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min at room temperature. Next, the cells were rinsed with 0.5% Triton X-100, stained with 100 μl 1 × Apollo<sup>®</sup> staining solution, and incubated for 30 min. Subsequently, the cells were rinsed with 0.5% Triton X-100, stained with 100 μl 1 × Hoechst 33342 staining solution, and incubated for 30 min. Pictures were taken under a fluorescence microscope to calculate the number of cells with EdU label (red) and unlabeled (blue). Labeling index = (number of labeled [red] cells/number of labeled [red] cells + number of unlabeled [blue] cells) × 100%.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Colony formation assay</title><p>After 72 h of transfection, the cells in logarithmic growth phase were inoculated in a six-well culture plate (200 cells per well). Three parallel wells were set up and cultured at rest for 2 weeks. When white colony spots were observed in the naked eye, the operation was terminated. The cells were fixed with methanol (2 ml) at room temperature for 15 min, then stained with Giemsa solution at room temperature for 15 min, washed with water slowly, and dried. Cell colonies with more than 50 cells were counted under an optical microscope and the colony formation rate was calculated as the number of colonized cells/inoculated cells × 100%. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p>The cells were seeded into six-well culture plates according to 1 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells per well. After cell adherence, cells were cultured synchronously for 12 h, then the original culture medium was discarded, and the corresponding treatment was given for a specific time. The cell culture medium was carefully collected into a sterile centrifuge tube, with the trypsin to detach the cells. When the cells could be gently pipetted with a pipette, the cells were added with the previously collected cell culture solution. All the adherent cells were triturated for scattering cells. The cell suspension was collected, and the cells were centrifuged to the bottom of the tube, with the supernatant discarded. After that, the cells were washed with PBS twice, resuspended with precooled 75% ethanol, and fixed overnight at −20°C. After centrifugation, the supernatant was removed, and the cells were rinsed with PBS twice. The cells were collected by centrifugation, and 500 μl of PBS (containing 50 mg/ml propidium iodide [PI] and 50 μg/ml RNAse A) was added to each sample, then mixed together, and placed in water-bath at 37°C for 30 min. After centrifugation, the supernatant was abandoned, and the cells were suspended with PBS. Cell cycle distribution was measured and analyzed by flow cytometer (BD FACSAria™, BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, U.S.A.). The experiment was repeated three times independently.</p><p>After 72 h of transfection, the cells were collected, rinsed with PBS three times, and then added to the precooled 1 × binding buffer (500 μl). Next, the cell suspensions were added with 5 μl Annexin-V-FITC and 2.5 μl PI and mixed gently. The cell apoptosis was detected by flow cytometer (BD FACSAria™, BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, U.S.A.). In the scattered plot, the lower left quadrant (Q4) showed healthy living cells (FITC<sup>−</sup>/PI<sup>−</sup>), the lower right quadrant (Q3) showed early apoptotic cells (FITC<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>−</sup>), the right upper quadrant (Q2) showed necrosis and late apoptosis cells (FITC<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>), and apoptosis rate = early apoptosis percentage (Q3) + late apoptosis percentage (Q2). The experiment was repeated three times independently.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Scratch test</title><p>The back of the six-well plate was perpendicular to the horizontal axis and marked with a marker at every 0.5–1.0 cm interval. Cells were inoculated in each well. When the cells grew to 90% confluence, the cells were treated with mitomycin C (10 μg/ml, Sigma, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.) for 2 h, and washed with PBS three times. The cells were scratched along the marking line using a gun head perpendicular to the plate and washed twice with PBS to remove the floating cells. The cells were supplemented with serum-free medium and placed under the conditions of saturated humidity with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37°C. Photographs were taken under an inverted microscope at 0 and 24 h. Image tool software (Bechtel Nevada, Los Alamos Operations) was used to calculate healing area, and the healing rate was: (width value of initial scratch − width value of current scratch)/width value of initial scratch × 100%. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Transwell assay</title><p>Preparation of single cell suspension from serum-free medium was conducted by conventional method, with 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/ml. Matrigel was dissolved overnight at 4°C. The Matrigel was diluted with serum-free medium at the ratio of 1:3, and 30 μl diluted Matrigel was added into the apical chamber in each Tanswell chamber in three times (15, 7.5, and 7.5 μl) (Corning, New York, U.S.A.). At intervals of 10 min, the Matrigel was evenly spread and all micropores on the bottom of the apical chamber were covered. The medium containing 10% FBS was added to the basolateral chamber of 24-well plate with the cells suspensions inoculated into the apical chamber of Transwell and incubated at 37°C for 24 h. After removing the chamber and aspirating the medium, the cells that had not passed through the membrane were gently wiped off with a cotton swab and fixed it with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min. After natural air drying, the cells were stained with crystal violet for 5 min, washed gently with distilled water several times and air-dried. The number of cells passing through the Matrigel was used as an indicator of invasion. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Reverse transcription quantitative PCR</title><p>TRIzol method (Takara, Dalian, China) was used to extract total RNA in cells and tissues to determine the concentration and purity of RNA. The sample RNA was reversed to cDNA according to the specifications of the Reverse Transcription Kit (DRR047S, Takara Biomedical Technology [Dalian] Co., Ltd), and the total system was 10 μl. The cDNA obtained from the above inversion was added with 65 μl diethyl pyrocarbonate water to dilute and mix well. The primers were synthesized by Shenzhen BGI Co., Ltd. (Shenzhen, China). MUC1-Forward: 5′-TCAGTGCCGCCGAAAGAAC-3′, MUC1-Reverse: 5′-GCTCATAGGATGGTAGGTATCCC-3′; glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH)-Forward: 5′-AACGGATTTGGTCGTATTGGG-3′, GAPDH-Reverse: 5′-TCGCTCCTGGAAGATGGTGAT-3′. GAPDH was an internal reference, with three repeats for per gene in each sample. The reliability of PCR results was evaluated by the dissolution curve. ΔCT = CT<sub>(target gene)</sub> − CT<sub>(internal reference)</sub>, ΔCT = ΔCT<sub>(experimental group)</sub> − ΔCT<sub>(control group)</sub>. The relative expression of target gene was calculated by 2<sup>−ΔΔ<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></sup><sub>T</sub> [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>The total protein was extracted from the tissues and cells of each group. The bicinchoninic acid protein concentration assay kit was used to measure protein concentration, and the protein concentration of each group was adjusted. After adding with 5 × SDS loading buffer, the cells were denatured at 95°C for 5 min, separated by SDS PAGE, transferred, added with 5% skim milk powder, and sealed overnight at 4°C. After the membrane was washed with Tris-buffered saline with Tween-20 (TBST), it was then added with the primary antibody MUC1 (1:1000, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.), Slug (1 μg/ml, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.), E-cadherin (1:50, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.), Vimentin (1:500, Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.) and GAPDH (1:1000, Millipore Inc., Billerica, MA, U.S.A.), and incubated overnight at 4°C. After the membrane was washed with TBST, it was then added with horseradish peroxidase-labeled secondary antibody and incubated overnight at 4°C. After the membrane was washed with TBST, enhanced chemiluminescence was used for developing. The gray value of the target band was analyzed by ImageJ software, and the experiment was repeated three times independently.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>SPSS 19.0 (IBM-SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, U.S.A.) software was used for data analyzing, and the experiment was repeated three times independently to calculate mean and standard deviation. The t test was used to analyze the difference between groups. One-way ANOVA was used to analyze the difference amongst multigroups. After ANOVA, pairwise comparisons were analyzed by the least significant difference t test (LSD-t). The enumeration data were expressed by rate or percentage, which was analyzed by χ<sup>2</sup> test. Bilateral analysis was used in all analyses, and significant differences were observed in <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Higher positive rate of MUC1 and Slug expression in OSCC tissue</title><p>With the aim to observe the expression of MUC1 in OSCC tissues and normal oral mucosa tissues, we performed immunohistochemistry to detect the expression of MUC1. To further investigate whether MUC1 acts on OSCC via Slug, we used immunohistochemistry to detect the expression of Slug. The immunohistochemical staining results demonstrated that MUC1 was mainly expressed in cell cytoplasm in light yellow to brown in OSCC and normal oral mucosa tissues, and the nucleus was basically not stained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The positive rate of MUC1 in OSCC tissues was 66.67% (60/90), which was significant different that in the normal oral mucosa tissues (17.14%; 6/35; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The positive rate of Slug in OSCC tissues was 73.33% (66/90), which was higher than that in normal oral mucosa tissues (14.28%; 5/35; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). According to Spearman correlation analysis, MUC1 expression was positively correlated with Slug expression (r = 0.731, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). To analyze the correlation between the expression of MUC1 and the clinicopathological features of OSCC tissues, the results showed that the positive rate of MUC1 expression in OSCC tissues was associated with differentiation degree and lymph node metastasis (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The positive expression rate of MUC1 increased with the degree of tumor differentiation. The positive expression rate of MUC1 in patients without lymph node metastasis was significantly lower than that in patients with lymph node metastasis. However, the expression of MUC1 was not related to gender and age of patients (both <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0. 05; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Higher expression of MUC1 and Slug are found in OSCC tissues by immunohistochemical staining; <bold>OSCC tissues = 90 and normal oral mucosa tissues</bold> = 35</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Expression of MUC1 and Slug in the OSCC group and the control group</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSCC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MUC1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive (n)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative (n)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive expression rate (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slug</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive (n)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative (n)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive expression rate (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The enumeration data were expressed by rate or percentage, which was analyzed by χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Relationship between expression of MUC1 protein and clinicopathological parameters in OSCC</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical features</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">MUC1 expression</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(-)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (45.00%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (63.33%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55.00%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (36.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.878</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (38.33%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (40.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (61.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (60.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differentiation degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.67%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (56.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (36.67%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (26.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (41.66%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (16.66%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymph node metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (55.00%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (30.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (45.00%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (70.00%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The data were expressed in rate or percentage, and the analysis was conducted by χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Higher expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein is found in OSCC cells</title><p>Subsequently, in order to observe the expression of MUC1 in OSCC tissues and normal oral mucosa tissues, we adopted RT-qPCR and western blot analysis to detect the expression of mRNA and protein of MUC1 in tissue samples. The results suggested that the expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein in OSCC tissues was higher than that in normal oral mucosa tissues (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). Additionally, mRNA and protein expression of MUC1 in normal oral epithelial cell line HOK and OSCC cell line SCC-4, Cal-27, TSCCA, and Tca8113 were detected by RT-qPCR and western blot analysis. The results suggested that the expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein in OSCC cell line SCC-4, Cal-27, TSCCA, and Tca8113 was higher than that in normal oral epithelial cell line HOK (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). The expression of MUC1 was the highest in TSCCA cells, so we have chosen it for subsequent interference test.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Higher expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein is found in OSCC tissues and cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein in OSCC tissues and normal oral mucosa tissues, OSCC tissues = 90, normal oral mucosa tissues = 35; (<bold>B</bold>) mRNA and protein expression of MUC1 in normal oral epithelial cell line HOK and OSCC cell line SCC-4, Cal-27, TSCCA, and Tca8113. *<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05 vs normal oral epithelial cell line HOK. Data analysis was performed by <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test or one-way ANOVA. After one-way ANOVA, the LSD-t test was utilized for pairwise comparison.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Expression of MUC1 in each group after transfection</title><p>Next, for the purpose of observing the effect of MUC1 silencing on MUC1 expression in OSCC cells, we used RT-qPCR and western blot analysis to detect the expression of MUC1 mRNA and protein in each group. First, we extracted the total RNA from the cells after 48 h of lentivirus infection of TSCCA cells, and RT-qPCR was then used to detect the expression of MUC1 in each group. The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A) indicated that compared with the blank group (uninfected TSCCA cells), the mRNA expression of MUC1 was significantly decreased in the MUC1 siRNA-1 group (1.00 ± 0.02 vs 0.37 ± 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) and the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (1.00 ± 0.02 vs 0.25 ± 0.02, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). Amongst them, the MUC1 mRNA expression in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group was significantly decreased, and the subsequent experiments were performed using MUC1 siRNA-2. There was no significant difference in MUC1 mRNA expression between the con-siRNA group (transfected with empty pGC-LV) and the siRNA NC group (transfected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC) in comparison to the blank group (1.02 ± 0.06 vs 1.00 ± 0.02, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05; 0.97 ± 0.08 vs 1.00 ± 0.02, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). The total protein was extracted by TSCCA cells infected with lentivirus for 72 h. The expression of MUC1 protein was detected by western blot analysis, and the results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B) indicated that compared with the blank group, the protein expression of MUC1 was significantly decreased in the MUC1 siRNA-1 group and the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (0.76 ± 0.06 vs 0.29 ± 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; 0.76 ± 0.06 vs 0.15 ± 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). The protein expression of MUC1 was significantly decreased in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group, and the subsequent experiments were interfered with MUC1 siRNA-2. There was no significant difference in MUC1 protein expression amongst the con-siRNA group, the siRNA NC group and the blank group (0.74 ± 0.08 vs 0.76 ± 0.06, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05; 0.78 ± 0.08 vs 0.76 ± 0.06, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>MUC1 gene silencing suppresses proliferation of OSCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Expression of MUC1 mRNA in TSCCA cells of each group after 48-h infection of empty lentiviral vector, recombinant lentivirus that interferes with MUC1 expression, and negative control; (<bold>B</bold>) expression of MUC1 protein in TSCCA cells of each group after 72-h infection of empty lentiviral vector, recombinant lentivirus that interferes with MUC1 expression, and negative control; (<bold>C</bold>) cell proliferation curve of cells in each group; (<bold>D</bold>) EdU assay for detection of DNA replication of cells; (<bold>E</bold>) cell colony formation rate in each group. Blank group: no virus infection; con-siRNA group: infected with empty pGC-LV; siRNA-NC group: infected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC; MUC1 siRNA-2 group: infected with pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2. *<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05 vs the blank group. Data analysis was performed by one-way ANOVA. After one-way ANOVA, the LSD-t test was utilized for pairwise comparison. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Silencing of MUC1 inhibits the proliferation of OSCC cells</title><p>In order to observe the effect of interfering MUC1 expression on the proliferation of OSCC cells, we performed the MTT assay. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C, at 0 and 24 h after transfection, the OD<sub>450nm</sub> value of the blank group, con-siRNA group, siRNA NC group, and MUC1 siRNA-2 group were 0.38 ± 0.03 vs 0.37 ± 0.04 vs 0.37 ± 0.03 vs 0.38 ± 0.04 and 0.60 ± 0.04 vs 0.55 ± 0.06 vs 0.57 ± 0.04 vs 0.50 ± 0.05, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). At 48 and 72 h after transfection, the OD<sub>450nm</sub> value of the blank group, con-siRNA group, siRNA NC group, and MUC1 siRNA-2 group were 0.94 ± 0.06 vs 0.89 ± 0.07 vs 0.91 ± 0.06 vs 0.64 ± 0.05 and 1.26 ± 0.08 vs 1.20 ± 0.08 vs 1.22 ± 0.07 vs 0.80 ± 0.07, respectively. The OD<sub>450nm</sub> value in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group was lower than that in the blank group, con-siRNA group and siRNA NC group (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). No significant difference was found amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group and siRNA NC group (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05).</p><p>EdU is a thymidine analog with an acetylenic group attached to it that is rare in natural compounds. It replaces thymine (T) in the DNA replication phase and penetrates into the DNA molecule being synthesized. Based on Apollo<sup>®</sup>-based fluorescence, the specific reaction of the dye with EdU allows direct and accurate detection of DNA replication. The DNA replication of cells was detected by EdU assay. The results suggested that the proportion of EdU-positive cells in the blank, con-siRNA, siRNA NC, and MUC1 siRNA-2 groups was 46.5 ± 2.5%, 45.0 ± 1.6%, 44.5 ± 2.2%, and 30.4 ± 2.0%, respectively. No significant difference was found amongst the blank, con-siRNA group and siRNA NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). When TSCCA cells interfered with MUC1, the DNA replication of the cells was significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D).</p><p>In order to observe the effect of interfering MUC1 expression on the colony formation of OSCC cells, we performed the colony formation assay. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E, the colony formation rate in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group was 21.45% ± 2.02%, which was significantly lower than that of the blank group (54.81 ± 5.89%), con-siRNA group (52.02 ± 5.63%), and the siRNA NC group (53.01 ± 5.62%) (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). There was no significant difference in colony formation rate amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group, and the siRNA NC group (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). These results suggest that interference with MUC1 gene can inhibit the proliferation of OSCC cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>MUC1 gene silencing inhibits cell cycle progression and induces apoptosis of OSCC cells</title><p>Flow cytometry was used to detect the effects of interfering with MUC1 on cell cycle and apoptosis of OSCC cells. The cell cycle results showed that (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A) in the blank group, the cells in G1 phase were 54.86 ± 3.21%, in G2 phase was 16.45 ± 1.25%, and in S phase was 27.69 ± 2.04%; in the con-siRNA group, the cells in G1 phase were 54.36 ± 3.78%, in G2 phase was 17.64 ± 1.22%, and in S phase was 28.00 ± 1.99%; the cells in G1 phase in the siRNA NC group were 54.42 ± 3.68%, in G2 phase, 17.32 ± 1.24%, and in S phase, 28.26 ± 1.94%; in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group, the cells in G1 phase were 70.88 ± 3.58%, in G2 phase, 8.76 ± 0.72% and in S phase, 20.36 ± 1.63%. In contrast with the blank group, the cells in G1 phase increased and those in G2 phase decreased in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). There was no significant difference in cell cycle distribution amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group, and the siRNA NC group (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0. 05).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>MUC1 gene silencing represses cell cycle entry and induces apoptosis of OSCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Comparison of cell cycle distribution in each group; (<bold>B</bold>) comparison of cell apoptosis in different groups. Blank group: no virus infection; con-siRNA group: infected with empty pGC-LV; siRNA-NC group: infected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC; MUC1 siRNA-2 group: infected with pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2. *<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05 vs the blank group. Data analysis was performed by one-way ANOVA. After one-way ANOVA, the LSD-t test was utilized for pairwise comparison. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g4.jpg"/></fig><p>The results of cell apoptosis showed that (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B) the cell apoptosis rate in the blank, con-siRNA, siRNA NC, and MUC1 siRNA-2 groups was 4.9 ± 0.7%, 4.7 ± 0.6%, 4.8 ± 0.6%, and 14.8 ± 0.9%, respectively. The cell apoptosis rate in the blank, con-siRNA and siRNA NC groups was lower than that in the MUC1 siRNA-2 groups (<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). There was no significant difference in cell cycle distribution amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group and the siRNA NC group (<italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). These results suggest that silencing of MUC1 gene induces apoptosis of OSCC cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>MUC1 gene silencing decrease Slug expression and inhibits the development of EMT in OSCC cells</title><p>We detected the expression of Slug, E-cadherin, and Vimentin by western blot analysis to observe the MUC1 gene silencing on expression of Slug, epithelial interstitial marker proteins E-cadherin, and Vimentin of OSCC cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A,B). In contrast with the blank group, the expression of E-cadherin was increased and expression of Slug and Vimentin was decreased in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (E-cadherin: 0.08 ± 0.02 vs 0.17 ± 0.03; Slug: 0.45 ± 0.05 vs 0.21 ± 0.05; Vimentin: 0.24 ± 0.04 vs 0.11 ± 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). The expression of Slug, E-cadherin, and Vimentin was not significantly differed amongst the blank, con-siRNA and the siRNA-NC groups (0.45 ± 0.05 vs 0.43 ± 0.06 vs 0.44 ± 0.07; 0.08 ± 0.02 vs 0.09 ± 0.03 vs 0.08 ± 0.03; 0.24 ± 0.04 vs 0.23 ± 0.04 vs 0.22 ± 0.03, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). These results suggest that MUC1 gene silencing can decrease Slug expression and prevent the occurrence of EMT in OSCC cells.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>MUC1 gene silencing decreases expression of Slug and inhibits the development of EMT in OSCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Protein bands of Slug, E-cadherin, and Vimentin in each group; (<bold>B</bold>) expression of Slug, E-cadherin, and Vimentin in each group. Blank group: no virus infection; con-siRNA group: infected with empty pGC-LV; siRNA-NC group: infected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC; MUC1 siRNA-2 group: infected with pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2. *<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05 vs the blank group. Data analysis was performed by one-way ANOVA. After one-way ANOVA, the LSD-t test was utilized for pairwise comparison. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>MUC1 gene silencing inhibits migration and invasion in OSCC cells</title><p>Transwell assay was used to detect the invasion ability of each group, and scratch test was used to detect the migration ability of each group. The results of Transwell assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) showed that compared with the blank group, the number of cells invading the membrane decreased significantly in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (88 ± 4 vs 48 ± 6, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). There was no significant difference in cell invasion amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group and the siRNA NC group (88 ± 4 vs 85 ± 7, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0. 05; 88 ± 4 vs 86 ± 6, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). The scratch test results revealed that (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B) compared with the blank group, the scratch repair rate decreased significantly in the MUC1 siRNA-2 group (51.23 ± 4.95% vs 30.26 ± 3.68%, <italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05). There was no significant difference amongst the blank group, con-siRNA group and the siRNA NC group (51.23 ± 4.95% vs 48.86 ± 5.21%, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05; 51.23 ± 4.95% vs 49.97 ± 5.03%, <italic toggle="yes">P&gt;</italic>0.05). These results suggest that silencing of MUC1 gene can prevent the invasion and migration in OSCC cells.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>MUC1 gene silencing inhibits migration and invasion in OSCC cells</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Invasive ability of cells in each group; (<bold>B</bold>) migration ability of cells in each group. Blank group: no virus infection; con-siRNA group: infected with empty pGC-LV; siRNA-NC group: infected with pGC-LV-siRNA-NC; MUC1 siRNA-2 group: infected with pGC-LV-MUC1 siRNA-2. *<italic toggle="yes">P&lt;</italic>0.05 vs the blank group. Data analysis was performed by one-way ANOVA. After one-way ANOVA, the LSD-t test was utilized for pairwise comparison. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20182193-g6.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>OSCC is the most common neoplasm in the oral cavity, which has poor clinical outcomes related to recurrence and metastasis [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Despite of the recent progress has been made in the diagnosis of together with the therapeutic modalities for OSCC, the 5-year OS rate has not been improved [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, early prevention, detection as well as treatment would be the key point for the improvement of the survival rate and quality of life of patients suffering from OSCC patients [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore, it is urgently needed to seek for new targets for the effective therapy through a more comprehensive understanding of the mechanism of OSCC. Collectively, MUC1 gene silencing can inhibit the proliferation, invasion, and migration while inducing apoptosis of OSCC cells.</p><p>First, our study showed that higher expression of MUC1 was found in OSCC tissues and cells. As previously reported, MUC1 is frequently up-regulated in various cancers, which is also regarded as a potential biomarker for diagnosis, prognosis, and therapy of cancers [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Many researches have demonstrated that MUC1, as an oncogenic protein, is overexpressed in ovarian, gastric cancer as well as acute myeloid leukemia [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Additionally, MUC1 has been suggested to be up-regulated in a great many of cancer types, such as breast cancer, gastric cancer as well as type B3 thymoma and thymic carcinoma [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref>]. Furthermore, a previous study revealed that both transcription and translation products of MUC1 presented high expression in OSCC-derived cell lines [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. All these mentioned above confirmed the results of our study.</p><p>Meanwhile, the findings of our study also suggested that silencing of MUC1 inhibited the proliferation, cell cycle progression and EMT while inducing apoptosis of OSCC cells. The involvement of mucins has also been proposed in the renewal and differentiation of the epithelium, and also, in the modulation of both cell adhesion and cell signaling [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Similar to our study, a previous study has found that silencing of MUC1 is able to inhibit cell proliferation though the activation of apoptosis pathways and the induction of apoptosis in PANC-1 cells [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Additionally, another study has indicated that silencing of MUC1 is capable of inhibiting the development of non-small cell lung cancer cells [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As for the role of MUC1 in OSCC, it could be explained by the following reasons. Studies have also demonstrated that MUC1 enables to interact with several signals that involving in cell adhesion, growth as well as survival, and these signals includes protein kinase C, c-Src, and family member of the human epidermal growth factor receptor [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In addition, MUC1 is closely related to other molecules, including β-catenin, or epidermal growth factor receptor, which is able to regulate transcription of different genes that is responsible for progression and invasiveness of cancer [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Besides, MUC1 results in the initiation of several signaling pathways, which could promote growth, migration, invasion, as well as metastasis of tumors [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Furthermore, MUC1 enhances invasion and metastasis, and promotes EMT via up-regulating the expressions of transcription factors, such as Snail and Slug, as well as down-regulation of E-cadherin expression [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It is reported that Slug has an essential role in the regulation of EMT by inhibiting several epithelial markers together with adhesion molecules, including E-cadherin [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. E-cadherin is known as an important factor for EMT, and the loss of E-cadherin has been discussed in invasion and metastasis of many cancers [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Slug (Snail2) is an EMT transcription factor with zinc finger structure. Various signaling molecules and transduction pathways are involved in the regulation of Slug expression. The zinc finger transcription factor Slug mainly participates in EMT by regulating E-cadherin [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Slug is an invasion-promoting factor that inhibits E-cadherin transcription and enhances tumor cell migration and invasion [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These results suggest that Slug plays an important role in cell invasion and migration. It is reported that the activation of Slug results in a reduction in the proliferation of human epidermal keratinocytes [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and ectopic expression of Slug in the developing neural tube results in reduced cell proliferation [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], suggesting that Slug has a close association with cell proliferation. In addition, evidence has shown that Slug promotes survival and hinders cell death by directly repressing PUMA, a key BH3-only antagonist of the antiapoptotic Bcl-2 protein [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Bcl-2 is a Slug-regulated gene in mouse [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. siRNA directed against the Slug gene increases cell death induction in human melanoma cell lines exposed to cisplatin and fotemustine [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], suggesting Slug has a close association with cell apoptosis. Based on the above findings, we hypothesized that MUC1 may affect cell proliferation, apoptosis, invasion, migration, and EMT through the action of Slug. The results in our study showed that the positive expression rate of Slug protein in OSCC group was higher than that in the control group; the expression of MUC1 was positively correlated with Slug expression; MUC1 gene silencing can reduce the expression of Slug. In summary, MUC1 gene silencing can inhibit proliferation, invasion, migration, EMT while promoting apoptosis of OSCC cells via the inhibition of Slug.</p><p>In conclusion, our study highlights the function of MUC1 in OSCC. Additionally, MUC1 gene silencing can inhibit the proliferation, invasion, and migration while inducing apoptosis of OSCC cells. However, the potential mechanisms of MUC1 in the progression of OSCC needs further explanation. Meanwhile, we would carry out immunohistochemical serial section to detect the MUC1 and Slug protein expression to further verify our results.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to acknowledge the reviewers for their helpful comments on the present study.</p></ack><sec id="sec5" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>A.M.Z., X.H.C., and J.Z. focussed on the study design. Z.Q.B. and X.F.H. carried out experimental studies. Z.Q.B. and X.F.H. performed statistical analysis. A.M.Z., X.H.C., and J.Z. dedicated to the manuscript preparation.</p></sec><sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that there are no sources of funding to be acknowledged.</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="G1">DAB</term><def><p>diaminobenzidine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">EMT</term><def><p>epithelial-mesenchymal transition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">LSD-t</term><def><p>least significant difference t test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">MUC1</term><def><p>mucin 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">OD</term><def><p>optical density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">OSCC</term><def><p>oral squamous cell carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">PBS</term><def><p>phosphate buffer saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">PI</term><def><p>propidium iodide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">TBST</term><def><p>Tris-buffered saline with Tween-20</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Interference of mucin 1 inhibits progression of colon carcinoma by repression of Wnt/beta-catenin signaling</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/dna.2013.2274</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24410135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>High PD-L1 expression correlates with metastasis and poor prognosis in oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0142656</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142656</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26562534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4642967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Outcome analysis of patients with well-differentiated oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>1091</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2011.07.018</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koumaki</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Novel mutations of the HRAS gene and absence of hotspot mutations of the BRAF genes in oral squamous cell carcinoma in a Greek population</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Rep.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1555</fpage>–<lpage>1560</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22294102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2012.1653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Detection of two novel mutations and relatively high incidence of H-RAS mutations in Vietnamese oral cancer</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>e161</fpage>–<lpage>e166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2009.05.638</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19628422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2011</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J. Clin.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Advances and applications of oral cancer basic research</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2011.07.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21802978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Potential biomarkers in saliva for oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2010.01.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bisen</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Oncoapoptotic signaling and deregulated target genes in cancers: special reference to oral cancer</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>1836</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23602834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbcan.2013.04.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahomed</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Recent advances in mucin immunohistochemistry in salivary gland tumors and head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>797</fpage>–<lpage>803</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2011.06.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21723776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narashiman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatraman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Expression of Mucin 4 in leukoplakia and oral squamous cell carcinoma: An immunohistochemical study</article-title>. <source>J. Oral Maxillofac. Pathol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-029X.131887</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24959033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4065443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaggi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mucins in ovarian cancer diagnosis and therapy</article-title>. <source>J. Ovarian Res.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-2215-2-21</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2804676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinn</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of Mucin-1 protein and mRNA expression as prognostic and predictive markers after neoadjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Ann. Oncol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2316</fpage>–<lpage>2324</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdt162</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23661292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Expression of mucin 1 and tumor invasiveness in breast carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15854526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woenckhaus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Prognostic value of FHIT, CTNNB1, and MUC1 expression in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Hum. Pathol.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2007.05.027</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17949785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatrai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mucin1 expression is enriched in the human stem cell fraction of cord blood and is upregulated in majority of the AML cases</article-title>. <source>Exp. Hematol.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>1254</fpage>–<lpage>1265</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2008.04.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18640764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>MUC1 downregulation inhibits non-small cell lung cancer progression in human cell lines</article-title>. <source>Exp. Ther. Med.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>4443</fpage>–<lpage>4447</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29104655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/etm.2017.5062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5658714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Human DF3/MUC1 carcinoma-associated protein functions as an oncogene</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>6107</fpage>–<lpage>6110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1206732</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12955090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4209839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horm</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MUC1 and metastatic cancer: expression, function and therapeutic targeting</article-title>. <source>Cell Adh. Migr.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cam.23131</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3954031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MUC1: a target molecule for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol. Ther.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cbt.6.4.4201</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18027437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Expression of MUC1 mucin in potentially malignant disorders, oral squamous cell carcinoma and normal oral mucosa: An immunohistochemical study</article-title>. <source>J. Oral. Maxillofac. Pathol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-029X.185916</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27601811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4989549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Canonical Wnt signaling regulates Slug activity and links epithelial-mesenchymal transition with epigenetic Breast Cancer 1, Early Onset (BRCA1) repression</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>16654</fpage>–<lpage>16659</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1205822109</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3478591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MUC1 enhances invasiveness of pancreatic cancer cells by inducing epithelial to mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1449</fpage>–<lpage>1459</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2010.526</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21102519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3063863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesting</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Psoriasin (S100A7) up-regulation in oral squamous cell carcinoma and its relation to clinicopathologic features</article-title>. <source>Oral Oncol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>731</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oraloncology.2008.11.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19147391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuo</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Long noncoding RNA UCA1 modulates breast cancer cell growth and apoptosis through decreasing tumor suppressive miR-143</article-title>. <source>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3403</fpage>–<lpage>3411</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26439035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naganuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic alterations of the keratin 13 gene in oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>988</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2407-14-988</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25527207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4364656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markopoulos</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Current aspects on oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Open Dent. J.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874210601206010126</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3428647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Axl is a prognostic marker in oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Ann. Surg. Oncol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>S500</fpage>–<lpage>S508</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-011-1985-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21842265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blatt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Biomarkers in diagnosis and therapy of oral squamous cell carcinoma: a review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J. Craniomaxillofac. Surg.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcms.2017.01.033</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28318929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gharat</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Momin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhavsar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Oral squamous cell carcinoma: current treatment strategies and nanotechnology-based approaches for prevention and therapy</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Ther. Drug Carrier Syst.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/CritRevTherDrugCarrierSyst.2016016272</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27910740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MUC1 protein induces urokinase-type plasminogen activator (uPA) by forming a complex with NF-kappaB p65 transcription factor and binding to the uPA promoter, leading to enhanced invasiveness of cancer cells</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>289</volume>, <fpage>35193</fpage>–<lpage>35204</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.586461</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4271208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kufe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Human mucin 1 oncoprotein represses transcription of the p53 tumor suppressor gene</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>1853</fpage>–<lpage>1858</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-3063</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17308127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Scoparone exerts anti-tumor activity against DU145 prostate cancer cells via inhibition of STAT3 activity</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e80391</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0080391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3829856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khodarev</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cooperativity of the MUC1 oncoprotein and STAT1 pathway in poor prognosis human breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>920</fpage>–<lpage>929</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2009.391</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19915608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2820589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Retterspitz</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Expression of {beta}-catenin, MUC1 and c-met in diffuse-type gastric carcinomas: correlations with tumour progression and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>4635</fpage>–<lpage>4641</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21115917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaira</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MUC1 expression in thymic epithelial tumors: MUC1 may be useful marker as differential diagnosis between type B3 thymoma and thymic carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Virchows. Arch.</source>
<volume>458</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00428-011-1041-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21253760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Muc-1 promotes migration and invasion of oral squamous cell carcinoma cells via PI3K-Akt signaling</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Clin. Exp. Pathol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>10365</fpage>–<lpage>10374</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26617744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4637559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Aberrant expression of transmembrane mucins, MUC1 and MUC4, in human prostate carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Prostate</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pros.20372</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16302265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Human MUC1 carcinoma antigen regulates intracellular oxidant levels and the apoptotic response to oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>, <fpage>35458</fpage>–<lpage>35464</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M301987200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Masri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gendler</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Muc1 affects c-Src signaling in PyV MT-induced mammary tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>5799</fpage>–<lpage>5808</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1208738</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinzaglia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>EIF6 over-expression increases the motility and invasiveness of cancer cells by modulating the expression of a critical subset of membrane-bound proteins</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-015-1106-3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4381359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Transient gene silencing of galectin-3 suppresses pancreatic cancer cell migration and invasion through degradation of beta-catenin</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Cancer</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>2775</fpage>–<lpage>2786</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.25946</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21448903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3833077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Decreased expression of MUC1 induces apoptosis and inhibits migration in pancreatic cancer PANC-1 cells via regulation of Slug pathway</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biomark</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/CBM-170297</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28869438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvan</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Expression of E-cadherin repressors SNAIL, ZEB1 and ZEB2 by tumour and stromal cells influences tumour-budding phenotype and suggests heterogeneity of stromal cells in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Cancer</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>1944</fpage>–<lpage>1950</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2015.177</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25989272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4580384</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11920104"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Prognostic impact of EMT (epithelial-mesenchymal-transition)-related protein expression in endometrial cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol. Ther.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cbt.22625</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23114646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3566047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Slug regulates integrin expression and cell proliferation in human epidermal keratinocytes</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>281</volume>, <fpage>21321</fpage>–<lpage>21331</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M509731200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16707493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Snail blocks the cell cycle and confers resistance to cell death</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1131</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.294104</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC415638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Slug antagonizes p53-mediated apoptosis of hematopoietic progenitors by repressing puma</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2005.09.029</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16286009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermejo-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Mouse cDNA microarray analysis uncovers Slug targets in mouse embryonic fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2005.09.014</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannini</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Short interfering RNA directed against the SLUG gene increases cell death induction in human melanoma cell lines exposed to cisplatin and fotemustine</article-title>. <source>Cell. Oncol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17641412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2007/540821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4617797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>