
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci. Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BSR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6614573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6614573.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6614573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6614573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31239367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20190700</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>22</subject><subject>52</subject><subject>53</subject><subject>46</subject><subject>51</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Down-regulation of microRNA-142-3p inhibits the aggressive phenotypes of rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes through inhibiting nuclear factor-κB signaling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names initials="T">Tingting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenbiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9187-8457</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xichao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Yan’An People’s Hospital, No. 57, Qilipu Street, Baota District, Yan’an City 716000, Shaanxi Province, China</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Rheumatology and Immunology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of The Fourth Military Medical University, No. 569, Xinsi Road, Xi’an City 710038, Shaanxi Province, China</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Immunology, The First Affiliated Hospital of The Fourth Military Medical University, No. 1, Changle East Road, Xi’an City 710032, Shaanxi Province, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Xichao Yang (<email>yangxichao258@163.com</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">337429</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20190700</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>07</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>07</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 12:25:10.757"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2019 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="expression-of-concern" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7317590"><article-title>Expression of Concern: Downregulation of microRNA-142-3p inhibits the aggressive phenotypes of rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes through inhibiting Nuclear factor-kappa B signaling</article-title><volume>40</volume><issue>6</issue><date><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-20190700_EOC</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-20190700_EOC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7317590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32584394</pub-id></related-article><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Biosci Rep" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC7463301"><article-title>Retraction: Downregulation of microRNA-142-3p inhibits the aggressive phenotypes of rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes through inhibiting Nuclear factor-kappa B signaling</article-title><volume>40</volume><issue>9</issue><date><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><elocation-id>BSR-20190700_RET</elocation-id><source>Bioscience Reports</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR-20190700_RET</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7463301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32869853</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The present study aimed to investigate the regulatory roles of miR-142-3p on the aggressive phenotypes of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) human fibroblast-like synoviocytes (RA-HFLSs), and reveal the potential mechanisms relating with nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) signaling. miR-142-3p expression was detected in RA synovial tissues and RA-HFLSs by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) and Northern blot analysis. RA-HFLSs were transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and/or treated with 10 µg/l tumor necrosis factor α (TNF-α). The viability, colony formation, apoptosis, migration, invasion, and the levels of interleukin (IL)-6, and matrix metalloproteinase 3 (MMP-3) were detected. The mRNA expressions of B-cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2), Bax, Bad, IL-6, and MMP-3 were detected by qRT-PCR. Moreover, the expression of Bcl-2, IL-1 receptor-associated kinase 1 (IRAK1), Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4), NF-κB p65, and phosphorylated NF-κB p65 (p-NF-κB p65) were detected by Western blot. The interaction between IRAK1 and miR-142-3p was identified by dual luciferase reporter gene assay. MiR-142-3p was up-regulated in RA synovial tissues and RA-HFLSs. TNF-α activated the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs, including enhanced proliferation, migration, invasion, and inflammation, and inhibited apoptosis. miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the cell viability, the number of cell clones, the migration rate, the number of invasive cells, the contents and expression of IL-6 and MMP-3, and increased the apoptosis rate and the expressions of Bax and Bad, and decreased Bcl-2 expression of TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs. MiR-142-3p inhibitor significantly reversed TNF-α-induced up-regulation of IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs. Besides, IRAK1 was a target of miR-142-3p. The down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs through inhibiting NF-κB signaling.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Inflammation</kwd><kwd>MicroRNA-142-3p</kwd><kwd>Nuclear factor-kappa B</kwd><kwd>Proliferation</kwd><kwd>Tumor necrosis factor α</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a common autoimmune disease that affects 0.5–1% of the population worldwide [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. RA is characterized by chronic inflammation in synovial tissues, and accompanied with the symptoms of pain, swelling, and stiffness of the joints [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Since RA contributes the destruction of cartilage and bone, RA is considered as one of the most common causes of disability [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In clinic practice, the therapeutic strategies for RA mainly focus on the control of pain and inflammation, as well as the protection of joint damage [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. With the increasing revelation of the molecular mechanisms involved in the pathogenesis of RA, molecular targeting therapy has become a promising therapeutic strategy for RA.</p><p>Tumor necrosis factor α (TNF-α) is a proinflammatory cytokine that plays a key role in the pathogenesis of RA [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Since activated TNF-α is closely associated with the inflammation of synovial tissues, anti-TNF-α has become a promising therapeutic target for RA [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Until now, drugs targeting TNF-α have been widely applied in the treatment of RA, such as adalimumab, etanercept and infliximab [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, the long-term application of TNF-α antagonists may be accompanied with the risk of infection and malignancy [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, novel therapeutic strategies for RA with high efficiency and safety are urgently needed.</p><p>MicroRNAs (miRs) are a family of small non-coding RNAs that involved in the occurrence and development of RA [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Previous studies have been proved that some miRs are up-regulated in RA, such as miR-146 [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], −155 [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], −203 [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], −221 [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and −126 [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and some are down-regulated, such as miR-34a [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], −124a [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], −22 [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and −188-5p [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These miRs exert diverse regulatory roles in the aggressive phenotypes of RA human fibroblast-like synoviocytes (RA-HFLSs). For examples, miR-221 inhibitor inhibits the migration and invasion, and promotes the apoptosis of RA-HFLSs [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Lentivirus-miR-126 promotes the proliferation and inhibits the apoptosis of RA-HFLSs [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The precursor miR-124a suppresses the proliferation of RA-HFLSs by arresting the cell cycle at the G<sub>1</sub> phase [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and miR-188-5p mimic inhibits the migration of RA-HFLSs [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. miR-142-3p is an important miR that involved in the regulation of inflammation [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It has been reported that miR-142-3p mimic alleviates bleomycin-induced apoptosis and overproduction of interleukin (IL)-1 and TNF-α in MLE-12 cells [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. MiR-142-3p was down-regulated in the articular cartilage tissues of osteoarthritis (OA) mice, and the overexpression of miR-142-3p inhibits lipopolysaccharide (LSP)-induced apoptosis and the production of IL-1, IL-6, and TNF-α [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, the specific regulatory roles of miR-142-3p on RA are still unclear.</p><p>In the present study, the expression of miR-142-3p was detected in both RA synovial tissues and RA-HFLSs. The regulatory effects of miR-142-3p on the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs, including the proliferation, apoptosis, migration, invasion, and inflammation were evaluated. In addition, the potential regulatory mechanisms of miR-142-3p related with nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) signaling were further analyzed. Our findings may not only provide a novel therapeutic target for RA, but also reveal new insights into the underlying mechanisms of RA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Patients</title><p>A total of ten RA patients (six males and four females, 52 ± 4 years old) were screened from our hospital between February 2017 and October 2017. During the same period, ten OA patients (three males and seven females, 52 ± 5 years old) were randomly screened. Both OA and RA were diagnosed according to the criteria established by the American College of Rheumatology. The present study was approved by the local Institutional Review Board, and informed consents were obtained from all subjects.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Isolation and culturing of HFLSs</title><p>RA-HFLSs and OA-HFLSs were isolated from synovial tissues of RA and OA patients, respectively. Simply, synovial tissues were washed with phosphate buffer saline (PBS), cut into fragments, and digested with 0.1% Type-I collagenase (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.) for 4 h at 37°C. Followed by 5 min of centrifugation at 1000 rpm/min, HFLSs were resuspended in High-glucose Dulbecco’s modified eagle medium (H-DMEM) (Hyclone, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, U.S.A.) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS). Normal HFLSs, and HEK-293T cells (human renal epithelial cell line) were purchased from The Cell Bank of Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China), and maintained in H-DMEM containing 10% FBS. All cells were cultured in a humidified incubator at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The medium was refreshed every 2 days, and cells were passaged until 80–90% confluence. Logarithmic growth phase cells (third to eigth generation) were used for treatments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Cell transfection and treatments</title><p>MiR-142-3p inhibitor and miR-142-3p inhibitor negative control (INC) were purchased from Guangzhou Ruibo Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Guangzhou, China). RA-HFLSs were seeded in 6-well plates at a density of 6×10<sup>5</sup> cell/well, and transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor or INC using lipofectamine 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific). After 24 h of transfection, the transfected-HFLSs were treated with 10 µg/l TNF-α for 24 h. RA-HFLSs were randomly divided into four groups, including Mock (RA-HFLSs without treatment), TNF-α (RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α), INC + TNF-α (RA-HFLSs transfected with INC and treated with TNF-α), and Inhibitor + TNF-α (RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from HFLSs using TRIzol agent (Thermo Fisher Scientific), and cDNA was reverse-transcribed using PrimeScript RT reagent Kit (TaKaRa, Japan) in accordance with manufacturer’s instructions. Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed on ABI 7500 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, U.S.A.) using specific primers (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The PCR program included 95°C for 3 min, 40 cycles at 95°C for 15 s, 60°C for 20 s, and 72°C for 20 s. U6 and GAPDH were used as internal controls. The relative expression of target genes were calculated according to the 2<sup>−ΔΔ<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></sup><sub>t</sub> method [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>The sequences of specific primers used in qRT-PCR</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primers</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Sequences</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">miR-142-3p</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GGGTGTAGTGTTTCCTACT-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CAGTGCGTGTCGTGGAGT-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-TGCGGGTGCTCCGCTTCGGCAGC-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CAGTGCAGGGTCCGAGGT-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-TGTAGCATGGGCACCTC-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CAGTGGACAGGTTTCTGAC-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bcl-2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GGTGGGGTCATGTGTGTGG-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CGGTTCAGGTACTCAGTCATCC-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bax</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-AGGCCATCAGCAACAACATAAGT-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GACAGCTTTGTGCTGGATCTGTG-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bad</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-AACTCGAGTGACAAGCCCGTA -3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GTACCACCAGTTGGTTGTCTTTGA -3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMP-3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CGGTTCCGCCTGTCTCAAG-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CGCCAAAAGTGCCTGTCTT -3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRAK1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CCAAACATTGTGGACTTTGC-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-GGCTGTACCCAGAAGGATGT-3′</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAPDH</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-TCCTCTGACTTCAACAGCGACAC-3′</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′-CACCCTGTTGCTGTAGCCAAATTC–3′</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Northern analysis of miRNAs</title><p>Northern analysis of miRNAs was performed as previously described [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Briefly, total 10 μg RNA was separated on 15% polyacrylamide–urea gels, transferred onto a Zeta-probe membrane (BioRad, Hercules, CA, U.S.A.) , and crosslinked by ultraviolet irradiation. The blots were pre-hybridized, and hybridized with specific probes, γ-32P end-labeled miR-142-3p probes or U6 at 37°C for 16 h.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>MTT assay</title><p>MTT was performed to detect the viability of RA-HFLSs. Simply, 200 μl RA-HFLSs were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 6×10<sup>3</sup> cells/well, and then incubated with 20 μg MTT (Sigma) for 4 h. After removing the medium, 150 μl DMSO was added into each well. Optical density (OD) at 495 nm was detected by a Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, U.S.A.).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Colony formation assay</title><p>Colony formation assay was performed to detect the colony-forming ability of RA-HFLSs. Simply, RA-HFLSs were seeded in 6-well plates at a density of 500 cells/well, and cultured for 14 days. After removing the medium, the colonies were fixed in methanol for 15 min and stained with crystal violet for 15 min. The stained colonies were observed under microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan), and counted by using the software of ImageJ version 1.48V (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, U.S.A.).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>TUNEL assay</title><p>TUNEL assay was performed to detect the apoptosis of RA-HFLSs. Simply, RA-HFLSs were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 1 h, permeabilized with 0.1% TritonX-100/0.1% sodium citrate for 2 min, and blocked with 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 10 min. Then cells were stained with TUNEL (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) in accordance with manufacturer’s instructions. Positive-stained cells were observed under microscope (Olympus), and counted in five randomly selected fields (×100).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Wound healing assay</title><p>Wound healing assay was performed to detect the migratory ability of RA-HFLSs. Simply, RA-HFLSs were seeded in 6-well plates at a density of 5×10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. When reaching 90% confluence, a wound track was scored in each well with a pipette tip. The cell debris were removed by washing with PBS. After 48 h of culturing, the migrated cells were observed under microscope (Olympus), and the migratory distance was measured.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Transwell assay</title><p>Transwell assay was performed to detect the invasive ability of RA-HFLSs by using transwell chambers (BD, Franklin Lakes, NJ, U.S.A.). Simply, 100 µl cells were seeded in the upper chamber (pre-coated with Matrigel) at a density 1×10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. The lower chamber is filled with 500 µl DMEM containing 10% FBS. Followed by 48 h of incubation at 37°C, cells on the upper chamber were removed with cotton swabs. Cells on the lower chamber were washed with PBS, fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min, and stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 10 min. Positive-stained cells were observed under microscope (Olympus), and counted in five randomly selected fields (×100).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Western blot</title><p>RA-HFLSs were lysed in RIPA Lysis buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China). Total proteins were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate/polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis on 10% polyacrylamide gels, and transferred to polyvinylidenefluoride membrane (Millipore, Billerica, MA, U.S.A.). Then the membrane was blocked with 0.5% skim milk in Tris-buffered saline Tween (TBST) for 1 h, and incubated with specific primary antibodies (rabbit anti-human; anti-IRAK1, #ab245342; anti-TLR4, #ab13556; anti-p-NF-κB p65, #ab86299; anti-Bcl-2, #ab196495; anti-Bax, #ab32503; Bad, #ab32445; anti-GAPDH, #ab9485; 1: 1000, Abcam, Cambridge, England; NF-κB p65, 1:1000, #3033, Cell Signal, U.S.A.) overnight at 4°C. Followed by three times of washing with TBST, the membrane was incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated secondary antibody (goat anti-rabbit; 1: 5000, Sigma) for 1 h at 37°C. The protein brands were visualized using HRP color development kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</title><p>The contents of IL-6, and matrix metalloproteinase 3 (MMP-3) were detected in RA-HFLSs by using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits (eBioscience, Thermo Fisher Scientific) in accordance with manufacturer’s instructions. The OD at 450/550 nm was measured by a Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Dual luciferase reporter gene assay</title><p>Dual luciferase reporter gene (DLR) assay was performed to identify the interaction between IL-1 receptor-associated kinase 1 (IRAK1) and miR-142-3p. Simply, HEK-293T cells were co-transfected with PsiCHECK-2 luciferase plasmids (Promega, Madison, WI, U.S.A.) carrying IRAK1-wild-type (PSMD11-WT)/IRAK1-mutant (PSMD11-MT) and miR-142-3p mimics/miR-142-3p mimics negative control (NC) (Ruibo). After 48 h of transfection, the fluorescence was visualized using a Dual Luciferase Reporter Assay Kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The fluorescence intensity was detected by a Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-14"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>All data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation. Statistical analysis was performed by SPSS version 18.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, U.S.A.). Comparison between different groups was determined by <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (two groups) or one-way ANOVA (more than two groups). A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 represented significantly different.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>MiR-142-3p was up-regulated in RA</title><p>The expression of miR-142-3p was detected in both RA tissues and RA-HFLSs. qRT-PCR showed that the expression of miR-142-3p in synovial tissues was significantly higher in RA patients than in OA patients, and was significantly higher in RA patients at stage IV than in those at stage III (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A,B). RA- and OA-HFLSs were isolated from synovial tissues of RA and OA patients, respectively. The expression of miR-142-3p was significantly higher in RA-HFLSs than in OA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). No significant difference on the expression of miR-142-3p was observed between OA-HFLSs and HFLSs (normal control) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). Additionally, Northern blot analysis showed that miR-142-3p was significantly up-regulated in RA patients compared with OA patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>D). Similarly, expression of miR-142-3p in RA-HFLSs was higher than that in OA-HFLSs and TFLSs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>E).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The expression of miR-142-3p detected by qRT-PCR</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Relative miR-142-3p mRNA expression in synovial tissues of OA and RA patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10); (<bold>B</bold>) Relative miR-142-3p mRNA expression in synovial tissues of OA patients at stage III and IV (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5); (<bold>C</bold>) Relative miR-142-3p mRNA expression in OA human fibroblast-like synoviocytes (OA-HFLSs), RA-HFLSs, and normal HFLSs; (<bold>D</bold>) Northern blot analysis of miR-142-3p in synovial tissues of OA and RA patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10); (<bold>E</bold>) Northern blot analysis of miR-142-3p in OA-HFLSs, RA-HFLSs and normal HFLSs. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus OA (A) RAIII (B) or HFLS and OA-HFLS (C).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited TNF-α-induced proliferation of RA-HFLSs</title><p>The viability of RA-HFLSs was detected by MTT assay. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A, the viability (OD<sub>495</sub> value) of RA-HFLSs was significantly increased with increasing concentrations of TNF-α in a dose-dependent manner until a peak at 10 µg/l (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The results of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B showed the mRNA expression of miR-142-3p in inhibitor group was significantly decreased compared with Mock group and INC group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05), suggesting miR-142-3p inhibitor was successfully transfected. The treatment of 10 µg/l TNF-α significantly increased the viability of RA-HFLSs with increasing times in a time-dependent manner (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The viability of RA-HFLSs was significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group at different time points (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). In addition, the transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the viability of TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs at different time points (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C). Furthermore, colony formation assay showed that the number of cell clones was significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the number of cell clones formed by TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D). The cell viability and colony formation were not significantly influenced by the transfection of INC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C,D).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The proliferation of RA-HFLSs</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The viability (OD<sub>495</sub> value) of RA-HFLSs under the treatment of different concentrations of TNF-α (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5); (<bold>B</bold>) The mRNA expression of miR-142-3p was detected by quantitative real-time PCR; (<bold>C</bold>) The viability of RA-HFLSs under the treatment of 10 µg/l TNF-α for different times (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5). (<bold>D</bold>) The number of cell clones formed by TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5). Mock, RA-HFLSs without treatment; TNF-α, RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α; INC + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p INC and treated with TNF-α; Inhibitor + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α. a, b, and c, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus 0, 5, 10, 20 mg/l TNF-α, respectively (A). *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock and INC (B). *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock; #, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus TNF-α and INC + TNF-α (B and C).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Down-regulation of miR-142-3p promoted TNF-α-induced apoptosis of RA-HFLSs</title><p>The apoptosis of RA-HFLSs was detected by TUNEL staining. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A,B, the apoptosis rate of RA-HFLSs was significantly lower in TNF-α group than in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly increased the apoptosis rate of TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A,B). In addition, the expression of B-cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2), an apoptotic marker was significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group at both the mRNA and protein level (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). On the contrary, the expressions of Bax and Bad in TNF-α group were remarkedly lower than those in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly down-regulated Bcl-2 and up-regulated Bax and Bad in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C,D). The apoptosis rate and the expressions of Bcl-2, Bax, and Bad were not significantly influenced by the transfection of INC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A–D).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The apoptosis of RA-HFLSs</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) TUNEL staining of RA-HFLSs under microscope (×100); (<bold>B</bold>) The apoptosis rate of RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5); (<bold>C</bold>) The relative mRNA expression of Bcl-2, Bax and Bad. (<bold>D</bold>) The relative protein expression of Bcl-2, Bax and Bad. Mock, RA-HFLSs without treatment; TNF-α, RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α; INC + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p INC and treated with TNF-α; Inhibitor + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock; #, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus TNF-α and INC + TNF-α.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited TNF-α-induced migration and invasion of RA-HFLSs</title><p>The migration and invasion of RA-HFLSs was detected by wound healing assay and transwell assay, respectively. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A, the migration rate of RA-HFLSs was significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the migration rate of TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The migration of RA-HFLSs was not significantly influenced by the transfection of INC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). Consistent results with the migration rate were observed on the number of invasive RA-HFLSs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The migration and invasion of RA-HFLSs</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The migration rate detected by wound healing assay (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5); (<bold>B</bold>) The number of invasive cells detected by transwell assay (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5). Mock, RA-HFLSs without treatment; TNF-α, RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α; INC + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p INC and treated with TNF-α; Inhibitor + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock; #, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus TNF-α and INC + TNF-α.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited TNF-α-induced inflammation of RA-HFLSs</title><p>The inflammation of RA-HFLSs was evaluated by the levels of IL-6 and MMP-3. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A,B, the contents of IL-6 and MMP-3 were significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the contents of IL-6 and MMP-3 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The contents of IL-6 and MMP-3 were not significantly influenced by the transfection of INC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A,B). Consistent results with the contents of IL-6 and MMP-3 were observed on the expression of IL-6 and MMP-3 in RA-HFLSs at the mRNA level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C,D).</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The levels of inflammatory factors in RA-HFLSs</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) IL-6 content; (<bold>B</bold>) MMP-3 content; (<bold>C</bold>) Relative IL-6 mRNA expression detected by qRT-PCR; (<bold>D</bold>) Relative MMP-3 mRNA expression detected by qRT-PCR. Mock, RA-HFLSs without treatment; TNF-α, RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α; INC + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p INC and treated with TNF-α; Inhibitor + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock; #, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus TNF-α and INC + TNF-α.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited TNF-α-induced activation of NF-κB in RA-HFLSs</title><p>In order to reveal the regulatory mechanisms of miR-142-3p relating with NF-κB signaling, the expression of IRAK1, Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4), NF-κB p65 and phosphorylated NF-κB p65 (p-NF-κB p65) were detected in RA-HFLSs. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, the expression of IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 in RA-HFLSs were significantly higher in TNF-α group than in Mock group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the expression of IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05). The expression of IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 were not significantly influenced by the transfection of INC. In addition, NF-κB p65 expression was not statistically siginificant between different groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>The expression of IRAK1, TLR4, NF-κB p65, and p-NF-κB p65 in RA-HFLSs detected by Western blot</title><p>Mock, RA-HFLSs without treatment; TNF-α, RA-HFLSs treated with TNF-α; INC + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p INC and treated with TNF-α; Inhibitor + TNF-α, RA-HFLSs transfected with miR-142-3p inhibitor and treated with TNF-α. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus Mock; #, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus TNF-α and INC + TNF-α.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g6.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>IRAK1 was a target of miR-142-3p</title><p>Since the miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly down-regulated IRAK1 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs, the specific interaction between IRAK1 and miR-142-3p was further analyzed. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A, a binding site of miR-142-3p was predicted at 3′-UTR of IRAK1 by an online target gene prediction software (Target Scan) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). In addition, DLR assay showed that the fluorescence intensity was significantly lower in HEK-293T cells co-transfected with IRAK1-WT + miR-142-3p mimics than those co-transfected with IRAK1-MT + miR-142-3p mimics, IRAK1-MT + NC, and COL1A1-WT + NC (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B).</p><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>The interaction between miR-142-3p and IRAK1</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) A binding site of miR-142-3p at 3′-UTR of IRAK1 predicted by the software of Target Scan; (<bold>B</bold>) Relative fluorescence intensity of HEK-293T cells co-transfected with IRAK1-wild-type (WT)/IRAK1-mutant (MT) and miR-142-3p mimics (mimics)/miR-142-3p mimics NC. *, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 versus MT + mimics, MT + NC, and WT + NC.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-39-bsr20190700-g7.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>HFLSs are key effector cells in RA, which exhibit aggressive phenotypes, such as enhanced proliferation and migration, and the overproduction of inflammatory cytokines and chemokines [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. TNF-α is a proinflammatory cytokine that plays a key regulatory role in the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs. It has been reported that TNF-α promotes the proliferation, migration, invasion, and MMPs expression in RA-HFLSs [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. TNF-α induces the proliferation of RA-HFLSs, and the production of IL-6 and IL-1β [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In the present study, we found that TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs exhibited significantly increased cell viability, number of cell clones, migration rate, number of invasive cells, expression of Bcl-2, and levels of IL-6 and MMP-3, as well as decreased apoptosis rate. Our findings are just consistent with pervious studies, and further illustrate that TNF-α activates the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs.</p><p>MiR-142-3p is a specific miR that plays a dual role in tumorigenesis. miR-142-3p not only acts as a tumor suppressor in osteosarcoma [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], gastric cancer [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], colon cancer [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and non-small-cell lung cancer [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], but also acts as a tumor promoter in pediatric brain tumor [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], renal cell carcinoma [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and colorectal cancer [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Over the past decade, non-coding RNAs including miRNAs and lncRNA gradually become important regulators of inflammation [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Until now, the knowledge on roles of miR-142-3p on RA are still limited. In the present study, we found that the expression of miR-142-3p was significantly higher in synovial tissues and RA-HFLSs of RA patients than those of OA patients. These results are consistent with pervious studies on miR-146 [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], -155 [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], -203 [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], -221 [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and -126 [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and illustrate that miR-142-3p is up-regulated in RA. In addition, we also found that the expression of miR-142-3p in synovial tissues was significantly higher in RA patients at stage IV than in those at stage III. This result indicates that miR-142-3p expression may be positively associated with the severity of RA. A pervious study indicates that circulating peripheral blood miRs, including miR-16, -21, -24, -26a, -125a-5p, -125b, -126-3p, -223, and -451 are promising non-invasive biomarkers for the detection of RA [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. We suspect that miR-142-3p may also be used as a biomarker for the diagnosis of RA.</p><p>The specific regulatory effects of miR-142-3p on the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs were further evaluated in the present study. We found that the transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the cell viability, the number of cell clones, the migration rate, the number of invasive cells, and the expression of Bcl-2 expression, and increased the expressions of Bax and Bad, and the apoptosis rate of TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs. A pervious study has proved that the down-regulation of miR-221 inhibits the migration and invasion, and promotes the apoptosis of HFLSs [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Our findings are just consistent with miR-221, and illustrate that the down-regulation of miR-142-3p reverses the promoting effects of TNF-α on the proliferation, migration, and invasion of RA-HFLSs. In addition, evidences have proved that miR-142-3p is involved in the regulation of inflammatory process. For examples, miR-142-3p overexpression inhibits LPS-induced production of IL-1, IL-6, and TNF-α in articular cartilage tissues of OA mice [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. MiR-142-3p overexpression alleviates bleomycin-induced production of IL-1 and TNF-α in MLE-12 cells [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In the present study, we found that the transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly decreased the contents and the expression of IL-6 and MMP-3 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs. These results indicate that the down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibits TNF-α-induced inflammation of RA-HFLSs. However, our findings are inconsistent with previous studies. Similar with the dual roles of miR-142-3p in tumorigenesis, we suspect that miR-142-3p may exert different regulatory roles on inflammation in different diseases. To sum up, the down-regulation of miR-142-3p may contribute to the amelioration of RA via relieving the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs, including the enhanced proliferation, migration, invasion, and inflammation, as well as inhibited apoptosis.</p><p>Since RA is a chronic inflammatory disease of the synovial joints, activated NF-κB is always detected in synovial tissues of RA [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In the present study, we found that TNF-α significantly up-regulated IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 in RA-HFLSs. These results illustrate that TNF-α induces the activation of NF-κB signaling in RA-HFLSs. In RA-HFLSs, TNF-α stimulation can result in phosphorylation of NF-κB and activation of NF-κB, and then induce the expression of target genes involved in proinflammation, cell cycle, and anti-apoptosis [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. TNF-α-induced activation of NF-κB signaling contributes to the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs. NF-κB is a common nuclear transcription factor appeared in osteoblasts. Studies have found that Runx [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], NF-κB signaling [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and other pathways play important role in osteogenesis differentiation and activity. Cross talks between these pathways or together they regulate osteoblast activity. Disruption of Runx1 and Runx3 could result in bone marrow failure [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and Runx3 deficiency leads to myeloproliferative disorder [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Changes in NF-κB pathway could regulate variations in osteogenesis activity. In the present study, the regulatory mechanisms of miR-142-3p relating with NF-κB signaling were further evaluated. We found that transfection of miR-142-3p inhibitor significantly down-regulated IRAK1, TLR4, and p-NF-κB p65 in TNF-α-treated RA-HFLSs. These results illustrate that the down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibits TNF-α-induced activation of NF-κB signaling in RA-HFLSs. We suspect that the down-regulation of miR-142-3p may relieve the aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs through inhibiting NF-κB signaling. Besides, our further assays showed that IRAK1 was a target of miR-142-3p. Since IRAK1 is partially responsible for IL1-induced activation of NF-κB signaling [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], the down-regulation of miR-142-3p may inhibit NF-κB signaling by targeting IRAK1.</p><p>In conclusion, miR-142-3p was up-regulated in RA synovial tissues and RA-HFLSs. The down-regulation of miR-142-3p significantly relieved TNF-α-induced aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs, including enhanced proliferation, migration, invasion, and inflammation, as well as inhibited apoptosis. In addition, the down-regulation of miR-142-3p inhibited NF-κB signaling by targeting IRAK1, thereby contributing to the remission of TNF-α-induced aggressive phenotypes of RA-HFLSs. Down-regulation of miR-142-3p may be used as a promising therapeutic target for RA.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="sec5" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The present study was conducted after obtaining approval of The First Affiliated Hospital of The Fourth Military Medical University’s ethical committee. The research has been carried out in accordance with the World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki, and that all subjects have been provided written informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that there are no sources of funding to be acknowledged.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>Jianhong Qiang: conception and design and analysis of data. Jianhong Qiang and Tingting Lv: drafting the article. Zhenbiao Wu and Xichao Yang: revising the article critically for important intellectual content. All authors read and approved the final manuscript</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="G1">ANOVA</term><def><p>analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">Bcl-2</term><def><p>B-cell lymphoma-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">DLR</term><def><p>dual luciferase reporter gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">DMSO</term><def><p>dimethyl sulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">FBS</term><def><p>fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">GAPDH</term><def><p>glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">H-DMEM</term><def><p>high-glucose Dulbecco’s modified Eagle medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">HEK</term><def><p>human embryonic kideney</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">HRP</term><def><p>horseradish peroxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10"> IL</term><def><p>interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">INC</term><def><p>inhibitor negative control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12">IRAK1</term><def><p>IL-1 receptor-associated kinase 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">MMP-3</term><def><p>matrix metalloproteinase 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G14">MTT</term><def><p>3-(4,5-dimethyl-2-thiazolyl)-2,5-diphenyl-2-H-tetrazolium bromide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G15">NC</term><def><p>negative control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G16">NF-κB</term><def><p>nuclear factor-κB</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G17">OA</term><def><p>osteoarthritis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G18">OA-HFLS</term><def><p>osteoarthritis human fibroblast-like synoviocyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G19">OD</term><def><p>optical density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G20">PBS</term><def><p>phosphate buffer saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G21">p-NF-κB p65</term><def><p>phosphorylated NF-κB p65</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G22">qRT-PCR</term><def><p>quantitative real-time PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G23">RA</term><def><p>rheumatoid arthritis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G24">RA-HFLS</term><def><p>rheumatoid arthritis human fibroblast-like synoviocyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G25">TBST</term><def><p>tris-buffered saline Tween</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G26">TLR4</term><def><p>toll-like receptor 4</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G27">TNF-α</term><def><p>tumor necrosis factor α</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G28">TUNEL</term><def><p>terminal dexynucleotidyl transferase-mediated dUTP nick end labeling</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aletaha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mcinnes</surname><given-names>I.B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><volume>388</volume>, <fpage>2023</fpage>–<lpage>2038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)30173-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27156434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Inflammation and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>J. Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>69</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13105-012-0216-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Development of evidence-based disease education literature for pakistani rheumatoid arthritis patients</article-title>. <source>Diseases</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>pii: E27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diseases5040027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5750538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29156638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmester</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Novel treatment strategies in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><volume>389</volume>, <fpage>2338</fpage>–<lpage>2348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31491-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28612748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arend</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dayer</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of the production and effects of interleukins‐1 and tumor necrosis factor α in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>38</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.1780380202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7848304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toussirot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wendling</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The use of TNF-alpha blocking agents in rheumatoid arthritis: an overview</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin. Pharmacother.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>2089</fpage>–<lpage>2107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14656566.8.13.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>C</surname><given-names>Y-F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A systematic review of the effectiveness of adalimumab, etanercept and infliximab for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis in adults and an economic evaluation of their cost-effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Health Technol. Assess. (Rockv)</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3310/hta10420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17049139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Development of TNF-alpha inhibitor drugs in treatment of rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>In Int. Conf. Biomed. Eng. Biotechnol.</source><fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keystone</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Does anti-tumor necrosis factor-α therapy affect risk of serious infection and cancer in patients with rheumatoid arthritis?: a review of longterm data</article-title><source>J. Rheumatol.</source><volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1552</fpage>–<lpage>1562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3899/jrheum.100995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moulis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cancer risk of anti-TNF-α at recommended doses in adult rheumatoid arthritis: a meta-analysis with intention to treat and per protocol analyses</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e48991</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0048991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23155441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3498371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Furer</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The role of microRNA in rheumatoid arthritis and other autoimmune diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin. Immunol.</source><volume>136</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2010.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20223711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomoyuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Expression of microRNA-146 in rheumatoid arthritis synovial tissue</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1284</fpage>–<lpage>1292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.23429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2749927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joanna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Altered expression of MicroRNA in synovial fibroblasts and synovial tissue in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.23386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18383392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joanna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Altered expression of microRNA-203 in rheumatoid arthritis synovial fibroblasts and its role in fibroblast activation</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>63</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.30115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21279994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3116142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Downregulation of microRNA-221 decreases migration and invasion in fibroblast-like synoviocytes in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2395</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2015.3642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25891943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-126 affects rheumatoid arthritis synovial fibroblast proliferation and apoptosis by targeting PIK3R2 and regulating PI3K-AKT signal pathway</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>74217</fpage>–<lpage>74226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.12487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27729613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5342047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Down-regulation of microRNA-34a* in rheumatoid arthritis synovial fibroblasts promotes apoptosis resistance</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1771</fpage>–<lpage>1779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.34334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22161761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamachi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>MicroRNA-124a is a key regulator of proliferation and monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 secretion in fibroblast-like synoviocytes from patients with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1294</fpage>–<lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.24475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19404929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>A novel p53/microRNA-22/Cyr61 axis in synovial cells regulates inflammation in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.38142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruedel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Expression and function of microRNA-188-5p in activated rheumatoid arthritis synovial fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Clin. Exp. Pathol.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>6607</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26261542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4525876</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC4713706"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Reference deleted</collab></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>microRNA-142-3p inhibits apoptosis and inflammation induced by bleomycin through down-regulation of Cox-2 in MLE-12 cells</article-title>. <source>Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res.</source><volume>50</volume>, <fpage>e5974</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1414-431x20175974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28678919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5496156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talebi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-142 regulates inflammation and T cell differentiation in an animal model of multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J. Neuroinflammation</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-017-0832-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28302134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5356264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-142-3p inhibits chondrocyte apoptosis and inflammation in osteoarthritis by targeting HMGB1</article-title>. <source>Inflammation</source><volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1718</fpage>–<lpage>1728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10753-016-0406-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27447821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T))Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garzon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distinctive microRNA signature of acute myeloid leukemia bearing cytoplasmic mutated nucleophosmin</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><volume>105</volume>, <fpage>3945</fpage>–<lpage>3950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0800135105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18308931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>SIRT1 inhibits rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocyte aggressiveness and inflammatory response via suppressing NF-κB pathway</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source><volume>38</volume>, <fpage>pii: BSR20180541</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BSR20180541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6013706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29784872</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="expression-of-concern" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10472205"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeshima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Abnormal PTPN11 enhancer methylation promotes rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocyte aggressiveness and joint inflammation</article-title>. <source>JCI Insight</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>e86580</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.86580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27275015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4889026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Halofuginone inhibits TNF-α-induced the migration and proliferation of fibroblast-like synoviocytes from rheumatoid arthritis patients</article-title>. <source>Int. Immunopharmacol.</source><volume>43</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2016.12.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28013187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Paeonol protects against TNF-alpha-induced proliferation and cytokine release of rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes by upregulating FOXO3 through inhibition of miR-155 expression</article-title>. <source>Inflamm. Res.</source><volume>66</volume>, <fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00011-017-1041-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28401267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-142-3p, a novel target of tumor suppressor menin, inhibits osteosarcoma cell proliferation by down-regulation of FASN</article-title>. <source>Tumour Biol.</source><volume>35</volume>, <fpage>10287</fpage>–<lpage>10293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13277-014-2316-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25034529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Downregulation of microRNA-142-3p and its tumor suppressor role in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Lett.</source><volume>15</volume>, <fpage>8172</fpage>–<lpage>8180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29849811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ol.2018.8330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5962855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MiR-142-3p functions as a tumor suppressor by targeting CD133, ABCG2, and Lgr5 in colon cancer cells</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Med.</source><volume>91</volume>, <fpage>989</fpage>–<lpage>1000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00109-013-1037-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23619912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>MiR-142-3p functions as a potential tumor suppressor directly targeting HMGB1 in non-small-cell lung carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Clin. Exp. Pathol.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>10800</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26617792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4637607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA142-3p promotes tumor-initiating and radioresistant properties in malignant pediatric brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Cell Transplant.</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>669</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3727/096368914X678364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24816458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Oncogenic microRNA-142-3p is associated with cellular migration, proliferation and apoptosis in renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Oncol. Lett.</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2015.4021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26893725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4734216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-142-3p promotes cellular invasion of colorectal cancer cells by activation of RAC1</article-title>. <source>Technol. Cancer Res. Treat</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>153303381879050</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1533033818790508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6069031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30064309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Noncoding RNAs: master regulators of inflammatory signaling</article-title>. <source>Trends Mol. Med.</source><volume>24</volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmed.2017.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29246760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Churov</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oleinik</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Knip</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs in rheumatoid arthritis: altered expression and diagnostic potential</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun. Rev.</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2015.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26164649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roman-Blas</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>NF-κB as a potential therapeutic target in osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2006.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16730463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Beyaert</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Negative regulation of NF-κB and its involvement in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res. Ther.</source><volume>13</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar3324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3218875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Zfp521 controls bone mass by HDAC3-dependent attenuation of Runx2 activity</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source><volume>191</volume>, <fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>1283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201009107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3010073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Involvement of p38MAPK/NF-κB signaling pathways in osteoblasts differentiation in response to mechanical stretch</article-title>. <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1884</fpage>–<lpage>1894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10439-012-0548-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22441665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Disruption of Runx1 and Runx3 leads to bone marrow failure and leukemia predisposition due to transcriptional and DNA repair defects</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep.</source><volume>8</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.06.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25066130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Runx3 deficiency results in myeloproliferative disorder in aged mice</article-title>. <source>Blood</source><volume>122</volume>, <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2012-10-460618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23741011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase (IRAK)-1-mediated NF-kappaB activation requires cytosolic and nuclear activity</article-title>. <source>FASEB J.</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2285</fpage>–<lpage>2296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.07-101816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18276832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>