
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Technol Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Technol. Cancer Res. Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3299</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tct</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101140941</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1533-0346</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1533-0338</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7144672</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7144672.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7144672</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7144672</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32266860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1533033820917978</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1533033820917978</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MiR-19-3p Induces Tumor Cell Apoptosis via Targeting FAS in Rectal Cancer Cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="YF">Ying-Feng</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033820917978">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zang</surname><given-names initials="YF">Yi-Feng</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1533033820917978">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9870-2155</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="YH">Yu-Hong</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1533033820917978">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="YL">Yin-Lu</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1533033820917978">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1533033820917978"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1533033820917978">
<label>1</label>Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, the People’s Hospital of Dezhou, Shandong, China</aff><aff id="aff2-1533033820917978">
<label>2</label>Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, the Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China</aff><aff id="aff3-1533033820917978">
<label>3</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Weifang People’s Hospital, Shandong, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1533033820917978">Yin-Lu Ding, Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, the Second Hospital of Shandong University, Jinan, Shandong, China. Email: <email>yinlu_ding11@sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">350554</issue-id><elocation-id>1533033820917978</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>04</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-09-29 15:25:18.037"><day>29</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="22" elocation-id="15330338221142012" journal-id="Technol Cancer Res Treat" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9893339"><article-title>Retraction Notice</article-title><volume>22</volume><date><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>15330338221142012</elocation-id><source>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9893339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653928</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>MicroRNAs are reported as a vital important factor in cancer cell initiation and progression processes. MicroRNA-19-3p has drawn the attention of many researchers in recent years because of its wide expression and its key role in serious kinds of tumor cells. However, the detailed mechanism of microRNA-19a-3p in these tumors is still poorly understood. So, in the present study, we aimed to explore the biological function and potential molecular mechanism of microRNA-19a-3p in different cancer cells. We first detect the relative level of miR-19a-3p in cancer cell lines and tumor tissues compared to normal cells and tissues. Results indicated the messenger RNA expression of microRNA-19a-3p existing in an aberrant low level in cancer cells and tissues. The overexpression of microRNA-19a-3p significantly reduced the cell proliferation, migration, and invasion ability in HCT116 cells. In addition to this, increased microRNA-19a-3p could induce cell apoptosis via promoting reactive oxygen species (ROS) accumulation, whereas inhibition of microRNA-19a-3p exhibited an opposite effect. Moreover, we predicated the target genes and the binding sites of microRNA-19a-3p and confirmed FAS as the targeting of microRNA-19a-3p through luciferase activity assay. Taken together, these results indicated that microRNA-19a-3p overexpression inhibited HCT116 cell proliferation, migration and invasion, induced cell apoptosis, and ROS accumulation via FAS targeting effect. It was conceivable that microRNA-19a-3p might serve as a potential molecular target for breast and liver cancer treatment.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>rectal cancer cells</kwd><kwd>micro-RNA</kwd><kwd>miR-19-3p</kwd><kwd>FAS</kwd><kwd>cell proliferation</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts3</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-1533033820917978"><title>Introduction</title><p>Up to now, cancer disease is still a worldwide public health problem in the world, changeling the quality and quantity in life with high death rate.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> In the past 3 decades, studies about cancer treatment has greatly changed and improved our understanding of cancer disease, resulting in further proficient treatments. In patients with cancer, different strategies of management are carried out according to the individuals’ physiological condition, such as targeted therapy, hormonal therapy, radiation therapy, surgery, chemotherapy, and so on.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> However, there are also some unpleasant side effects of current treatments, one of which is cancer resistance.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Therefore, it is urgent for researchers to explore new strategy for cancer treatment.</p><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are short (20-24 nucleotides) noncoding and endogenous RNAs that are involved in posttranscriptional regulation of gene expression in multicellular organisms by directly binding to the 3′-untranslated region (UTR) of its target gene at the posttranscriptional level and affecting both the stability and translation of mRNAs, then regulate various cellular functions.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In recent years, a growing number of studies have demonstrated that miRNAs participate in tumor initiation and progression processes and have the potential to be a promising target for diagnosis and therapy of cancers.</p><p>MicroRNAs-19a-3p is a member of the highly conserved miR-17-92 cluster located on chromosome 13. Accumulated reports indicated that the miR-19a-3p play the function of oncogenic gene in multiple cancer cells and may be to be the molecular biomarkers for the therapy and diagnosis of cancers. The aberrant expression of miR-19a-3p has been reported in hepatocellular carcinoma,<sup><xref rid="bibr8-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> prostate cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr9-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> acute myeloid leukemia,<sup><xref rid="bibr10-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> esophageal squamous cells,<sup><xref rid="bibr11-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and so on. However, up to now, little is known about the important role of miR-19a-3p and its molecular mechanism and this needs to be further explored.</p><p>In the present study, we firstly evaluated the relative expression of miR-19a-3p in different types of cancer cell lines as well as the cancer tissues and its non-tumor adjacent tissues. We found there was a significant reduced level of miR-19a-3p in rectal cancer tissues. Then, we investigated molecular mechanism of miR-19a-3p in rectal cancer cells. Results suggested that miR-19a-3p overexpression inhibited cell proliferation, migration, and invasion ability, and induced cancer cell apoptosis by upregulating ROS accumulation. Further study revealed the anticancer activity of miR-19a-3p owing to the directly binding between miR-19a-3p and Fas protein in cells. Our study provided a novel strategy of rectal cancer treatment with the clearly mechanism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-1533033820917978"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section3-1533033820917978"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cell, human cervical cancer cell line (HeLa), colon cancer cell line (HCT-8), rectal cancer cell line (HCT116), liver cancer cell line (HepG2), and normal human bronchial epithelial cell line (HBE) were purchased from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Rockville, Maryland). Chinese hamster ovary cell line was cultured in RPMI-1640 medium (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA), the HeLa, HCT-8, HCT116, and HepG2 cell lines were cultured in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s Medium (Gibco, Grand Island, NY, USA). Both the culture medium was supplemented with 10% (vol/vol) heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco, Life Technologies), 1% penicillin-streptomycin sulfate solution and 2% L-glutamine. All the cells were incubated in in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/water-saturated incubator at 37°C. The rectal cancer tissue and their adjacent normal tissue were harvested from the 74 patients collected in our hostel from July 2018 to July 2019. All the patients were informed about the detail experiments. This preformation was approved by the ethics committee of the Second Hospital of Shandong University (SHOU-DW-2019-050).</p></sec><sec id="section4-1533033820917978"><title>Cell Proliferation</title><p>The cell proliferation of HCT116 cancer cells cell was examined by cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8; Dojindo, Tokyo, Japan) according to the manufacturer’s protocol.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Briefly, the HCT116 cancer cells in the logarithmic growth period were collected and seeded into 96-well culture plates at the density of 1 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well (200 μL/well). All the cells were incubated at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> humidified environment for 12 hours. When the cells research the confluences of 70% to 80%, the compound was added into wells for 48 hours treatment. After that, the CCK-8 solution (20 μL/well) was added for another 24 hours incubation. Subsequently, the absorbance (optical density) values of each well were detected at a wavelength of 450 nm on an enzyme immunoassay analyzer (Bio-Rad, California, USA ). This assay was performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="section5-1533033820917978"><title>Cell Migration and Invasion Assays</title><p>To confirm the effect of miR-19-3p on HCT116 cell migration and invasion ability, the transwell assays were further carried out as the protocols reported previously.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bibr14-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Before experiment, 24-well transwell chambers (8 µm pore size, 6.5 mm diameter; Corning, NY, USA) were placed in 24-well plates. For cell migration assays, 5 × 10<sup>4</sup> transfected cells within free-FBS medium were seeded onto the upper chamber, combined with the 10% FBS-supplemented culture medium added into the lower chamber. After 24 hours of incubation at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> condition, the cells remaining on the upper membrane were carefully wiped off with wet cotton, and the cells on the lower side of the membrane were stained with 0.5% crystal violet. The number of cells on the lower surface was quantified in 6 randomly independent fields under a microscope. All experiments were performed at least 3 times. For cell invasion assays, the 24-well transwell chambers were precoated with matrigel matrix (1:8; 50 μL/well; BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, New Jersey) and then performed as the method described above.</p></sec><sec id="section6-1533033820917978"><title>Cell Apoptosis</title><p>The apoptosis level of HCT116 cancer cells after indicated treatment was detected using Cell Apoptosis Assay Kit (Life Technologies) in flow cytometry under the guidance of the manufacturer’s instruction.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> In brief, the cells were transfected with the recombinant plasmid or miRNAs, and then the cells were seeded onto 6-well plates and cultured to reach 40% to 50% convergence. After 48 hours of treatment, the cells were harvested with trypsin and resuspended in 1× binding buffer at a concentration of 1 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL. Following PBS washing for 3 times, the Annexin V-fluoresceine isothiocyanate (FITC) and propidium iodide (PI) solution was subjected into the suspension for 15 minutes incubation in the dark. Finally, the cell samples were analyzed using flow cytometry (FACScan; BD Biosciences). Experiments with triplicate were performed.</p></sec><sec id="section7-1533033820917978"><title>Micro RNA-19-3p Transfection</title><p>To overexpress or knock down the expression of miR-19-3p, the miR-19-3p overexpression plasmid pcDNA3.1-miR-19-3p (pc miR-19-3p), miR-19-3p mimic, and miR-19-3p inhibitor were designed and synthesized (Ruibobio, Guangzhou, China). The plasmid vector, nontargeting negative control sequences for miR-19-3p mimic and inhibitor were used as mimic control and inhibitor control. In brief, the breast cancer cells were planted into wells at the final destiny of 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL. The plasmid or miRNAs were transfected into HCT116 cells using Lipofectamine 3000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California) according to the manufacturer’s protocols.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec id="section8-1533033820917978"><title>RNA Isolation and Quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>Micro RNA-19-3p transfection efficiency was assessed by quantitative real-time reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) in accordance with the instructions with some modification.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> In brief, the total RNA was isolated from transfected cells using TRIzol Reagent (Sigma, St Louis, Massachusetts), then the concentration and quality of RNA was quantified by a NanoDrop 2000C instrument. The complementary DNA (cDNA) was synthesized with cDNA reverse transcription kit. To determine the relative expression level of the miR-19-3p, the RT-PCR was performed using SYBR Green Master Mix (Roche), and the β-actin were used as internal reference. The primer sequences used in this study are as follows: miR-19-3p, forward: CCGTCGGCTTGTTGAGGTAG and reverse: TTCCGTCAGCTCGGAAAGTT; β-actin, forward: TGGAACGGTGAAGGTGACAG and reverse: CGCATCTCATATTTGGAATGACT. All data were normalized using 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method as relative quantification. This experiment was repeated at least 3 times.</p></sec><sec id="section9-1533033820917978"><title>Target Gene Prediction and Luciferase Activity Assay</title><p>The target genes and the binding sites of miR-19-3p were predicated with TargetScan software (TargetScanHuman 7.1). According to the results of the target genes predicted by bioinformatics software, luciferase activity assay was performed for further confirmation according to the protocols.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> In brief, the wild-type (WT, UCUACCUCAAAGACCUUUGCACA) and mutant miR-19-3p binding regions in the 3′-UTR of <italic toggle="yes">fas</italic> gene (UCUACCUCAAAGACCCAAUUCGC) were cloned into pMIR-REPORT luciferase reporter plasmids (Promega Corporation, Madison, Wisconsin). Micro RNA-19-3p mimic, inhibitor, and negative control were co-transfected into HCT116 cells with luciferase reporter plasmids. The cells were cultivated at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> condition for 24 hours, followed by the fluorescence intensity measurement using GloMax20/20 illuminometer (Promega Corporation). All experiments were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="section10-1533033820917978"><title>Western Blotting</title><p>After transfected with miR-19-3p mimic, inhibitor, and negative control, the HCT116 cancer cells were collected with Trypsin and lysed using radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) lysis buffer (Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, China) containing protease inhibitor cocktail (78437; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc). The total protein concentration was detected using BCA Protein Assay kit (23225, Pierce, Washington, USA) for “Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc,” “Roche,” “Life Technologies,” and “Abcam Biotechnology.”]. Equal amounts of protein samples were separated on 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide denaturing gels by electrophoresis and transferred onto a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (PVDF; EMD Millipore, Billerica, Massachusetts). Then, the membranes were blocked in 5% nonfat milk for 2 hours at room temperature and then incubated with the appropriate primary antibody against FAS (ab82419, Abcam Biotechnology) or glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (ab9485, Abcam Biotechnology) overnight at 4°C hours. The membranes were then washed with PBST for 3 times and incubation with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody for 1 hour at room temperature. Finally, the proteins were visualized using an enhanced chemiluminescence detection kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc), and quantified using ImageJ software (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland).<sup><xref rid="bibr19-1533033820917978" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> The experiment was repeated 3 times independently.</p></sec><sec id="section11-1533033820917978"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All the data in this study were presented as means ± standard error of mean. Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS version 17.0 Software (IBM, Armonk, New York). One-way analysis of variance was carried out for statistical comparisons of more than 3 groups. Differences were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results|discussion" id="section12-1533033820917978"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="section13-1533033820917978"><title>Micro RNA-19-3p Expression was Downregulated in Rectal Cancer Cell Line and Tissues</title><p>To investigate the important role of miR-19-3p in cancer cells, the relative expression of miR-19-3p in CHO, HeLa, HCT-8, HCT116, and HepG2 cancer cells were detected by real-time RT-PCR. Firstly, the RT-PCR results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033820917978">Figure 1A</xref> indicated there is an obviously downregulation of miR-19-3p mRNA expression only in the HCT116 cancer cells, there was a significant difference when compared with the normal cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .005). Besides, we can see miR-19-3p mRNA has not been changed the expression of miR-19-3p in CHO, HeLa, HCT-8, and HepG2 cell lines. To exclude the effects of miR-19a-3p on rectal cancer migration, invasion, and apoptosis was not due to the cell line specific, we further chose 2 another different rectal cancer cell lines and did the same experiment. The results indicated the miR-19a-3p showed significant inhibitory effects on all these rectal cancer cells but not due to the cell line–specific (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033820917978">Figure 1B</xref>). In the further investigation, the HCT116 cell line was highlighted for the following experiments. Next, we also analyzed the miR-19-3p mRNA expression level in rectal cancer tissues (n = 25) and paired adjacent non-tumor tissues (adjacent tissue, n = 25), and the results confirmed that the expression level of miR-19-3p mRNA was obviously reduced in cancer tissues compared with that of adjacent normal tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033820917978">Figure 1C</xref>). These results above indicated that miR-19-3p mRNA expression was downregulated significantly in both the rectal cancer cell lines and tissues.</p><fig id="fig1-1533033820917978" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Reduced miR-19-3p expression cell lines and tissues. A, The expression level of miR-19-3p mRNA was examined by RT-PCR in human CHO, HeLa, HCT-8, HCT116, and HepG2 cancer cell lines as well as the normal human bronchial epithelial cell line. B, The miR-19-3p mRNA expression level in different rectal cancer cell lines. C, The expression level of miR-19-3p mRNA detected by RT-PCR in rectal cancer tissues and paired adjacent non-tumor tissues. CHO indicates Chinese hamster ovary; HeLa, human cervical cancer cell line; HCT-8, colon cancer cell line; HCT116, rectal cancer cell line; HepG2, liver cancer cell line.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978-fig1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section14-1533033820917978"><title>Micro RNA-19-3p Regulates Cancer Cell Proliferation, Migration, and Invasion</title><p>To explore the important role of miR-19-3p in rectal cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion, the HCT116 cancer cells were transfected with miR-19-3p mimic, miR-19-3p inhibitor, miR-19-3p negative control, and inhibitor control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033820917978">Figure 2A</xref>). The cell proliferation was detected by CCK-8. From the results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033820917978">Figure 2B</xref>, we found that compared with control groups, the miR-19-3p mimic inhibited the HCT116 cancer cell proliferation significantly. In control with that, the miR-19-3p inhibitor significantly promoted the cancer cell viability and proliferation. Besides, the cell migration and invasion assay were also performed in this study, as results showed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033820917978">Figure 2C and D</xref>, the miR-19-3p mimic significantly reduced the number of migrated and invaded cancer cells, whereas miR-19-3p inhibitors exhibited opposite promotion effect. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1533033820917978">Figure 2E</xref> further convinced the influence of the compound on the cancer cell migration and invasion ability. Taken together, all these results suggested miR-19-3p could regulate rectal cancer cells proliferation migration, and invasion ability.</p><fig id="fig2-1533033820917978" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Micro RNA-19-3p takes part in HCT116 cancer cells proliferation, migration, and invasion. The miR-19-3p mimic and miR-19-3p inhibitor as well as their corresponding controls were constructed and transfected into HCT116 cancer cells. A, The relative expression of miR-19-3p mRNA was confirmed by RT-PCR. B, Cell counting kit-8 assay on HCT116 cancer cells after transfection. C, Transwell migration assay was performed to measure the miR-19-3p effect on HCT116 cell migration capability. D, The cell invasion of HCT116 cancer cells examined by Transwell. E, The original images of cell migration and invasion assays photographed by microscope. ** means <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .01, and the *** means <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .005.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-1533033820917978"><title>Micro RNA-19-3p Regulates Cancer Cells Apoptosis and ROS Accumulation</title><p>Furthermore, the effect of miR-19-3p on HCT116 cancer cell apoptosis was conducted by Annexin V-FITC/PI double staining assay. The cancer cells were transfected with miR-19-3p mimic and inhibitors, followed by apoptosis detection in flow cytometer. Micro RNA -19-3p mimic significantly increased the percentage of apoptotic cancer cells, and the inhibitors downregulated the cell apoptosis obviously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033820917978">Figure 3A</xref>). The average and standard deviation of apoptosis in each group was showed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033820917978">Figure 3</xref>.</p><fig id="fig3-1533033820917978" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Micro RNA-19-3p participates in cancer cell apoptosis and ROS accumulation. The HCT116 cancer cells were transfected with miR-19-3p mimic and inhibitors for 24 hours. A, Annexin V FITC Apoptosis Detection kit was used to detect the cell apoptosis in flow cytometry. B, The average and standard deviation of apoptosis in each group. C, The cellular ROS content in HCT116 cancer cells was quantified with ROS detection kit in flow cytometry. D, The average and standard deviation of ROS in each group. RT-PCR indicates reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978-fig3.jpg"/></fig><p>Most cell apoptosis was induced by the increased level of intracellular ROS. As the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033820917978">Figure 3C</xref>, the miR-19-3p mimic significantly increased the intracellular ROS accumulation and the miR-19-3p inhibitors significantly downregulated the accumulation of intracellular ROS. All the results above indicated that the miR-19-3p play a vital important role in cell apoptosis and intracellular ROS accumulation. The average and standard deviation of ROS in each group is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1533033820917978">Figure 3D</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="section16-1533033820917978"><title>Micro RNA-19-3p Targets Directly and Negatively Regulates Fas</title><p>The TargetScan software was used to predicate the target genes and the binding sites of miR-19-3p in HCT116 cancer cells. Fas protein was identified as one of the most potential target gene of miR-19-3p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033820917978">Figure 4A</xref>). According to the bioinformatics prediction, the correlation between miR-19-3p and FAS was further explored in rectal cancer tissues. There was and obviously negative correlation between miR-19-3p expression and Fas expression in cancer tissues (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.9939, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033820917978">Figure 4B</xref>). Moreover, we also observed a negative regulation of miR-19-3p on FAS expression in HCT116 cancer cell lines (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033820917978">Figure 4C and D</xref>). Then, the luciferase reporter assay was conducted to verify the directly binding of miR-19-3p and Fas. The results suggested that miR-19-3p mimic significantly reduced the luciferase activity in HCT116 cancer cells and that miR-19-3p inhibitor obviously elevated the luciferase activity obviously (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .005, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1533033820917978">Figure 4E</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4-1533033820917978" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Micro RNA-19-3p regulates Fas by directly binding. A, The potential binding sites between miR-19-3p and Fas. The sequences of Fas mRNA 3′-UTR are shown allied with the miR-19-3p sequence. B, The negative correlation between miR-19-3p expression and Fas expression calculated from breast tissues. C and D, Micro RNA-19-3p negatively regulated Fas expression in HCT116 cancer cell line, detected by RT-PCR and Western blot. E, Relative luciferase activity was evaluated to detect the direct binding between miR-19-3p and Fas. RT-PCR indicates reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction; 3′-UTR, untranslated region.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section17-1533033820917978"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Micro RNAs are noncoding single-stranded RNAs widely exist in eukaryotes. It can bind to the sequences of the 3′-UTR of the target genes mRNA, regulating the cleavage or translation of target mRNA. Recently, a growing number of researches reported that the miRNAs play important regulatory roles in cancer cells in a series of physiological and pathological processes, such as cell proliferation, migration and invasion, and apoptosis. Up to now, no cancer resistance was reported according to the treatment targeting miRNAs, which is the biggest advantage of this treatment method over traditional anticancer drugs. So, revealing the specific mechanism of miRNAs is crucial for cancer treatment in the future.</p><p>Fas is a number of the TNF receptor superfamily known as “death receptors.” In the past decades, numbers of studies about Fas have revealed the important role of Fas as the initiators of cell apoptosis. In our reach, we predicated the Fas as the target gene of miR-19-3p and confirmed the interactive binding with each other with luciferase reporter assay. While, the biological functions mediated by Fas was still needed to be conducted. So, the apoptosis and ROS accumulation in HCT116 cancer cells were carried out. Results indicated the proapoptotic effect of overexpressed miR-19-3p is certainly mediated by Fas. Through the results in this article, we the miR-19-3p plays a vital important role in the HCT116 cancer treatment by inducing the cancer cell ROS accumulation and cell apoptosis, which also provide a foundation for the anti-rectal cancer treatment via targeting miR-19-3p.</p><p>In conclusion, the present study demonstrated for the first time that the miR-19-3p showed and abnormal low expression in rectal cancer cells and tissues. Micro RNAs -19-3p overexpression could significantly inhibited cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion and induced cell apoptosis and ROS production by target the FAS protein in cancer cells. These results suggest that miR-19-3p has the potential to be a novel target for rectal cancer treatment.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1533033820917978"><p><bold>Authors’ Note:</bold> Our study did not require an ethical board approval because it did not contain human or animal trials.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2-1533033820917978"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1533033820917978"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1533033820917978"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Yu-Hong Wang <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033820917978-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9870-2155">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9870-2155</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><glossary content-type="abbr"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1-1533033820917978">CCK-8</term><def><p>cell counting kit-8</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2-1533033820917978">CHO</term><def><p>Chinese hamster ovary</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3-1533033820917978">FBS</term><def><p>fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4-1533033820917978">HeLa</term><def><p>human cervical cancer cell line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5-1533033820917978">HCT-8</term><def><p>colon cancer cell line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6-1533033820917978">HCT116</term><def><p>rectal cancer cell line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7-1533033820917978">HepG2</term><def><p>liver cancer cell line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8-1533033820917978">HBE</term><def><p>normal human bronchial epithelial cell line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9-1533033820917978">MiRNAs</term><def><p>microRNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10-1533033820917978">RT-PCR</term><def><p>reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11-1533033820917978">UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1533033820917978"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniyal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Awareness and current knowledge of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Biol Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28969709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40659-017-0140-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5625777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1533033820917978"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino Bonilla</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres Tabanera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ros Mendoza</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Breast cancer in the 21st century: from early detection to new therapies</article-title>. <source>Radiologia</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28712528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rx.2017.06.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1533033820917978"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonissen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Update on cancer treatment in exotics</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Exot Anim Pract</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29655479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cvex.2018.01.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1533033820917978"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riechelmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grothey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antiangiogenic therapy for refractory colorectal cancer: current options and future strategies</article-title>. <source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28203302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1758834016676703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5298403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1533033820917978"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of alternative splicing in cancer drug resistance</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>. <year>2018</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29080552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gde.2017.10.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1533033820917978"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Circulating microRNAs and long non-coding RNAs in gastric cancer diagnosis: an update and review</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>9863</fpage>–<lpage>9886</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26379393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3748/wjg.v21.i34.9863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4566381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1533033820917978"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oskouian</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tubbs</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The current understanding of MicroRNA’s therapeutic, diagnostic, and prognostic role in chordomas: a review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Cureus</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e3772</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30820391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.3772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6389020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1533033820917978"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>microRNA-19a-3p promotes tumor metastasis and chemoresistance through the PTEN/Akt pathway in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1147</fpage>–<lpage>1154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30021351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.06.097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1533033820917978"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wa</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Downregulation of miR 19a 3p promotes invasion, migration and bone metastasis via activating TGF β signaling in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29138858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2017.6096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5783607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1533033820917978"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>High bone marrow miR-19b level predicts poor prognosis and disease recurrence in de novo acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>640</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29032147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gene.2017.10.034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1533033820917978"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Plasma microRNA-19a as a potential biomarker for esophageal squamous cell carcinoma diagnosis and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Biomark Med</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28621611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2217/bmm-2016-0286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1533033820917978"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Cysteine-rich intestinal protein 1 suppresses apoptosis and chemosensitivity to 5-fluorouracil in colorectal cancer through ubiquitin-mediated Fas degradation</article-title>. <source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>120</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30850009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13046-019-1117-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6408822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1533033820917978"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>AKR1B10 promotes breast cancer cell migration and invasion via activation of ERK signaling</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>33694</fpage>–<lpage>33703</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.16624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5464903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1533033820917978"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reduced CENPU expression inhibits lung adenocarcinoma cell proliferation and migration through PI3K/AKT signaling</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1084</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30849291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09168451.2019.1588094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1533033820917978"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>MicroRNA-148b regulates tumor growth of non-small cell lung cancer through targeting MAPK/JNK pathway</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30849960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-019-5400-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6408859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1533033820917978"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>MicroRNA-148b regulates tumor growth of non-small cell lung cancer through targeting MAPK/JNK pathway</article-title>. <source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1563</fpage>–<lpage>1573</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30840279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26355/eurrev_201902_17115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1533033820917978"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Increased NHE1 expression is targeted by specific inhibitor cariporide to sensitize resistant breast cancer cells to doxorubicin in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30849956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-019-5397-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6408845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1533033820917978"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Downregulation of miR-210 protected bupivacaine-induced neurotoxicity in dorsal root ganglion</article-title>. <source>Exp Brain Res</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>234</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00221-015-4513-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1533033820917978"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Propranolol inhibits proliferation and invasion of hemangioma-derived endothelial cells by suppressing the DLL4/Notch1/Akt pathway</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol Interact</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>294</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30130526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cbi.2018.08.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>