
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Womens Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Womens Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1312</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">intjwh</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101531698</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijwh</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Women's Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1411</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7797326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7797326.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7797326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7797326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33442301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJWH.S279698</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">279698</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Early Initiation of Breastfeeding and Its Associated Factors Among Mothers Who Delivered Vaginally in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Getnet Kassa</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Getnet Kassa</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2837-922X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Getnet Kassa</surname><given-names initials="B">Bekalu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Midwifery, <institution>College of Health Science, Debre Tabor University</institution>, <addr-line>Debre Tabor</addr-line>, <addr-line>Amhara</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Bekalu Getnet Kassa Email bekalugetnet947@gmail.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">372604</issue-id><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-10-02 17:25:25.297"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021 Getnet Kassa.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Getnet Kassa.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ijwh-13-9.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" journal-id="Int J Womens Health" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8140920"><article-title>Early Initiation of Breastfeeding and Its Associated Factors Among Mothers Who Delivered Vaginally in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020 [Retraction]</article-title><volume>13</volume><date><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><source>International Journal of Women's Health</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJWH.S318646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8140920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34040453</pub-id></related-article><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Purpose</title><p>The early onset of skin-to-skin contact encourages the infant to breastfeed within one hour of birth. The aim of this study was to assess the prevalence of early onset breastfeeding and its associated factors among vaginal delivered mothers in hospitals in the South Gondar Zone of Northwest Ethiopia in 2020.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>From January 12 to February 03, 2020, an institutional-based cross-sectional study was used in South Gondar Zone hospitals. A total of 356 mothers delivered by vaginal were included. Data was collected using a questionnaire administered by the interviewer and entered into version 3.1 of EpiData, and then exported to SPSS version 23.0.0. To classify factors correlated with the outcome variables, logistic regression statistical analyses were used.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>In the study area, the prevalence of early breastfeeding initiation among vaginally delivered mothers was 88.2%. Mothers who had unintended pregnancy [adjusted OR=6.00, 95% CI=2.8, 12.5], had professional guidance [adjusted OR=2.75, 95% CI=1.2, 5.6] and experience with breastfeeding [adjusted OR=1.79 95% CI=1.19, 2.68] among vaginal delivered mothers were positively correlated with early breastfeeding initiation.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The type of pregnancy and professional guidance among vaginally delivered mothers were significantly associated with early initiation of breastfeeding. Community-based education and counseling on breastfeeding for pregnant mothers and encouraging all mothers to start early breastfeeding.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>proportion</kwd><kwd>early initiation of breastfeeding</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="6"/><ref-count count="35"/><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Background</title><p>Breastfeeding (BF) is the act of feeding the mother’s milk to the infant. It is the preferred food to any product provided to the baby for all children, and it is cost effective, new, and easily accessible.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>In order to minimize baby, child and maternal morbidity and mortality, breastfeeding is both a primary public health policy and helps to manage a health-care costs. In addition to health benefits for the mother and economic benefits for the family and the society as a whole, it also offers the child nutritional, immunological, developmental and psychological benefits.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></p><p>Early breastfeeding initiation (EIBF) is described as bringing the newborn to the breast within one hour of birth. It is one of the ten effective steps of breastfeeding practice and one of the main measures of determining the effective practice of feeding infants and young children.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p>The EIBF is important for stimulating the production of breast milk by mothers, increasing maternal-infant bonding, improving cognitive development, promoting optimal growth and metabolic skills, improving infant responses to infection and reducing allergic diseases, etc.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>Globally, in the first month of life, 2.5 million children died in 2017, most of which occurred in the first week, of around 1 million dying on the first day and about 1 million dying in the next six days. In sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia, neonatal mortality was also highest, with an estimated 27 deaths per 1000 live births each in 2017.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p>In developing countries alone, the EIBF could save as many as 1.45 million lives each year by reducing deaths mainly due to childhood diarrheal disorders and lower respiratory tract infections, but children are still death in the area because of diarrheal disorders and lower respiratory tract infections due to delayed initiation of breastfeeding.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>Children in Ethiopia suffer from poor health; before their 5th birthday, approximately 472,000 children are dying every year, making Ethiopia 6th among the world’s countries in terms of absolute number of child deaths. In the first 30 days of life, the age distribution of deaths under Five was 55 per thousand live births, 29% from the first month to the 11th month of life, and 42% from the first year to the fourth decade. In Ethiopia, neonatal mortality is very high, making Ethiopia sixth in the world in neonatal mortality, and children in Ethiopia suffer and die in large numbers from preventable and treatable factors, particularly delayed initiation of breastfeeding.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>Some factors influence the EIBF, including such socio-demographic, obstetric characteristics of mothers and health care support services exposure.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p><p>The Ethiopian Ministry of Health also targeted an increase in the proportion of newborn babies put to breast within the first hour of life to 92% by 2015 as one strategy to improve infant health by recognizing the undeniable role of the EIBF in reducing child mortality.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p><p>Fortunately, the 2016 Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey (EDHS) showed that 73% of children who were breast-fed in the first hour of life and the Amhara region was the second lowest region in the EIBF, which was 66%.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p><p>While evidence exists on the proportion and associated factors of EIBF in different regions of the world, so far there has been an information gap on the proportion and associated factors of early onset of breastfeeding among vaginal mothers who have been delivered. The goal of this study was indeed to determine the proportion of EIBF among vaginal delivered mothers and to identify factors affecting the EIBF in the South Gondar Zone, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Study Setting</title><p>The study was conducted in the South Gondar Zone, which is situated in the central part of the region of Amhara and in the northwestern part of Ethiopia. The area is located about 668 km from the capital city of Ethiopia, Addis Ababa, and 103 km from the regional state of Amhara, Bahir Dar. The administrative town of the South Gondar Zone is Debre Tabor. With a population of 2,609,823, the Zone has 18 districts (1,304,911 females and 1,304,912 males). There are eight government hospitals, 96 public health centers, 140 private clinics and 403 state health facilities in the Zone.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Study Design and Period</title><p>An institutional cross-sectional study was conducted in hospitals in the South Gondar Zone, Ethiopia, from 12 January 2020 to 03 February 2020.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Source Population</title><p>All mothers who delivered vaginally in South Gondar hospitals.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Study Population</title><p>All mothers who delivered vaginally during the study period in South Gondar Zone hospitals were considered as the study population.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Eligibility Criteria</title><p>The study included all mothers who gave birth and registered in the delivery registration book in hospitals in the South Gondar Zone. Mothers with postnatal complications (third degree tear, PPH, postpartum eclampsia, postpartum depression) and babies have some medical conditions that include separation from the mother; the study excluded neonates admitted to the NICU.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Sample Size Determination</title><p>The sample size was estimated using a single population proportion formula and the required sample size was determined using the following assumptions for this study; desired precision (d) = 4%, confidence level = 95% (Z alpha/2 = ±1.96 value) and 81.9% of the prevalence of vaginally delivered mothers.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Therefore, 356 was the final calculated sample size.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Sampling Procedures</title><p>In order to obtain appropriate samples, all hospitals that offer vaginal delivery service were taken. Then, using proportional allocation of size (PAS), a sample from each hospital was calculated. Finally, all mothers who delivered vaginally to get the appropriate sample size were selected using simple random sampling (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic presentation of sampling procedures in selecting VD mothers in South Gondar zone hospitals, 2020.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJWH-13-9-g0001.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> DGH, Debre Tabor General Hospital; NMH, Nifas Mewucha Hospital; MEH, M/eyesus Hospital; AZH, A/Zemen Hospital; EBH, Ebenat Hospital; AGH, Arba Gebeya Hospital; SH, Simada Hospital; AH, Andabet Hospital.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Operational Definitions</title><p>Early initiation of breastfeeding: mothers who have begun breastfeeding within one hour of birth.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p><p>Knowledge about early initiation of breastfeeding: eight knowledge-related EIBF questions were posted to mothers and each correct answer was given a value of 1 and an incorrect answer was given a value of 0. It was dichotomized into good knowledge, mean, bad knowledge, &lt; mean,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> after measuring the sum for and respondent and mean.</p><p>Professional guidance to initiate BF: Professionals who instruct and assist the mother by explaining how to carry the infant, how to practice positioning and bonding within one hour to begin breastfeeding.</p><p>EIBF social/family support: any attendant who promotes, supports and shares the mother’s experience in order to start breastfeeding within an hour.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Data Collection Tools and Procedure</title><p>For data collection, a pre-tested and structured, self-administered questionnaire was used. After reviewing related work in scientific literature, the questionnaire was adopted. In order to ensure the accuracy of the instrument, the instrument was first prepared in English, then translated to Amharic and back to English by language experts. Using a standardized and pre-tested questionnaire, data was collected via face-to-face interviews. The face-to-face interviews were performed by six diploma holder nurses and two BSc degree midwives supervised the data collection process.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2010"><title>Data Quality Assurance</title><p>A pre-test was performed in Addis Alem hospital on 36 mothers who gave birth vaginally; the instrument was then amended accordingly. Any mistake, uncertainty or incompleteness found was immediately corrected. The data collectors were trained on the contents of the questionnaire, data collection methods and the purpose of the study for one day. The method of data collection was supervised during the data collection period by the supervisor and the investigator.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2011"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Using Epi data version 3.1, the data collected was entered and cleaned, then exported to SPSS version 23 for analysis. To summarize the data, descriptive analysis was performed and the final outcome of the study was interpreted in the form of text, figures and tables. Binary logistic regression analysis was carried out to see the association between independent and dependent variables. All explanatory variables with p&lt;0.2 in bivariable logistic regression were entered into a multivariable logistic regression model and a significant correlation was established based on p&lt;0.05 and an odds ratio with 95% CI in multivariable logistic regression.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2012"><title>Ethical Approval and Consent to Participants</title><p>This study was carried out according to the Helsinki Declaration. Ethical clearance was obtained from the Institutional Review Board (IRC) of Debre Tabor University College of Health Sciences University (IRB reference number: CHS/IRB 03–008). Further approval was also granted from the South Gondar Zone Administrative Health Office. The purpose of the study has been told for each study participant and the participants in the study have the right to refuse or discontinue participation in the research without restriction. Written informed consent was obtained from each participant before data collection and confidentiality was assured; and written informed consent was obtained from parent or guardians for those age&lt;18 years.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Socio-Demographic Characteristics of Mothers and Their Husbands</title><p>Of the 356 mothers, 348 mothers participated in a survey with a response rate of 97.8%. The highest proportion of VD mothers in the age group was 159 (45.7%) aged 25–29 years. The average age of the mother was 26.71 (SD ± 4.8) years. Nearly three-fourth 259 (74.5%) of VD mothers were urban residents. Almost all mothers, 342 (98.3%) were ethnic Amhara and 272 (78.2%) were Orthodox Christian followers. As far as mothers’ educational status is mentioned, at least 184 (52.7%) mothers have finished secondary school. As far as husbands ‘educational status is concerned, 233 (67%) mothers’ husbands attended at least secondary school (see <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-Demographic Characteristics of Mothers and Their Husbands in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">EIBF (n=348)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">No</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 15–19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 20–24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 25–29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 30–34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 35 and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urban</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rural</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unmarried<sup>#</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Orthodox</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Muslim</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Not formal education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Secondary school and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Husband education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Not formal education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primary school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Secondary school and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal occupation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Government employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Self employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Daily laborer Housewife</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Farmer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Husband occupation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Government Employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Self employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Daily laborer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Farmer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Other*, Protestant, catholic, Jehovah, no religion; <sup>#</sup>Single, divorced and widowed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Maternal Knowledge on EIBF and BF Experience</title><p>Two hundred and sixty-seven (76.7%) mothers knew about the EIBF. With regard to the EIBF information source, 236 (67.8%) mothers stated that the key source of information on EIBF was health professionals. Almost all mothers, 347 (99.7%) confirmed that breast milk had to be given to the baby first after birth. Two hundred and fifty-six (73.5%) mothers knew the recommended time to start BF. As far as maternal knowledge of the EIBF is concerned, two hundred and sixty (74,7%) mothers had good knowledge of the EIBF. Regarding BF experience, 205 (58.9%) of mothers were experienced in BF (see <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Maternal Knowledge on EIBF and BF Experience in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">EIBF &amp; BF (n=348)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">No</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency Percent</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did you hear about BF?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source of Information</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Health professional’s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Media</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did you know recommended timing of initiating of BF?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maternal knowledge on EIBF &amp; BF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breastfeeding experiences</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Obstetric and Health Service-Related Characteristics</title><p>As for the form of pregnancy, 295 (84.8%) of mothers indicated that their pregnancy was expected. Almost all 345 (99.1%) mothers had a history of ANC visits during pregnancy. Ninety-one (26.1%) mothers offered guidance from the EIBF during the ANC visit. As far as the EIBF’s professional advice was concerned, two hundred ninety-nine (85,9%) of mothers had professional guidance from the EIBF. Two hundred and nine (60.1%) of mothers were multi gravidas. In terms of duration of labor pain, 330 (94.8%) of mother’s labor pain was less than 12 hours (see <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Obstetric and Health Service-Related Characteristics of Mothers versus EIBF Among VD Mothers in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">EIBF (n=348)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Yes</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">No</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency Percent</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of pregnancy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intended</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unintended</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place of ANC follow-up</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Public institution</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Private clinic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NGO maternity center</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Number of ANC visit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less than four visits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Four and above visits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EIBF counseling during ANC visits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of labor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less than 12 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Greater than 12 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Received professional Guidance for EIBF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Primi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>Infant and Social-Related Characteristics</title><p>According to this result, 180 (51.7%) mothers gave birth to a female child. Three hundred and twenty (92%) of mothers received social assistance from the EIBF.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Proportion of EIBF Among Vaginal Delivered Mothers</title><p>In South Gondar Zone hospitals, the total proportion of EIBF among vaginal delivered mothers was 88.2% with (95% CI (85%, 92%) with p&lt;0.001.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Reasons for Late Initiation of BreastFeeding</title><p>The main reasons for delayed (late) initiation of breastfeeding claimed by the study participants were 58.3% of pain and discomfort, 33.3% of delayed milk secretion, and 8.3% of no specific reason.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Factors Associated with EIBF Among Vaginal Delivered Mothers</title><p>In order to test EIBF practice, two models were fitted. The first model was designed to analyze EIBF-related factors among vaginal delivered mothers. Among vaginally delivered mothers, variables such as type of pregnancy and professional advice for EIBF were significantly associated with EIBF. In contrast to mothers with unintended pregnancy, mothers with planned pregnancy were 6.00 times (AOR=6.00, 95% CI= 2.86, 12.56) more likely to start BF within one hour. Mothers who obtained professional guidance from the EIBF were 2.75 times more likely to start BF early than those mothers who did not receive professional guidance from the EIBF (AOR=2.75, 95% CI=1.20, 6.34). Mothers with BF experience were 1.79 times (AOR=1.79, 95% CI=1.19, 2.68) more likely than their counterparts to start BF within one hour (see <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Multivariable Analysis of EIBF Among VD Mothers in South Gondar Zone Hospitals, Northwest Ethiopia, 2020 (N= 348)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">EIBF</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">COR, 95% CI</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">AOR, 95% CI</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Receive professional guidance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59 (1.20, 5.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75 (1.20, 6.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of labour</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤ than 12hrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">295</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 (1.48, 11.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02 (0.95, 9.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt; 12 hrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of pregnancy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intended</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08(6.99, 12.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 (2.86, 12.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unintended</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge on EIBF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 (0.81, 3.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (0.66 3.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BF experience</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99 (1.03, 3.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 (1.19, 2.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of ANC visit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Four and above</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 (1.06, 4.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.55, 2.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less than four</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> *p-value &lt;0.05, **p-value &lt;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>The goal of this study was to determine the prevalence of EIBF and associated factors among mothers with vaginal delivery in the South Gondar Zone of Northwest Ethiopia.</p><p>The study found that the prevalence of early initiation of breastfeeding among vaginal delivery within one hour was 88.2%. The result was consistent with the study in Bahir Dar, Ethiopia (87%).<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> This may be due to the similarity of the nature of the study, the social demographic variables and the population of the study.</p><p>On the other hand, this result was higher than the two studies in Bangladesh, which were 57% and 67% among vaginal delivered mothers.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> This disparity may be due to the difference in nature of the study, because the study performed in Bangladesh was an observational study, but this study was a cross-section study.</p><p>This result was also higher compared to the study conducted in India (65.2%),<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Nepal (55%)<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and Bangladesh (67%)<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> among vaginal delivered mothers who began breastfeeding within one hour. This disparity may be due to variations in the time of the research, the nature of the study, maternal socio-demographic characteristics such as access to information, educational status, cross-cultural disparities in breastfeeding practice and the characteristics of health service use.</p><p>However, the EIBF rate in our study was 88.2% higher than the other studies performed in Ethiopia (48.8% in 2000 to 75.7% in 2016),<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Debre Tabor (76.8%),<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Tigray (61.9%)<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and Wolayita zone (81.1%).<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> This discrepancy may be attributable to the study’s time gap; as the study develops their awareness, attitude and practice towards early initiation of breastfeeding close to this century.</p><p>The results of the multivariate analysis showed that the variables were statistically significant to the practice of the EIBF, including professional guidance received, unintended pregnancy and prior experience of breastfeeding.</p><p>This result showed that the professional guidance received was substantially correlated with early initiation of breastfeeding. This finding was supported by studies conducted in Brazil,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Indonesia,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Bangladesh,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Romania<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and Uganda;<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> which showed that professional assistance or advice after delivery increased the EIBF by mothers.</p><p>This may be due to the fact that the support and inspiration of health professionals encourages mothers to take a stand in EIBF service. A professional and well-trained health-care provider can encourage mothers to encourage early breastfeeding and explain the benefits of early breastfeeding, counseling on the risks and long-term risks of pre-lacteal feeding, and the benefits of the EIBF and the continuation of breastfeeding.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p><p>The type of pregnancy has also been significantly associated with EIBF for mothers with vaginal delivery. According to this result, mothers with intended pregnancy were more likely to initiate BF early than mothers with unintended pregnancy, which was consistent with studies conducted in Turkey,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Philippines<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> and Eastern zone Tigray Ethiopia.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> This may be explained by the fact that the attitude of women towards their baby will affect their probability of child care and, ultimately, their decision to initiate breastfeeding timely.</p><p>Mothers who had prior breastfeeding experience were 1.79 times more likely to start breastfeeding within one hour compared to their counterparts. This finding was supported by studies in Tabriz [35], Nigeria,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> and Egypt.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The reason for this may be due to the exposure of mothers who have breastfeeding experience to professional counseling, their experience of how to feed the baby breast and how to hold and attach the baby could assist mothers to start early breastfeeding.</p><p>One of the strengths of this study random selection of almost 356 women from a representative list should minimize the likelihood of selection bias. This study has some limitations. First; data of the study are cross-sectional nature of the study limits to set a causal-effect relationship between dependent and independent variables. Second; since it is based on mothers report the exact time that is the first one hour after birth might be difficult to measure. Third; selection bias might be also the limitation of the study. Forth; vaginal delivered mothers delivered in health centers in south Gondar zone were not included.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In the study area, the prevalence of early initiation of early breastfeeding was high. Professional advice on EIBF, type of pregnancy and prior experience of breastfeeding among vaginal delivered mothers was significantly associated with early initiation of breastfeeding. Community-based breastfeeding education and counseling is recommended for pregnant mothers and encourages all mothers to promote early breastfeeding.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The author would like to acknowledge Debre Tabor University for ethical clearance and technical support as well as the study participants and data collectors and supervisors.</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>BF, Breastfeeding; EDHS, Ethiopian Demographic and Health Survey; EIBF, Early initiation of breastfeeding; NICU, Neonatal intensive care unit.</p></sec><sec id="s0007" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The author declares that they have no conflict of interest regarding this work or the publication of this paper.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Breastfeeding and the risk of sudden infant death syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>890</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/22.5.885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8282468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zenebu</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Knowledge and practice of mothers towards exclusive breastfeeding and its associated factors in ambo woreda west shoa zone oromia region</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ethiopia Epidemiology</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of birth of girls with postnatal depression and exclusive breastfeeding: an observational study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4054658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Victora</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bahl</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barros</surname>
<given-names>AJD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Breastfeeding in the 21st century: epidemiology, mechanisms, and lifelong effect</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>387</volume>(<issue>10017</issue>):<fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>490</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01024-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26869575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karkee</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Initiation of breastfeeding and factors associated with prelacteal feeds in Central Nepal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Human Lactation</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0890334414529845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24729005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edmond</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Delayed breastfeeding initiation increases risk of neonatal mortality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e380</fpage>–<lpage>e386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2005-1496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16510618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.unicef.org.Child-survival/neonatal-mortality">https://data.unicef.org.Child-survival/neonatal-mortality</ext-link>. <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Woldemichael</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Timely initiation of breastfeeding and its associated factors among mothers in Tiyo Woreda, Arsi Zone, Ethiopia: A community-based cross sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clinics Mother Child Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2090-7214.1000221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baye</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimates of Dietary Quality in Infants and Young Children (6–23 Months): evidence from Demographic and Health Surveys of 48 Low-And Middle-Income Countries’</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">SSRN Electronic J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3279184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32653760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IBFAN</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Report on the Situation of Infant and Young Child Feeding in Ethiopia</italic></source>. <month>4</month>
<year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Senarath</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siriwardena</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Godakandage</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jayawickrama</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dibley</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determinants of breastfeeding practices: an analysis of the Sri Lanka demographic and health survey 2006–2007</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Matern Child Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8709.2011.00321.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21507202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6860852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karkee</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gavidia</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factors associated with early initiation of breastfeeding among Nepalese mothers: further analysis of Nepal Demographic and Health Survey, 2011</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Breastfeed J</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>21</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-014-0021-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25493094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4260185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ip</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Breastfeeding and maternal and infant health outcomes in developed countries</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep)</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4781366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17764214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Central Stastics Agency (CSA)</collab>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ethiopian Demographic Health Survey</italic></source>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source><italic toggle="yes">Survey of South Gondar Zonal Health Office Report</italic></source>. Health department office, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Butte</surname>
<given-names>NF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Alarcon</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garza</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutrient Adequacy of Exclusive Breastfeeding for the Term Infant During the First Six Months of Life</italic></source>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chekol</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exclusive breastfeeding and mothers’ employment status in Gondar town, Northwest Ethiopia: a comparative cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Breastfeed J</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-017-0118-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28638435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5473972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Musa Seid</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Vaginal delivery and maternal knowledge on correct breastfeeding initiation time as predictors of early breastfeeding initiation: lesson from a community-based cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">ISRN Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>904609</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/904609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samad</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sultana</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pattern of delivery and early initiation of breastfeeding: an urban slum based cross cut study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Nutr Health Food Engineering</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>00244</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karim</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Billah</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>MAK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Initiation of breastfeeding within one hour of birth and its determinants among normal vaginal deliveries at primary and secondary health facilities in Bangladesh: a case-observation study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0202508</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0202508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30114288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6095597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Badaya</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time of initiation of breastfeeding in various modes of delivery and to observe the effect of low birth weight and period of gestation on initiation of breastfeeding</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Contemporary Pediatrics</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1509</fpage>–<lpage>1517</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18203/2349-3291.ijcp20182555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghimire</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The effect of maternal health service utilization in early initiation of breastfeeding among Nepalese mothers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Breastfeed J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-019-0228-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31384286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6668139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>KY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Trends and determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding and exclusive breastfeeding in Ethiopia from 2000 to 2016</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Breastfeed J</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>40</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13006-019-0234-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31528197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6740001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abie</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goshu</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Early initiation of breastfeeding and colostrum feeding among mothers of children aged less than 24 months in Debre Tabor, northwest Ethiopia: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Res Notes</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4094-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30696481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6352422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gebremeskel</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gebru</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gebrehiwot</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Early initiation of breastfeeding and associated factors among mothers of aged less than 12 months children in rural eastern zone, Tigray, Ethiopia: cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Res Notes</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>671</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-019-4718-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6805677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lake</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gelaw</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of timely initiation of breastfeeding practice among primiparous mothers at Bedessa Town, Wolaita Zone, Southern Ethiopia, 2018: A community based cross-sectionals study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Preg Child Health</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>408</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname>
<given-names>TO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname>
<given-names>GO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Giugliani</surname>
<given-names>ERJ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Determinants of breastfeeding initiation within the first hour of life in a Brazilian population: cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>760</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3020684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nisa</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salimo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Budihastuti</surname>
<given-names>UR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Factor of socio demography and obstetric that influence the timeliness of early breastfeeding in tegal regency</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Maternal Child Maternal</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26911/thejmch.2017.02.02.01</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cozma-Petruţ</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Badiu-Tişa</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stanciu</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding among mothers of children aged less than 24 months in Northwestern Romania</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nutrients</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2988</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11122988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6950271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31817702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalisa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malande</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nankunda</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Magnitude and factors associated with delayed initiation of breastfeeding among mothers who deliver in Mulago hospital, Uganda</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Afr Health Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1130</fpage>–<lpage>1135</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ahs.v15i4.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26958013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4765405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Falle</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Potential role of traditional birth attendants in neonatal healthcare in rural southern Nepal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Health Popul Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19248648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3329/jhpn.v27i1.3317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2650835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yılmaz</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doğa Öcal</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vural Yılmaz</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Early initiation and exclusive breastfeeding: factors influencing the attitudes of mothers who gave birth in a baby-friendly hospital</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Turkish J Obstetrics Gynecol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4274/tjod.90018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5558311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28913128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ulep</surname>
<given-names>VGT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Borja</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between pregnancy intention and optimal breastfeeding practices in the Philippines: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2393-12-69</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3500720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Berde</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yalçın</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determinants of early initiation of breastfeeding in Nigeria: a population based study using the 2013 demographic and health survey data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Pregnancy Childbirth</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12884-016-0818-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26852324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4744410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname>
<given-names>NA-E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thabe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Barriers of Initiation and exclusive breast feeding among infants</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">IOSR J Nursing Health Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>01</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>