
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Stem Cell Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Stem Cell Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1238</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">stemcellres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101527581</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1757-6512</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7374869</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7374869.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7374869</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7374869</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32698911</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-020-01826-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1826</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Overexpression of TGFβ1 in murine mesenchymal stem cells improves lung inflammation by impacting the Th17/Treg balance in LPS-induced ARDS mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianxiao</given-names></name><address><email>cjx20051987@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiwen</given-names></name><address><email>xiwen_zhang@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianfeng</given-names></name><address><email>xie820405@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names initials="M">Ming</given-names></name><address><email>xueming0304@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="L">Ling</given-names></name><address><email>liulingdoctor@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name><address><email>yiyiyang2004@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names initials="H">Haibo</given-names></name><address><email>haiboq2000@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452290.8</institution-id><institution>Jiangsu Provincial Key Laboratory of Critical Care Medicine, Department of Critical Care Medicine, School of Medicine, </institution><institution>Zhongda Hospital, Southeast University, </institution></institution-wrap>87 Dingjiaqiao Road, Nanjing, 210009 People’s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">348945</issue-id><elocation-id>311</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-01 13:25:10.283"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13287_2020_Article_1826.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="13" journal-id="Stem Cell Res Ther" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8889642"><article-title>Retraction Note: Overexpression of TGFβ1 in murine mesenchymal stem cells improves lung inflammation by impacting the Th17/Treg balance in LPS-induced ARDS mice</article-title><volume>13</volume><date><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date><elocation-id>84</elocation-id><source>Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-022-02779-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8889642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35232477</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">T helper 17 cells (Th17)/regulatory T cells (Treg), as subtypes of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, play an important role in the inflammatory response of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). However, there is still a lack of effective methods to regulate the differentiation balance of Th17/Treg. It was proven that mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) could regulate the differentiation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, but the mechanism is still unclear. TGFβ1, a paracrine cytokine of MSCs, could also regulate the differentiation of Th17/Treg but is lowly expressed in MSCs. Therefore, mouse MSCs (mMSCs) overexpressing TGFβ1 were constructed by lentivirus transduction and intratracheally transplanted into LPS-induced ARDS mice in our study. The aim of this study was to evaluate the therapeutic effects of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on inflammation and immunoregulation by impacting the Th17/Treg balance in LPS-induced ARDS mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 were constructed using lentiviral vectors. Then, mouse bone-marrow-derived MSCs (mBM-MSC) and mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 (mBM-MSC overexpressing TGFβ1) were transplanted intratracheally into ARDS mice induced by lipopolysaccharide. At 3 and 7 days after transplantation, the mice were sacrificed, and the homing of the mMSCs was assayed by ex vivo optical imaging. The relative numbers of Th17 and Treg in the lungs and spleens of mice were detected by FCM. IL-17A and IL-10 levels in the lungs of mice were analysed by western blot. Permeability and inflammatory cytokines were evaluated by analysing the protein concentration of BALF using ELISA. Histopathology of the lungs was assessed by haematoxylin and eosin staining and lung injury scoring. Alveolar lung fibrosis was assessed by Masson’s trichrome staining and Ashcroft scoring. The mortality of ARDS mice was followed until 7 days after transplantation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The transduction efficiencies mediated by the lentiviral vectors ranged from 82.3 to 88.6%. Overexpressing TGFβ1 inhibited the proliferation of mMSCs during days 5–7 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) but had no effect on mMSC differentiation or migration (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Compared to that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group mice, engraftment of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 led to much more differentiation of T cells into Th17 or Treg (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), improved permeability of injured lungs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and ameliorative histopathology of lung tissue in ARDS mice (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, IL-17A content was also decreased while IL-10 content was increased in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group compared with those in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Finally, mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 did not aggravate lung fibrosis in ARDS mice (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">MSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could regulate lung inflammation and attenuate lung injuries by modulating the imbalance of Th17/Treg in the lungs of ARDS mice.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Acute respiratory distress syndrome</kwd><kwd>Mesenchymal stem cells</kwd><kwd>TGFβ1</kwd><kwd>Th17/Treg</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>81571874</award-id><award-id>81930058</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Haibo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Postgraduate Research &amp; Practice Innovation Program of Jiangsu Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>KYCX17_0168</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jianxiao</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Jiangsu Provincial Special Program of Medical Science</institution></funding-source><award-id>BE2019749</award-id><award-id>BE2018743</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Haibo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Science and Technology Major Project for Control and Prevention of Major Infectious Diseases of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>2017ZX10103004</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Haibo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par42">Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), which was initially defined 52 years ago as a multifactorial syndrome of severe lung injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], is characterised by hypoxaemia, loss of lung compliance, and pulmonary oedema, which can in some instances progress to multiple organ failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. ARDS can develop in response to multiple predisposing factors, including pneumonia, systemic infection, and major surgery or multiple traumas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and results in death in 30–45% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">In the past 50 years, considerable progress has been made in understanding the pathology of ARDS, and the development of ARDS is strongly associated with a disordered immune response in the lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In previous studies, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, as an important component of adaptive immune cells, were significantly activated in the early stage of ARDS, and the differentiation of T helper 17 cells (Th17)/regulatory T cells (Treg) played an important role in the development of ARDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Th17 can release many inflammatory cytokines that mediate the acute inflammatory response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Treg, as important immunosuppressive cells, can also be activated in ARDS, and the transplantation of Treg into an ARDS model mice may reduce the levels of proinflammatory cytokines in the alveoli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and inhibit neutrophil apoptosis and fibrocyte recruitment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In addition, the differentiation balance of Th17/Treg is an independent predictor for 28-day mortality in patients with ARDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Thus, there is still a lack of effective methods to regulate the differentiation balance of Th17/Treg.</p><p id="Par44">Our previous study proved that mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs), with their multipotency and immunoregulation properties, could significantly improve inflammation and repair lung injuries in ARDS mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The mechanism of their immunological regulation may be related to the modulation of T cell expansion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. It has also been confirmed in a recently published study that MSCs could regulate the imbalance of Th17/Treg, which is regulated by antigen-stimulated costimulatory molecules, antigen-presenting cells, cytokines, and intracellular signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. TGFβ1, an important cytokine that regulates the differentiation of Th17/Treg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], is expressed at low levels in MSCs, which was proven by our preliminary data. Thus, overexpression of TGFβ1 is expected to further optimise MSC treatment for immunoregulation.</p><p id="Par45">Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of mouse MSCs (mMSCs) overexpressing TGFβ1 on inflammation and immunoregulation in LPS-induced ARDS mice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par46">mMSCs isolated from the bone marrow of C57BL/6 mice (mBM-MSC) were purchased from Cyagen Biosciences, Inc. (Guangzhou, China), and 293 T cells were supplied by Zoonbio Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Nanjing, China). The mBM-MSC were identified by detecting cell surface phenotypes and their multipotent potential for differentiation along the adipogenic, osteogenic, and chondrogenic lineages as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par47">Either mBM-MSC or 293 T cells were cultured in a 1:1 mix of Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium/nutrient mixture F-12 (DMEM/F12) (Wisent, Inc., St-Bruno, Montreal, Quebec, Canada) containing 10% FBS (Wisent, Inc.) and 1% antibiotic-antimycotic (streptomycin, penicillin and amphotericin B; Wisent, Inc.), incubated at 37 °C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and passaged every 3–4 days by 0.25% trypsin-ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA; Gibco, Carlsbad, CA, USA) when they reached approximately 80% confluence. Passages between 5 and 10 were used for the experimental protocols.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Recombinant lentivirus vector construction and packaging</title><p id="Par48">The full-length coding sequence (CDS) of mouse TGFβ1 was transferred into the CMV promoter-dependent lentivirus vector PDS159_pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES-MCS (Zoonbio Biotechnology Co., Ltd.). Subsequently, the lentivector CL721-pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES-mus-TGF-β (overexpressing TGFβ1), which co-expresses enhanced green fluorescent protein (eGFP) and TGFβ1, was obtained, and the empty vector CL721-pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES was used as an empty vector control. Then, the recombinant plasmids CL721-pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES-mus-TGF-β and CL721-pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES were separately co-transfected with packaging plasmids into 293 T cells at the indicated concentrations using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, producing the lentivirus LV402-pL6.3-CMV-GFPa1-IRES-mus-TGF-β and the negative control PDS019.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Lentiviral vector transduction and eGFP reporter gene detection</title><p id="Par49">The mBM-MSC (1 × 10<sup>6</sup>/well seeded in six-well cell culture plates) were transduced with viral supernatant at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 160:1 for 24 h. Then, the stable cell lines were harvested after selection using blasticidin (BSD; InvivoGen) at the minimal lethal concentration (6 μg/mL) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and cultured in normal culture medium for 20 passages after transduction. Finally, the transduction efficiency of mBM-MSC and the percentage of eGFP-positive cells were evaluated by fluorescence microscopy and flow cytometry (FCM) analysis using a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (Becton-Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Cell surface phenotype detection</title><p id="Par50">The cells were also identified by detecting cell surface phenotypes after lentivirus transduction. Fluorescein conjugated monoclonal antibodies, including CD29, CD34, CD44, CD105, and CD45, and the respective isotype controls were purchased from Becton-Dickinson (Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). FCM analysis was performed with fluorescence-activated cell sorting analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>RNA isolation and quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par51">Total RNA was isolated from the cells and tissues using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Austin, TX, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol, and the purity of the RNA (260/280 nm absorbance ratio of 1.8–2.2) was assessed by a spectrophotometer (Tecan, Switzerland). Reverse transcription was completed using a RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific) with 1 mg of RNA according to the manufacturer’s instructions. qRT-PCR was performed using a CFX96™ Real-Time system (Bio-Rad). Relative changes in gene expression were normalised to the expression of actin and calculated by the 2(−ΔΔCt) method. The primer sequences used for PCR amplification in our study were designed based on the sequences of the genomic clones and are as follows:
<table-wrap id="Taba" position="float" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primer</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primer sequence</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCR amplified product (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Actin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-AGAGGGAAATCGTGCGTGAC-3′</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">195</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-CCATACCCAAGAAGGAAGGCT-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">GADPH</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-TGTGTCCGTCGTGGATCTGA-3′</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">150</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-TTGCTGTTGAAGTCGCAGGAG-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">TGFβ1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-GACTCTCCACCTGCAAGACC-3′</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-GGACTGGCGAGCCTTAGTTT-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Collagen I</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-GTGTTTCCTGTGCTACTG-3′</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">132</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-TCTTTCTCCTCTCTGACC-3′</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">α-SMA</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-CCTCGCCTCTACCCCTTA-3′</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2" colspan="1">120</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5′-ATTCGCTTGCCTTTGCTT-3′</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="Par52">To evaluate the TGFβ1 concentration in mBM-MSC, the total cellular protein was extracted by RIPA lysis buffer (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China) containing an antiprotease cocktail (1 mmol/L PMSF, 1 mmol/L NaF and 1 mmol/L Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>; US Biological Inc., Swampscott, MA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, quantified by a BCA protein assay kit (Beyotime), separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) (10%), electro-transferred to PVDF membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA), and then incubated with primary antibodies against TGFβ1 (1:5000 dilution; Abcam Incorporated, Cambridge, MA) or β-actin (1:3000 dilution; Abcam Incorporated, Cambridge, MA) at 4 °C overnight. The blots were washed three times with TBST and then incubated for 1 h at room temperature with goat anti-rabbit IgG conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (1:5000 dilution; Zoonbio Biotechnology). Immunoreactive complexes were visualised by chemiluminescence reagents (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA), and immunoreactive bands were obtained using a chemiluminescence imaging system (BioshineChemiQ4800 mini; Ouxiang, Shanghai, China). Finally, the intensity of those bands was analysed by Image J software (NIH, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Protein concentration in culture medium</title><p id="Par53">mBM-MSC, mBM-MSC-NC, and mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 were seeded in a 12-well plate at a density of 1 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well. After 12 h, the culture medium was changed, and mBM-MSC were cultured in an incubator at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24 h. The culture medium was then collected, and TGFβ1 protein levels in the culture medium were quantified using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kit (Abcam, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Cell proliferation assay</title><p id="Par54">Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8; Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China) assays were used to further investigate the effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on mBM-MSC proliferation according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, cells were seeded in 96-well plates at 2 × 10<sup>3</sup> cells per well in 100 μL of growth medium. After staining with CCK-8 (10 μL per well), the cells were incubated for 4 h at 37 °C. Absorbance was assessed at 450 nm with a microplate reader (Tecan, Switzerland).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Multidifferentiation of mMSCs after gene transduction</title><p id="Par55">For osteogenic differentiation, the cells were seeded in 6-well plates and cultured in 2 mL of DMEM/F12 supplemented with 10% FBS. When the cells reached approximately 80–90% confluence, they were switched to C57BL/6 mMSC osteogenic differentiation medium (Cyagen Biosciences, Inc., Guangzhou, China) for 2–3 weeks. Calcium deposition was assessed by staining the cells with 40 mM Alizarin Red S solution at room temperature for 10 min.</p><p id="Par56">For adipocytic differentiation, when reaching confluence, the cells were treated with mMSCs adipogenic differentiation basal medium A (Cyagen Biosciences, Inc., Guangzhou, China) for 3 days, followed by exchange with mMSCs adipogenic differentiation basal medium B (Cyagen Biosciences, Inc., Guangzhou, China) for 24 h and then switching back to basal medium A. After five to six cycles, the cells were cultured in basal medium B for 3 days until their lipid vacuoles enlarged. To assess the accumulation of neutral lipid vacuoles, the cells were stained with filtered Oil Red O solution for 10 min at room temperature, and the incorporated Oil Red O was extracted by adding 1 mL of isopropanol to each well at room temperature for 15 min.</p><p id="Par57">For chondrogenic differentiation, 2.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells were centrifuged in a 15 mL tube at 150×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 5 min to form a pellet. Chondrogenic differentiation was achieved by the three-dimensional culture method and C57BL/6 mMSCs chondrogenic differentiation medium (Cyagen Biosciences, Inc., Guangzhou, China). After 28 days, the pellets were embedded in paraffin and then fixed in dimethylbenzene and ethanol. Five-micrometre sections were cut and stained with Alcian blue to determine the polysaccharide accumulation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>In vitro scratch assay</title><p id="Par58">The horizontal migration of cells was determined by the in vitro scratch assay. Cells were seeded in six-well culture plates. After reaching approximately 100% confluence, a scratch was made with a 10-μL sterile pipette tip. Then, the cells were cultured in serum-free DMEM/F12 for another 12 h. The images of the wound area were recorded by a light microscope immediately after scratching and 12 h later. The horizontal migration ability of the cells was quantified by measuring the wound area in each group by Image J analysis software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Transwell migration assay</title><p id="Par59">The vertical migration of cells was determined by the Transwell migration assay. Transwell inserts (6.5 mm diameter and 8 mm pore size; Millipore) that were seeded with 2 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells in 100 μL of serum-free DMEM/F12 were loaded into lower chambers with 600 μL of DMEM/F12 supplemented with 10% FBS. After incubation for 12 h, the cells remaining on the upper surface of the inserts were removed with cotton swabs, and the cells that had migrated to the lower surface were stained with crystal violet (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China) for 20 min. The stained cells from four randomly chosen areas were measured under a light microscope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="Par60">All animal experiments in this study were performed in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals and were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Southeast University. Wild-type (WT) C57BL/6 mice aged 6–8 weeks were purchased from the Laboratory Animal Centre (Shanghai, China). Mice were housed in individual microisolator cages under specific pathogen-free conditions with free access to water and chow.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Murine model of lipopolysaccharide-induced acute respiratory distress syndrome</title><p id="Par61">After anaesthetization with an intraperitoneal injection of pentobarbital at 50 mg/kg, mice were subjected to intratracheal (i.t.) administration of LPS (2 mg/kg, <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> serotype 0111:B4; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) dissolved in 20 μL of sterile normal saline (NS). Sham operation was performed in a similar manner with the same volume of only 0.9% NS instead of LPS. Then, the mice recovered until fully awake in a 100% oxygen chamber.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Experimental protocol</title><p id="Par62">The mice were randomly divided into five groups as follows: the control group, mice that received phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) intratracheally 4 h after i.t. administration of 0.9% NS; the ARDS group, mice that received PBS intratracheally 4 h after LPS challenge; the LPS + mBM-MSC group, mice that received WT mBM-MSC (2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per mouse) intratracheally; the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group, mice that received mBM-MSC-NC (normal control, 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per mouse) intratracheally; and the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group, mice that received mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 (overexpressing TGFβ1, 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per mouse) intratracheally. The mice were sacrificed at 1, 3, or 7 days after mBM-MSC injection, and the lung lobes were collected for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Preparation of lung tissue lymphocytes and flow cytometry analysis</title><p id="Par63">After the mice were sacrificed, 5 mL of PBS/0.6 mM EDTA was injected into the right ventricular cannula for lung perfusion. The lung was then isolated from the surrounding tissue and added to medium containing digestive enzymes (RPMI 1640, 20 mM HEPES, 10% FCS, 175 U/mL collagenase, 75 U/mL DNAse I, 0.2 U/mL pancreatic elastase, 35 U/mL hyaluronidase, 100 IU/mL penicillin, and 100 mg/mL streptomycin) for incubation for 45 min at 37 °C. The resulting suspension was passed three times through a 19-gauge needle to break up clumps and then through a 40-mm filter to remove debris. The leukocytes were enriched by discontinuous Percoll gradient centrifugation and recovered at the interface between 40% Percoll and 70% Percoll layers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">The following antibodies (Miltenyi, USA) were used for surface and nuclear staining: FITC-labelled anti-CD4, APC-labelled anti-CD25, PE-labelled anti-Foxp3, and PE-labelled anti-RORγt. For the analysis of Treg, cells were incubated with the surface marker antibodies FITC-anti-CD4 and APC-anti-CD25, followed by fixation and permeabilization with Foxp3-staining buffer (Miltenyi) and intracellular staining with PE-labelled anti-Foxp3. To detect the phenotypes of Th17 cells in the lungs, cells were incubated with the surface markers FITC-anti-CD4 and APC-anti-CD25. Then, the cells were fixed and permeabilized using RORγt-staining buffer (Miltenyi), followed by intracellular staining with PE-labelled anti-RORγt.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Protein concentration in the lungs and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid</title><p id="Par65">To analyse the expression of IL-17A, IL-10, and occludin in the lungs after transplantation, total protein lysates were extracted by RIPA lysis buffer (Beyotime) from left lung lobes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 per group at each time-point) and measured by western blot as previously described. The PVDF membranes were incubated with primary antibodies against IL-17A (1:5000 dilution, Abcam), IL-10 (1:5000 dilution, Abcam), occludin (1:5000 dilution; Abcam), or β-actin (1:3000 dilution; Abcam Incorporated, Cambridge, MA).</p><p id="Par66">Bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) was collected by flushing 1 mL of ice-cold PBS back and forth three times through a tracheal cannula as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. After centrifugation at 800×<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min, total protein (TP), albumin (ALB), tumour necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and IL-1β and IL-6 concentrations in the BALF were measured by ELISA kits (Cusabio Biotech, Wuhan, China; Excell Bio, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Labelling and tracing of mesenchymal stem cells</title><p id="Par67">WT mBM-MSC, mBM-MSC-NC, and mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 were labelled with CellVue NIR815 dye (eBioscience Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Then, NIR815-labelled cells (5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells) were directly administered into the trachea of the mice in different groups according to the protocol. After 1, 3, and 7 days post-transplantation, three mice at each time point were sacrificed, and ex vivo lungs were imaged using a Maestro in vivo optical imaging system (excitation = 786 nm, emission = 814 nm, and 4000 ms exposure time; Caliper Life Sciences, MA, Boston, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The autofluorescence spectra were then unmixed based on their spectral patterns using Maestro 2.4 software (Caliper Life Sciences). The fluorescence intensity of the lungs was measured by placing the regions of interest (ROIs) on the lungs, and the signals were analysed based on the total fluorescence counts of the ROIs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Evaluation of lung oedema</title><p id="Par68">Lung oedema was evaluated using the ratio of lung wet weight to body weight (LWW/BW), which was measured as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Briefly, the whole lung was removed and cleared of all extrapulmonary tissues, and the LWW/BW was calculated based on the values of the lung wet weight and the body weight (mg/g).</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Lung histopathology analysis</title><p id="Par69">The right lung lobes (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 for each group at each time-point) were collected and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, embedded in paraffin, and sliced into 5 μm sagittal sections. After staining with a haematoxylin and eosin staining kit (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China), the slices were then viewed by a pathologist based on ten randomly selected high-power fields (× 400) in each section according to oedema, alveolar and interstitial inflammation, alveolar and interstitial haemorrhage, atelectasis, and necrosis, which was graded on a 0- to 4-point scale (0, no injury; 1, injury in 25% of the field; 2, injury in 50% of the field; 3, injury in 75% of the field; and 4, injury throughout the entire field). The total lung injury score was calculated as the sum of these scores, which has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Lung fibrosis analysis</title><p id="Par70">The lung sections were stained sequentially with Weigert’s iron haematoxylin solution, Biebrich scarlet-acid fuchsin solution, and aniline blue solution, and a blue signal indicated positive staining for collagen. The criteria of Ashcroft were used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] to assess lung fibrosis, which was quantified based on the findings in ten randomly selected high-power fields (× 400) for each slide by histopathologists blinded to the protocol. Collagen-I and α-SMA mRNA expression in lung tissues was measured by RT-PCR.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par71">The data are presented as the means ± standard deviations (SDs). Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 26.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) and GraphPad Prism 8 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, California USA). Comparisons among multiple groups were performed by one-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni’s post hoc test if the data were normally distributed. Kaplan-Meier curves were used to describe the survival rate of mice in each group, and log-rank tests were performed to analyse the significance of differences. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec25"><title>The efficiency of lentiviral vector-mediated TGFβ1 overexpression in mMSCs</title><p id="Par72">The transduction efficiency, which was reflected by the eGFP-positive cell ratio in our study, mediated by the lentiviral vectors after 20 passages was detected by fluorescence microscopy and FCM analysis. The transduction efficiencies of cells overexpressing TGFβ1 were 82.3–88.6% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). TGFβ1 mRNA levels in mMSCs were detected by qRT-PCR. TGFβ1 mRNA expression was significantly higher in the mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group than in the mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). However, there was no significant difference between the mBM-MSC and mBM-MSC-NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Secreted TGFβ1 levels in the culture media of mMSCs were significantly higher in the mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group than in the mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). The western blot analysis also showed similar results for TGFβ1 protein expression in mMSCs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e). Thus, lentivirus-mediated TGFβ1 transduction was stable and efficient.
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Measurement of TGFβ1 expression in mMSCs after lentiviral vector transduction. <bold>a</bold> mBM-MSC, mBM-MSC-NC, and mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 were cultured for 20 passages and observed by light microscopy (top) and fluorescence microscopy with green fluorescent protein (bottom), × 200. <bold>b</bold> The percentage of GFP-positive cells was analysed by flow cytometry at passage 20 after transduction. <bold>c</bold> Evaluation of TGFβ1 mRNA expression in mMSCs after transduction (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 vs. mBM-MSC-NC). <bold>d</bold> Evaluation of secreted TGFβ1 in the culture medium of mMSCs after transduction by ELISA (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 vs. mBM-MSC-NCs). <bold>e</bold> Detection by western blot analysis of TGFβ1 protein levels in mMSCs after transduction (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 vs. mBM-MSC-NCs). mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par73">In this study, calcium deposition examined by Alizarin Red S staining, lipid accumulation by Oil Red O staining, and polysaccharide accumulation by Alcian blue staining experiment were used to evaluate the multidifferentiation of mMSCs after gene transduction. TGFβ1 transduction did not change the multipotential differentiation ability of mMSCs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the proliferation, differentiation, and migration of mMSCs. <bold>a</bold> The effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the proliferation of mMSCs. The growth curves of the cells after transduction for 7 days were evaluated by CCK-8 assay (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. mBM-MSC-NCs). <bold>b</bold> The effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the multipotential differentiation of mMSCs. Calcium deposition (top), accumulation of neutral lipid vacuoles (middle), and polysaccharide accumulation (bottom) were detected respectively, × 200. <bold>c</bold> The effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the horizontal migration of mMSCs. The wound areas were photographed at 0 and 12 h and quantified by measuring the wound area in each group, × 100 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3). <bold>d</bold> The effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the vertical migration of mMSCs. The migrated cells on the lower surface of Transwell inserts were stained with crystal violet and measured under a light microscope from four randomly chosen areas, × 100 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3). CCK-8, Cell Counting Kit-8; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par74">According to FCM analysis, CD29, CD44, and CD105 were positive while CD34 and CD45 were negative on mBM-MSC-TGFβ1, which was in line with the surface markers of mBM-MSC (Supplementary Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the proliferation of mMSCs</title><p id="Par75">A CCK-8 assay was used to evaluate the effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on cell proliferation. By comparing different growth curves, it was found that overexpression of TGFβ1 significantly decreased cell proliferation in the mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group compared to that in the mBM-MSC-NC group from days 5 to 7 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). There was no significant difference between the mBM-MSC and mBM-MSC-NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the migration of mMSCs</title><p id="Par76">The scratch assay and Transwell assay were used to indicate the horizontal and vertical migration abilities of mMSCs. There were no significant differences in the wound areas in the scratch assay among the mBM-MSC, mBM-MSC-NC, and mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups after 12 h of incubation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Similar results were also detected in the Transwell assay. No significant differences among the groups were observed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Effects of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the graft retention of mMSCs in the lung after lipopolysaccharide challenge</title><p id="Par77">To track intrapulmonary mMSCs, ex vivo NIR imaging was performed on the lungs at 1, 3, and 7 days after mMSCs administration. There were no significant differences in the fluorescent counts of ROIs among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, b).
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The effect of overexpressing TGFβ1 on the graft retention of mMSCs in the lungs after LPS challenge. <bold>a</bold> Typical ex vivo NIR images of injured lungs from mice at 1, 3, and 7 days after mMSCs administration. <bold>b</bold> Average signal from ex vivo NIR imaging of injured lungs from mice at 1, 3, and 7 days after mMSCs administration (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3). mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NIR, near-infrared fluorescence</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Mesenchymal stem cells overexpressing TGFβ1 inhibited lung inflammation in lipopolysaccharide-induced ARDS mice</title><p id="Par78">The differentiation of Th17 and Treg in the lungs of LPS-induced ARDS mice was detected by FCM. At 3 days after mMSCs transplantation, the number of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in the lungs increased significantly in the LPS + mBM-MSC, LPS + mBM-MSC-NC, and LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups compared with that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Meanwhile, the proportion of Th17 significantly decreased in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups compared to that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) but significantly increased in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group compared to that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) but was still lower than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). In addition, the proportion of Treg in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups was significantly lower than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the proportion in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group was significantly higher than that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and even higher than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). Moreover, the Th17/Treg ratio in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups was significantly lower than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group was even lower than that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d).
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on the differentiation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in the lungs of ARDS mice at 3 d after mMSC transplantation. <bold>a</bold>–<bold>d</bold> The differentiation of Th17 and Treg in the lungs of LPS-induced ARDS mice was detected by flow cytometry (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). <bold>e</bold> Representative flow cytometry analysis was shown for each treatment group. ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par79">In addition, similar results were also observed at 7 days after mMSCs transplantation. Compared with that in the lungs of the ARDS group, the number of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells increased significantly in the lungs of the LPS + mBM-MSC, LPS + mBM-MSC-NC, and LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). At the same time, the proportion of Th17 in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups decreased significantly compared to that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the proportion in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group decreased further relative to that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). In addition, the proportion of Treg in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups was significantly lower than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the proportion in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group was slightly higher than that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) but still lower than that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). The Th17/Treg ratio in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group was significantly lower than that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). It was suggested that mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could further regulate the differentiation of Th17 and Treg and improve the balance of Th17/Treg in the lungs of ARDS mice.
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on the differentiation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in the lungs of ARDS mice at 7 days after mMSCs transplantation. <bold>a</bold>–<bold>d</bold> The differentiation of Th17 and Treg in the lungs of LPS-induced ARDS mice was detected by flow cytometry (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). <bold>e</bold> Representative flow cytometry analysis was shown for each treatment group. ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par80">The levels of IL-17A and IL-10 were measured in lung homogenates at 3 and 7 days after mMSCs transplantation by western blot. Compared with that in the ARDS group, IL-17A content was significantly decreased in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 further reduced the concentration of IL-17A in the lungs compared with that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). Meanwhile, compared with that in the ARDS group, IL-10 content was significantly elevated in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could further increase the concentration of IL-10 in the lungs compared with that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). It was suggested that mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could inhibit the expression of IL-17A while increasing IL-10 levels in the lungs of ARDS mice.
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on inflammatory factors in the lungs of ARDS mice. <bold>a</bold> The expression of the IL-17A and <bold>b</bold> IL-10 proteins in the lungs of all the experimental groups at 3 and 7 days after mMSCs administration was evaluated by western blot analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par81">To further evaluate the inflammation in the lungs of ARDS mice, proinflammatory cytokines TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 concentration in BALF of ARDS mice were also measured using ELISA. The expression of TNF-α, IL-1β and IL-6 in BALF were all significantly elevated in response to the LPS challenge (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The treatment with mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 statistically decreased TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 levels than the mBM-MSC-NC did at both 3 and 7 days (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Supplementary Figure <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>A-C).</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Overexpression of TGFβ1 in mesenchymal stem cells improved the lung permeability of ARDS mice</title><p id="Par82">The LWW/BW was calculated to evaluate lung oedema. The LWW/BW was significantly reduced in the LPS + mBM-MSC, LPS + mBM-MSC-NC, and LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups compared with that in the ARDS group at 3 and 7 days (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a).
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on the permeability of LPS-induced lungs in mice. <bold>a</bold> Lung oedema was analysed by LWW/BW (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group). <bold>b</bold> Total protein and <bold>c</bold> albumin concentrations in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid were analysed by a mouse-specific ELISA kit to evaluate the permeability of the lung (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). <bold>d</bold> Expression of the occludin protein in the lungs of all the experimental groups at 3 and 7 days after mMSCs administration was evaluated by western blot analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). ALB, albumin; ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; LWW/BW, lung wet weight/body weight; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control; TP, total protein</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO7" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par83">To evaluate whether mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could alter the permeability of the lung, total protein and albumin concentrations in the BALF were measured by mouse-specific ELISAs. The total protein and albumin concentrations were significantly reduced in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups compared with those in the ARDS group at both 3 and 7 days (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Significant decreases in the total protein and albumin concentrations were also observed in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group compared with those in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group at 3 and 7 days (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b, c).</p><p id="Par84">Additionally, the occludin protein expression level increased significantly in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups compared with that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). A significant increase was also observed in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups compared to that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the increase was much greater than that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Mesenchymal stem cells overexpressing TGFβ1 improved the pulmonary histopathology of lipopolysaccharide-induced ARDS mice</title><p id="Par85">After LPS-induced lung injury, alveolar wall thickening, alveolar and interstitial inflammatory cell infiltration, haemorrhage, alveolar exudate, and oedema were observed in the lung tissues of ARDS group mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a), and the Smith score for quantifying lung injury was also increased significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b) in the ARDS group. However, compared to those in the ARDS group, histopathologic characteristics and the Smith score were alleviated at 3 and 7 days in the LPS + mBM-MSC and LPS + mBM-MSC-NC groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a, b). The effects were greater in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group than in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a, b).
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on the histopathology of LPS-induced lung injury in mice. <bold>a</bold> Typical histopathological images of the lung tissues from mice of all the experimental groups at 3 and 7 days after LPS exposure (HE staining, × 50). <bold>b</bold> Lung injury score (Smith score) of the lung tissues from mice of all the experimental groups at 3 and 7 days after LPS challenge (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 at each time-point for each group; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; #<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; δ<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO8" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Effects of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on lung fibrosis in ARDS mice</title><p id="Par86">To assess lung fibrosis, collagen deposition (which was stained blue) in lung tissue at 7 days after LPS challenge was analysed by Masson’s trichrome staining and was markedly increased in the ARDS group compared with that in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The lung fibrosis score decreased significantly in the LPS + mBM-MSC, LPS + mBM-MSC-NC, and LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups compared to that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Reduced collagen I and α-SMA mRNA was also observed after intervention with mBM-MSC, mBM-MSC-NC, or mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 compared with that in the ARDS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), but increased α-SMA mRNA was found in the LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 group compared with that in the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a–d).
<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>The effect of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on lung fibrosis in ARDS mice. <bold>a</bold> Lung fibrosis was evaluated by Masson’s trichrome staining at 7 days after LPS exposure (× 200). A blue signal indicated positive staining for collagen, and a red signal represented muscle fibrosis and cellulose. <bold>b</bold> The quantification of lung fibrosis is shown as an Ashcroft score (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group). <bold>c</bold> Collagen I and <bold>d</bold> α-SMA mRNA in lungs was quantified by qRT-PCR (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 at each time-point for each group; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group; <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; <sup>δ</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group). ARDS, acute respiratory distress syndrome; α-SMA, alpha smooth muscle actin; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; NC, normal control</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO9" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Effects of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on the survival of ARDS mice</title><p id="Par87">Mice that received LPS challenge had a significantly decreased survival rate at 7 days compared with that of the control mice (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Although there was no significant difference in the survival rate in the LPS + mBM-MSC, LPS + mBM-MSC-NC, and LPS + mBM-MSC-TGFβ1 groups compared to that in the ARDS group, an upward trend was still found after mMSCs treatment (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>).
<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier survival curves. Mice that received LPS challenge in each group were followed for 7 days after mMSCs administration (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18 for each group, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO10" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_Fig10_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par88">Immunotherapy, one of the important treatments for ARDS, has not made any breakthroughs in the past two decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. A large number of studies have shown that MSCs, multifunctional stem cells with low immunogenicity, could significantly improve the immunity state of ARDS in animal models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The mechanism is due mainly to the paracrine regulation of cell function and state by a variety of cytokines. TGFβ1, as a main paracrine cytokine of MSCs, could regulate the systemic immunity state by modulating the differentiation of T cells in ARDS. In our study, we first constructed mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1, and the main findings were as follows. (1) Overexpressing TGFβ1 inhibited the proliferation of mMSCs during days 5–7 but had no effect on their differentiation or migration. (2) mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 decreased lung permeability and inflammatory cytokine levels and improved the histopathology of lung tissue and in ARDS mice. (3) mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could significantly modulate the differentiation of T cells into Th17 and Treg while inhibiting the ratio of Th17 and Treg. IL-17A content was also decreased while IL-10 content was increased in the lungs of ARDS mice after treatment with mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1. (4) mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 did not aggravate lung fibrosis in ARDS mice.</p><p id="Par89">As an important part of adaptive immunity, T cell immunity is involved in the development of ARDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Several studies have shown that specific regulation of T cell differentiation could improve the immunity and inflammation state of ARDS in animal models, resulting in prognosis improvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. It was also found in our study that the regulation of T cell differentiation in patients with community-acquired pneumonia was directly related to their prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Th17 and Treg, as paired CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell subsets, directly contribute to the prognosis of patients with ARDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. At present, the regulation of Th17 and Treg differentiation depends mainly on antigen-presenting cells, cytokines, and intracellular signalling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, TGFβ1, an important factor regulating T cell differentiation, had very low expression in MSCs. In our study, overexpression of TGFβ1 in mMSCs by lentivirus transduction significantly increased TGFβ1 mRNA and protein levels in the cells, as well as in the supernatant of culture media. However, there was no significant effect on the differentiation and migration of MSCs after transduction. The inhibited migration of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 may be related to the involvement of TGFβ1 in the differentiation of MSCs via cell cycle regulation, which still needs further study.</p><p id="Par90">In this study, the therapeutic effect of MSCs after TGFβ1 transduction was significantly improved, due mainly to the better regulation of T cell differentiation in ARDS mice on day 3 and day 7 and reduced Th17/Treg ratio, thus balancing inflammatory cytokines in vivo. In our previous studies, specific regulation of inflammatory cytokines such as angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) or prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) in MSCs could also improve their therapeutic effects in ARDS animals, which paralleled the results of this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In addition, a recent study also indicated that MSCs could prevent the differentiation of naive CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells into Th17, inhibit the production of inflammatory cytokines by Th17, and induce the Treg phenotype in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. However, in our study, the effect of MSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 on CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells was mainly to increase the amount of Treg without reducing the number of Th17, which may be related to the animal status and detection methods. How to regulate Th17 and Treg differentiation specifically still needs further study in vitro.</p><p id="Par91">TGFβ1 is also an important index of fibrosis and inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Despite this, pulmonary fibrosis in ARDS mice was also detected after MSCs transplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. According to Masson’s staining or specific mRNA expression, MSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 did not significantly increase pulmonary fibrosis in ARDS mice. In addition, our previous study also found that mMSCs could further improve the epithelial injury and pulmonary fibrosis of ARDS mice by increasing differentiation into type II epithelial cells through p130/E2F4 pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], indicating that there might be no side effects related to MSCs transplantation.</p><p id="Par92">This study still has several limitations. First, we induced ARDS by LPS treatment in mice. The murine model of ARDS induced by intratracheal LPS injection focuses only on inflammation in the lungs and cannot fully reflect the complexity of systematic inflammation seen in ARDS patients. Second, MSCs were only administered once intratracheally, and the mice were then sacrificed 3 and 7 days later, which may also not fully reflect the clinical application of such therapeutics; further studies focusing on different routes and doses for MSCs treatment are still needed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par93">MSCs overexpressing TGFβ1 could regulate lung inflammation and attenuate lung injuries by modulating the imbalance of Th17/Treg in the lungs of ARDS mice.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec36"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_MOESM1_ESM.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Supplementary Figure 1.</bold> Flow cytometry identification of mMSCs overexpressing TGFβ1. Cell surface markers of mMSCs, including CD29, CD44, and CD105 were positive. Additionally, CD34 and CD45 of hematopoietic stem cells were negative. Red lines represent the isotype controls. FSC-A, forward scatter height; mMSCs, mouse mesenchymal stem cells; SSC-A, side scatter height.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_MOESM2_ESM.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Supplementary Figure 2.</bold> Pro-inflammatory cytokines concentrations in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid of ARDS mice. A. TNF-α, B. IL-1β and C. IL-6 were analyzed by mouse specific ELISA to evaluate inflammation in lungs of ARDS mice. (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 compared with the Control group; #<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the ARDS group; δ<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 compared with the LPS + mBM-MSC-NC group).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13287_2020_1826_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3.</bold></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACE2</term><def><p id="Par5">Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALB</term><def><p id="Par6">Albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARDS</term><def><p id="Par7">Acute respiratory distress syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BALF</term><def><p id="Par8">Bronchoalveolar lavage fluid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BSD</term><def><p id="Par9">Blasticidin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CCK-8</term><def><p id="Par10">Cell counting kit-8</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDS</term><def><p id="Par11">Coding sequence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMEM/F12</term><def><p id="Par12">Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s media/nutrient mixture F-12</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDTA</term><def><p id="Par13">Trypsin-ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>eGFP</term><def><p id="Par14">Enhanced green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ELISA</term><def><p id="Par15">Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBS</term><def><p id="Par16">Foetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FCM</term><def><p id="Par17">Flow cytometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p id="Par18">Interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LPS</term><def><p id="Par19">Lipopolysaccharide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LWW/BW</term><def><p id="Par20">Lung wet weight/body weight</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mBM-MSCs</term><def><p id="Par21">Mouse bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mBM-MSC-NC</term><def><p id="Par22">Mouse bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells carrying green fluorescent protein (normal control)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mBM-MSC-TGFβ1</term><def><p id="Par23">Mouse bone marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells carrying TGFβ1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mMSCs</term><def><p id="Par24">Mouse mesenchymal stem cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MOI</term><def><p id="Par25">Multiplicity of infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NS</term><def><p id="Par26">Normal saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBS</term><def><p id="Par27">Phosphate-buffered saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PGE2</term><def><p id="Par28">Prostaglandin E2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PVDF</term><def><p id="Par29">Polyvinylidene difluoride</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIPA</term><def><p id="Par30">Radioimmunoprecipitation assay buffer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROIs</term><def><p id="Par31">Regions of interest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par32">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS-PAGE</term><def><p id="Par33">Sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBS</term><def><p id="Par34">Tris-buffered saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBST</term><def><p id="Par35">Tris-buffered saline with Tween-20</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TGFβ1</term><def><p id="Par36">Transforming growth factor β1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Th17</term><def><p id="Par37">T helper 17 cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TP</term><def><p id="Par38">Total protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF-α</term><def><p id="Par39">Tumour necrosis factor-α</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Treg</term><def><p id="Par40">Regulatory T cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WT</term><def><p id="Par41">Wild-type</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s13287-020-01826-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None declared.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>CJX participated in the study design, performed the laboratory work and statistical analysis, prepared the drafts of the manuscript, and revised the manuscript according to advice from the other authors. ZXW and XM participated in the laboratory work, performed the statistical analysis, and drafted the manuscript. XJF participated in the study design and assisted in the statistical analysis. LL and YY participated in the study design and helped to revise the manuscript. QHB were responsible for the study design and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundations of China (No. 81571874, 81930058), the Postgraduate Research &amp; Practice Innovation Program of Jiangsu Province (KYCX17_0168), Jiangsu Provincial Special Program of Medical Science (BE2019749, BE2018743), and National Science and Technology Major Project for Control and Prevention of Major Infectious Diseases of China (2017ZX10103004).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par94">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par95">All the authors have given final approval of the version to be published and have agreed to be accountable for all aspects of this work.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par97">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashbaugh</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute respiratory distress in adults</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><year>1967</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(67)90168-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4143721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenfeld</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peabody</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence and outcomes of acute lung injury</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>1685</fpage><lpage>1693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa050333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffey</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology, patterns of care, and mortality for patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome in intensive care units in 50 countries</article-title><source>JAMA.</source><year>2016</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2016.0291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1608077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28792873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin-Loeches</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Artigas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of severe sepsis: advances, challenges, and current status</article-title><source>Drug Des Devel Ther</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2079</fpage><lpage>2088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DDDT.S78757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4403600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25926718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Th17 cells: positive or negative role in tumor?</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-010-0849-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20352428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11031007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Alessio</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsushima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD4+CD25+Foxp3+ Tregs resolve experimental lung injury in mice and are present in humans with acute lung injury</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2009</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>2898</fpage><lpage>2913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI36498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19770521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2752062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garibaldi</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Alessio</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulatory T cells reduce acute lung injury fibroproliferation by decreasing fibrocyte recruitment</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2012-0198OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23002097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3547087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ratio of Th17/Treg cells as a risk indicator in early acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>Critical care (London)</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-015-0811-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4355972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells overexpressing angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 rescue lipopolysaccharide-induced lung injury</article-title><source>Cell Transplant</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1699</fpage><lpage>1715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3727/096368914X685087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25291359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luz-Crawford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo-Alegria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells generate a CD4+CD25+Foxp3+ regulatory T cell population during the differentiation process of Th1 and Th17 cells</article-title><source>Stem Cell Res Ther</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>65</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/scrt216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23734780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3706898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konkel</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of thymic Foxp3(+) regulatory T cells: TGF-beta matters</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2015</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.201444999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4428761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stable overexpression of p130/E2F4 affects the multipotential abilities of bone-marrow-derived mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>9739</fpage><lpage>9749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.26926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29987913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic modification of mesenchymal stem cells overexpressing angiotensin II type 2 receptor increases cell migration to injured lung in LPS-induced acute lung injury mice</article-title><source>Stem Cells Transl Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sctm.17-0279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30133167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6186265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpressing p130/E2F4 in mesenchymal stem cells facilitates the repair of injured alveolar epithelial cells in LPS-induced ARDS mice</article-title><source>Stem Cell Res Ther</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>74</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-019-1169-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30841904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6404316</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9092810"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endotoxin-induced maturation of monocytes in preterm fetal sheep lung</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>L345</fpage><lpage>L353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00003.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17513458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activation of Wnt/beta-catenin signalling promotes mesenchymal stem cells to repair injured alveolar epithelium induced by lipopolysaccharide in mice</article-title><source>Stem Cell Res Ther</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>65</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-015-0060-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4414385</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC8812256"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannino</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of sepsis in the United States from 1979 through 2000</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>1546</fpage><lpage>1554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa022139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12700374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardenes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romagnoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells: a promising therapy for the acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>Respiration</source><year>2013</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000347072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23428562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moraes-Vieira</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring the role of soluble factors associated with immune regulatory properties of mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>Stem Cell Rev Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12015-011-9311-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lomas-Neira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel role for PD-1:PD-L1 as mediator of pulmonary vascular endothelial cell functions in pathogenesis of indirect ARDS in mice</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3030</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.03030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30619369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6306416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulatory T-cells promote pulmonary repair by modulating T helper cell immune responses in lipopolysaccharide-induced acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>Immunology.</source><year>2019</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imm.13060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30919408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6526643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resolution acute respiratory distress syndrome through reversing the imbalance of Treg/Th17 by targeting the cAMP signaling pathway</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2016.5222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27176453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguee</surname><given-names>SYT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balachander</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lung endothelial cell antigen cross-presentation to CD8(+)T cells drives malaria-associated lung injury</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-12017-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31534124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6751193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early and dynamic alterations of Th2/Th1 in previously immunocompetent patients with community-acquired severe sepsis: a prospective observational study</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-019-1811-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30813927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6391803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PGE2 promotes the migration of mesenchymal stem cells through the activation of FAK and ERK1/2 pathway</article-title><source>Stem Cells Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>2017</volume><fpage>8178643</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28740516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2017/8178643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5504996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devshilt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fennel main constituent, transanethole treatment against LPSinduced acute lung injury by regulation of Th17/Treg function</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29901094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2018.9149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6072219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progressive pulmonary fibrosis is caused by elevated mechanical tension on alveolar stem cells</article-title><source>Cell.</source><year>2020</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31866069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fanelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and modulation of microenvironment is crucial for effective mesenchymal stromal cell therapy in acute lung injury</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>1214</fpage><lpage>1224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201802-0356OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30521764</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>