
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101672560</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7347657</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7347657.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7347657</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7347657</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32671252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04327</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(20)31171-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e04327</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A novel immunosensor for the monitoring of PSA using binding of biotinylated antibody to the prostate specific antigen based on nano-ink modified flexible paper substrate: efficient method for diagnosis of cancer using biosensing technology</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farschi</surname><given-names initials="F">Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saadati</surname><given-names initials="A">Arezoo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names initials="M">Mohammad</given-names></name><email>hasanzadehm@tbzmed.ac.ir</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Pharmaceutical Analysis Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Food and Drug Safety Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Nutrition Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Biotechnology Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Liver and Gastrointestinal Diseases Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Hematology-Oncology Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>hasanzadehm@tbzmed.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Co-First Author and equal contribution.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">360737</issue-id><elocation-id>e04327</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-26 17:25:13.067"><day>26</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Prostate cancer is the most significant reason for deaths in men, outside of lung cancer. The clinical examination of cancer proteins or biomarkers is extremely significant in early examination and monitoring of recurrence of disease after treatment. Biomarkers have expanded great clinical significance owing to their extensive spectra in the identification, elimination, early diagnosis and cure of cancer. In this work, novel, ultrasensitive sandwich-type portable bio device based on citrate-capped silver nanoparticles (Citrate-AgNPs) modified graphene quantum dots (GQDs) nano ink for detection of Prostate specific antigen (PSA) was fabricated. Functionalized cysteamine with gold nanoparticles (Cys-AuNPs) was also utilized to amplify the signal. It provides a good and high external area for the immobilization biotinylated antibody of PSA in the large amount. For the first time, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink was directly written on the cellulose paper surface (ivory sheet and photographic paper) and modified by Cys-AuNPs. So, final structure of the immunodevices was completed after including of Ab1 and PSA (antigen). The immunosensors were used for the recognition of PSA by using DPVs (differential pulse voltammetry) technique. The obtained low limit of quantification (LLOQ) of the first immunodevice (ivory sheet/Citrate AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/CysA-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2) was 0.07 μg/L and the linear range for the calibration plot was from 0.07 to 60 μg/L. Also, the achieved LLOQ of the second immunodevice (photographic paper/Citrate AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2) was 0.05 μg/L with the linear range of 10 to 0.05 μg/L. It is noteworthy that, proposed immunoassay was effectively utilized to the monitoring of PSA glycoprotein in unprocessed human plasma sample. Obtained results show that the constructed immunosensor is able to apply as portable bio device for the clinical analysis of PSA in human plasma samples.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Electrochemistry; Biomedical engineering; Cancer research; Immunology; Nanotechnology; Conductive ink; Affinity binding; Biomedical analysis; Immunodevice; Prostate cancer; Nanostructure</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Electrochemistry</kwd><kwd>Biomedical engineering</kwd><kwd>Cancer research</kwd><kwd>Immunology</kwd><kwd>Nanotechnology</kwd><kwd>Conductive ink</kwd><kwd>Affinity binding</kwd><kwd>Biomedical analysis</kwd><kwd>Immunodevice</kwd><kwd>Prostate cancer</kwd><kwd>Nanostructure</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Cancer is one of the most community reason for death in the world, surpassed by heart disease and accounts for about 1 in 4 deaths. Therefore, easy and early-stage detection of cancer is particularly important [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Prostate cancer is the most significant reason for deaths in men, outside of lung cancer. The clinical examination of cancer proteins or biomarkers is extremely significant in early examination and monitoring of recurrence of disease after treatment [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In addition to during prognosis, biomarkers usually increased a lot of clinical importance because of their extensive spectra in the identification, elimination, early diagnosis and cure of cancer. For early treatment of cancer, biomarkers play an essential role during analysis for grading and staging of cancer and tumors [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Prostate specific antigen (PSA) is one of the semen mutual proteins, and it could be transferred to the stream of blood. PSA is a significant biomarker for detection of prostate cancer and it can use for identification, the follow up to treatment, and recurrence examination after cessation of treatment [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Prostatic dysfunction in peoples with prostate cancer makes the PSA concentration in the blood to significantly increased [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Commonly, the PSA standard range is 4.0 ng mL<sup>−1</sup> and the unusual range is 4–10 ng.mL<sup>−1</sup> in human blood. So, for prostate cancer diagnosis the detection of PSA is necessary [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">So far, several conventional techniques were reported for diagnosis of prostate cancer. For example, fluorescence-based immunoassay, radioimmunoassay and ELISA (enzyme linked immunosorbent assay) [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] was used for this purpose. But these methods were time consuming, sophisticated, necessitate expert operator [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p id="p0020">Biosensors as diagnostic devices are highly specific, affordable, quick, and transportable with great performance. These bio-devices can be used in various areas such as medicine, environmental monitoring, farming and food production [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Lately, immunoassays which are significant kind of biosensors have been utilized as a specific device for calculating of biomarkers [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Nowadays, electrochemical immunosensors because of their unique features such as sensitive, rapid and selectivity in analysis have attracted attention. Furthermore, electrochemical biosensors with the sandwich structure are more sensitive and elective, and the most appropriate type of immunosensors to biomarkers discovery [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">Ordinarily immunosensors applied in many areas because they are so sensitive. But those biosensors need different stages of preparation, accomplished technicians and expensive apparatus [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. To solve this problem, paper-based immunoassays have been developed and considered by many researchers [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Paper is one of the best and useful materials because it has great features such as easy manipulation, tools-free, reusable and it is cheap and also it has nice capability to permit liquid substances through its hydrophilic platform without using external power. So it is used as an important factor in the preparation of paper-based immunosensor [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Paper can use as a large and low-cost matrix for the reagents immobilization and its reaction because the paper has a fibrous porous form can direct aqueous liquid streams by capillary force and supplies a wide surface for immobilization of reagents and a big area for reactions of reagents [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p id="p0030">Newly, designing conductive models on paper has used as affordable and easy technique for sketching paper-based sensors [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. So this technique helps to have low-cost and rapid screening to designing the customized electrodes. Hence paper-based sensors are a nice alternatives to usual electrochemical biosensors [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Because of the health centers requisiteness such as clinical laboratories and medical research centers for the early-stage discovery of the prostate cancer, and there is essential necessity for these new kinds of biosensors based on nano-inks which have an important role in the efficient performance of the electrochemical immunosensors for quick and easy detection of cancers [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="p0035">In this study, we reported a first unique paper-based sandwich kind of electrochemical immunoassay based on Citrate- AgNPs-GQDs conductive nano ink for measuring the prostate cancer biomarker (PSA) in the early stages of the disease. For this purpose, ink synthesized and employed to prepare a new platform on the cellulose paper surface to develop sandwich immunoassay. Also, Cys-AuNPs was utilized to amplify the signal on the immune-device structure. Cys is bonded to the AuNPs via sulfur group, and from the –NH<sub>2</sub> (amine) group with –OH (hydroxyl) and –COOH (carboxyl) functional groups of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs ink which electrodeposited on the paper surface (citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-AuNPs). Then, primary antibodies (Biotinilated-Ab1) was immobilized on the modified paper surface via gold NPs and PSA absolutely charged interaction of –NH<sub>2</sub> groups. Besides that, HRP-Ab2 immobilized on the prepared paper-electrode surface as a secondary Ab. The electrochemical response of the designed immunosensor was investigated by ChA (Chronoamperometry) and DPV (differential pulse voltammetry) methods. The analysis revealed ultrasensitive performance to PSA detection in real specimens (human plasma). This electrochemical immunodevice illustrated excellent sensitivity and has the great potential to be used for timely detection of prostate biomarker in clinical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Methods and materials</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Chemicals</title><p id="p0040">Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), sodium citrate, Chloroauric acid (HAuCl<sub>4</sub>), <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Hydroxysuccinimide (NHS), EDC (1-Ethyl-3-(3-dimethylaminopropyl) carbodiimide), sodium hydrogen phosphate, BSA (bovine serum albumin), NaOH (sodium hydroxide), Cys (Cysteamine), EG (ethylene glycol), potassium Ferricyanide K<sub>3</sub>Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>, potassium Ferrocyanide K<sub>4</sub>Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>, AgNO<sub>3</sub>, potassium dihydrogen orthophosphate, potassium chloride (KCl) and ethanol were obtained from Sigma Aldrich (Ontario, Canada). Phosphate-buffered saline saline solution was provided by dissolving NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (0.2M) and Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (0.2M) in DW (deionized water). Human PSA ELISA kit (CanAg/PSA EIA) including PSA antigen, biotinylated antibody, HRP Labeled anti-prostate cancer biomarker, and standard buffer were obtained from Can Ag Diagonestic AB Technology Co, (Gutenberg, Sweden). Human plasma specimen were taken from the IBTRC (Iranian Blood Transfusion Research Center) (Tabriz, Iran).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Equipment</title><p id="p0045">Electrochemical measurements were accomplished with a PalmSens 4c system. This system was used on laptop by PSTrace software. For ChA measurements equilibrium time was 2 s and the voltage amplitude was 10 mV. Paper electrodes which designed by Citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink was used as a working electrode, a reference electrode and a counter electrode.</p><p id="p0050">It should be noted that, Citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink was synthesized and prepared by ourselves high-resolution field emission scanning electron microscope (FE-SEM), Hitachi SU8020, Czech was employed for studying the morphology of electrode surface, and energy dispersive spectroscopy (EDS) was employed for analysis of the chemical compounds which created on the surface of the electrode. For studying of synthesis mechanism, transmission electron microscopy (TEM), Adelaide, Australia was employed. Size frequency and zeta potential of Citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink was studied by DLS (dynamic light scattering) with zeta potential instrument Malvern Instruments Ltd (Zetasizer Ver. 7.11, MAL1032660, England). For measuring the electrical resistance of nano-ink estimate, Ohmmeter, XIOLE, XL830L, China, multi-meter employed. Falling ball viscometer (Anton Paar-AMVn, Germany) was utilized to measure the viscosity of nano-ink. The surface tension of the synthesized ink was evaluated using a contact angle optical measuring device (Data physics-OCA20, Germany).</p><p id="p0055">This project was approved by regional ethics committees; IR.TBZMED.VCR.REC.1399.050.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Cys-AuNPs synthesis</title><p id="p0060">At the first step, 50 mL of HAuCl<sub>4</sub> (0.5 mM) was stirred magnetically under reflux states and heated until 100 °C. Then, 5 mL of Na<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub> (38.8 mM) solution was added to the HAuCl<sub>4</sub> solution. By mixing the Trisodium citrate (Na<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub>) (0.5 M) solution and HAuCl<sub>4</sub> the color of solution was changed from yellow to wine red. Magnetic stirring of blend was also continued till wine red color was stable. The solution was cooled at room temperature and it is stable at 4 °C up to 60 days. For preparing the Cys and AuNPs solution (100:1 v:v) was stirred with continually addition of Cys for functionalizing citrate -Au NPs with Cys A. The final color of Cys A-Au NPs solution is deep-red color.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Synthesis and conductivity study of ink</title><sec id="sec2.4.1"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Synthesis of Citrate-AgNPs</title><p id="p0065">At the first step, an ice water bath (around 0 °C) was prepared. Next, 400 mL of Na<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub> (1.06 mM) solution was completely mixed with 25 mL of AgNO<sub>3</sub> (5 Mm) solution and it was placed in the ice water bath and stirred. Then, 2500 μL of a recently prepared aqueous solution of NaBH<sub>4</sub> (100 mM) was added drop-wise to it during 5 min. The solution color changes from colorless to light yellow. Then the solution was stirred under dark conditions for about 105 min until a shiny yellow hue becomes visible. The synthesized solution was further centrifuged at 6000 rpm for 15 min at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.2"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Synthesis of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink</title><p id="p0070">GQDs was synthesized as stated by our earlier works [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For preparing the nano ink, 0.013 g of chitosan was dissolved in acetic acid 0.1 M for about 30 min then 0.6 of GO (graphene oxide) and PVP (0.2 g) was added in compound and it was stirred magnetically till completely dissolved.</p><p id="p0075">Next, GQDs (2 ml) and 600 μL of citrate-AgNPs solution was mixed with above solution. To assure effective blending of graphene oxide and Ag+, magnetically stirring was continued for about 20 min. Later, the prepared solution was permanently placed in the incubator for 12 h at 60 °C. After 12 h, the solution was magnetically stirred again and heated at 80 °C. At the end, 500 μL of NaOH (sodium hydroxide) (8 M) solution was added drop by drop for increasing reduction permeation. The solution was centrifuged at 8000 rpm for 30 min and washed 3 times with distilled water (DW) to remove extra reactant. For preparing hybrid conductive ink, the obtained citrate AgNPs-GQD nano ink were dispersed into ethanol, DW, and EG (9:9:3) and sonicated for 30 min so the achieved ink was water-based.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.3"><label>2.4.3</label><title>Conductivity study of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nanoink</title><p id="p0080">For this purpose, several conductive patterns of citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink drawn on the photographic papers surface using pellet with various thicknesses. As revealed in Fig. S1 (see supporting information), diverse kind of conductive lines was drawn on the surface of paper and a LED lamp (3.0 V) with a battery (3.0 v and for spiral conductive lines 15.0 V battery was used) was fabricated on paper substrate. One side of LED lamp (cathode) was connected to battery anode and so cathode surface of battery fixed to one side of conductive line. Whenever the anode side of LED connected to other side of conductive line, the electrical circuit worked and the LED lamp was lighted up. Then, the resistor of conductive lines was measured by ohmmeter (Please see all media file as supporting information).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Characterizations</title><sec id="sec3.1.1"><label>3.1.1</label><title>Characterization of citrate-AgNPs</title><p id="p0085">The size and morphology of the citrate-AgNPs were investigated through TEM imaging. Particles were either spherical or irregular in shape, and also we prepared FE-SEM (field emission scanning electron microscopy) and EDC. The results are shown in Figs. S2–S4 (see supporting information).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2"><label>3.1.2</label><title>Characterization of bulk citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs and citrate- AgNPs-GQDs/Cys-AuNPs prepared on the photographic paper-based electrode</title><p id="p0090">To evaluate the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink synthesis mechanism and confirm the binding of Citrate and Ag NPs on to graphite sheets, TEM images were recorded. It was clearly showed that the many dispersed spherical silver nanoparticles were decorated on the surface of graphite sheets. Fig. S5 (see supporting information), displays the FE-SEM images of bulk citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink constructed on photographic paper and Cys/Au NP modified citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink constructed on photographic paper to evaluate the morphology of the electrodes surface. Accordingly, in the bulk citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink, the small-sized silver nanoparticles with the spherical uniform structure were located on the surface of graphite sheets. It is noteworthy that citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink solved in ethanol/water/EG shows no nanoparticles aggregation.</p><p id="p0095">For measuring the concentration of silver nanoparticles in the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink, ICP (inductively coupled plasma) technique was used to the measurement of silver nanoparticles in the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink which obtained as 0.33 mg/L (Fig. S6 (see supporting information)).</p><p id="p0100">Viscosity of the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink was measured by the falling ball method is 7.64Cp, and also the density of the mentioned nano-ink is 1.07 g/cc.</p><p id="p0105">The surface tension using contact angle optical measuring device and obtained as 35.52 n M/m. The XRD determine the crystalline phase and phase purity of the particles.</p><p id="p0110">Raman spectroscopy is an important tool for structural characterization and chemical/biosensing. So, we developed this technique to investigate the role of GQDs in the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink (Fig. S7 (see supporting information)).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3"><label>3.1.3</label><title>Characterization of various steps of prepared immunosensor</title><p id="p0115">Surface morphology of the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink and citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink modified using Cys-AuNPs were characterized by FE-SEM. Fig. S8 (A-Q) (see supporting information) reveals the scanning electron micrographs of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 deposited on the surface of paper electrode, respectively. Citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink has a bumpy surface because of irregular graphite plates in its groundwork.</p><p id="p0120">Fig. S8(F–H) (see supporting information) obviously show that the photographic paper/citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink morphology changed after the electrodeposition of Cys-AuNPs.</p><p id="p0125">The covered layer affords a high surface area, which allows more antibodies to be placed on the surface. In the presence of antibody, diverse morphology was extended on the electrode surface.</p><p id="p0130">Also, the surface roughness of the electrode was increased after binding the antibody to the polymer (Fig. S9 (see supporting information)). Lastly, after PSA (antigen) and Ab2 (HRP-PSA antibody) immobilization, the electrode morphology was changed. It shows that preparation of immune complex between the antibody (Ab1) and antigen was successfully. Similar protocol was used for the immobilization of inks on the surface of ivory sheets.</p><p id="p0135">The comparable EDS spectra of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink written on the paper surface and Cys-AuNPs electrodeposited on the surface of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/photo graphic paper are shown in Fig. S9 (see supporting information). The sharp and great Ag and C peaks were the regular signal for the graphite and Ag in the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink, signals of S and N were depended to Cys, whereas signals of N, C and O elements were depended to both GQDs and Cys. Also, it shows that in the case of citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-AuNPs the S element overlapped with gold.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Assembly of electrochemical immunodevice</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/CysA-Au NPs paper-based electrode production</title><p id="p0140">Initially, to make paper-based electrode (PBE), conductive lines were immediately drawn on the surface of the ivory sheet and photographic paper by citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink and allowed to dry at room temperature for 5min using pen-on-paper technology. So, in order to electrodeposition of Cys-Au NPs on the surface of citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink paper based electrode, the prepared electrode dipped into Cys-Au NPs solution and electrodeposition was carried out by ChA technique (duration time = 500 s, E = 0.8 V) which leads to the bonding of the amine groups of Cys-Au NP with carboxyl groups of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink PBE (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Afterward, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs paper-based electrode was washed with double distilled water in order to remove unbound particles then placed at room temperature to dry (25 °C).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Single steps chronoamperograms for the electrodeposition of Cys/Au NP on the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink paper-based electrode surface; photographic paper (A) and ivory sheet (B). E = 0.0V vs. and the duration time was 500s.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Immunodevice fabrication</title><p id="p0145">In order to the preparation of sandwich type immunoassay, for activation of the –COOH groups of antibodies, 10 μL of biotinylated antibody (anti PSA) was mixed with NHS/EDC and incubated for 30 min at 25 °C.</p><p id="p0150">Then, 10 μL of activated antibody with NHS/EDC was drop-casted onto the sensing area of prepared paper-based electrode (3 × 2 mm<sup>2</sup>) and incubated at 25 °C for 30 min. BSA (0.1M) was used for blocking the non-specific active sites. For this purpose, BSA solution (3%) was added on the surface of prepared electrodes and putted at 4 °C for 30 min to minimize the non-specific binding sites. After 30 min, to detect the PSA biomarker, PSA antigen (10 μL) were dropped onto sensing area of the prepared sensor and incubated for 30 min at 4 °C.</p><p id="p0155">Consequently, 5μL of HRP-anti PSA solution (Ab2) was immobilized onto sensing area of engineered sensor for extra 30 min. Finally, the electrochemical behavior of the sandwich type immunoassay was evaluated by DPV technique. It is noteworthy that after all incubation steps, the surface of the sensors was washed in standard buffer solution. <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="fig">Scheme 1</xref> shows all of the preparation steps for the PSA immunodevice.<fig id="sch1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption><p>Construction of paper based sandwich type immunosensor for the PSA biomarker detection.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Scheme 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="sc1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Electrochemical performance of immunodevice</title><p id="p0160">The preparation steps of immunodevice were studied by recording DPV (different pulse voltammetry) methods in the presence of [Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub>]<sup>3-/4-</sup> solution as electrochemical probe. Different kinds of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink modified PBE (citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2) were evaluated on the ivory sheet and photo graphic paper surface for their electrochemical behavior in the 0.01M Ferricyanide (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>DPVs of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/AuNP-CysA, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/AuNPs-CysA/Ab, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/AuNPs-CysA/Ab1/BSA, citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/AuNPs-CysA/Ab1/BSA/PSA and citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/AuNPs-CysA/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 on the surface of photographic papers(A) and ivory sheets(B). (C) Histogram of peak current in diverse steps of electrode fabrication on the photographic paper and ivory sheet surface (D), Supporting electrolyte is 0.01M ferricyanide.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0165">Au NPs were functionalized with Cys. They bonded covalently with the sulfur group of Cys, therefor AuNPs-Cys were more convenient for use in the immunosensors [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Also, Cys-Au NPs provide free amine group for interplay with a –COOH (carboxylic) group of Fc region of the antibody by covalent bond [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and, they provide an appropriate condition for the immobilization of Ab against intended purpose analyte such as PSA biomarker. To find this out, the DPVs of the ivory sheet/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 electrode were shown in the <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> (B and D) and it indicated that Cys/Au NPs increased the signal intensity.</p><p id="p0170">Eventually, the biotinylated PSA antibody was immobilized on the citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs electrode surface which lead to extra visibility of the peak with weak current because of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs interaction with Ab. A notable decrease in peak current was seen after immobilization of PSA antigen on the electrode surface, which shows that PSA has been favorably bonded to Ab1 on the surface of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NP/Ab1 paper-based electrode. At the last stage after immobilization of HRP-Anti PSA (Ab2), the peak current was decrease owing to obstructed the effect of electron transfer. On the other hand, the Abs perform as an insulator and decrease the rate of electron transfer.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Analytical performance</title><p id="p0175">According to the obtained results on the previous action, proposed immune device is able to use for determination of PSA in different concentrations. Therefore, DPVs of immunosensor in the presence of 0.01 M Ferricyanide/Ferrocyanide and different concentration of PSA were recorded.</p><p id="p0180">For this purpose, citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 was incubated in various concentrations of PSA antigen to electrochemical analysis of PSA. The immunoassays were washed completely with 0.1% Tween-PBS (pH 7.4) before electrochemical evaluations, to remove antigens which were not interaction with antibody. The DPVs of photographic paper/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 and ivory sheet/citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 were obtained and calibration diagrams were plotted (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>DPVs of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Au NPs- CysA/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 for study of various concentrations of PSA Ag (60–0.07 μg/L) in supporting electrolyte is 0.01M ferricyanide on the surface of ivory sheet papers(A) and photographic paper(B) Calibration plots of the citrate- AgNPs/GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NP/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 on the surface of ivory sheet papers(C) and photographic paper(D).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0185">The calibration curve was achieved by drawing the peak current against the Neperian logarithm of PSA Ag concentration.</p><p id="p0190">The detection ranges of photographic paper/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 was found between 0.05 to 10 μg/L. The lower limits of quantitation (LLOQ) was obtained to be 0.05 μg/L and the detection ranges of ivory sheet/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 was found as 0.07–60 μg/L. The LLOQ was obtained to be 0.07 μg/L.</p><p id="p0195">The comparison of engineered immunodevice with other biosensors for PSA detection were shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Based on the obtained results, it can be said that the constructed immune-device has very nice performance for the detection of PSA in human bio fluids. Also, suggested immunosensors are portable, low-cost and simple. Among the electrochemical methods, the DPV technique is the most sensitive method. Comparison of the obtained results by proposed immunosensor with previous reports, show that this biosensor is simple sensitive than others. Compared with other immunosensors reported by analytical studies (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], the developed immunosensor showed better analytical performance in view of the linear range and the limit of detection. Efficient function of this sensor can be due to unique structure and unique electrical behavior of AgNPs, which lead to sensing of PSA in μg/ml concentration. Also, high surface area of interface (citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs) for dense loading of Ab1 local to excellent sensitivity of the engineered immunedevice.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>A comparison of the achievement of diverse immunodevices for PSA identification.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Detection method</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Used materials</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Detection Range</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">LOD</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cantilever</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Antigen-Antibody reaction</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2–60 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 mg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electrochemical (CV)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Graphene (GR)-based gold (Au) composite</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–10 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electrochemical (DPV)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SiO<sub>2</sub>- AgNPs/Ab/BSA/Ag</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03–0.001 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amperometric</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single-walled carbon nanotubes (SWNTs</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5–5 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Surface Plasmon Resonance</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sandwich assay</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29–2.3 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amperometric</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peptide nanotube/AuNPs/PANI modified electrode. Sandwich assay. HRP as label.</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–100 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Capillary-based</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pt@AuNPs Sandwich assay</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02–2.5 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.044 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chemiluminescence</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gold nanoparticles (AuNPs).</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08–5 ng/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 × 10<sup>−13</sup> g/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">[<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Electrochemical (DPV)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ivory sheet/citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/CysA-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07–60 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">This work</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">photographic paper/citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/CysA-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–10 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05 μg/cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0200">It is important to point out that, beside investigated research work for detection of prostate cancer based on PSA biomarker analysis, there is some of other reports [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] which are most efficient methods in this research are.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Real sample analysis</title><p id="p0205">As previously mentioned, it was probable to use constructed immune device to the quantitative analysis of PSA biomarker in the human plasma samples using DPV technique (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). In this way, 10 μL of unprocessed human plasma were blended with 10 μL of various concentrations of PSA and casted on to the sensing zone of electrode. In optimum states, the calibration curve was achieved by plotting the peak current versus the concentration of PSA. Using DPV technique, dynamic range and LLOQ of the first immunosensor (ivory sheet/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-AuNPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2) were 0.07–10 μg/L and 0.07 μg/L, respectively. Also, dynamic range of the second immunodevice (photographic paper/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2) was obtained as 0.001–10 μg/L with LLOQ of 0.001 μg/L.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>DPVs of citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 for analysis of different concentrations of PSA Ag in human plasma specimens on the surface of ivory sheets (A)and photographic papers(B). Supporting electrolyte is 0.01M ferricyanide. Calibration curves of concentration effect on the surface of ivory sheets (C) and photographic papers (D).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Selectivity of immunodevice</title><p id="p0210">For control experiments, some interferential proteins such as CA 15.3, CEA, CA125 and BSA in real human samples were investigated by DPV technique in 0.01M Ferricyanide/Ferrocyanide to evaluate the selectivity of the immune device as serum proteins.</p><p id="p0215"><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> shows that, the current signals of the prepared immunodevice were compared with the current signal achieved in 5-fold excess of different interfering species solution.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>DPVs of the designed immunosensor in the presence of a serum protein (BSA, CA15.3, CA125, CEA) on the surface of ivory sheet (A) and photographic paper (B). Histogram of peak potential (E) and currents versus time of interfering species (C-D).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0220">The peak current produced by ivory sheet/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 is very similar and higher concentrations of interfering proteins did not make any considerable increase in peak (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5 A-</xref>C). On the other hand, <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> (B and D) show the current signals of the photographic paper/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs/Ab1/BSA/PSA/Ab2 are changed. Suggesting immunodevice fabricated on the photographic paper has the acceptable selectivity for identification of PSA in the presence of some interfering proteins.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Stability and reproducibility of the substrate and immunedevice</title><p id="p0225">Stability is one of the important factors for the evaluation of biosensor performance and the reusability of biosensor is very remarkable. To evaluation the stability of photo graphic paper/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano-ink/Cys-Au NPs, CVs were recorded after 2, 5, 10, 50 and 100 cycles in 0.01M Ferricyanide/Ferrocyanide as mediator solution. <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> (A and C). Based on the obtained results, there is no change in the redox peak currents which confirm good stability of the substrate (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>B). Therefore, this substrate is suitable for the immobilization of biomolecule and construction of immunodevice. Also, for the evaluation of ivory sheet/citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink/Cys-Au NPs stability, CVs were recorded after 1, 11, 21, 41 and 101 cycles in 0.01M Fe (CN<sub>6</sub>) <sup>3-/4-</sup> as mediator solution. As can be seen, after 100 cycles the prepared electrode has not an acceptable performance.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Cyclic voltammograms and histograms of engineered immunosensor stability on the surface of ivory sheet(A) and photographic paper(B) study in potential range of -1 to +1 and scan rate of 100 mV/s in 0.01M ferricyanide C) Histogram of engineered immunosensor on the surface of ivory sheets (C) and photographic paper(D).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Figure 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0230">In this work, a novel paper based immunosensor based on citrate-AgNPs-GQDs nano ink for sensitive detection of PSA tumor biomarker was developed. In this way, easy handwriting technique using electro-conductive nanocomposite was employed to design electrodes on paper. Cys-Au NPs were used as signal amplification element and they covalently bonded to citrate- AgNPs-GQDs nano ink on the surface of the ivory sheet and photographic paper and used to immobilization of PSA-Ab. Therefore, an ultrasensitive and innovative sandwich-type paper based immunodevice was successfully created on the surface of ivory sheet and photographic paper. In optimal conditions, the immunodevice, on the surface of photographic paper presents a highly linear range from 0.05 to 10 μg/L with LLOQ of 0.05 μg/L. Also, the dynamic range of immunedevice on the surface of ivory sheet was found as 0.07–60 μg/L. The low limit of quantitation (LLOQ) was determined to be 0.07 μg/L. All these observations show that, this immunedevice can be employed as an adaptable platform for detection other biomarkers and has excellent potential in clinical diagnoses and bioanalysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0235">Fatemeh Farschi, Arezoo Saadati: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0240">Mohammad Hasanzadeh: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0245">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004366</institution-id><institution>Tabriz University of Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0250">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0255">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>e. World Cancer Report 2014</chapter-title><year>2014</year><publisher-name>International Agency for Research on Cancer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc><comment>IARC Publications Website:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://publications.iarc.fr/Non-Series" id="intref0015">http://publications.iarc.fr/Non-Series</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partin</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination of prostate-specific antigen, clinical stage, and Gleason score to predict pathological stage of localized prostate cancer: a multi-institutional update</article-title><source>Jama</source><volume>277</volume><issue>18</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>1445</fpage><lpage>1451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9145716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farshchi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtarzadeh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel electroconductive interface based on Fe3O4 magnetic nanoparticle and cysteamine functionalized AuNPs: preparation and application as signal amplification element to minoring of antigen-antibody immunocomplex and biosensing of prostate cancer</article-title><source>J. Mol. Recogn.</source><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2825</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jmr.2825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31828877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikkaveeraiah</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrochemical immunosensors for detection of cancer protein biomarkers</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>6546</fpage><lpage>6561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22835068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/nn3023969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3429657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maginnity</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-paper sensing apparatus</article-title><source>Google Pat.</source><year>1998</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilja</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulmert</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostate-specific antigen and prostate cancer: prediction, detection and monitoring</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Canc.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc2351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suaifan</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent progress in prostate-specific antigen and HIV proteases detection</article-title><source>Expert Rev. Mol. Diagn.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24063398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1586/14737159.2013.835576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armbruster</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostate-specific antigen: biochemistry, analytical methods, and clinical application</article-title><source>Clin. Chem.</source><volume>39</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1993</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7679336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Etzioni</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the role of PSA screening in the US prostate cancer mortality decline</article-title><source>Canc. Causes Contr.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10552-007-9083-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3064270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18027095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavosi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A highly sensitive prostate-specific antigen immunosensor based on gold nanoparticles/PAMAM dendrimer loaded on MWCNTS/chitosan/ionic liquid nanocomposite</article-title><source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24016535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bios.2013.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasensitive bioassay of epitope of Mucin-16 protein (CA 125) in human plasma samples using a novel immunoassay based on silver conductive nano-ink: a new platform in early stage diagnosis of ovarian cancer and efficient management</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30615961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.01.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feyziazar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An innovative method to electrochemical branching of chitosan in the presence of copper nanocubics on the surface of glassy carbon and its electrical behaviour study: a new platform for pharmaceutical analysis using electrochemical sensors</article-title><source>React. Funct. Polym.</source><year>2019</year><fpage>104402</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrochemical immunosensors for food analysis: a review of recent developments</article-title><source>Anal. Lett.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasensitive immunoassay of tumor protein CA 15.3 in MCF-7 breast cancer cell lysates and unprocessed human plasma using gold nanoparticles doped on the structure of mesoporous silica</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><volume>120</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2493</fpage><lpage>2508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30195002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.09.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzu-Nascimento</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and statistical assessment of a paper-based immunoassay for detection of tumor markers</article-title><source>Anal. Chim. Acta</source><volume>950</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27916120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aca.2016.11.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahavarnia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paper based immunosensing of ovarian cancer tumor protein CA 125 using novel nano-ink: a new platform for efficient diagnosis of cancer and biomedical analysis using microfluidic paper-based analytical devices (μPAD)</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><volume>138</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31326512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.07.109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballerini</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A perspective on paper-based microfluidics: current status and future trends</article-title><source>Biomicrofluidics</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">011301</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1063/1.3687398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3365319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22662067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanpour</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel paper based immunoassay of breast cancer specific carbohydrate (CA 15.3) using silver nanoparticles-reduced graphene oxide nano-ink technology: a new platform to construction of microfluidic paper-based analytical devices (μPADs) towards biomedical analysis</article-title><source>Microchem. J.</source><volume>146</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>358</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alatraktchi</surname><given-names>F.A.a.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Based sensors for rapid detection of virulence factor produced by Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0194157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5863975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29566025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemzadeh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graphene quantum dot modified glassy carbon electrode for the determination of doxorubicin hydrochloride in human plasma</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Anal.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jpha.2016.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5762600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadjou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marandi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graphene quantum dot functionalized by chitosan and beta-cyclodextrin as a new support nanocomposite material for efficient methanol electrooxidation</article-title><source>J. Alloys Compd.</source><volume>688</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadjou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graphene quantum dot functionalized by chitosan as an electrically conductive nano-material toward low potential detection: a new platform for interface science</article-title><source>J. Mater. Sci. Mater. Electron.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>11834</fpage><lpage>11843</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadzinsky</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of a thiol monolayer-protected gold nanoparticle at 1.1 Å resolution</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>318</volume><issue>5849</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1148624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gold nanoparticles are taken up by human cells but do not cause acute cytotoxicity</article-title><source>Small</source><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17193451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/smll.200400093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioassay of prostate-specific antigen (PSA) using microcantilevers</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11533645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt0901-856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D label-free prostate specific antigen (PSA) immunosensor based on graphene–gold composites</article-title><source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source><volume>63</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25150936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bios.2014.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farshchi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solhi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunosensing of prostate cancer in human plasma samples using immobilization of antibody on the surface of mesoporous silica-modified silver nanoparticles and its immunocomplex with prostate-specific antigen</article-title><source>Anal. Methods</source><volume>11</volume><issue>48</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>6159</fpage><lpage>6167</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maehashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasensitive detection of DNA hybridization using carbon nanotube field-effect transistors</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Appl. Phys.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>12A</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>L1558</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uludag</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tothill</surname><given-names>I.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer biomarker detection in serum samples using surface plasmon resonance and quartz crystal microbalance sensors with nanoparticle signal amplification</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><volume>84</volume><issue>14</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>5898</fpage><lpage>5904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22681722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ac300278p</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vural</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrochemical immunoassay for detection of prostate specific antigen based on peptide nanotube-gold nanoparticle-polyaniline immobilized pencil graphite electrode</article-title><source>J. Colloid Interface Sci.</source><volume>510</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28957748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcis.2017.09.079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pt@AuNPs integrated quantitative capillary-based biosensors for point-of-care testing application</article-title><source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source><volume>85</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27240013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bios.2016.05.074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrogenerated chemiluminescence peptide-based biosensor for the determination of prostate-specific antigen based on target-induced cleavage of peptide</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><volume>86</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1372</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24437695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ac402991r</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Xiuli.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly sensitive detection of prostate cancer specific PCA3 mimic DNA using SERS-based competitive lateral flow assay</article-title><source>Nanoscale</source><volume>11</volume><issue>33</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>15530</fpage><lpage>15536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31393497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c9nr04864b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Yunyun.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multicolor and photothermal dual-readout biosensor for visual detection of prostate specific antigen</article-title><source>Biosens. Bioelectron.</source><volume>140</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bios.2019.111345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silver nanoparticles deposited on graphene oxide for ultrasensitive surface-enhanced Raman scattering immunoassay of cancer biomarker</article-title><source>Nanoscale</source><volume>10</volume><issue>25</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>11942</fpage><lpage>11947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29901677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c8nr02820f</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Xiange</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rotational paper-based electrochemiluminescence immunodevices for sensitive and multiplexed detection of cancer biomarkers</article-title><source>Anal. Chim. Acta</source><volume>1007</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29405986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aca.2017.12.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Ziyi</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous detection of dual prostate specific antigens using surface-enhanced Raman scattering-based immunoassay for accurate diagnosis of prostate cancer</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>4926</fpage><lpage>4933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28441008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acsnano.7b01536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Xiuli</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical nanoprobes for ultrasensitive immunoassay</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28105817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.analchem.6b02251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yingcong</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sandwich-type ECL immunosensor based on signal amplification using a ZnO nanorods-L-cysteine-luminol nanocomposite for ultrasensitive detection of prostate specific antigen</article-title><source>Anal. Chim. Acta</source><volume>1109</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32252911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aca.2020.02.056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hui-Min</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of efficient “on-off-on” fluorescence aptasensor for ultrasensitive detection of prostate specific antigen via covalent energy transfer between g-C3N4 quantum dots and palladium triangular plates</article-title><source>Anal. Chim. Acta</source><volume>1104</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32106957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aca.2020.01.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Dandan</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of highly sensitive Pt nanoparticles-carbon quantum dots/ionic liquid functionalized graphene oxide nanocomposites and application for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detection</article-title><source>Sensor. Actuator. B Chem.</source><volume>255</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1500</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0265">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supp. Info</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>Supp. Info</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc3.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>3</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc4.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>3</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>4</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc5.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>4</alt-text></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>5</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc6.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"><alt-text>5</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></back></article>