
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101672560</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7895722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7895722.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7895722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7895722</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33644474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(21)00310-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e06205</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Dobera glabra</italic> (Forssk.) Poir. (<italic toggle="yes">Salvadoraceae</italic>); phenolic constituents of the aqueous leaves extract and evaluation of its anti-inflammatory, analgesic activities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emam</surname><given-names initials="M">Mahmoud</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names initials="PE">Passant E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhateeb</surname><given-names initials="A">Ahmed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names initials="SR">Sameh R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names initials="MM">Mona M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Rahman</surname><given-names initials="SS">Sahar S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hameed</surname><given-names initials="ESS">El-Sayed S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names initials="RF">Rehab F.</given-names></name><email>rehabs2001@yahoo.com</email><email>rf.abdelrahman@nrc.sci.eg</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Pharmaceutical Science &amp; Collaborative Innovation Center of Yangtze River Delta Region Green Pharmaceuticals, Zhejiang University of Technology, Hangzhou 310014, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Phytochemistry and Plant Systematics, National Research Centre, 33 El Bohouth St., Dokki, Giza P. O. 12622, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Pharmacology, Medical Research Division, National Research Centre, Giza, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Pathology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Cairo University, Giza, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry, Theodor Bilharz Research Institute, Giza, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>rehabs2001@yahoo.com</email><email>rf.abdelrahman@nrc.sci.eg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374569</issue-id><elocation-id>e06205</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-11 13:25:15.120"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="9" journal-id="Heliyon" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10722317"><article-title>Retraction notice to “Dobera glabra (Forssk.) Poir. (Salvadoraceae); Phenolic constituents of the aqueous leaves extract and evaluation of its anti-inflammatory, analgesic activities” [Heliyon <bold>7</bold> (2021) e06205]<sup/><sup/></article-title><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><date><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>e22367</elocation-id><source>Heliyon</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e22367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10722317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38106672</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The plant kingdom is considered one of the most common sources for structural and biological diversity. In particular, the wild category acquires our attention to investigate the phytochemical and the biological evaluations.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Dobera glabra</italic> was exposed to phytochemical examination using HPLC-ESI-MS analysis. Furthermore, the anti-inflammatory activity was evaluated using carrageenan-induced rat paw edema model, whereas both the central and peripheral analgesic activities were tested via hot plate test in rats and acetic acid-induced writhing in mice, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Twenty phenolic compounds of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> aqueous leaves extract were emphasized by liquid chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> exhibited both anti-inflammatory and peripheral analgesic activities. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> significantly decreased the immune expression of MMP-9, TNF-α and TGF-β1 in the hind paw of rats.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> possess peripheral anti-nociceptive and anti-inflammatory effects in rats mediated through its anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory activities. The activity of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> leaves extract might be attributed to the presence of hydroxy and keto structures.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p><italic toggle="yes">Dobera glabra</italic>; Anti-Inflammatory; Analgesic; Flavonoids; Rat</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Dobera glabra</italic></kwd><kwd>Anti-Inflammatory</kwd><kwd>Analgesic</kwd><kwd>Flavonoids</kwd><kwd>Rat</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Inflammation represents a multifaceted biological defensive response of the body to detrimental stimuli introduced to the host (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Seddighfar et al., 2020</xref>). These deleterious stimulants include physical, chemical and biological, radiation, contagious and immunological incitation (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Tsai et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Mondal et al., 2019</xref>). Inflammatory disorders, including asthma, hepatitis, allergy, inflammatory bowel disease, autoimmune diseases, glomerulonephritis, coeliac disease, pre-perfusion injury, rheumatic disorders and transplant rejection affect a substantial portion of the worldwide population (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Straub and Schradin, 2016</xref>). Long-lasting inflammation result in numerous metabolic disorders, such as obesity, neurogenerative and cardiovascular diseases and cancer (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Okin and Medzhitov, 2012</xref>). The primary phase of acute inflammation comprises the cellular influx accompanied by the release of mediators such as histamine and serotonin that are initially released from mast cells, along with the production of bradykinin and prostaglandins (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Coura et al., 2015</xref>). Throughout an inflammatory response, stimulation of inflammatory cells takes place that in turn produce prominent levels of many pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin-1 beta (IL-1β), interleukin 6 (IL-6) and tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α), while inflammatory mediators such cyclooxygenase-1 (COX-1), cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2), nitric oxide (NO) and inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) negatively impact the functionality of tissues and organs (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kulinsky, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Rho et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">The non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are considerably used for their painkilling, anti-pyretic and anti-inflammatory activities (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Seddighfar et al., 2020</xref>). Particularly, many NSAIDs pose a substantial risk of toxicity after acute and chronic use (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Tasneem et al., 2019</xref>). Medicinal plants encompass a variety of compounds with promising pharmacological and biological activities (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Mondal et al., 2019</xref>). Herbal drugs are beneficial because of their low price and fewer adverse effects (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Oguntibeju, 2018</xref>). Notably, traditional medicines play a crucial role in remedying inflammation-associated diseases (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, the present research study can open up new frontiers in the treatment of inflammation and managing pain.</p><p id="p0020">Wild plants are considered alternative source of food for both human and animals in poor areas. Dobera <italic toggle="yes">glabra</italic> (Forssk.) Poir. (<italic toggle="yes">Salvadoraceae</italic>) is common in the Arabian and African regions (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Vogt, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Aregawi et al., 2008</xref>). It is characterized taxonomically as an ever-green tree (up to 8 m) with alternate thick skinny leaves, white flowers and purple fruits with 1–2 flat seeds (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Teklehaymanot and Giday, 2010</xref>). Commonly in folk medicine, it has named as Garsa (Afargna), Garas and mikah (Arabic) according to its region (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Tsegaye et al., 2007</xref>). The folk uses of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> as a technique for prediction of droughts and an edible food at the starvation, back to its nutritional values of high protein and minerals content (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Tsegaye et al., 2007</xref>). Recently, the flavonoid constituents of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> aqueous methanol leaves extract showed antioxidant and genotoxic protection activities (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al., 2017</xref>). Indeed, the extinction of wild plants is believed to be the most considerable problem that face the botanists through years which may back to the lack of interest in rare small trees, desertification and grazing, in addition to the lack of preservation of old trees as in <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aref et al., 2009</xref>)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Consequently, substantial attention needs to be given to this species to prevent its extinction in the future.</p><p id="p0025">Bearing in mind the ethnobotanical uses of the plant in the management of inflammation and pain, this investigation was undertaken to evaluate the potential anti-inflammatory and analgesic activities of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> owing to therapeutic claims for its efficacy and usefulness in alternative medicine.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant material and extraction</title><p id="p0030">April 2011, the <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> plant was collected from Sudan country and kept at the herbarium of the National Research Centre, Dokki, Giza, Egypt (CAIRC) (No. M89) (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al., 2017</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> leaves (800 g) were dried in shadow, grinded and extracted with boiling water. The aqueous extract was evaporated under reduced pressure and temperature, at 70 °C (Rotavapor®, Heidolph, Germany), to obtain a residue of 130 g (16.2 %) of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> aqueous leaves extract (DGALE). The obtained DGALE was then stored at 4 °C until further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Acid hydrolysis and paper chromatography</title><p id="p0035">Both kind of the sugars and the aglycones were identified depending on the complete acid hydrolysis using 10 mL of 2N HCl (Sigma-Aldrich) at 100 °C for 2 h with a portion of the prepared aqueous extract (100 mg). After cooling, 10 mL of ethyl acetate were used to fractionate the acidic solution. The ethyl acetate layer was passed through anhydrous Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (drying agent) (Sigma-Aldrich) then evaporated. Also, the hydrolyzed fraction was inserted into 1D paper chromatography (PC) [Whatman No. 1, Whatman Ltd. Maidstone, Kent, England] and eluted with mixture solvent systems [50%, AcOH:H<sub>2</sub>O, <italic toggle="yes">v:v</italic> 1:1) and BAW (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>-BuOH-HOAc-H<sub>2</sub>O 4:1:5, upper layer) to detect the aglycones. As well as, the aqueous layer was neutralized, then subjected to PC investigation using BBPW (Benzene: n-BuOH: pyridine: H2O; 1:5:3:3; upper layer) solvent system to detect the sugars (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Marzouk et al., 2016</xref>). All the flavonoid aglycones (Fluka AG, Bucns SG; Switzerland) and sugar samples (E. Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) were used as authentic references in high grades.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>LC-ESI-MS analysis</title><p id="p0040">The DGALE was subjected to LC-ESI-MS analysis system that consists of HPLC (Waters Alliance, 2695) and MS (Waters, 3100) according to the methods of <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2019)</xref>. The peaks and spectra were processed using the Maslynx 4.1 software. The authentic reference standards were obtained from Prof. Dr. Mona M. Marzouk, Phytochemistry and Plant Systematics department, National Research Centre. The obvious peaks were tentatively identified by comparing their mass fragmentation pattern with literatures.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Animals</title><p id="p0045">All animal experiments were approved by the Ethics Committee of National Research Centre (permit number: 15/047) and performed in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals published by the US National Institutes of Health (NIH Publication No. 85-23, revised 1996). Mice and rats used in this study were obtained from The Animal House Colony at the National Research Centre (NRC), Egypt. Mature male albino mice of 20–25 g each, were utilized. Male Wistar rats weighing 200 ± 20 g were utilized. All animals were housed in hygienic polypropylene cages (5 animals/cage) in well ventilated rooms with exhaust fans; mice cage size: 220 × 182 × 120 mm, and rat cage size 421 × 290 × 190 mm. All animals were maintained under standard conditions (22 ± 3 °C, 60 ± 5% humidity, and 12 h light/12 h dark cycle). Animals were fed a commercial pellet diet (Al-Marwa for Animals Feed Manufacturing, Egypt) and received water <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>. Animals were allowed to adapt to the laboratory environment for a week before carrying out tests.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Experimental design</title><sec id="sec2.5.1"><label>2.5.1</label><title>Induction of paw edema</title><p id="p0050">The anti-inflammatory testing was performed according to the method of <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Winter et al. (1962)</xref>. Induction of paw edema was done in male rats via subcutaneous (s.c.) injection of 0.1 ml of 1% (w/v) carrageenan dissolved in distilled water in the sub-plantar region of their left hind paws. A negative control group of rats was left without any treatment but given a respective volume of the solvent (few drops of tween-80 in distilled water), and was kept as positive control. <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> fractions were administered at doses of (100, 200 and 300 mg/kg, p.o.), according to <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2017)</xref>. Indomethacin (20 mg/kg, p.o.) was used as a reference drug, according to <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ammar et al. (2016)</xref>. The paw volumes were measured in rats by using a plethysmometer, 1 h before (baseline) and after injection of 1% carrageenan at different time intervals (1, 2, 3 and 4 h).</p><p id="p0055">Edema rate <sup>(1)</sup> and inhibition rate <sup>(2)</sup> of each group were calculated at the above-mentioned time intervals according to <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Elhenawy et al. (2019)</xref> as follows:<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label>Edema rate (%) = Vt - Vo/ Vo</disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label>Inhibition rate (%) = Ec - Et/ Ec</disp-formula>where:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><p id="p0060">Vo is the volume before carrageenan injection (mL).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><p id="p0065">Vt is the volume at t hour after carrageenan injection (mL).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><p id="p0070">Ec is the edema rate of control group.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><p id="p0075">Et is the edema rate of treated group.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0080">Animals were sacrificed four hours after carrageenan injection and left hind paws were cut and kept in formol saline 10%. A group of rats were orally administered the vehicle (negative control) and were utilized for the histological examination and for the determination of inflammatory biomarkers.</p><sec id="sec2.5.1.1"><label>2.5.1.1</label><title>Blood and tissue samples</title><p id="p0085">Blood samples were collected from the retro-orbital venous plexus of each rat under mild ketamine anesthesia after the last recording of paw volume (4 h after carrageenan). The blood samples were allowed to clot at room temperature and the sera were separated by centrifugation at 4000 rpm for 15 min then stored at -80 °C until assayed. After the collection of blood, euthanasia or humane killing of rats was done by methods that induce rapid unconsciousness and death without pain or distress by cervical dislocation. The left hind paws of each animal were immediately dissected and were kept in 10% buffered neutral formalin for histopathological and immunohistochemical examinations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.1.2"><label>2.5.1.2</label><title>Determination of inflammatory biomarkers</title><p id="p0090">Serum samples were used for the estimation of interleukin-6 (IL-6), interleukin-10 (IL-10) and cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2), using ELISA kit purchased from (Immuno-Biological Laboratories (IBL)-America, Minneapolis, USA, catalogue number: BE76152), (Cloud-Clone, Texas, USA, catalogue number: SEA0206Ra96), and (Cusabio, Houston, USA, catalogue number: CSB-E13519r), respectively, based on the manufacturer procedures.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.1.3"><label>2.5.1.3</label><title>Histopathologic studies</title><p id="p0095">Specimens of the soft tissues of the paw were processed for paraffin embedding and 3–4 mm sections were prepared. The specimens were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) for light electric microscope examination (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bancroft and Gamble, 2008</xref>). Qualitative histopathological damage in paw specimen were graded based on the severity of degenerative findings: (0) no observable damage, (1) mild damage less than 25% of paw cells affected, (2) mild/moderate damage 25–50% of paw cells affected, (3) moderate damage 50% of paw cells affected, (4) moderate to severe inflammation more than 50% of paw cells affected (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bang et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.1.4"><label>2.5.1.4</label><title>Immunohistopathological examination</title><p id="p0100">The expression of MMP-9, TNF-α and TGF-β1 in the paw specimens were carried out using a modified avidin-biotin (DAB, Sigma Chemical Co.) immunochemistry technique as reported previously (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2015</xref>). Paraffinized paw sections were rehydrated in xylene and graded ethanol solutions. All specimens were heated in citrate buffer (pH = 6) for 20 min, cooled, and then immunolabeled with primary polyclonal rabbit antibodies against MMP-9, TNF-α and TGF-β1 at dilutions of (1:100, 1:200 and 1:100 respectively) and incubated overnight at 4 °C. Afterward, tissue sections were washed with phosphate buffered saline, and incubated for 30 min at 37 °C with Avidin DH and biotinylated horseradish peroxidase <italic toggle="yes">H complex</italic> according to (Vactastain ABC peroxidase kit, Vector Laboratories) based on the methods mentioned by <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Ramadan et al. (2018)</xref>. Subsequently, tissue samples were washed again with phosphate buffered saline and the reaction was revealed by diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride (DAB, Sigma Chemical Co.) and the sections were counterstained with hematoxylin, dehydrated, and cleared in xylene then cover slipped for light microscopic examination. The intensity of the immunostaining was scored according to the scoring system described by <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Mori et al. (2003)</xref> as severe (+++), moderate (++), mild (+), or nil (-). Furthermore, quantification of the three inflammatory biomarkers were done by calculating the fraction of diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride-positive immunoreactive area in five fields/section (18.8913 Sqmm) as area percentage of immunopositive cells to the total area of the microscopic field using image analysis software (Leica QWin Plus v3; Leica Microsystems Ltd, Heerbrugg, Switzerland). A random sample distribution has been applied to provide unbiased and quantitative data. An experienced investigator blinded to sample identity has performed all histopathological assessments to avoid any bias.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.1.5"><label>2.5.1.5</label><title>Peripheral analgesic activity in mice (Writhing test)</title><p id="p0105">Acetic acid induced writhing assay was done as described by <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ammar et al. (2016)</xref>, by an intraperitoneal injection of acetic acid (0.7% aqueous solution) in a dose of 10 mL/kg b.wt, 30 min before drug administration. The number of writhes per animal was recorded for 20 min after acetic acid injection. Percent protection <sup>(3)</sup> was calculated based on the following ratio, according to <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2019)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label>Protection% = (Control Mean-Treated Mean)/Control Mean ×100</disp-formula></p><p id="p0110">Twenty-five mice were pseudo-randomly allocated into 5 groups using computer-generated randomization table, so that each group reached the required size of animals (n = 5 mice each). Group 1 was kept as normal control. <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract was administered at doses of (100, 200 and 300 mg/kg, p.o.) to mice of groups 2, 3, 4, respectively. Mice of group <italic toggle="yes">5</italic> (reference group) were orally treated with acetyl salicylic acid in a dose of 150 mg/kg b.wt., according to <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2019)</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.5.2"><label>2.5.2</label><title>Central analgesic activity in rats (Hot plate test)</title><p id="p0115">The experiment was carried out as described by (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">El-Serwy et al., 2015</xref>) using hot-plate apparatus. The plate temperature was maintained at 53 ± 0.5 °C.</p><p id="p0120">Twenty-five male rats were pseudo-randomly divided into 5 groups using computer-generated randomization table, so that each group reached the required size of animals (n = 5 rats each). The reaction time of the rat to the thermal stimulus was the time interval between placing the animal in the hot plate and when it licked its hind paw or jumped. Reaction time was measured prior to extract and drug treatment (0 min). The reaction time was again measured at 30 min and repeated at 60- and 90-min post-treatment.</p><p id="p0125">Group 1 was kept as normal control. <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract was administered at doses of (100, 200 and 300 mg/kg, p.o.) to rats of groups 2, 3, 4, respectively. Rats of group 5 (reference group) were orally treated with acetyl salicylic acid in a dose of 150 mg/kg b.wt.</p><p id="p0130">Response latency or reaction time was the time between placing the animal on the plate and its reaction. The cut-off time of 30 s was used to avoid tissue damage. Latency was converted to percent of maximum possible effect (% MPE) <sup>(4)</sup> according to <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2019)</xref> using the following formula:<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label>% MPE= (Post drug latency-pre-drug latency/cut-off latency-pre drug latency) × 100</disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0135">Data were expressed as means ± standard deviation (S.D.). Comparisons between means were carried out using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons test, except for paw edema rate and hot plate which were carried out using two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons test.</p><p id="p0140">Statistics and graphical presentations were performed using Graphpad Prism software, version 7 (Inc., San Diego, USA). A probability level of less than 0.05 was accepted as being significant in all statistical tests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Acid hydrolysis</title><p id="p0145">The paper chromatography of the ethyl acetate fraction gave spots under UV lamp with color reaction and R<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></sub> values as kaempferol, quercetin and isorhamnetin. In addition to, the glucose and rhamnose were detected as major sugar moieties in the aqueous portion.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Identification of polar constituents by HPLC-ESI-MS</title><p id="p0150">HPLC-ESI-MS analysis has provided comprehensive structural information that successfully led to the identification and characterization of secondary metabolites representing flavonoids glycosides (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The twenty detected chromatographic peaks were identified and the results are listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of DGALE using LC-ESI-MS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">t<sub>R</sub> (min)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">[M-H]<sup>-</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> fragments</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tentatively identified compound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">195</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">177,151,</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gluconic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">191</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Citric acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">209</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">165, 131</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydroxy ferulic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">191</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">173, 127,85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quinic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">371</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">209, 165,147,131</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hydroxyferulic acid -<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">337</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">191, 173,163,119</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coumaroyl quinic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">353</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">191, 179, 135</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Caffeoyl quinic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">385</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">223, 205, 179</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sinapoyl-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">755</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">609, 301</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quercetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(2՛՛-rhamnosyl) rutinoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">797</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">755, 609, 301</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quercetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(2՛՛-rhamnosyl) rutinoside-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-acetate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">739</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">593, 285</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kaempferol 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(2՛՛-rhamnosyl) rutinoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">769</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">623, 315</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isorhamnetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(2՛՛-rhamnosyl) rutinoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">609</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">301</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quercetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside <xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">463</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">301, 300</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quercetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside <xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">577</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">431, 285</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kaempferol 3,7-di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-α-rhamnopyranoside<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">∗</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">623</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">477,461,315,301</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isorhamnetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O-α</italic>-rhamnopyranoside-7-<italic toggle="yes">O-β</italic>-glucopyranoside<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">∗</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">593</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">285</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kaempferol 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside<xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">623</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">477, 461, 315</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isorhamnetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O-β</italic>-glucopyranoside-7-<italic toggle="yes">O-α</italic>-rhamnopyranoside<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">∗</xref><sup><italic toggle="yes">,</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">623</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">315</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isorhamnetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">315</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">301,299,151</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isorhamnetin<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">∗</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="tbl1fndollar" ref-type="table-fn">$</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fnlowast"><label>∗</label><p id="ntpara0010">Compounds isolated previously from the aqueous methanol extract of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> [16].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fndollar"><label>$</label><p id="ntpara0015">Compounds identified by comparing their retention times and mass spectra with the authentic.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>LC-ESI-MS chromatogram of DGALE leaves aqueous extract.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract in carrageenan-induced rat paw edema</title><p id="p0155">Carrageenan-induced paw edema is a broadly used animal model for determine the acute phase of inflammation. The experimental data showed that intra-planter injection of carrageenan in rats' hind paw started off the vascular phase of inflammation, which caused an increase in the paw volume, indicating edema, that peaked after 4 h in the control group. It was observed that administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract (300 mg/kg) resulted in significantly suppression of paw edema throughout the 4-time period which was dose dependent as compared to the control group. The inhibitory effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract (300 mg/kg) was 30.7%, 27.0%, 23.9% and 22.3% at the 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup>, 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> hour. In addition, it was noticed that administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract (100 and 200 mg/kg) resulted in markedly inhibition of paw edema in the first hour to 17.4% and 18.1%, respectively as compared to the indomethacin group. Administration of the standard drug, indomethacin, markedly decreased edema induced by carrageenan beginning from the first hour and was steady till the end of the experiment as compared to the control group. The prohibitive effect of indomethacin was 39.5%, 29.1%, 28.5% and 26.7% at the 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup>, 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> hour, respectively (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Acute anti-inflammatory activity of DGALE in carrageenan-induced rat paw edema.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 h<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 h<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 h<hr/></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 h<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Edema rate (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Edema rate (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Edema rate (%)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Edema rate (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Positive control</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.6<sup>b</sup> ± 4.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.4<sup>b</sup> ± 12.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.2<sup>b</sup> ± 10.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.7<sup>b</sup> ± 3.50</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (100 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.1<sup>b</sup> ± 4.69 (17.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.8 ± 3.09 (8.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.2 ± 7.05 (7.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.9 ± 8.52 (8.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (200 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.8<sup>b</sup> ± 5.38 (18.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.2 ± 5.74 (12.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.8 ± 8.83 (11.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.8 ± 10.45 (8.4)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (300 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0<sup>a</sup> ±3.55 (30.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.5<sup>a</sup> ±5.49 (27.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.5<sup>a</sup> ±2.71 (23.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6<sup>a</sup> ±2.48 (22.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indomethacin (20 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.8<sup>a</sup> ±2.66 (39.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.5<sup>a</sup> ±9.02 (29.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.9<sup>a</sup> ±8.06 (28.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.0<sup>a</sup> ±6.80 (26.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Each value represents the mean of 5 rats ±S.D. Statistical analysis was performed using two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons test. (<sup>a</sup> vs positive control group at same time interval, <sup>b</sup> vs indomethacin group at same time) at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05. Each value in parenthesis indicates the percentage inhibition rate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extraction serum inflammatory biomarkers</title><p id="p0160">Injection of carrageenan showed a significant increase in serum levels of IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2 to 135.0%, 327.3% and 98.0%, respectively, compared with the negative control. Administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract (100, 200, 300 mg/kg) resulted in significant decrease in IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2 dose-dependently, in comparison with the control group. Administration of indomethacin showed significant decrease in IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2 by 35.5%, 49.2%, 30.9%, correspondingly, in comparison with the control group (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of DGALE on serum inflammatory biomarkers. (a) Interleukin-6, (b) Interleukin-10 and (c) Cycloxygenase-2. Each bar represents the results as (ng/mL). The numbers above each bar represents the mean ± SD of five rats. IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2 were measured using corresponding rat-specific ELISA kits. Multiple group comparisons were performed by analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey's multiple comparison post hoc test at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05. <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from negative control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from positive control.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract on inflammation induced histopathological changes in rats' hind paw</title><p id="p0165">The hind paw of control rats showed normal histological structure (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>a), while carrageenan model rats showed increase in the thickness of the sub-epithelial layer with marked edema that dispersing the dermal connective tissue fibers from each other, congestion and severe inflammatory reaction. The later characterized by diffuse mononuclear inflammatory cells infiltration (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>b and c) with large number of neutrophils (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>d), accompanied with marked hyalinization. Vasculitis was an obvious finding with edema in the vascular wall and sometimes marked endothelial injury with early thrombus formation (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>e). The administration of indomethacin to carrageenan model rats showed decreased inflammatory reaction of moderate degree; few inflammatory cells were diffusely infiltrating the paw tissue with moderate degree of edema particularly sub-epithelial (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>f). On the other hand, the administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabera</italic> to carrageenan-induced inflammation rats revealed a dose-related decrease in the inflammatory reaction of the paw tissue (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>a–c) particularly at the high dose which showed mild inflammatory cells infiltration. The scoring of the inflammatory reaction in carrageenan model rats and different treated groups is presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure (4</xref>d).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>H&amp;E-stained sections of hind paw of rats. (a) Control rat showing normal histological structure. (b–e) Carrageenan model rat showing; severe inflammatory reaction; marked edema (Ed) and diffuse mononuclear inflammatory cells infiltration (IF) admixed with (d) many neutrophils, (e) vasculitis (arrow) with vascular wall edema and early thrombus formation. (f) Indomethacin treated carrageenan model rat showing sub-epithelial edema (Ed) and few inflammatory cells infiltration.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Histological evaluation of the anti-inflammatory effects of different doses of DGALE. H&amp;E-stained sections of hind paws of DGALE treated carrageenan model rats showing a dose related pattern decreased inflammatory reaction at 100 mg (a), 200 mg (b) and 300 mg (c). (d) The scores of inflammatory reactions in indomethacin and different doses of DGALE treated groups compared to carrageenan model group. <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from positive control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from indomethacin, using one-way ANOVA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract on inflammation induced changes in inflammatory biomarkers expression in rats' hind paw</title><p id="p0170">The paw of normal control rats showed negative expression of MMP-9 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>a), TNF-α (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>a) and TGF-β1 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>a). However, the paw of carrageenan model rats showed significant increased expression of MMP-9 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>b), TNF-a (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>b) and TGF-β1 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>b). The immune expression of the three tissue markers was significantly reduced with the treatment with indomethacin (Figures 5c, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c), as well as the three doses of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabera</italic> extract (Figures <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>d-f and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d-f), particularly with the highest dose which showed the significant highest reduction. The (g) figure in each panel represents the quantitative image analysis of the immune-expression of each marker expressed as optical density (OD) in five different microscopic fields, which showing significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05) dose-related decreased expression of MMP-9, TNF-α and TGF-β1 in the hind paw of rats treated with <italic toggle="yes">D. glabera</italic>.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical stained sections of rats' hind paw for MMP-9 expression. (a) control rat, (b) carrageenan model rats, (c) Indomethacin treated carrageenan model rat, (d–f) DGALEtreated carrageenan model rats at doses 100, 200 and 300 mg respectively. (g) The quantitative image analysis of MMP-9 expression in each group presented as OD of the positive brown colour in 5 microscopic fields using image analysis software (Image J, 1.46a, NIH, USA). <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from negative control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from positive control, using one-way ANOVA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical stained sections of rats' hind paw for TNF-α expression. (a) control rat, (b) carrageenan model rats, (c) Indomethacin treated carrageenan model rat, (d–f) DGALE treated carrageenan model rats at doses 100, 200 and 300 mg respectively. (g) The quantitative image analysis of MMP-TNF-α 9 expression in each group presented as OD of the positive brown colour in 5 microscopic fields using image analysis software (Image J, 1.46a, NIH, USA). <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from negative control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from positive control, using one-way ANOVA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Figure 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical stained sections of rats' hind paw for TGF-β1 expression. (a) control rat, (b) carrageenan model rats, (c) Indomethacin treated carrageenan model rat, (d–f) DGALE treated carrageenan model rats at doses 100, 200 and 300 mg respectively. (g) The quantitative image analysis of TGF-β1 expression in each group presented as OD of the positive brown colour in 5 microscopic fields using image analysis software (Image J, 1.46a, NIH, USA). <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from negative control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from positive control, using one-way ANOVA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Figure 7</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract on peripheral nociceptive threshold</title><p id="p0175">Investigation of the peripheral anti-allodynic effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract was done using acetic acid-induced intestinal compressions in mice (writhing effect). The tabulated data shows administration of acetic acid induces peritoneal inflammation resulted in a reaction described by tightening of the intestinal muscle along with forelimbs extension and lengthening of the body. The obtained data revealed that <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract possess peripheral pain-relieving effect at the three tested dosage levels in comparison to the control group. The protection percentage arranged was 21.4%, 35.7%, 43.8% and 53.6% for <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract (100, 200, 300 mg/kg) and acetylsalicylic acid (150 mg/kg), correspondingly (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>).<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Peripheral analgesic activity of DGALE using writhing test. Each bar represents the mean ± S.D. of five mice for each group. <sup>a</sup> statistically significant from control, <sup>b</sup> statistically significant from acetyl salicylic acid, using one-way ANOVA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure 8</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><label>3.8</label><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract on hot-plate latency</title><p id="p0180">In the current investigation, administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract at the three dose levels (100, 200 and 300 mg/kg) could not expand the reaction time after 30, 60 and 90 min of administration as compared to the control group. Acetyl salicylic acid (150 mg/kg) was the most effective among all the treated groups (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Additionally, the maximal possible effect of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract at a dose of 300 mg/kg showed significant difference compared to the control group with MPE value of 3.1%, whereas acetyl salicylic acid revealed MPE value of 10.1%.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Central analgesic activity of DGALE using hot plate test in rats.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Groups</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Reaction time (sec.)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">%MPE</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 min</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 min</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 min</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 min</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Control</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2 ± 0.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7<sup>b</sup> ± 0.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3<sup>b</sup> ± 1.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.8<sup>b</sup> ± 1.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0<sup>b</sup> ± 1.41</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (100 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0 ± 0.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3<sup>b</sup> ± 1.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6<sup>b</sup> ± 0.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4<sup>b</sup> ± 0.82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8<sup>b</sup> ± 0.57</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (200 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.1 ± 0.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0<sup>b</sup> ± 0.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7<sup>b</sup> ± 0.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.8<sup>b</sup> ± 0.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3<sup>b</sup> ± 0.22</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DGALE (300 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0 ± 0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3<sup>b</sup> ± 1.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0<sup>b</sup> ± 0.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7<sup>b</sup> ± 0.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1ab ± 0.82</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acetyl salicylic acid (150 mg/kg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0 ± 1.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.8<sup>a</sup> ±2.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2<sup>a</sup> ±1.72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.3<sup>a</sup> ±1.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.1<sup>a</sup> ±1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0030"><p>Each value represents the mean of 5 rats ±S.D. Statistical analysis was performed using two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons test. (<sup>a</sup> vs positive control group at same time interval, <sup>b</sup> vs acetyl salicylic acid group at same time) at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0035"><p>MPE refers to the maximal possible effect.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0185">The compounds were identified by mass information fragments and their relative retention times compared with the authentic reference standards and the published literature data. In brief, the fragmentation patterns of glycosides can be explained as simple regular cleavages of repeated glycosidic bonds in the [M−H]<sup>−</sup> ion under negative ion mode and observed the aglycone molecule in the mass spectra. Peak <bold>1</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 195) was characterized as gluconic acid, suggested by fragment ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 177 [M-H-H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>-</sup> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Marzouk et al., 2019</xref>). Citric acid was presented as peak <bold>2</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 191), confirmed by the presence of the fragment ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 111 [M-H–CO<sub>2</sub>–2H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>-</sup> (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Taamalli et al., 2015</xref>). Compound <bold>3</bold> produced a molecular ion peak at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 209 and is identified as hydroxy ferulic acid, confirmed by the fragment ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 165 [M-H-CO<sub>2</sub>]<sup>-</sup>, which corresponds to the loss of CO<sub>2</sub> molecule. Peak <bold>4</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 191) was characterized as quinic acid. Its spectrum showed a fragment ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 127 which corresponds to the loss of H<sub>2</sub>O and CO molecules [M-H–CO–2H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>-</sup>. Compound <bold>5</bold> presented a molecular ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 371 and revealed fragments at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 209 [M-H-glucose]− and 165 [M-H-glucose-CO<sub>2</sub>]−, indicating the detection of hydroxyferulic acid-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>—glucoside (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al., 2014</xref>). Peaks <bold>6</bold> showed a molecular ion peak at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 337 with product ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 191 [Quinic acid-H]<sup>−</sup>, corresponding to quinic acid and at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 163 [Coumaric acid-H]<sup>−</sup>, corresponding to coumaric acid. Additional fragment ions were observed for peak <bold>6</bold> at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 173 [quinic acid–H<sub>2</sub>O–H]<sup>−</sup> and 119 [Coumaric acid–CO<sub>2</sub>–H]<sup>-</sup>, which is characteristic to coumaroyl quinic acid (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0190">Another chlorogenic acid at peak <bold>7</bold> was characterized with a molecular ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 353 and fragmentation ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 191 [quinic acid-H]<sup>−</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 179 [Caffeic acid- H]−, 173 [quinic acid–H<sub>2</sub>O–H]<sup>−</sup> and 135 [Caffeic acid–CO<sub>2</sub>–H]<sup>-</sup>. Thus compound <bold>7</bold> has been tentatively identified as caffeoylquinic acid (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Ncube et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">Peak <bold>8</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 385) suggesting the occurrence of a sinapoylhexoside structure, which confirmed by the presence of fragment ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 223 [sinapic acid-H]<sup>-</sup> (after loss of hexosyl moiety), <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 205 [sinapic acid-H-H<sub>2</sub>O]<sup>-</sup> (after loss of water molecule) and <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 179 [sinapic acid-H-CO<sub>2</sub>]<sup>-</sup> (after loss of CO<sub>2</sub> molecule).</p><p id="p0200">The flavonol-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosides were understood by the consecutive losses of aglycone fragment ions <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 301 (quercetin), <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 285 (kaempferol) or <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 315 (isorhamnetin) from [M−H]<sup>−</sup> with rhamnose and/or glucose moieties, supported by acid hydrolysis. As enumerated in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, peak <bold>9</bold> exhibited the same molecular parent ion [M-H]<sup>-</sup> at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 755 with MS main fragment at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 301 indicating the loss of triglycosides [monosaccharide and disaccharide residues, rhamnosyl (146 amu) and rutinoside (308 amu)] suggesting a flavonoid nucleus of quercetin. The homolytic cleavage between the aglycone part and the saccharide moieties exhibited a pronounced [M-H-454]<sup>-</sup> ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 301 and missing other fragments indicated that the 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-triglycosides linkage (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Vukics and Guttman, 2010</xref>). As well, the lowering abundance of the fragment at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 609 [M-H-146]<sup>-</sup> may be indicated the 1→2 connected glycosides between one of the external rhamnose unit and the internal glucose moiety (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Vukics and Guttman, 2010</xref>). Consequently, it was tentatively identified as quercetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(2<sup>՛՛</sup>-rhamnosyl)-rutinoside as illustrated in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref> (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Ferreres et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Farias and Mendez, 2014</xref>). Analogously, peaks <bold>11</bold>&amp;<bold>12</bold> which retained at 33.81 and 34.23 min and showed the [M−H]<sup>−</sup> ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 739 and 769 with mass fragment at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 285 and 315,corresponding to kaempferol and isorhamnetin, respectively. In addition, the lower abundance of the fragment ions indicating the loss of sugar moieties may be attributed to the direct interglycosidic linkage between the three monosaccharides in this compound and the position 3 of the aglycone. Apparently, the lowering abundance of the fragments at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 593 and 623 may be indicated the 1→2 connection. Thus, compounds <bold>11</bold> and <bold>12</bold> were tentatively identified as kaempferol -3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-2<sup>՛՛</sup>-rhamnosylrutinoside and isorhamnetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-2<sup>՛՛</sup>-rhamnosylrutinoside, respectively (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>). Moreover, peak <bold>10</bold> showed typical fragments of compound <bold>11</bold> with an extra 42 amu, suggestive for an acetyl group connected with one of the two rhamnose moieties and identified as kaempferol -3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-2<sup>՛՛</sup>-rhamnosylrutinoside-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-acetate. In reference to peaks <bold>13</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 609) and <bold>14</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 463), they showed the same MS fragment at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 301, also identified as quercetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside (rutin) and quercetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside (Isoquercitrin), respectively, by comparing with the authentic samples. Peaks <bold>15</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 577) and <bold>17</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 593) were identified as kaempferol 3,7-di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rhamnoside and kaempferol-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside based on the retention time and the fragmentation pattern of authentic (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">El Raey et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Emam et al., 2019</xref>). Peak <bold>19</bold> was suggested as isorhamnetin-3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-rutinoside based on the parent ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 623 and fragments ions at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 315, 300 and 301, representing isorhamnetin aglycone attached with rutinose at C-3 (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>). Peaks <bold>16</bold> and <bold>18</bold> were identified as isorhamnetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">α</italic>-rhamnopyranoside-7-O-<italic toggle="yes">β</italic>-glucopyranoside and isorhamnetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O-β</italic>-glucopyranoside-7-<italic toggle="yes">O-α</italic>-rhamnopyranoside according to the negative ion MS spectra and the retention time of authentic, which exhibited the same unique [M-H]<sup>-</sup> ion at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 623 and fragments at <italic toggle="yes">m/z</italic> 477, 461 and 315. By the same way, peak <bold>20</bold> was identified as isorhamnetin aglycone. Compounds <bold>15</bold>, <bold>16</bold>, <bold>18</bold> and <bold>20</bold> have been reported in our previous study from the same plant species (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al., 2017</xref>) (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>).<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The structures of the tentatively identified flavonoids and the selected MS fragments in negative ion mode.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Figure 9</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0205">The current study imparts for the first time the potential anti-inflammatory and analgesic activities of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> attributable to therapeutic claims for its effectiveness and usefulness in Egyptian unconventional medicine. Treatment with <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> ameliorated inflammation and showed analgesic activity as verified by enhancement in carrageenan-induced edema, nociceptive threshold, alleviation of histopathological injury of rats' hind paw, accompained by mitigation of oxidative burst, matrix metalloproteinases activation and inflammatory burden.</p><p id="p0210">Various factors leaded to the multifaceted progression of inflammatory reactions. Immunological, microbiological and noxious agents can recruit inflammatory response through a diversity of cellular and hormonal mediators. In the present work, rat paw edema induced by carrageenan is a widely used test for the determination of anti-inflammatory activity of pharmacological substances (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">El-Serwy et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ammar et al., 2016</xref>). Intra-planter injection of carrageenan in rats resulted in an increase in rat's paw volume indicating edema in the non-treated group, which is consistent with previous studies (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ammar et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Anyasor et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Santos et al., 2019</xref>). It has been shown that the injection of carrageenan into the sub-planter surface of rat paw promote a biphasic edema. The primary phase witnessed around one hour is related to the release of serotonin, histamine, bradykinin and kind of prostaglandins produced by cyclooxygenase enzymes (COX). Whereas, the delayed phase, after one hour, is associated with neutrophil infiltration and the steady the prostaglandin generation (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gilligan et al., 1994</xref>). Production of the neutrophil-derived free radicals, nitric oxide (NO) as well as pro-inflammatory mediators comprising tumor necrosis factor (TNF-α), and interleukin-1 β (IL-1 β) are, likewise, associated with the delayed phase of carrageenan-induced acute inflammation (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Mansouri et al., 2015</xref>). Herein, treatment with <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> attenuated carrageenan-induced edema in inflamed rat paw. In support, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hussein et al. (2013)</xref> reported that Gelam honey contains many phenolic compounds that are similar to <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> such as quercetin and caffeic acid which correlated to their anti-inflammatory activity. Moreover, indomethacin treatment ameliorated the inflammatory burden induced by the injection of carrageenan into the sub-planter surface of rats' paw. These findings are consistent with <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2019)</xref>, which showed that the cyclooxygenase inhibitor, indomethacin can significantly reduce edema during the second phase of the edema process.</p><p id="p0215">Indeed, oxidative stress stimuluses numerous inflammatory mediators; through triggering NF-κB pathway, that lead to devastation of the membrane lipids and tissue damage (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ammar et al., 2016</xref>). Herein, intra-planter injection of carrageenan in rats resulted in a significant increase in IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2. This totally agrees with the former research studies. For instance, the elevation of IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2 levels have been previously reported in paw tissue after carrageenan-induced inflammation (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">El-Shitany et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Haddadi and Rashtiani, 2020</xref>). Meanwhile, the synthesis of several cytokines is influenced by variations in the cellular oxidant/anti-oxidant balance (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Mansour et al., 2015</xref>). Carrageenan-prompted inflammatory reaction has been portrayed as a two-phased incident, whereupon numerous cytokines would be functioned. In the initial stage, many inflammatory cytokines including serotonin, histamine as well as bradykinin were liberated, and subsequently TNF-α, TGF-β1, prostaglandins, IL-6, and IL-1β are generated in the second phase. COX-2 expression is released at its maximum level at the late stage of carrageenan-provoked rats' paw edema that was resulted in the biosynthesis of prostaglandins in inflammatory reactions. In line with this, we observed that treatment with <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> and indomethacin resulted in marked decrease in IL-6, IL-10 and COX-2. In support, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al. (2017)</xref> revealed that flavonoid constituents of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> leaves extract showed antioxidant and genotoxic protection activities. In this context, histopathological examination showed that carrageenan model resulted in increase in the thickness of the sub-epithelial layer with marked edema that dispersing the dermal connective tissue fibers from each other, congestion and severe inflammatory reaction. The later characterized by diffuse mononuclear inflammatory cells infiltration. This is in line with previous studies (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Ben Khedir et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al., 2019</xref>) which showed that carrageenan model induced morphological injury and neutrophil infiltration that in turn result in local inflammation. Treatment with <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> retained the normal histopathological structure retained the normal histopathological structure of hind paw of rats after carrageenan-induced inflammation.</p><p id="p0220">To our knowledge, this is the first report for the anti-inflammatory activity of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic>, possessing a significantly high <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> anti-inflammatory activity compared to indomethacin. This effect could be attributed to its content of quercetin, kaempferol, caffeoylquinic acid, and hydroxyl ferulic acid. Quercetin and kaempferol are known for their antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities, inhibition of histamine release and reducing the pro-inflammatory cytokines (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Tanwar and Modgil, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Mlcek et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, previous records indicated that the caffeoylquinic acids exhibited significant activities such as anti-oxidation and anti-inflammation via suppression of iNOS, COX-2, and TNF-α gene expressions (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hong et al., 2015</xref>). Additionally, ferulic acid has strong antioxidant properties, as well as anti-inflammatory activity (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Zduńska et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0225">In mice, the acetic acid-induced writhing model is an effective peripheral analgesic test for examining natural treatments alongside inflammatory soreness (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">McCarson, 2015</xref>). Acetic acid-induced writhing model results in pain sensation by triggering inflammatory response accompanied with pain stimulus, leading to release of arachidonic acid from tissue (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ezeja et al., 2011</xref>). In the current study, acetic acid injection into mice's peritoneal cavity resulted in shriveling of the intestinal muscle associated with an elongation of the forelimbs and extension of the body. These indications are alleged to be prompted by the prostaglandin pathways (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Elkhateeb et al., 2019</xref>). Herein, <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract possesses peripheral analgesic effect at the three tested dose levels in comparison to the control group and thus implies the incidence of analgesic constituents that might affect prostaglandins pathways. Notably, flavonoids such as quercetin known of their anti-inflammatory activity due to their inhibitory effect on the metabolism of histamine and arachidonic acid and prostaglandins release. Flavonoids can reduce the secretion of lysosomal enzyme as well as the release of arachidonic acid from membranes through reducing lipoxygenase cyclooxygenase, and phospholipase. Subsequently, arachidonic acid reduction by tendered cells could diminish endoperoxides, prostaglandins, prostacyclin, and thromboxanes from the lipoxygenase pathway as well as hydroperoxy- and hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acids and leukotrienes from the cyclooxygenase pathway. In addition, quercetin can inhibit different pro-inflammatory mediators such as eicosanoids, cytokines, adhesion molecules and C-reactive protein. Likewise, it inhibits several transcription factors such as NF-kB and activating protein-1 (AP-1), as well as activation of nuclear factor-erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Gabor, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Tanwar and Modgil, 2012</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> contents of quercetin, kaempferol and its glycosides, could offer antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, analgesic and anti-allergic activities (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Kong et al., 2013</xref>). Conversely, in the current investigation, administration of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract at the three dose levels failed to increase the reaction time after 30, 60 and 90 min of administration as compared to the control group. These results suggest that the analgesic activity of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> extract may be not fully mediated through central mechanism.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0230">Counting them all, the results of the present study postulate a confirmation for the peripheral analgesic and anti-inflammatory effects of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic> against carrageenan induced inflammation in rats mediated through its anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory activities. Given the efficacy of <italic toggle="yes">D. glabra</italic>, it would be desirable to prolong these investigational studies to clinical trials to help in halting the development of inflammatory diseases in patients.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec6.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0235">Rehab F. Abdel-Rahman; Ahmed Elkhateeb; Passant E. Moustafa: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0240">Sameh R. Hussein; Mona M. Marzouk; Mahmoud Emam: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0245">Sahar S Abd El-Rahman: Performed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0250">El-Sayed S. Abdel-Hameed: Performed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0255">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec6.3"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0260">Data included in article/supplementary material/referenced in article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec6.4"><title>Declaration of interests statement</title><p id="p0265">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.5"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0270">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammar</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hawary</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Anssary</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Desoky</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelaal</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelrahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical study of the bioactive fractions of Chrysanthemum fructescens L. cultivated in Egypt</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharmacognosy Phytochem. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1314</fpage><lpage>1321</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anyasor</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okanlawon</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunbiyi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of anti-inflammatory activity of Justicia secunda Vahl leaf extract using in vitro and in vivo inflammation models</article-title><source>Clin. Phytosci.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>49</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aref</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Atta</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Ghtani</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological study on Dobera glabra Forssk. At Jazan region in Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>J. Hortic. For.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>204</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aregawi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melaku</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigatu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management and utilization of browse species as livestock feed in semi-arid district of North Ethiopia</article-title><source>Livest. Res. Rural Dev.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>86</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Theory and Practice of Histological Techniques</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sur</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahm</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory and antiarthritic effects of piperine in human interleukin 1β-stimulated fibroblast-like synoviocytes and in rat arthritis models</article-title><source>Arthritis Res. Ther.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/ar2662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2688199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Khedir</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mzid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardaa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moalla</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahnoun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo evaluation of the anti-inflammatory effect of Pistacia lentiscus fruit oil and its effects on oxidative stress</article-title><source>Evid. Based. Complement Alternat. Med.</source><volume>2016</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>6108203</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2016/6108203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5192325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Areche</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sepúlveda</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simirgiotis</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HPLC-UV-MS profiles of phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity of fruits from three citrus species consumed in Northern Chile</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>17400</fpage><lpage>17421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules191117400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6271594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and quantification by LC-MS/MS of the chemical components of the heating products of the flavonoids extract in Pollen typhae for transformation rule exploration</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>18352</fpage><lpage>18366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26457703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules201018352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6331955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coura</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderlei</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Araújo</surname><given-names>I.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frota</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms involved in the anti-inflammatory action of a polysulfated fraction from Gracilaria cornea in rats</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0119319</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0119319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4373681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25807556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Raey</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hagrassi</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darwish</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acalypha wilkesiana flowers: phenolic profiling, cytotoxic activity of their biosynthesized silver nanoparticles and molecular docking study for its constituents as Topoisomerase-I inhibitors</article-title><source>Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>101243</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhenawy</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Harbi</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>G.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Gazzar</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, comparative docking, and pharmacological activity of naproxen amino acid derivatives as possible anti-inflammatory and analgesic agents</article-title><source>Drug Des. Dev. Ther.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1773</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/DDDT.S196276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6540076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31213767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhateeb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel Latif</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kassem</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ansari</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavonoid constituents of Dobera glabra leaves: amelioration impact against CCl4-induced changes in the genetic materials in male rats</article-title><source>Pharm. Biol.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27659804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13880209.2016.1230879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7011971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhateeb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shabrawy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Desoky</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hameed</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LC-MS-based metabolomic profiling of Lepidium coronopus water extract, anti-inflammatory and analgesic activities, and chemosystematic significance</article-title><source>Med. Chem. Res.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>514</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Serwy</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and anti-inflammatory properties of novel 1, 2, 4-triazole derivatives</article-title><source>Res. Chem. Intermed.</source><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2543</fpage><lpage>2554</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Serwy</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Serwy</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, docking studies and discovery of novel antiinflammatory and analgesic benzofuran derivatives</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Technol.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>7781</fpage><lpage>7798</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shitany</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Masry</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ghareib</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Desoky</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioctic acid protects against carrageenan-induced acute inflammation in rats by reduction in oxidative stress, downregulation of COX-2 mRNA and enhancement of IL-10 mRNA</article-title><source>Fundam. Clin. Pharmacol.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19735303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1472-8206.2009.00744.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezeja</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omeh</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezeigbo</surname><suffix>II</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekechukwu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the analgesic activity of the methanolic stem bark extract of Dialium guineense (Wild)</article-title><source>Ann. Med. Health Sci. Res.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23209955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3507093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Raey</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Haddad</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Awdan</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabie</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ansari</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new polyoxygenated flavonol gossypetin-3-o-β-d-robinobioside from Caesalpinia gilliesii (Hook.) D. Dietr. and in vivo hepatoprotective, anti-inflammatory, and anti-ulcer activities of the leaf methanol extract</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>138</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules24010138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6337366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farias</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LC/ESI-MS method applied to characterization of flavonoids glycosides in B. forficata subsp. pruinosa</article-title><source>Quim. Nova</source><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreres</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Llorach</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil-Izquierdo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the interglycosidic linkage in di-, tri-, tetra-and pentaglycosylated flavonoids and differentiation of positional isomers by liquid chromatography/electrospray ionization tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J. Mass Spectrom.</source><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15039939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jms.586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory and anti-allergic properties of flavonoids</article-title><source>Prog. Clin. Biol. Res.</source><volume>213</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>471</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2872680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilligan</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovato</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erion</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of carrageenan-induced hind paw edema by substance P</article-title><source>Inflammation</source><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1994</year><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7522223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF01534269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddadi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashtiani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory and anti-hyperalgesic effects of milnacipran in inflamed rats: involvement of myeloperoxidase activity, cytokines and oxidative/nitrosative stress</article-title><source>Inflammopharmacology</source><volume>28</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32518981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10787-020-00726-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jhoo</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities of 3, 5-dicaffeoylquinic acid isolated from Ligularia fischeri leaves</article-title><source>Food Sci. Biotechnol.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>263</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>S.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makpol</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yusof</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gelam honey attenuates carrageenan-induced rat paw inflammation via NF-κB pathway</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e72365</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0072365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3756081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anti-inflammatory effect of kaempferol on early atherosclerosis in high cholesterol fed rabbits</article-title><source>Lipids Health Dis.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23895132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1476-511X-12-115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3735477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulinsky</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical aspects of inflammation</article-title><source>Biochemistry (Mosc.)</source><volume>72</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1134/s0006297907060028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nada</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Denshary</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omara</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asaad</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Milk whey proteins modulate endotoxemia-induced hepatotoxicity in rats</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Pharmaceut. Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmati</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naghizadeh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mard</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghorbanzadeh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of the mechanisms underlying the anti-inflammatory effect of ellagic acid in carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats</article-title><source>Ind. J. Pharmacol.</source><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0253-7613.157127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4450555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26069367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhateeb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel Latif</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hameed</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawashty</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-glycosyl flavonoids-rich extract of Dipcadi erythraeum bulbs: phytochemical and anticancer evaluations</article-title><source>J. Appl. Pharmaceut. Sci.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhateeb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farid</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hameed</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic profiling of Rorippa palustris (L.) Besser (Brassicaceae) by LC-ESI-MS: chemosystematic significance and cytotoxic activity</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Dis.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>637</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarson</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Models of inflammation: carrageenan-or complete Freund's Adjuvant (CFA)–Induced edema and hypersensitivity in the rat</article-title><source>Curr. Protoc. Pharmacol</source><volume>70</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>5.4.1</fpage><lpage>5.4.9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/0471141755.ph0504s70</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26331888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mlcek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurikova</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skrovankova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sochor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quercetin and its anti-allergic immune response</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>623</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules21050623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6273625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27187333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maity</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishayee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analgesic and anti-inflammatory activities of quercetin-3-methoxy-4′-glucosyl-7-glucoside isolated from Indian medicinal plant Melothria heterophylla</article-title><source>Medicines</source><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>59</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/medicines6020059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6631596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31137810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashibara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geleziunas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Helicobacter pylori induces matrix metalloproteinase-9 through activation of nuclear factor κB</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>124</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/gast.2003.50152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ncube</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mhlongo</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyses of chlorogenic acids and related cinnamic acid derivatives from Nicotiana tabacum tissues with the aid of UPLC-QTOF-MS/MS based on the in-source collision-induced dissociation method</article-title><source>Chem. Cent. J.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25426160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13065-014-0066-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4242998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oguntibeju</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants with anti-inflammatory activities from selected countries and regions of Africa</article-title><source>J. Inflamm. Res.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30122972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/JIR.S167789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6086115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medzhitov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of inflammatory diseases</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>R733</fpage><lpage>R740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22975004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cub.2012.07.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3601794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afifi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassin</surname><given-names>N.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Rahman</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fayed</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesalazine, an osteopontin inhibitor: the potential prophylactic and remedial roles in induced liver fibrosis in rats</article-title><source>Chem. Biol. Interact.</source><volume>289</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29738702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cbi.2018.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rho</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel triterpene saponin from Panax ginseng seeds, pseudoginsenoside RT8, and its antiinflammatory activity</article-title><source>J. Ginseng. Res.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32148397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jgr.2018.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7033336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Morais Oliveira</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>do Nascimento</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Alencar</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Fátima Sousa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>Á.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Araújo Delmondes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of herb products from Licania rigida Benth</article-title><source>Compl. Ther. Med.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ctim.2019.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31331571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seddighfar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirghazanfari</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadpay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analgesic and anti-inflammatory properties of hydroalcoholic extracts of Malva sylvestris, Carum carvi or Medicago sativa, and their combination in a rat model</article-title><source>J. Integr. Med.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32113847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joim.2020.02.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upregulation of cyclooxygenase-2 is associated with activation of the alternative nuclear factor kappa B signaling pathway in colonic adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Am. J. Transl. Res.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26550460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4626422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schradin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic inflammatory systemic diseases: an evolutionary trade-off between acutely beneficial but chronically harmful programs</article-title><source>Evol. Med. Public Health</source><volume>2016</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26817483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emph/eow001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4753361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taamalli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arráez-Román</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abaza</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iswaldi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarrouk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Carretero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LC-MS-based metabolite profiling of methanolic extracts from the medicinal and aromatic species Mentha pulegium and Origanum majorana</article-title><source>Phytochem. Anal.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25982347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pca.2566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanwar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Modgil</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavonoids: dietary occurrence and health benefits</article-title><source>Spatula DD</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tasneem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular pharmacology of inflammation: medicinal plants as anti-inflammatory agents</article-title><source>Pharmacol. Res.</source><volume>139</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30395947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phrs.2018.11.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teklehaymanot</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of wild edible plants of Kara and Kwego semi-pastoralist people in lower Omo river valley, Debub Omo zone, SNNPR, Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20712910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1746-4269-6-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2933608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term frequent use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs might protect patients with ankylosing spondylitis from cardiovascular diseases: a nationwide case-control study</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0126347</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0126347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4430238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25970845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsegaye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balehgn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebrehiwot</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebresamuel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aynekulu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of garsa (Dobera glabra) for household food security at times of food shortage in Aba’ala Wereda, North Afar: ecological adaptation and socio-economic value: a study from Ethiopia</article-title><source>DCG Rep.</source><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>A Field Worker's Guide to the Identification, Propagation and Uses of Common Trees and Shrubs of Dryland Sudan</chapter-title><year>1996</year><publisher-name>SOS Sahel</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vukics</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization of flavonoid glycosides by multi-stage mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Mass Spectrom. Rev.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19116944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mas.20212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naturally derived anti-inflammatory compounds from Chinese medicinal plants</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>146</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23274744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jep.2012.12.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risley</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuss</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carrageenin-induced edema in hind paw of the rat as an assay for antiinflammatory drugs</article-title><source>Proc. Soc. Exp. Biol. Med.</source><volume>111</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1962</year><fpage>544</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14001233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3181/00379727-111-27849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zduńska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodziejczak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotsztejn</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant properties of ferulic acid and its possible application</article-title><source>Skin Pharmacol. Physiol.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30235459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000491755</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>