
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JVS Vasc Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JVS Vasc Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4100</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jvssci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101767073</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JVS-Vascular Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-3503</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8034587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8034587.2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8034587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8489207</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33842897</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvssci.2020.09.002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-3503(20)30023-7</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">2</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Neointimal hyperplasia after carotid transection and anastomosis surgery is associated with degradation of decorin and platelet-derived growth factor signaling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Cruz</surname><given-names initials="RJ">Roshan J.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names initials="VB">Valerie B.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Askinas</surname><given-names initials="CA">Carly A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names initials="RA">Rebecca A.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names initials="KG">Karyn G.</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaty</surname><given-names initials="CA">Claude A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hesek</surname><given-names initials="AM">Anne M.</given-names></name><degrees>AS</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akins</surname><given-names initials="RE">Robert E.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, FAHA</degrees><email>robert.akins@nemours.org</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Nemours—Alfred I. duPont Hospital for Children, Wilmington, Del</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Tulane University School of Medicine, New Orleans, La</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Materials Science &amp; Engineering, University of Delaware, Newark, Del</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Delaware, Newark, Del</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Correspondence: Robert E. Akins, PhD, FAHA, Nemours—Alfred I. duPont Hospital for Children, 1600 Rockland Rd, Wilmington, DE 19803 <email>robert.akins@nemours.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">391219</issue-id><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-22 09:00:00.000"><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8034587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvssci.2020.09.002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS1680135</article-id><article-version>1</article-version><pub-date><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date></event><event event-type="pmc-version" specific-use="live"><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8489207</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvssci.2020.09.002</article-id><article-version>2</article-version><pub-date><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of the Society for Vascular Surgery.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="5" journal-id="JVS Vasc Sci" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11563159"><article-title>Retraction notice to “Neointimal hyperplasia after carotid transection and anastomosis surgery is associated with degradation of decorin and platelet-derived growth factor signaling” [JVS–Vascular Science 2 (2021) 2 - 12]</article-title><volume>5</volume><date><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><elocation-id>100216</elocation-id><source>JVS-Vascular Science</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvssci.2024.100216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39544907</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Objective</title><p>Intimal hyperplasia (IH) is the expansion of the vascular intimal region after intervention, which can lead to stenosis and eventual failure of vascular grafts or interventional procedures such as angioplasty or stent placement. Our goals were to investigate the development of IH in a rabbit open surgical model and to evaluate the associated pathophysiologic processes involving decorin and the platelet-derived growth factor-BB/platelet-derived growth factor receptor-β/mitogen-activated protein kinase (PDGF-BB/PDGFR-β/MAPK) pathway.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted carotid transection and primary anastomosis on five New Zealand white rabbits to induce IH and examined the associated pathophysiologic changes. Tissue was obtained for histological and protein analysis on postoperative day 21 using the contralateral vessel as a control. Intimal medial thickness (IMT) was calculated to measure IH and compared with the unoperated side. Western blot analysis was performed on tissue lysates to determine the expression of decorin core protein, PDGF-BB, PDGFR-β, and phosphorylated-MAPK (ph-MAPK). Immunofluorescence microscopy was used to assess tissue distribution of matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) and ph-PDGFR-β.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Bilateral carotid arteries were harvested on postoperative day 21. We compared the IMT in operated with unoperated specimens. IMT was significantly elevated in operated arteries vs unoperated arteries in all five animals (148.6 μm ± 9.09 vs 103.40 μm ± 7.08; 135.2 μm ± 8.30 vs 92.40 μm ± 2.35; 203.1 μm ± 30.23 vs 104.00 μm ± 4.52; 236.2 μm ± 27.22 vs 141.50 μm ± 9.95; 226.9 μm ± 11.12 vs 98.8 μm ± 3.78). Western blot analysis revealed degradation of decorin protein in the operated tissue, including loss of a 50 kDa band and the appearance of a cleaved fragment at 10 kDa. Decorin and MMP-2 were observed, via immunofluorescence microscopy, in the neointima of the operated vessels. Western blot analysis also revealed increased PDGF-BB, PDGFR-β, and ph-MAPK levels in operated tissue. Immunofluorescent staining for ph-PDGFR-β primarily localized to the neointima, indicating increased signaling through PDGF in this region.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Carotid transection and primary reanastomosis in rabbits induced IH that was associated with MMP-2 activation, degradation of decorin, and activation of the PDGF/PDGFR-β/MAPK pathway. The findings in this study should lead to further mechanistic evaluation of these pathways to better understand the potential to modify the intimal hyperplastic response to surgery. (JVS–Vascular Science 2020;2:2-12.)</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical Relevance</title><p>Intimal hyperplasia remains a significant challenge to the vascular surgeon in open and interventional procedures. Basic science studies have made headway into understanding the process, but this has not translated into many therapeutic options particularly for primary prevention after a procedure. Decorin is gaining popularity as an important mediator of various pathophysiologic processes involving the extracellular matrix. We sought to determine the possible role of decorin in the development of neointimal hyperplasia in an open surgical model. This study provides a replicable model for the development of intimal hyperplasia and potential therapeutic targets going forward.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Artery</kwd><kwd>Remodeling</kwd><kwd>Neointima</kwd><kwd>Decorin</kwd><kwd>MAPK</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">
<boxed-text id="dtbox1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Article Highlights</title></caption><p id="p0015">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0020"><bold>Type of Research:</bold> Single-center, prospective study of open arterial surgery in a rabbit model</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>•</label><p id="p0025"><bold>Key Findings:</bold> Carotid transection and reanastomosis surgery leads to intimal hyperplasia and degradation of the proteoglycan decorin in the arterial wall. These changes are associated with an increase in signaling through platelet-derived growth factor-BB (PDGF-BB), PDGF receptor β, and mitogen-activated protein kinase.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>•</label><p id="p0030"><bold>Take Home Message:</bold> Decorin degradation and activation of PDGF-BB/PDGF receptor β/mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling in intimal hyperplasia may provide targets for effective therapy to prevent intimal hyperplasia after arterial surgery.</p></list-item></list>
</p></boxed-text>
</p><p id="p0035">Intimal hyperplasia (IH) is defined as a thickening of the vascular intima due to abnormal accumulation of proliferating and/or migrating cells and deposition of proteoglycan-rich extracellular matrix (ECM).<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Cells in intimal hyperplastic regions originate from the vascular media or adventitia or from circulating progenitor cells.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> IH-associated changes are seen after endovascular and open surgical procedures irrespective of the conduit being used (artery, vein, or prosthetic) and are believed to be major causes of mid-term (30 days to 2 years) negative outcomes, restenosis, and thrombosis in these procedures.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> IH can have significant cost and quality of life consequences for percutaneous coronary and peripheral vascular procedures due to the need for repeat angioplasties or stent placement.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">Although the detailed mechanisms associated with IH are only partially understood, the principal trigger for the development of IH is thought to be the traumatic insult associated with angioplasty or surgery, especially endothelial injury and the associated increase in platelet recruitment and local inflammation.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Numerous studies show that cytokines from activated endothelial cells, inflammatory cells, and recruited platelets act on nearby cells, smooth muscle cells (SMCs) in particular, to alter cell phenotype, stimulate or inhibit proliferation, induce the deposition of collagen and other ECM molecules, and trigger multicellular signaling cascades.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Activated cells recruited to the site of vascular damage can release proteases that damage the arterial wall, especially its elastic laminae, allowing cells to migrate from the adventitial and medial layers into the intima.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Cells within the neointima can include activated medial SMCs, fibroblasts that migrate from the adventitia, or circulating mesenchymal stem cells that differentiate locally to SMCs or fibroblasts within the neointima.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Medial SMCs are thought to be the predominant cell in neointimal formation. However, other heterogeneous cells types (eg, vascular stem cells and migrating adventitial cells) may also contribute.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> In addition, a discrete subpopulation of SMCs within the media have been shown to contribute to neointimal development.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Yuan et al<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> showed that there are varying types of neointima depending on which cell types are primarily activated.</p><p id="p0045">ECM deposition within the neointima critically affects disease progression and pathophysiology. In particular, decorin, a small leucine-rich proteoglycan that binds collagen, is an integral component of ECM in IH.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In general, decorin modulates collagen fibrillogenesis and plays key roles in angiogenesis,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> cancer progression,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> and endothelial and SMC proliferation, migration, and differentiation.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Decorin exerts its effects by direct interaction with collagens,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> cell surface receptors,<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> or cytokines or growth factors.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> The decorin core protein has a single glycosaminoglycan attachment site near the amino terminus, and the linkage of dermatan or chondroitin sulfate at this site is associated with differential decorin localization, function, and growth factor binding.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> In particular, decorin has been shown to bind platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) by preventing it from interacting with its tyrosine kinase receptor, thereby inhibiting downstream activation of the PI3K, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK), and Akt.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In IH, alterations in decorin can result in reduced growth factor binding and consequently increased growth factor activity. These alterations have been implicated in the development of IH through activation of PDGF-related pathways.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p><p id="p0050">Several animal models for studying IH have been developed, with most revolving around percutaneous interventions and arteriovenous fistula surgery.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> To better understand IH in open vascular surgery, we created a model that involves arterial skeletonization, transection, and reanastomosis. In a previous study, our group found that skeletonization alone led to alteration of the vascular ECM as evidenced by disruption of elastin laminae in the media and collagen structure in the adventitial layer within 21 days but was not associated with the development of IH.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Accordingly, we investigated the effects of arterial transection/reanastomosis on IH, degradation of decorin, and PDGF signaling.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0055">(a) List of drugs: see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table I</xref> (b) List of antibodies: see <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref></p><sec id="sec1.1"><title>Surgical procedure and perioperative care</title><p id="p0070">Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee approval for all animal procedures was obtained, and animal care complied with the <italic toggle="yes">Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic>.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> New Zealand white male rabbits were used for the study (weight range, 2.8-3.8 kg) (Covance, Princeton, NJ). Only males were used because of housing and workflow limitations. A preoperative dose of meloxicam (Norbrook Laboratories, Northern Ireland) was given 1 day before surgery. Animals were anesthetized with an initial intramuscular dose of ketamine (35 mg/kg) and xylazine (5 mg/kg). Intravenous access was obtained via an ear vein. Anesthesia was maintained with subsequent doses of ketamine and xylazine as needed to maintain an appropriate level of anesthesia. Euthermia was maintained with the use of a warming pad. Under aseptic conditions, a paramedian skin incision (3-4 cm) was made over the palpable left common carotid artery (CCA). This was extended through the platysma. The plane between the sternomastoid and cleidomastoid muscles was identified and separated to expose the neurovascular bundle (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) containing the CCA and vagus nerve. The left CCA was isolated with a vessel loop. Skeletonization of a 3-cm segment of artery was performed in preparation for clamp application. Intravenous heparin (100 U/kg; Mylan Institutional LLC, Rockford, Ill) was administered, and Schwartz clamps were applied proximally and distally after 3 minutes. Heparin dosing was repeated at 30-minute intervals until arterial clamps were removed. The artery was transected between the clamps, and the cut ends were reanastomosed in an end-to-end fashion with interrupted 7-0 or 8-0 Prolene sutures (Ethicon, Somerville, NJ). The clamps were removed to restore antegrade flow. Care was taken to minimize trauma to the endothelium during all steps of the procedure by minimal handling of the endothelial layer. The platysma was closed with a running 5-0 Vicryl suture (Ethicon). Finally, the skin was closed with a running 5-0 Vicryl subcuticular suture. Postoperatively, the animals were continuously observed until they were sternal and mobile and given an additional dose of meloxicam. Food and water consumption and behavior were monitored throughout the study period (21 days). Ultrasonography was performed preoperatively and on postoperative days 7, 14, and 21 using a Vevo 2100 (VisualSonics, Toronto, Ontario, Canada) with a 40 MHz MicroScan transducer. Brightness mode (B-mode) cine-loop images were obtained in the transverse view to ensure patency of the vessel.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table I</label><caption><p>List of drugs used for the surgical procedures with dose, route, and primary use</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dose</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Route</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Use</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Meloxicam (Norbrook Laboratories, Northern Ireland)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3 mg/kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IM/IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Analgesia</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ketamine (Mylan Institutional LLC, Rockford, Ill)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 mg/kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IM/IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anesthesia induction and maintenance</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xylazine (Lloyd Laboratories, Shenandoah, Iowa)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 mg/kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IM/IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anesthesia induction and maintenance</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cefazolin (Hospira Inc, Lake Forest, Ill)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 mg/kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Antibiotic</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heparin (Mylan institutional LLC, Rockford, Ill)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 U/kg</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Anticoagulant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pentobarbital sodium and phenytoin sodium (Euthasol) (390 mg/mL) (VedCo, St. Joseph, Mo)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5 mL</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Euthanasia</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">IM</italic>, Intramuscular; <italic toggle="yes">IV</italic>, intravenous.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table II</label><caption><p>Antibodies used for western blot and immunofluorescence staining</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Antibody</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Host species</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Isotype</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conjugate</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source (Catalog number)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1. Western blots</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> A. Primary antibodies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-decorin (N-terminal)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sheep</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abcam (ab189071)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-phosphorylated-p 44/42 MAPK (ERK 1/2) (Thr202/Tyr204)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rabbit</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Signaling Technology (9101S)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-PDGFR-β</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rabbit</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Signaling Technology (3169)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-hPDGF-BB</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">R&amp;D Systems (AF-220-NA)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-β-actin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sigma (A5441)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> B. Secondary antibodies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-sheep secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donkey</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HRP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ThermoFisher (A16041)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-rabbit secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HRP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Signaling (7074S)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-mouse secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Horse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HRP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Signaling (7076S)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-goat secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donkey</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HRP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">R&amp;D Systems (HAF 109)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2. Immunofluorescence</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> A. Primary antibodies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-decorin (N-terminal)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sheep</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abcam (ab189071)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-phosphorylated PDGFR-β (Tyr751)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mouse</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG2B</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unconjugated</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cell Signaling (3166S)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-MMP-2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rabbit</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Biotin</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LifeSpan BioSciences (LS-C142016)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> B. Secondary antibodies</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-sheep secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donkey</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alexa Fluor 647</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ThermoFisher (A21448)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Anti-rabbit secondary</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Goat</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">IgG</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alexa Fluor 647</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ThermoFisher (A21245)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Streptavidin peptide</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alexa Fluor 647</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ThermoFisher (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="S21374">S21374</ext-link>)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">HRP</italic>, Horse radish peroxidase; <italic toggle="yes">MAPK</italic>, mitogen-activated protein kinase; <italic toggle="yes">MMP-2</italic>, matrix metalloprotease 2; <italic toggle="yes">PDGFR-β</italic>, platelet-derived growth factor receptor β.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p><bold>A,</bold> Intraoperative image showing operated left common carotid artery (CCA) (<italic toggle="yes">white arrow</italic>) after transection and reanastomosis with adjacent preserved vagus nerve (<italic toggle="yes">yellow arrow</italic>). <bold>B,</bold> Graph showing increased intimal medial thickness (IMT) at the anastomotic site in the operated artery. Each bar represents the mean of eight IMT measurements taken at equal distances along the circumference of the vessel for each animal (<italic toggle="yes">blue</italic> = unoperated artery, <italic toggle="yes">red</italic> = operated artery) (∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). <bold>C,</bold> Hematoxylin and eosin stained section of the anastomotic site of an operated artery with apparent suture holes and residual suture; the <italic toggle="yes">black arrow</italic> represents IMT and the <italic toggle="yes">blue arrow</italic> indicates the region of intimal hyperplasia (scale bar: 400 μm). <bold>D,</bold> Hematoxylin and eosin stained section of an unoperated artery with <italic toggle="yes">black arrow</italic> representing IMT (scale bar: 200 μm).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>Tissue harvest and histological analysis</title><p id="p0075">Euthanasia was achieved in a humane manner after sedation (IM ketamine/xylazine) with intravenous Euthasol (VedCo, St. Joseph, Mo) on postoperative day 21. A 2-cm segment of artery was harvested and included arterial tissue proximal and distal to the anastomotic site. A similar segment of the unoperated right CCA was also excised. Tissue samples were divided into two parts and either fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) (pH 7.0-7.6) (Electron Microscopy Sciences, Hatfield, Pa) for histological analysis or placed in normal saline (0.9%) solution for immediate preparation of tissue lysates for protein analysis. The fixed arteries were dehydrated with graded alcohol and embedded in paraffin. Sections (5 μm) were deparaffinized, stained with hematoxylin and eosin, and imaged at ×20 magnification using the EVOS FL Imaging System (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, Calif). The average intimal medial thickness (IMT) for each vessel was measured at eight sites at equally spaced intervals in a circumferential manner using Image Pro Plus software (version 6.3; Media Cybernetics, Rockville, Md).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Immunological staining and confocal microscopy</title><p id="p0080">Deparaffinized and rehydrated arterial sections (thickness = 5 μm) were used with antigen retrieval by steam heating sections in 10 mM citrate buffer (pH 6.0) for 30 minutes. Samples were permeabilized with 0.1% Triton-X-100 (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Mo) and blocked with 3% bovine serum albumin in PBS-Tween-20 (PBS-T; 0.3% w/v; pH 7.2). Samples were incubated with monoclonal or polyclonal primary antibodies (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>) at 1:100 dilution overnight at 4°C. This was followed by treatment with the appropriate species specific conjugated secondary antibody (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>) for 1 hour at room temperature. Nuclei were stained with Hoechst 33258 dye. Images were obtained using a Zeiss LSM 880 (Coherent Inc, Santa Clara, Calif) confocal microscope with 25× or 63× oil objective lenses (Plan-Apochromat 25×/0.8 Oil, Plan-Apochromat 63×/1.4 Oil, NA = 0.09). Elastin autofluorescence was acquired at 488 nm. Images were processed to optimize brightness and contrast for visualization using Photoshop (version 21.0.1) (Adobe Systems Inc., San Jose, Calif).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Protein analysis of tissue lysates</title><p id="p0085">Unoperated and operated CCA tissue lysates were prepared by homogenization with radio-immunoprecipitation assay buffer (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, Mass) supplemented with a 1× phosphatase and protease inhibitor cocktail (ThermoFisher Scientific). Lysates were precleared by centrifugation (16,200 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>) for 15 minutes, and protein concentrations were determined using the bicinchoninic acid assay (Pierce, Calif).<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Absorbance at 560 nm was taken on a VICTOR X4 2030 Multilabel Plate Reader (PerkinElmer, Waltham, Mass) and compared with a standard curve for the protein estimation of the tissue lysates.</p><p id="p0090">Lysates were denatured with 4× Laemmli sample buffer (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, Calif) and boiled at 100°C for 5 minutes. Proteins were separated on precast 10% SDS-PAGE gels (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, Calif) and transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane (0.2 μm pore size; Invitrogen). Membranes were washed with PBS-T and blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk in PBS-T for 1 hour. Blots were exposed to the respective primary antibody (1:1000 dilution) in 5% bovine serum albumin in PBS-T overnight at 4°C. This was followed by treatment with the appropriate species specific conjugated secondary antibody (1:1000-2000 dilution in 5% non-fat dry milk in PBS-T) for 1 hour at room temperature. Blots were visualized with chemiluminescence detection reagent (Licor, Lincoln, Neb), and imaging was performed using a LiCOR Odyssey (Licor). In some cases, conventional radiographic film (Phoenix Research Products, Pittsburgh, Pa) was used to document blot staining results. Image J was used for the semiquantitative analysis of Western blots via densitometric analysis. The absolute density of each band was normalized to β-actin. The density of the protein band on the operated side was then normalized to the unoperated side, and relative density values were reported.</p><p id="p0095">Staining for β-actin was used as an internal loading control for normalization for all samples.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0100">Statistical analyses were conducted with Prism version 8 (Graphpad Software Inc, San Diego, Calif) using Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test to compare IMT between the operated and unoperated sides. Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05. Data are expressed as the mean values ± standard error.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>IH developed in common carotid arteries after transection and reanastomosis</title><p id="p0105">To evaluate the level of IH on postoperative day 21 in rabbit CCAs, we measured the IMT in paraformaldehyde fixed tissue. Although vascular diameters varied between samples, nonoperated, contralateral control arteries exhibited a normal vascular structure in all cases. Sections of the five operated CCAs were evaluated at the anastomosis and within 0.5 cm distal to it. IH measurements were variable, but all operated arteries developed IH, evidenced by a significant increase in IMT on the operated CCA when compared with unoperated control arteries (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table III</label><caption><p>Intimal medial thickness (<italic toggle="yes">IMT</italic>) in operated vs unoperated carotid arteries for all animals at the level of the anastomosis in tissue harvested on postoperative day 21</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Animal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean IMT of operated side (μm) (±SEM)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean IMT of unoperated side (μm) (±SEM)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148.6 ± 9.09</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103.40 ± 7.08</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.008</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135.2 ± 8.30</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.40 ± 2.35</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">203.1 ± 30.23</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104.00 ± 4.52</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.024</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236.2 ± 27.22</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141.50 ± 9.95</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.011</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">226.9 ± 11.12</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.8 ± 3.78</td><td align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">SEM</italic>, Standard error of the mean.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Alteration of tissue decorin and metalloprotease distribution in the perianastomotic region of operated vessels</title><p id="p0110">In operated arteries, at the level of the anastomosis, thickening between the innermost layer of cells and the internal elastic lamina correlated with increased cell numbers in the neointimal regions, evidenced by nuclear staining in the IH region (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, panels I and IX). Elastin autofluorescence detected with 488 nm excitation revealed fragmentation of the elastic laminae within the medial layer and expansion of the neointima due to deposition of ECM (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, panels II and X). Immunofluorescence microscopy performed at the level of the anastomosis revealed strong signals for decorin in the neointima of operated vessels after surgery (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, panels VII and XV). Decorin staining was also observed in the medial and adventitial layers of the vessel wall. Interestingly, the pattern of decorin distribution appeared more diffuse and less organized in the operated vessels than in unoperated control vessels.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p>Fluorescence micrographs and decorin Western blot showing alteration in the distribution of decorin and matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) in tissue samples harvested on postoperative day 21 (<italic toggle="yes">L</italic> = lumen, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> = intima/neointima, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = media, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> = adventitia). Both decorin and MMP-2 were highly present in the neointima. <bold>A,</bold> Immunofluorescent staining of decorin in unoperated (panels I-VIII) and operated (panels IX-XVI) arteries (level of the anastomosis). Panels I, V, IX, and XIII: DNA staining within the nuclei with Hoechst 33258 (blue); panels II, VI, X, and XIV: elastin autofluorescence (<italic toggle="yes">green</italic>); panels VII and XV: decorin (<italic toggle="yes">red</italic>) (panels III and XI represent negative control staining with secondary antibody only); panels IV, VIII, XII, and XVI: composite image of cell nuclei, elastin, and decorin. <italic toggle="yes">White arrow</italic> indicates neointima. Scale bar = 50 μm. <bold>B,</bold> Western blot of tissue lysates prepared from operated tissue at the anastomotic site and unoperated control tissue to detect decorin. 50 kDa bands were present in all controls but absent in operated tissue samples; 15 kDa fragments representing cleaved decorin protein (cl. decorin) were present in all operated tissue samples. Table represents relative intensities of decorin 50 kDa and 15 kDa bands measured with Image J. Intensities were normalized to β-actin, which was used as the loading control. <bold>C,</bold> Immunofluorescent staining of MMP-2 in unoperated (panels I-VIII) and operated (panels IX-XVI) arteries. Panels I, V, IX, and XIII: DNA staining within the nuclei with Hoechst 33258 (<italic toggle="yes">blue</italic>); panels II, VI, X, and XIV: elastin autofluorescence (<italic toggle="yes">green</italic>); panels VII and XV: MMP-2 (<italic toggle="yes">red</italic>) (III and XI represent staining with secondary antibody only); panels IV, VIII, XII, and XVI: composite image of cell nuclei, elastin, and MMP-2. <italic toggle="yes">White arrow</italic> indicates neointima. Scale bar = 50 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0115">We also examined the level of decorin protein expression within the tissue by semiquantitative Western blot. Fresh tissue lysates were prepared and an anti-decorin antibody that binds near the N-terminus of the decorin core protein (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table II</xref>) was used. Because decorin can be variably glycosylated and can undergo differential proteolytic degradation, it often shows up on Western blots as multiple bands. Banding patterns in our samples demonstrated differences in the decorin composition in the operated vessels compared with the unoperated vessels. Specifically, in the unoperated vessels, several high-molecular-weight decorin bands were located between 50 and 150 kDa with the most prominent bands occurring at 50, 75, and 150 kDa. On the operated side, on the other hand, we noted an N-terminal peptide at 15 kDa for all operated vessels along with decreased expression of the 50 kDa band in comparison with the unoperated vessels (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>).</p><p id="p0120">Previous studies have identified matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) as a key mediator of decorin degradation and reduction of the growth factor binding functions of decorin.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> Accordingly, we performed immunofluorescent staining to localize MMP-2 and observed a signal within the neointimal regions of operated vessels. The distribution pattern of MMP-2 correlated with the expanding neointima (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). Thus, the neointimal expansion observed on the operated side was associated with the degradation of decorin and elevation of MMP-2.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>IH induced by carotid surgery is associated with increased PDGF-BB, PDGFR-β, ph-PDGFR-β, and ph-MAPK expression</title><p id="p0125">PDGF has been implicated in the progression of IH, and multiple reports identify decorin as a key regulator of PDGF-mediated signaling by sequestering the ligand and preventing receptor binding.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> To evaluate the potential contribution of PDGF to IH in our reanastomosis model, we used Western blotting to assess PDGF, PDGFR-β, and downstream MAPK. PDGF-BB, which has been shown to have the highest growth stimulation of SMCs,<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> and total PDGFR-β, which is one of the main targets of PDGF-BB, were assessed. As shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, both were upregulated in operated vessels, compared with unoperated vessels. To further evaluate potential PDGFR signaling, we investigated the activation of PDGFR-β with immunofluorescence microscopy for phosphorylated-PDGFR-β (ph-PDGFR-β). Levels of ph-PDGFR-β appeared to be elevated in operated vessels compared with unoperated vessels, particularly within the neointima, suggesting that there was increased activity through this receptor associated with arterial surgery (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Finally, because PDGFR-β acts via the MAPK pathway, the level of phosphorylated-MAPK (ph-MAPK) intermediate was evaluated next. Western blot analysis revealed increased ph-MAPK in the operated vessels compared with the unoperated control vessels (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). Overall, these results are consistent with activation of the PDGF-BB/PDGFR-β/MAPK signaling pathway in our arterial transection/reanastomosis model.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p>Activation of the platelet-derived growth factor/platelet-derived growth factor receptor/mitogen-activated protein kinase (<italic toggle="yes">PDGF</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">PDGFR</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">MAPK</italic>) pathway in tissue samples harvested on postoperative day 21. <bold>A,</bold> Western blot analysis of tissue lysates for PDGF-BB and PDGFR-β receptor with β-actin as loading control. Table represents relative intensities of PDGF-BB and PDGFR-β measured with Image J. Intensities were normalized to β-actin, which was used as the loading control. Both PDGF-BB and PDGFR-β were upregulated in the operated vessels. <bold>B,</bold> Immunofluorescent staining of unoperated (panels I-VIII) and operated (panels IX-XVI) arteries for phosphorylated PDGFR-β, indicating activated PDGFR signaling in the neointima. Panels I, V, IX, and XIII: DNA staining within the nuclei with Hoechst 33258 (<italic toggle="yes">blue</italic>); panels II, VI, X, and XIV: elastin autofluorescence (<italic toggle="yes">green</italic>); panels VII and XV: phosphorylated PDGFR-β (<italic toggle="yes">red</italic>) (III and XI represent staining with secondary antibody only); panels IV, VIII, XII, and XVI: composite image of cell nuclei, elastin, and phosphorylated PDGFR-β. <italic toggle="yes">White arrow</italic> indicates neointima (<italic toggle="yes">L</italic> = lumen, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> = intima/neointima, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = media, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> = adventitia). Scale bar = 20 μm. <bold>C,</bold> Western blot for ph-MAPK in tissue lysates showing upregulation of MAPK signaling in operated arteries compared with unoperated control arteries. β-Actin antibody was used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0130">Our study demonstrates that IH in an artery-to-artery graft model is associated with alterations in decorin and correlates with elevations of PDFG-BB, PDGFR-β, ph-PDGFR activation, and MAPK signaling. IH is known to be a significant contributor to midterm vascular graft failure after surgery and percutaneous interventions.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Currently, there are no preventive strategies available for IH. Management includes risk factor modifications and invasive percutaneous interventions when clinically significant stenosis develops though this is probably too late in the disease process. A better understanding of the pathophysiology of IH is needed to help in the identification of potential targets for noninvasive therapies and possibly develop ways to prevent the vessel stenosis due to IH.</p><p id="p0135">In this study, we developed a rabbit open surgical model of carotid transection and reanastomosis that was used to investigate the development of IH in operated vessels compared with unoperated, contralateral controls. We also analyzed alterations in the ECM protein decorin, the pathophysiologic signaling pathways associated with decorin disruption, and how these relate to the development of IH in our model. Our study demonstrates varying severity of IH across animals. We believe that the animal to animal variability mimics the clinical spectrum of disease as not all individuals develop clinically significant stenosis. The observation that all animals had statistically significant elevation in IMT is encouraging to us that this is reproducible, though not similar in each animal.</p><p id="p0140">Many previous studies have primarily focused on percutaneous injury models to assess IH.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> In these models, a balloon or wire is passed percutaneously to the target artery and a mechanical injury of the vessel wall is performed to trigger the development of IH. Although these models are suitable to address the mechanism of injury in percutaneous procedures, they may not accurately reflect the changes associated with open surgical procedures due to the differences in the mechanism of injury in open procedures. Open surgeries often involve arterial skeletonization, transection of the vessel, and creation of a new anastomosis. Our model showed that significant IH develops after open carotid transection and reanastomosis as early as 21 days after surgery. This allowed us to investigate the molecular changes associated with IH.</p><p id="p0145">An important component of IH is the alteration in ECM molecules within the wall of the affected vessel. Small leucine-rich proteoglycans have been shown to be pivotal molecules that regulate the assembly of the ECM and affect tissue function.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> In particular, decorin has been linked to vascular effects, and Scott et al<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> have shown that a synthetic decorin mimic decreased SMC proliferation, migration, and protein synthesis in vitro. The mimic also decreased platelet activation in an in vivo swine model,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> which is believed to be an inciting factor in the development of IH.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Using our surgical model, we have linked the degradation of decorin with the development of IH. The appearance of a cleaved N-terminal decorin band at 15 kDa on Western blot was observed only in operated tissue. Detection of this degradation product of decorin by immunofluorescence may result in the diffuse, less organized appearance in the tissues (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, panels VII and XV). This is consistent with previous work, implicating the degradation of decorin by MMP-2, granzyme B, or other enzymes in pathophysiologic conditions.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> MMP-2 elevation has been shown to be a potential biomarker for IH.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> We observed an increase in total MMP-2 staining by immunofluorescence particularly in the neointimal region consistent with possible ongoing turnover of decorin and ECM. Decorin cleavage by MMPs has been shown to enhance angiogenesis due to the loss of the protective role of decorin in corneal neovascularization.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> The immunofluorescence images (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) indicate the distribution of total N-terminal containing decorin per tissue volume, whereas the Western blot images (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) indicate the different decorin moieties per total protein. The difference in the appearance of decorin signals in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, which indicates an increase in decorin per tissue volume, and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, which indicates a decrease in decorin per total protein, may be due to these differences in approach. The change in the banding pattern on Western blot between unoperated and operated vessels, specifically the changes in the 50 and 15 kDa bands, further illustrates that there is a change in the type of decorin.</p><p id="p0150">Alterations in decorin have been linked to loss of its function by decreasing its ability to bind and sequester growth factors.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> This leads to an increase in free PDGF, PDGFR-dependent signaling through MAPK, specifically the ERK1/2 pathway. Subsequent downstream effects include cell proliferation, migration, and differentiation. The hyperplasia and changes in the neointima seen in our surgical model were accompanied by increases in the expression of PDGF-BB, PDGFR-β, and ph-MAPK in operated tissue compared with unoperated controls.</p><p id="p0155">Treatments to control IH primarily involve percutaneous intervention once significant stenosis has occurred and preventive measures have been unsuccessful in translating to clinically approved therapies. Our results suggest that the decorin/PDGF-signaling axis may provide additional therapeutic targets. The possibility that small molecules could be used to block PDGFR or MMPs in order to reduce IH has been tested, but these approaches have not yet translated to clinical utility.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> In addition, the model lends itself to the study of biomarkers associated with disease progression as a means to predict the severity and progression of IH. Studies are currently underway to investigate this possibility. Recently, Neill et al<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> reviewed preclinical studies investigating decorin as a potential therapeutic agent in cancer, which like IH displays dysregulated cell proliferation, migration, and ECM deposition.</p><p id="p0160">Limitations of our study include the use of a healthy animal model with a small number of replicates as a surrogate for vascular surgery in patients with pathology warranting surgery. Only male animals were used because of housing and workflow limitations. We note that reports associate female sex with elevated early and late mortality in coronary artery bypass grafting; however, the reasons for these differences have been ascribed to the smaller body size, smaller arterial diameters, and higher comorbidities seen in the female patients studied.<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> Other reports suggest that sex may not be a factor in survival or that females may actually be protected to some degree.<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> Future studies are necessary to validate these findings in females.The use of an end-to-end anastomosis approach is less common overall in surgery than an end-to-side anastomosis; these different approaches expose vessels to different flow dynamics at the level of the anastomosis. In a transection model, an end-to-end anastomosis preserves the length of the vessel and reduces tension on the anastomosis, and results in lower turbulent flow at the anastomosis compared with an end-to-side anastomosis by preserving the orientation of the vessel. This is a descriptive study of the changes in decorin within operated tissue, and we have not investigated the mechanistic relationship between decorin alterations and the development of IH. Despite these limitations, our model faithfully recapitulates the development of IH in arterial surgery and allows us to study biological effects through the activation of intracellular signal transduction pathways that regulate subsequent pathophysiology.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0165">These studies demonstrate that degradation of decorin is associated with an increase in the activity of the PDGF/PDGFR-β/MAPK signaling pathway and the development of IH in an animal open vascular surgical model of carotid transection and reanastomosis. Transection and primary reanastomosis in a male rabbit carotid artery model resulted in significant IH that was associated with MMP-2 elevation, degradation of decorin, and apparent activation of the PDGF/PDGFR/MAPK pathway. The findings in this study should lead to further mechanistic evaluation of these pathways to better understand the potential to modify the intimal hyperplastic response to surgery.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0170">Conception and design: RD, CB, RA</p><p id="p0175">Analysis and interpretation: RD, VS, RS, KR, RA</p><p id="p0180">Data collection: RD, CA, KR, AH</p><p id="p0185">Writing the article: RD, VS, RA</p><p id="p0190">Critical revision of the article: RD, VS, CA, RS, KR, CB, AH, RA</p><p id="p0195">Final approval of the article: RD, VS, CA, RS, KR, CB, AH, RA</p><p id="p0200">Statistical analysis: Not applicable</p><p id="p0205">Obtained funding: RA</p><p id="p0210">Overall responsibility: RA</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>P.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathobiology of intimal hyperplasia</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><volume>81</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>1254</fpage><lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7953384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/bjs.1800810904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimiento</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teso</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paszkowiak</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smooth muscle cell signal transduction: implications of vascular biology for vascular surgeons</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><volume>45</volume><issue>Suppl A</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>A15</fpage><lpage>A24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17544020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2007.02.06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1939976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaarslan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abud</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albayrak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aykut</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ergur</surname><given-names>B.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silistreli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of resveratrol on intimal hyperplasia and endothelial proliferation of rabbit carotid artery anastomosis</article-title><source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source><volume>20</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25269652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/icvts/ivu316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><part-title>Sabiston Textbook of Surgery: The Biological Basis of Modern Surgical Practice</part-title><edition>20th ed.</edition><year>2016</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathophysiology and burden of restenosis</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><volume>100</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>3K</fpage><lpage>9K</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjcard.2007.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17719351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Protack</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic strategies to combat neointimal hyperplasia in vascular grafts</article-title><source>Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther</source><volume>10</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22651839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1586/erc.12.33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3401520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonatti</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberhuber</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schachner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerer-Lercher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermair</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neointimal hyperplasia in coronary vein grafts: pathophysiology and prevention of a significant clinical problem</article-title><source>Heart Surg Forum</source><volume>7</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14980855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1532/hsf.910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amento</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehsani</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokines and growth factors positively and negatively regulate interstitial collagen gene expression in human vascular smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb</source><volume>11</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>1230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1911708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.atv.11.5.1223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wamhoff</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular regulation of vascular smooth muscle cell differentiation in development and disease</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><volume>84</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15269336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/physrev.00041.2003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating bone marrow cells can contribute to neointimal formation</article-title><source>J Vasc Res</source><volume>38</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11316947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000051038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoggatt</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burlak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Offermanns</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Previously differentiated medial vascular smooth muscle cells contribute to neointima formation following vascular injury</article-title><source>Vasc Cell</source><volume>6</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25309723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/2045-824X-6-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4193961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foote</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive proliferation of a subset of differentiated, yet plastic, medial vascular smooth muscle cells contributes to neointimal formation in mouse injury and atherosclerosis models</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><volume>119</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1313</fpage><lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27682618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.309799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5149073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of vascular cells to neointimal formation</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e0168914</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28060852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0168914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5218548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krusius</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary structure of an extracellular matrix proteoglycan core protein deduced from cloned cDNA</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>83</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>7683</fpage><lpage>7687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3484330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.83.20.7683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC386785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nili</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheema</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barolet</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babaei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin inhibition of PDGF-stimulated vascular smooth muscle cell function: potential mechanism for inhibition of intimal hyperplasia after balloon angioplasty</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><volume>163</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)63447-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1868258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvelainen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sainio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wight</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pivotal role for decorin in angiogenesis</article-title><source>Matrix Biol</source><volume>43</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25661523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.matbio.2015.01.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4560244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>R.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin: a guardian from the matrix</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><volume>181</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22735579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajpath.2012.04.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3409438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvinen</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin: a growth factor antagonist for tumor growth inhibition</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><volume>2015</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>654765</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26697491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2015/654765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4677162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schonherr</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waddington</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin regulates endothelial cell motility on collagen I through activation of insulin-like growth factor I receptor and modulation of alpha2beta1 integrin activity</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>283</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>17406</fpage><lpage>17415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18413316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M710025200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>R.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin binds to a narrow region of the epidermal growth factor (EGF) receptor, partially overlapping but distinct from the EGF-binding epitope</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>277</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>35671</fpage><lpage>35681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12105206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M205317200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comalada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xaus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valledor</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloberas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin reverses the repressive effect of autocrine-produced TGF-beta on mouse macrophage activation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>170</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>4450</fpage><lpage>4456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12707320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.170.9.4450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural correlations in the family of small leucine-rich repeat proteins and proteoglycans</article-title><source>J Struct Biol</source><volume>155</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16884925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsb.2006.01.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the dimeric protein core of decorin, the archetypal small leucine-rich repeat proteoglycan</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>101</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>15633</fpage><lpage>15638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0402976101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC524833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin and its galactosaminoglycan chain: extracellular regulator of cellular function?</article-title><source>IUBMB Life</source><volume>60</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18800386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/iub.115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumsden</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mouse models of neointimal hyperplasia: techniques and applications</article-title><source>Med Sci Monit</source><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>RA177</fpage><lpage>RA185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16940942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alp</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banning</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Channon</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased intimal hyperplasia in experimental vein graft stenting compared to arterial stenting: comparisons in a new rabbit model of stent injury</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><volume>56</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12237177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0008-6363(02)00503-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemson</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daemen</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitslaar</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tordoir</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new animal model to study intimal hyperplasia in arteriovenous fistulas</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><volume>85</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10383837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jsre.1999.5566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hesek</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodford</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amir</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Planchon</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced arterial elasticity due to surgical skeletonization is ameliorated by abluminal PEG hydrogel</article-title><source>Bioeng Transl Med</source><volume>2</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28932820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/btm2.10060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5579730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Research Council (US) Committee for the Update of the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</collab></person-group><part-title>Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</part-title><edition>8th ed.</edition><year>2011</year><publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radke</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of protein using flow injection analysis with bicinchoninic acid</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><volume>161</volume><year>1987</year><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3578779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0003-2697(87)90665-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierschbacher</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of decorin by matrix metalloproteinases: identification of the cleavage sites, kinetic analyses and transforming growth factor-beta1 release</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>322</volume><issue>Pt 3</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9148753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/bj3220809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1218259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Amore</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth factor effects on cells of the vascular wall: a survey</article-title><source>Growth Factors</source><volume>8</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7680568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/08977199309029135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paderi</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panitch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin mimic inhibits vascular smooth muscle proliferation and migration</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>e82456</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24278482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0082456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3838406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolva</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albertini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvillo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A successful experimental model for intimal hyperplasia prevention using a resveratrol-delivering balloon</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><volume>63</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25446284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2014.09.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birk</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The regulatory roles of small leucine-rich proteoglycans in extracellular matrix assembly</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><volume>280</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2120</fpage><lpage>2137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/febs.12136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3651807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Breton</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plow</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of platelets in restenosis after percutaneous coronary revascularization</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>28</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8962547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0735-1097(96)00417-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shackleford</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanden Hoek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Granzyme B cleaves decorin, biglycan and soluble betaglycan, releasing active transforming growth factor-beta1</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>e33163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0033163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3316562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tummers</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mountain</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mix</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassada</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum levels of matrix metalloproteinase-2 as a marker of intimal hyperplasia</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><volume>160</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19726059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jss.2009.04.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onguchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MT1-MMP-mediated cleavage of decorin in corneal angiogenesis</article-title><source>J Vasc Res</source><volume>46</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19571574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000226222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3709025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Englesbe</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenagy</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clowes</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concomitant blockade of platelet-derived growth factor receptors alpha and beta induces intimal atrophy in baboon PTFE grafts</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><volume>39</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14743150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvs.2003.07.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitogenesis of vascular smooth muscle cell stimulated by platelet-derived growth factor-bb is inhibited by blocking of intracellular signaling by epigallocatechin-3-O-gallate</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><volume>2013</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>827905</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24307927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2013/827905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3836374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Englesbe</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenagy</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arterial injury repair in nonhuman primates—the role of PDGF receptor-beta</article-title><source>J Surg Res</source><volume>119</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15126086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jss.2003.10.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iozzo</surname><given-names>R.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin as a multivalent therapeutic agent against cancer</article-title><source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source><volume>97</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26522384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.addr.2015.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4753134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gertner</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weymann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veres</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Female gender and differences in outcome after isolated coronary artery bypass graft surgery: does age play a role?</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>e0145371</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26845158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0145371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4741386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toumpoulis</surname><given-names>I.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaram</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rokkas</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swistel</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of independent predictors for long-term mortality between women and men after coronary artery bypass grafting: are women different from men?</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><volume>131</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16434263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2005.08.056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faerber</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zacher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reents</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boergermann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kappert</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boening</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Female sex is not a risk factor for post procedural mortality in coronary bypass surgery in the elderly: a secondary analysis of the GOPCABE trial</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e0184038</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28854266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0184038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5576733</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d35e586"><p id="ntpara0020q">The sources of funds and resources supporting the study included the <funding-source id="gs4"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100012465</institution-id><institution>Nemours Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>; the <funding-source id="gs5">Delaware Bioscience Center for Advanced Technology</funding-source>; the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>NIH</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><funding-source id="gs6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000050</institution-id><institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grant <italic toggle="yes">Cell Instructive Materials for Engineering Vascular Grafts</italic> (R01 HL108110); the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>NIH</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><funding-source id="gs7"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000050</institution-id><institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grant <italic toggle="yes">Instructive Materials for Directing Neovascularization and Inflammation</italic> (F32 HL127983); and the <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000057</institution-id><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grants <italic toggle="yes">The Delaware IDeA Network for Biomedical Research Excellence</italic> (P20 GM103446).</p></fn><fn id="d35e628"><p id="ntpara0010">Author conflict of interest: none.</p></fn><fn id="d35e631"><p id="ntpara0015">The editors and reviewers of this article have no relevant financial relationships to disclose per the JVS-Vascular Science policy that requires reviewers to decline review of any manuscript for which they may have a conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>