
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chic Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4237</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">chicmedj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0027576</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Chicago Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Journal Digitization Project</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9801800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9801800.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9801800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9801800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37412893</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Contributions</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Treatment of Malarial Disease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names initials="W">W.</given-names></name><degrees>M. D.</degrees><aff id="af1-chicmedj144546-0007">Benjaminville, Ill.</aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>1867</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">424799</issue-id><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>1867</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-12 18:25:09.330"><day>12</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="cc0license">https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is free of known copyright restrictions. For more information, please see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="//www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/scanning/">PMC Back Issue Digitization</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="chicmedj144546-0007.pdf"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><preformat preformat-type="pmc-ocr-text" xml:space="preserve" position="float" orientation="portrait">
					﻿Treatment of Malarial Disease.—By W. Anderson, M.D., of&#xD;
Benjaminville, Ill.&#xD;
The commonly received opinion of medical writers and phy-&#xD;
sicians generally, is, that the above class of diseases is of a&#xD;
zymotic character, or, at least, that they are produced by the&#xD;
continual presence, in the blood, of a morbific and foreign&#xD;
substance. Hence, medical men continually talk of cleansing&#xD;
the system by means of emetics, cathartics, cholagogues, dia-&#xD;
phoretics, diuretics, etc.; and we hear such phrases as, “eradi-&#xD;
cating the disease,” “driving it out of the system,” and the&#xD;
like. The last article I read was devoted entirely to diuretics.&#xD;
It might do for old women and empirics to talk of such things,&#xD;
but certainly not for a philosophical physician. For conven-&#xD;
ience, I will confine myself to ague, as a type of the whole&#xD;
class. Some of the foregoing remedies, and others that might&#xD;
be mentioned, might serve a purpose in particular emergencies,&#xD;
but, in my humble opinion, they have little or no bearing on&#xD;
the disease itself, and are as often injurious, by weakening and&#xD;
otherwise injuring the system, as they are beneficial. Judging&#xD;
from experience and my opinion, (as well as that of some emi-&#xD;
nent writers,) antipeYiodics are alone beneficial in all cases.&#xD;
Even cholagogues should be dispensed with, except the biliary&#xD;
symptoms are very prominent; for their secondary effect is to&#xD;
rendei* the portal system more torpid, the same as cathartics&#xD;
exhaust the action of the bowels.&#xD;
I do not derive these opinions from experience alone, but&#xD;
also from what I conceive to be the true nature of the disease.&#xD;
I do not believe malarious poison to be zymotic; that a small&#xD;
portion operates on the blood like contagion, and produces, cat-&#xD;
alytically, an indefinite quantity of a similar material, though&#xD;
this opinion is very generally received. Were it true, then,&#xD;
ague would be of the character of contagious diseases, to which&#xD;
it bears no possible resemblance, and, what is more certain, a&#xD;
very small portion of the morbific matter would produce the&#xD;
disease, and every individual in miasmatic districts would be&#xD;
troubled with the affection continually.&#xD;
If this theory were true, it does not follow that depleting&#xD;
remedies are available, for who would think of eradicating var-&#xD;
iola or measles from the system in such a way, or of using them&#xD;
at all, except as palliating measures?&#xD;
Nor is it probable that the removal of the cause will cure the&#xD;
disease. If a small portion of medicine breaks the paroxysms,&#xD;
by neutralizing the poison, it follows that a necessary quan-&#xD;
tity of the same medicine would neutralize all the poison in the&#xD;
system, and that thejre would be no relapse till farther exposure&#xD;
to the original cause, which we all know is not the fact. The&#xD;
morbific matter, if not continued by zymotic action or renewed&#xD;
by repeated exposure, probably does not remain in the system&#xD;
over thirty-six hours, yet, with the best treatment and in the&#xD;
purest atmosphere, the disease often lingers and is liable to&#xD;
return for many weeks. From this, it is reasonable to conclude&#xD;
that the commonly received opinion of medical men (and the&#xD;
learned Headland, in particular,) in regard to the action of&#xD;
quinia and other antiperiodics, namely, that they neutralize&#xD;
the malarial poison, etc., is not correct, and also that this dis-&#xD;
ease is a nervous affection alone, which, when once established,&#xD;
is no longer dependent upon its original cause.&#xD;
If these views are correct, it obviously follows that medicine&#xD;
which acts merely upon the blood, liver, etc., is of little or no&#xD;
avail in the ordinary treatment of the milder form of these dis-&#xD;
orders, and, when not available, are actually injurious, by&#xD;
weakening the system. These remarks, of course, do not ap-&#xD;
ply to stimulants and tonics, many of which are antiperiodic&#xD;
in their nature and support the nervous system, which is doubt-&#xD;
less the real and only seat of the disease, all other morbid&#xD;
phenomena being only symptoms.&#xD;
A diversity of remedies may serve to amuse the patient, but&#xD;
in my practice I have but little use for anything save antiperi-&#xD;
odics, with a very few palliatives during the paroxysms. Nor&#xD;
do I consider antiperiodics as specifics. I believe they merely&#xD;
support the nerves against a relapse till they regain their natu-&#xD;
ral vigor. I believe they all act in the same manner, and that&#xD;
those which have sufficient power are about equally curative.&#xD;
Their order of efficiency is, in my opinion, as follows:—quinia,&#xD;
arsenic, salicine, etc. In all that has been written during the&#xD;
past twenty-five years, I think there has been no improvement&#xD;
on the plain, simple, and comprehensive plan of treatment, in&#xD;
ordinary agues and remittents, laid down by the illustrious&#xD;
Watson. His views of the nature of the disease, however, are&#xD;
not explicit, nor have they been much elucidated by more re-&#xD;
cent authors.
				</preformat></body><floats-group><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="sp1" content-type="scanned-page" xlink:role="53" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="chicmedj144546-0007.jpg"/><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="sp2" content-type="scanned-page" xlink:role="54" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="chicmedj144546-0008.jpg"/><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="sp3" content-type="scanned-page" xlink:role="55" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="chicmedj144546-0009.jpg"/></floats-group></article>