
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101672560</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10008990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10008990.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10008990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10008990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36923855</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e12306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(22)03594-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e12306</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Weibo users and Academia's foci on tourism safety: Implications from institutional differences and digital divide</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="L">Liyun</given-names></name><email>nonsar@foxmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="RYM">Rita Yi Man</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="H">Huiling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Civil &amp; Architecture Engineering School, Panzhihua University, Panzhihua, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Sustainable Real Estate Research Center, Hong Kong Shue Yan University, Hong Kong, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Rajamangala University of Technology Tawan-ok, Bangkok, Thailand</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. <email>nonsar@foxmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">429787</issue-id><elocation-id>e12306</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-03 20:25:13.160"><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2022 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Tourism safety is essential for tourists and tourism practitioners. This study conducted a bibliometric analysis using VOSviewer and CiteSpace for 2018 articles indexed on the Web of Science (WoS). It also analysed 7293 Weibo posts between 1977 and 2022 using Python, MYSQL, AI sentiment, and Tableau. The first tourism safety publication on WoS appeared in 1977, while the first Weibo microblog dated was dated back to 2011. Compared to the information posted on Weibo, the annual publications about tourism safety on WoS recorded a stable increment. On Web of Science (WoS), the academic staff and universities produced the largest number of tourism safety posts. On the flip side, the most productive organisations on Weibo are government agencies in popular tourism destinations. “Accident”, “medical tourism”, “environment”, “mediating role”, and “hospitality” were important burst nodes in tourism safety on WoS. “Quality”, “accident”, and health-related words were the foci on both Weibo and WoS. On Web of Science, the top 10 most popular keywords of tourism safety-related articles could be classified into two groups: health (“Covid-19”, “restoration”, “pandemics”, “Sars-Cov-2”, “Sars”, “mental health”) and IT terminologies (“big data”, “artificial intelligence”). It has been concluded that “artificial intelligence (AI)” is more likely to be included in the keywords on tourism researched by academia. In contrast, the public may not know about or use AI in the tourism industry. Besides, the top 10 most popular keywords on Weibo related to tourism risks and hazards were drowning and traffic risks and hazards, such as drowning and traffic risks. The digital divide may explain such a difference: the academic circle benefits more from the digital age than laypersons. It may also be the result of institutional differences and information asymmetry.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tourism safety</kwd><kwd>Web of science</kwd><kwd>Weibo</kwd><kwd>Bibliometrics</kwd><kwd>Comparative analysis</kwd><kwd>Artificial intelligence</kwd><kwd>Digital divide</kwd><kwd>Information asymmetry</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">With millions of active users per month, Weibo is one of the most popular social media in China. Information from Weibo is an essential source for studies in science and social sciences. Aside from providing advertisements and marketing services, Weibo plays an important role in emergency management, which is related to public health and safety [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The posting patterns and behaviours on Weibo during the COVID-19 pandemic were studied [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In a study on Sina Weibo (2013–2020), Song et al. [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] investigated the development of various approaches to pediatric care in the public sphere. Based on Weibo big data, scholars could identify rainstorm disasters in real-time [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. For example, Shan et al. [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] developed a real-time disaster damage assessment model based on Weibo's data. Furthermore, social media is an important data source that reflects various social dynamics. As social media and platforms have gained popularity, many people have begun to share their ideas about tourism safety via Weibo using smartphones [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], which makes it less difficult to document their daily life through words, pictures, videos, emotions, etc.</p><p id="p0015">Many people think that there are significant differences between the real world and academia. For example, the artificial intelligence technologies that are developed in university labs may end up not being put to practical use. Differences between laypersons and academia have become one of the research topics in the academic circle. For example, Zeng and Li [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] studied the construction safety and health hazard awareness of users on the Web of Science and Weibo between 1991 and 2021. They demonstrated that academia focused more on high technology, such as artificial intelligence, while Weibo users seldom did so [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. As comparative analysis between the Web of Science (WoS) and Sina Weibo on tourism safety is scarce, this study aims to fill in the academic gaps in this context.</p><p id="p0020">Due to information asymmetry and people's cognitive limitations under the new institutional economics, individual perceptions and foci on a subject are affected by their backgrounds [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Policymakers, academics, and laypersons are from different backgrounds and may have different ideas and thoughts on the same issue. For example, one of the previous studies found that the public's risk perception of nanotechnologies was generally higher than those of academics and policymakers [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. On the contrary, nanotechnology in food and cosmetics/sunscreens was considered riskier, irrespective of stakeholders, including academics, policymakers and laypersons [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The “digital divide” that is caused by the discrepancy between demographic data and areas with access to current information, as well as communications technologies, might also lead to a difference in perception between laypersons and academia. Therefore, microblogs and journal articles were expected to have a different approach to tourism safety. Weibo posts are made by celebrities, government agencies, social organisations and laypersons, while papers indexed in WoS mainly constitute academic papers. The results of this study can provide useful information to tourism practitioners and academia towards the conduct of impactful research.</p><p id="p0025">The research objectives include a bibliometric analysis of the targeted organisations with regard to tourism safety on WoS, an analysis of the trend of tourism safety, and a comparison between academic and public positions on tourism safety.</p><p id="p0030">There are eight sections in this study. Section <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">1</xref> is the introduction, Section <xref rid="sec2" ref-type="sec">2</xref> is the conceptual framework of the study, and section <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="sec">3</xref> describes the research method and framework. Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref> introduces the related publications and information on WoS and Weibo. Section <xref rid="sec5" ref-type="sec">5</xref> presents the results and a discussion on WoS. A comparative analysis between WoS and Weibo is included in Section <xref rid="sec6" ref-type="sec">6</xref>. Section <xref rid="sec7" ref-type="sec">7</xref> describes the conclusion of the study. Finally, the research limitations and further directions are covered in Section <xref rid="sec8" ref-type="sec">8</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Conceptual framework</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Tourism safety</title><p id="p0035">Tourism safety refers to the personal and psychological safety of tourists as well as to the protection of their properties [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It is an important issue affecting travellers and destination operators worldwide [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Tourism safety is also a factor of critical success towards tourism-led economic growth [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Maintaining and ensuring the safety of tourists has become even more important with an increased number of tourists travelling overseas for business and leisure purposes. Nevertheless, tourists' safety is one of the most challenging issues in the tourism industry [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Disasters or accidents are the main problems for tourism safety. For example, many tourists lost their lives in the 2011 Japan earthquake [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In New Zealand's adventure tourism, falls from height injuries were the most common ones among visitors, and involved accidents of falling from moving vehicles or animals (cycle touring, quad biking, horse riding and whitewater rafting) [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In 2003, 595 tourists lost their lives visiting Thailand [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In China, Zoonotic diseases in tourist areas attracted scholarly attention. Some scholars studied how to prevent imported zoonotic diseases, reduce their spread and improve tourism safety [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Some tourists died from tsunami in southern Thailand in 2004 [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In China and Romania, geological disasters imposed safety risks on the mountain tourism [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In April 2016, two earthquakes in Kumamoto seriously affected tourists in the area [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. All in all, tourism safety incidents have attracted scholarly attention worldwide.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Tourism safety as an emerging topic in academia</title><p id="p0040">Tourism safety has been a point of study for various researchers with different perspectives. Tourism safety problems and issues have been analysed in different tourist segments. Regarding leisure tourism safety, some scholars have proposed a theoretical framework that includes the fire-scenario-related effects, hazard distances, and response time scales of fuel leaks and smoke spread from the cruise tourism [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Also, regarding gender tourism safety, lesbian, gay, bisexual, or transgender (LGBT) tourism is an emerging topic in academia. Safe destinations and cultural conservativeness influenced the travel decisions of gay people in Asia [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Some scholars examine different ways of adopting a feminist approach towards tourism safety research. Tourism safety and approaches to risk factors were reflected in the diverse activities of women who were aware of the risks involved in tourism and underlying power relationships [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p id="p0045">Tourists' main concerns regarding adventure tourism, physical safety, travel comfort and experience quality were found to be about wilderness tourism [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In winter tourism, leisure enthusiasts’ practice without ski lifts was affected by avalanche hazards in remote areas [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Mou et al. [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] found that the safety of the national highway infrastructure and the availability of tourism infrastructure were crucial factors that affected tourists who joined bike tourism in Tibet. Murgante et al. [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] reported that safety was one of the major factors affecting desert tourism.</p><p id="p0050">What is more, the way that tourist safety is perceived plays an important role in tourism safety as they mitigate the risk of life-threatening events in cruise tourism according to [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Indeed, “safety perception” is a factor that affects tourists’ motivation for adventure tourism activities to a great extent [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p id="p0055">Furthermore, ecological, and environmental safety also constitute an emerging topic over recent years. Scholars evaluate mountain tourism's ecological safety by taking China's Qilian Mountains National Park as an example. They proposed an index for diagnosing significant obstacles, including the excessive use of natural resources, massive pollutants (solid waste, sewage) discharged into nature, and extreme concentrations of sulphur dioxide and carbon dioxide [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Yang et al. [<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] explored tourist viewpoints around safety and microclimates and suggested ways to mitigate safety problems.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Sina Weibo is one of the most convenient and popular social media</title><p id="p0060">Social media platforms are increasingly becoming central sources of information and communication exchange for people [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A growing number of people are using the internet to discuss about various social topics and express opinions and attitudes [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. For example, Weibo was launched by Sina Corporation in 2009 as a microblogging application. As of Q4 2019, it had over 516 million monthly active users (compared to Twitter's 300 million users), making it the largest social media platform in China, second to WeChat [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. As of the end of the first quarter of 2022, the monthly active users of Weibo reached 582 million in number, with a net year-on-year increase of 51 million, and the daily active users reached 252 million with a net year-on-year increase of 22 million [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Characterised as open access, convenient, and efficient social media, Weibo has become one of the most important social network platforms [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is a leading social media for people who create, share, and discover content online and it combines different ways of expressing oneself publicly in real-time with a powerful platform available for social interaction, content aggregation, and distribution [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p id="p0065">According to the official websites of Weibo [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], its popularity is based on the following reasons. The speed of information dissemination on Weibo is faster compared to other websites. If we take COVID-19 as an example, we can see that before the media broadcasted the news about it, the netizens had already started posting information about what later became a pandemic situation. What is more, information dissemination on Weibo is broader as more people follow the news that Weibo users forward. Moreover, new media allow more freedom of speech and expression and the censorship mechanism for media like Weibo is less complicated than in traditional media. Furthermore, the expression of public opinion on Weibo offers useful advice towards emerging social issues. Tourism safety is no exception. In addition, there are diverse users on Weibo, including sports and entertainment stars, professionals, tourists, help seekers, sharers, idlers, etc. Thus, it is necessary to take Sina Weibo as a case study and to conduct research on public opinion on tourism safety.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Research method and research framework</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Research method: bibliometrics analysis</title><p id="p0070">Bibliometrics has become a major tool for the evaluation of scientific research. By visualising metrics that contain quantitative data about a domain, scientometrics allows researchers to gain insights into the research focus, including institutions, scholars, etc. [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. At the same time, there is more in-depth scientometrics analysis in different scientific domains [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Previous studies adopted the bibliometrics approach in the safety research domain, including construction safety [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], shipboard decision support systems for accident prevention [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], Arctic shipping risk management [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], etc. The application of bibliometrics in tourism safety is scarce. Besides, only a few studies have conducted a comparative analysis based on social media like Weibo.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Research framework</title><p id="p0075">The research framework of the study is shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. In the WoS Core Collection, the topic “tourism safety” was used to search for the related papers sorted by title, abstract, and authors’ keywords on January 11, 2022, and 3850 documents from the earliest publication dates in 1977–2022 were searched. The document type was used as a criterion to select articles and reviews and those were later separated from the rest of the literature.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Research framework.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">As shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, there were two steps in screening the literature. This study removed any irrelevant articles based on topics and titles, such as medical safety, food safety, etc., leaving behind 2507 articles. Then, the researchers screened out the documents in which the abstracts, objectives and aims were unrelated to tourism safety. This study finally included 2018 documents. In addition, 7293 microblogs were included after deduplication. The keywords were used for retrieving the tourism safety-related content on Weibo using Python 3.6.1 and MySQL.</p><p id="p0085">VOSviewer is a software used to create maps based on network data and it visualises and explores these maps. It is a visual analysis software for business intelligence. The research samples of 2018 documents from WoS were visualised using VOSviewer 1.6.17, including published sources, research organisations, keywords, researchers, countries, and papers. 7293 Weibo microblogs, including their publication time, content, keywords, username, number of likes, reposting and comments, were analysed using Tableau 2021.3.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>The trend of publications and posts about tourism safety on WoS and Weibo</title><p id="p0090"><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows that the number of publications on tourism safety on WoS is smaller than that of Weibo posts on the same topic. Compared with information posted on Weibo, the annual publications on WoS about tourism safety recorded a relatively stable increase. On WoS, the first document related to tourism safety appeared in 1997, while the first information on Weibo about tourism safety was posted in 2011. There was an increase in tourism safety publications indexed on WoS from 2008 to 2013. While the number of posts on Weibo rose from 2011 to 2014, it dropped in 2015. In 2015, the number of publications decreased to 76. Wang and Yang [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] pointed out that according to the overall classification of the top 100 popular events on Sina Weibo, the most popular events in the previous two years included stars and entertainment, policies and systems, and community and sustenance topics. That said, tourism attracted less attention than the abovementioned topics on Weibo.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Annual publications and posts on tourism safety on WoS and Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0095">On WoS, the number of documents related to tourism safety has increased since 2016, indicating that tourism safety is an emerging topic in academia. In 2016, Weibo's microblogs about tourism safety also started to increase in number. In 2017, the number of posts peaked at 1468 and then declined to 15 and 11 in 2018 and 2019, respectively. According to the report by Weibo [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], tourist expenses accounted for a higher percentage of all topics in 2016. In 2017, some hot topics about tourism safety attracted an increasing number of user attention on tourism safety, including hashtags #Jiu Zhai Gou earthquake, #travel tips, #visitors opening their windows to eat got bitten by black bears, # Bali Agung volcano eruption, etc. [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In 2018, although tourism was among the top 25 hot searches, the topics about tourism centred around complaints about hospitality, airport tickets, and overseas travel, especially on 15th March [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], were not directly related to tourism safety. In 2019, the hot topics mainly focused on entertainment, electronic products made in China, sports events, National Day, etc. [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. At the end of 2019, health, safety and security were at the heart of the closed and controlled tourism development during the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. As one of the first COVID-19 epicentres, China had fewer visitors during the epidemic [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p id="p0100">Between 2020 and 2021, especially during the post-COVID-19 period when some scenic spots removed restrictions on tourists, the number of posts about tourism safety increased from 132 to 474 on Weibo. The number of relevant journal articles published on WoS peaked at 365 in 2021.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Results and discussion on WoS</title><sec id="sec5.1"><label>5.1</label><title>Research organisation</title><p id="p0105">The research organisations' productivity, citations, average citations, and average norm citations about tourism safety are shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In VOSviewer, an organisation's minimum number of relevant documents was set to 5. What is more, only 187 out of 2635 organisations fit the research criteria when the minimum number of citations for an organisation was set as 2. The strengths of the co-authorship links with other organisations were calculated, and the organisations with the most important link were selected as visualised pictures from VOSviewer. 187 items in the network were not linked to the remaining ones and, the most extensive set of related items was 163.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Research organisations on WoS in the context of tourism safety.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Top ten most cited research organisations in tourism safety research.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0090">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Organisation</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Documents)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Norm. citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. pub. Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. norm. citations)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hongkong Polytechnic University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">983</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pennsylvania State University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">637</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">University of Surrey</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">608</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arizona State University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kansas State University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">592</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Griffith University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">525</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bournemouth University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">502</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Texas A&amp;M University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">484</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">James Cook University</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">444</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">University of Central Florida</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">440</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0110">The Chinese Academy of Sciences produced the most significant number of documents about tourism safety on WoS (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Capital Normal University, Griffith University and National Cheng Kung University were among the top 5 most productive organisations in delivering tourism safety-related publications. Hong Kong Polytechnic University (983) was the most cited organisation for articles on tourism safety (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The top 10 most cited organisations with over 400 citations were Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Pennsylvania State University (637), University of Surrey (608), Arizona State University (600), Kansas State University (592), Griffith University (525), Bournemouth University (502), Texas A&amp;M University (484), James Cook University (444) and University of Central Florida (440). These organisations were also productive institutions with significant influence in the tourism safety academic circle. The Chinese Academy of Sciences and Hongkong Polytechnic University were more prolific in delivering tourism safety-related content on WoS.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><label>5.2</label><title>Cited countries/regions</title><p id="p0115">In VOSviewer, the minimum number of documents of a country was 5, the minimum number of a country's citations was 2, and the citation threshold of 109 organisations was 64. The most extensive set of related items consisted of 62 items. As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, the USA, the People's Republic of China, Australia, the UK, and Spain were the top 5 productive countries publishing tourism safety research. Amongst them, the USA was not only the most popular but also the most cited country in tourism safety research. Besides, the People's Republic of China, the UK, Australia, and Spain were also active in this research area, as shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Countries/regions active in tourism safety research on WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The top ten most cited countries/regions in tourism safety research.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0095">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Label</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Documents)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Normalised citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average publication Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average normalised<break/>citations)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">USA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">442</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8959</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">529.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peoples Republic of China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">385</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4865</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">402.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3656</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">234.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Australia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">188</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3259</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">209.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">158.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1957</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Netherlands</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1459</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Italy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1338</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Korea</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1325</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1170</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><label>5.3</label><title>Research sources</title><p id="p0120">Out of 815 papers, 69 met the threshold requirements in VOSviewer when the minimum number of documents and citations of a source was set as 5 and 2, respectively. The most extensive set of related items consisted of 54 items. “Tourism Management”<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> “Sustainability”, “Current Issues in Tourism”, “International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health” and “Journal of Coastal Research” published the most considerable number of papers in the academic community on tourism safety (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Research sources in tourism safety research from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">Tourism Management can be considered the most influential journal in the academic community of tourism safety. As shown in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, “Tourism Management” was the most-cited journal (5,462). “Annals of Tourism Research”, “Food Control”, “Journal of Travel Research”, “Current Issues in Tourism”, “International Journal of Hospitality Management” and “International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management” were highly cited, and thus they have a significant influence on tourism safety research.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Top ten most cited research sources in tourism safety research from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0100">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">label</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Documents)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Norm. citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. pub. Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. citation)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Avg. norm. citation)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tourism Management</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5462</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">208.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annals of Tourism Research</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1122</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Food Control</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">867</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Travel Research</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">782</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Current Issues in Tourism</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">659</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">International Journal of Hospitality Management</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">610</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">577</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">International Journal of Tourism Research</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">469</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Coastal Research</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">414</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">370</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><label>5.4</label><title>Keywords</title><sec id="sec5.4.1"><label>5.4.1</label><title>Co-occurrence of keywords</title><p id="p0130">A total of 622 out of 10,492 keywords met the threshold requirements when the minimum number of occurrences of a keyword was set at 5 in VOSviewer. Before visual analysis, “tourism”, “safety”, and some other keywords were removed to enable us to see what keywords were included clearly. Besides, the keywords with the same meaning were combined. For example, “covid-19”, “covid-19 pandemic”, and “coronavirus” were combined in one keyword, “covid-19”. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, “management” was the keyword with the largest node size. Other highly mentioned keywords included “impact”, “perceptions”, “risk”, “behaviour”, “covid-19”, “satisfaction”, “food safety”, “quality”, and “health” (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Co-occurrence of keywords in tourism safety research from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0135">As shown in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, covid-19 was the latest popular keyword, with an average year of publication of 2020.9. “SARS” (2020.9), “restoration” (2020.8), “pandemic” (2020.8), “sars-cov-2” (2020.7), “mental health” (2020.6), “acceptance” (2020.5), “big data” (2020.5), “artificial intelligence” (2020.5), and “tourism destination” (2020.4) were also amongst the top 10 latest keywords related to tourism safety. This indicates that health problems, such as SARS, pandemics, SARS-COV-2, and mental health issues, were associated with tourism safety around 2021 and that big data and artificial intelligence (AI) were brought to the centre of research in 2020 and 2021. As effective methods to solve health problems, big data and AI have become a research trend in recent years. According to UNWTO, Jeju Special Self-Governing Province and the Jeju Tourism Organisation launched a real-time tourism congestion analysis service in December 2020, actively using big data technology to help Jeju tourists enjoy their tours without worrying about the coronavirus pneumonia (COVID-19).</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4.2"><label>5.4.2</label><title>Keywords with an emerging trend</title><p id="p0140">Burst words are essential for literature content mining when focusing on a particular period. A burst word is a keyword (node) that always appears in a specific period, indicating that it is highly valued by researchers in a certain period [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Citation Burst is used to detect the dynamic concepts and potential research problems that emerge in a field [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. It is suitable for examining emerging trends and sudden changes, reflecting active or cutting-edge research nodes. According to Kleinberg [<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], a cluster containing more burst nodes denotes an emerging research trend. Using Citespace 5.8.R3, the top 20 keywords with the highest citations from 1993 to 2021 were generated. The Year Per Slice value was set as 1. “Accident”, “medical tourism”, “environment”, “mediating role”, and “hospitality” were popular topics in tourism safety research (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>):<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>(1)</label><p id="p0145"><bold>Accidents in Tourism Safety</bold></p></list-item></list><fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Top 20 keywords with the strongest citation bursts on tourism safety from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0150">On WoS, the burst node of “accident” was a popular and emerging trend in tourism safety during the first period. It had the highest strength value of 4.67 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>) and proved to be popular in the early years of WoS. As shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, “accident” emerged earlier in academic research and increased substantially between 1999 and 2008. Thus, accidents have been a popular area of the discourse around tourism safety since 1999.</p><p id="p0155">Earlier studies usually linked tourism safety to tourists' life safety and accidents. Accidents are common tourist safety issues. Various accidents can happen during travelling, especially traffic accidents [<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], such as car accidents [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], air accidents, etc. [<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. For example, Nepal was the site of a string of deadly plane crashes, raising serious concerns about civil aviation safety and passenger safety [<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Scholars have shed light on the accidents, arranging before, during and after accident safety management to reduce the probability of tourist accidents.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0015"><list-item id="o0015"><label>(2)</label><p id="p0160"><bold>Tourism Market Segmentation and Management</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0165">Scholars mainly focused on tourism market segmentation (i.e., “adventure tourism”, “marine tourism”, “medical tourism”, etc.) and management of tourism safety. Apart from “adventure tourism”, which experienced a burst in searches, “Balanophyllia Europaea Scleractinia”, “management”, and “medical tourism” were popular keywords from 2001 onwards. Amongst them, “medical tourism” had a secondary strength value of 4.58. Thus, medical tourism was a popular area in discussions about tourism safety between 2010 and 2014. Below are some active burst words related to tourism market segmentation and management.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0020"><list-item id="o0020"><label>a.</label><p id="p0170"><bold>Adventure Tourism</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0175">Accident rates increased when some tourists engaged in high-risk activities, which made the problem of tourism safety more complicated [<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Adventure tourism, including wilderness survival, cycling tourism activities and other tourism projects [<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], was often associated with high-risk activities [<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Over the last ten years, adventure tourism has become popular in academia in the context of tourism safety.</p><p id="p0180">Adventure tourism activities are generally taking place in the context of a specific tourist destination. Scholars' research on adventure tourism safety issues mainly focused on mountaineering, skiing, diving sports, marine adventure tourism, outdoor wildlife tourism, etc. For example, the climbing accidents on Mount McKinley in North America and Denali attracted scholarly attention [<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Non-indigenous tourists participating in mountaineering in Nepal's high-altitude mountains (i.e. Himalayas) suffer from altitude sickness, respiratory diseases, musculoskeletal symptoms, intestinal infections, eye diseases and other health problems [<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. A ski tourist suffered from fractures and concussions after falling alone or colliding with others [<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Diving fatalities in New Zealand were analysed by some tourist researchers [<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. South African wild mammals attacked tourists, causing injuries and a certain number of deaths [<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].<list list-type="simple" id="olist0025"><list-item id="o0025"><label>b.</label><p id="p0185"><bold>Balanophyllia Europaea Scleractinia</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0190">When marine tourism became popular amongst tourists, ecological safety problems emerged. “Balanophyllia Europaea” (Risso, 1826) is a common Scleractinia coral living on subtidal rocky substrates in the Mediterranean Sea [<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Kružić and Popijač [<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] explored the mass mortality events of the coral “Balanophyllia Europaea” (“Scleractinia, Dendrophylliidae”) in the Mljet National Park (eastern Adriatic Sea), a principal attraction for visitors, which were caused by sea temperature anomalies. Balanophyllia Europaea Scleractinia was regarded as one of the essential indicators of marine tourism ecological safety from 2009 onwards.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0030"><list-item id="o0030"><label>c.</label><p id="p0195"><bold>Management</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0200">As tourist risks and accidents increased, tourist management became a focus of academic research. While negligence and mistakes in management make the social environment worse, uncontrolled tourism activities increase ecological pressure and over-exploitation of natural ecotourism resources [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Tourist safety management is important for addressing tourism safety issues. The research on tourism management mechanisms, legal systems, construction of insurance systems and other aspects of tourism has attracted the attention of scholars. It focuses on the prevention and readiness of tourist safety management, monitoring and early warning, emergency rescue, and post-disaster restoration.</p><p id="p0205">Tourist safety management is a necessary subject to be studied. It includes risk management, crisis management (i.e. tsunami safety measures) [<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], accident management, international tourism and transport group management for road safety initiatives [<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], etc. The research on tourist safety management mainly focused on tourist destination management [<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Some scholars have also studied different types of tourism, including nature tourism [<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], adventure-oriented tourism [<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], intelligent tourism [<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], geotourism (e.g. volcanic, geothermal environments) [<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], marine tourism (e.g. bathing beaches) [<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], ecotourism [<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>], medical tourism [<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], etc.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0035"><list-item id="o0035"><label>d.</label><p id="p0210"><bold>Medical Tourism</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0215">Medical tourism refers to travelling abroad for accessing health care services [<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Modern transportation, network communication technology development, and the accelerating world political and economic integration have boosted the medical tourism industry. According to Health-Tourism.com [<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], many countries became tourist destinations for medical travellers during 2010–2014, including Thailand, Singapore, Latin America, Malaysia, India, etc. Medical tourism meets people's health and beauty needs and carries over health and safety risks. Scholars reported that infection outbreaks amongst US patients arose from treatment at an overseas medical tourism facility [<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].</p><p id="p0220">Scholarly reviews initiated discussions on medical tourist safety by assessing the research evidence on medical treatment abroad [<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. In South Korea, the critical task ahead was to assure the potential customers of the protection and reliability of Korean medical tourism through continued efforts in advertising, which eventually resulted in attracting more customers [<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. As medical tourism is becoming increasingly popular, more attention is being paid to medical tourism safety research.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0040"><list-item id="o0040"><label>(3)</label><p id="p0225"><bold>Physical and Psychological Safety of Tourists</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0230">The emerging research trends covered the physical and psychological health and safety of tourists, as indicated by the keywords of “behaviour”, “health”, “quality of life”, and “physical activity”.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0045"><list-item id="o0045"><label>a.</label><p id="p0235"><bold>Behaviour</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0240">Tourist behaviour has become a popular research topic on WoS since 2001. By sorting out the relevant literature on tourist safety behaviour, this study found that tourist safety behaviour before, during and after a trip can be divided into four categories. These categories include safety decision-making behaviour, safety preparation behaviour before a trip, preventative safety behaviour during a trip, and tourist remedial safety behaviour after a disaster or accident. Cheng et al. [<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] identified management and behaviour as the two main components of tourism safety. Other scholars studied the “unsafe behaviour” of tourists. Non-compliance with instructions, poor physical health, and littering of cigarette butts in mountain tourism spots were found to be risk factors for adventure tourism safety [<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>].<list list-type="simple" id="olist0050"><list-item id="o0050"><label>b.</label><p id="p0245"><bold>Health, Quality of Life and Physical Activity</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0250">With the improvement in the quality of life of tourists and the changes in consumer behaviour, tourism safety researchers began focusing on tourists’ healthy lifestyles, requirements for a good quality of life, and fitness activities in 2012. The emerging keywords included “health”, “life quality”, and “physical activity”. Health was always associated with safety. Santos et al. [<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] indicated that health and safety requirements are one dimension of the global framework of the wine tourism system. Tourism safety and health affect tourist satisfaction [<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] and benefit the quality of life of locals and tourists. It is also evident that community-based tourism impacts the quality of life, community and emotional well-being, and general health, safety, and the well-being of host community residents [<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].<list list-type="simple" id="olist0055"><list-item id="o0055"><label>(4)</label><p id="p0255"><bold>Environmental Safety in Tourism</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0260">“Environment”, “association”, “decision making”, “loyalty”, “China”, “service quality”, “water”, “transport” and “strategy” became the burst nodes and most popular fields of research about tourism safety from 2016. “Environment” was one of the most popular keywords with the highest strength value during this period.</p><p id="p0265">In addition to the unsafe behaviour of tourists, dangerous conditions of the tourism environment are also major factors affecting the occurrence of tourism accidents. Scholars studied the weather patterns related to airports and air routes in the complex terrain of the Himalayas and their impact on aviation activities [<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</p><p id="p0270">The types of threats to tourism safety in natural and social environments include natural disasters (i.e., hurricanes, tornadoes, floods, earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, extreme climate, typhoons and tsunamis), man-made tragedies (including crime, terrorism, civil unrest/political unrest and war) [<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], traffic accidents [<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], such as car accidents [<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and air accidents [<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], as well as health hazards, such as SARS and COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,<xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>].</p><p id="p0275">While nature and adventure sports gained popularity among tourists, they also brought over tourist safety problems [<xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Tourism spots may become unsafe because of reasons, such as climate change, overtourism and infectious diseases [<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. These factors are beyond the control of tourism destinations [<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>].<list list-type="simple" id="olist0060"><list-item id="o0060"><label>(5)</label><p id="p0280"><bold>Hospitality Safety and Application of Mediators in Tourism safety</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0285">“Mediating role” and “hospitality” emerged as keywords. “Hospitality” (strength value = 3.35) and “mediating role” (strength value = 3.36) became the top two keywords with the highest strength value after 2018, indicating the emerging trend in further research.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0065"><list-item id="o0065"><label>a.</label><p id="p0290"><bold>Mediating Role</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0295">Mediating variables explain the relationship between the independent and the dependent variables [<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]<bold>.</bold> Due to an increase in scholars' interest in tourists' psychological health over the last five years, stakeholder and tourist satisfaction, loyalty, motivation, and behaviour have become hot topics. “Mediating role” became a popular term to analyse the relationship between these factors. In academic research, scholars have studied the variables mediating tourist safety behaviour, motivations to travel, and tourists' approach towards safety over the recent years, which were especially popular between 2019 and 2020. For instance, Biswas et al. [<xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] studied the mediating roles of tourist health, precautionary security behaviour and media engagement in influencing tourists' post-COVID-19 travel. Sarfraz et al. [<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] aimed to explore the role of tourists’ approach towards safety in the choice of a tourism destination with the mediating effect of tourist trust in the context of the Chinese tourism sector. Motivations to travel had a mediating role in travelling and willingness to pay for travelling during the pandemic, and that was reflecting a tourist safety problem for visitors [<xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>].<list list-type="simple" id="olist0070"><list-item id="o0070"><label>b.</label><p id="p0300"><bold>Hospitality</bold></p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0305">Hospitality search has existed as a topic on the Web of Science (WoS) for an extended period and it attracted more views and searches from 2019 to 2021. For example, some scholars who studied and identified crimes in hospitality have revealed tourist viewpoints on crime and risk, the impact of crime on hospitality and tourism, and the crime control methodology [<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Hospitality safety includes two aspects, i.e., food and accommodation safety for tourists and occupational safety for staff. In their study on staff safety, Sonmez et al. [<xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] found that large numbers of Hispanic immigrant workers in low-skill/low-wage hospitality service jobs worked in professional settings that caused disproportionate health and safety risks. These scholars analysed infectious diseases that have threatened the physical and mental health and safety of millions of hospitality service workers [<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Tourist accommodation safety hazards include crime, infectious diseases, accidents, etc. Popularity in artificial intelligence (AI) allows contactless hospitality services that impact psychological safety, entertainment and service quality of tourists in a positive way (Li et al., 2021).</p><p id="p0310">Tourism development, such as the commercialisation of traditional practices and festivities, the relocation of indigenous people to develop tourism, and the destructive renovation of traditional buildings, may amplify the marginalisation of indigenous people in the community. That leads to the loss of the indigenous culture and their approach to hospitality and increases the sense of hostility coming from the indigenous people and being directed to tourists. Thus it leads to tourist insecurity. On the other hand, a lack of local welcome (such as unfriendly and unwelcoming attitudes) causes negative travel experiences and a sense of psychological insecurity among tourists [<xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5.5"><label>5.5</label><title>Cited documents: content analysis</title><p id="p0315">In VOSviewer, “citations” were selected as a type of analysis, and “documents” were chosen as units of study. The minimum citation number for a document was set at 80. Furthermore, out of 2018 documents, only 60 met the threshold requirements. A few items out of 60 in the visual network were not connected to the present study. The largest set of related items comprised of 8 documents with the highest citations amongst 2018 documents. They all belong to the topic of tourism safety management, mainly focusing on the impact of risk and safety approaches. The results illustrated the top three popular topics mentioned above (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The content of the top three cited articles is analysed below, as shown in <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> [<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>].<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Top ten most frequently used keywords in tourism safety research indexed in WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0105">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Label</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Occurrences)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average publications Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average normalised citations)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Management</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Impact</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Perceptions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Risk</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Behaviour</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Covid-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Satisfaction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Food Safety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quality</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Health</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Top ten latest popular keywords in tourism safety research from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0110">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Label</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (Occurrences)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average publications Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average citations)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Average normalised citations)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Covid-19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sars</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Restoration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pandemic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sars-Cov-2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mental-Health</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acceptance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Big Data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Artificial Intelligence</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tourism Destination</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Top eight cited documents of tourism safety from WoS.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0115">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Author (Year)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Documents' titles</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Journal</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score (Citations)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sonmez (1998) [<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Influence of terrorism risk on foreign tourism decisions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Annals of Tourism Research</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">457</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fuchs (2011) [<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">An exploratory inquiry into risk perceptions on destination and risk reduction strategies of first-time vs. repeat visitors to a highly volatile destination</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tourism Management</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">221</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yuksel (2007) [<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shopping risk perceptions: effects on tourists' emotions, satisfaction and expressed loyalty and intentions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tourism Management</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">George (2003) [<xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tourist's perceptions of safety and security while visiting cape town</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tourism Management</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">163</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cavlek (2002) [<xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tour operators and safety of destinations</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Annals of Tourism Research</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Seabra (2013) [<xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heterogeneity in risk and safety perceptions of international tourists</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tourism Management</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">George (2010) [<xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Visitor perceptions of crime-safety and attitudes towards risk: the case of Table Mountain National Park, cape town</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Tourism Management</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">De Albuquerque (1999) [<xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tourism and crime in the Caribbean</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Annals of Tourism Research</italic></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0320">First, Sonmez and Graefe [<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] explored the factors that affect the decision-making process in international vacation tourism. Risk perceptions directly influence tourist decisions. Fuchs and Reichel [<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] studied the relationship between first-time and repeat-visit tourists and highly volatile destinations regarding destination risk perception, risk reduction strategies, and visit motivation. First-time visitors faced physical, psychosocial, food safety and weather risks. On the contrary, repeat-visit tourists were associated with destination risk factors, including financial risk, service quality risk, natural disasters and car accidents [<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. After citation analysis, the most cited articles were related to the mediating variables/roles in tourism safety, especially between 2019 and 2021.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>6</label><title>Comparative analysis and discussion between WoS and Weibo</title><sec id="sec6.1"><label>6.1</label><title>Keywords of Weibo</title><p id="p0325">According to <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, “visitors” is the most frequently mentioned keyword about tourism safety on Weibo, followed by “accident”, “market”, “water”, “traffic”, “management”, “sea”, “order”, “China”, and “culture”. Weibo users pay more attention to the tourists themselves, which can be seen from the keywords including “visitors”, “water draining”, “traffic”, “dangerous”, “sea”, “risk” and any other accidents. Amongst these, “sea” was popular on Weibo in 2014, 2016 and 2017 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>. Regarding the number of likes, “China” and “ice” are the two words getting the most likes on Weibo. Sina Weibo had more Chinese users, and the keyword of “ice” indicated that skiing tourism safety was popular on Weibo in 2021.<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Occurrence of tourism safety-related keywords on Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><label>6.2</label><title>Comparative analysis and discussion of keywords</title><sec id="sec6.2.1"><label>6.2.1</label><title>“Accident” is an early hot search on Weibo and WoS</title><p id="p0330">“Accident” was not only the most popular keyword on Weibo in 2013 and 2017 (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>), but also one of the hot searches on WoS in the early days.</p><p id="p0335">According to a previous study “accident” used to be a popular word in academia in previous years because accidents were imposing most risks to tourist safety. In the past, scholars believed that tourism safety was about the personal accidents of tourists. Most academic studies focused on prior, during and post-accident safety, which is more consistent with our conclusions about Weibo.</p><p id="p0340">On the social media channel Weibo, posts, and comments on tourist accidents can quickly attract wide public attention. After analysing the content of Weibo, it has been found that most of the Weibo accounts releasing news about travel safety incidents belong to Chinese government agencies. Some of their Weibo posts reported that local spots had seen no accidents after tourist activities, warning against accidents or setting reminders to the localities to strengthen safety management measures before the holiday season commences. At the same time, some relatively adverse security incidents were reported below.</p><p id="p0345">During the earthquake in Japan in 2011, people from foreign countries started taking jewellery from people on the street. In 2014, tourists suffered massive robberies in Brazil during the World Cup. In 2015, several accidents took place, including a fire accident in the Royal Ocean Park, and drowning accidents of Chinese tourists in the United States were taking place regularly. The outbreak of anti-China demonstrations in Turkey led China's embassy to issue a travel safety reminder. In 2016, holiday travel accidents were regular; earthquakes happened in Honshu, Afghanistan, Myanmar, Kyushu, Japan, and other places in April alone. In the same year, some tourists were attacked by monkeys while playing in scenic spots, and there were also accidents of tourists where they were hit and killed. In 2017, a boat capsized in the Philippines and killed eight people; a female graduate student at Peking University died while skiing and people were warned to pay more attention to the safety rules of skiing when travelling.</p><p id="p0350">Travel incidents are often discussed in the media. Most of the abovementioned incidents were related to overseas travel in the scenarios, which were mostly natural disasters such as earthquakes, accidents, man-made crimes, fires, etc. The related news was mainly published by local government agencies.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.2.2"><label>6.2.2</label><title>Health-related words are research foci on Weibo and WoS</title><p id="p0355">As shown in Figs. <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, although “visitors”, “accident”, “sea”, and “China” were popular words, “COVID-19” has attracted the widest attention since 2020. The findings regarding tourism safety are identical on the Web of Science (WoS) and Weibo. “COVID-19” was the most mentioned keyword on WoS and Weibo between 2020 and 2022. Therefore, in recent years, especially since 2020, health problems have been closely related to tourism safety for academics and laypersons. Popular health keywords on WoS include “Covid-19”, “restoration”, “pandemic”, “sars-cov-2”, “Sars”, and “mental health”.<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Annual occurrence of keywords to related tourism safety on Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec6.2.3"><label>6.2.3</label><title>“Quality” is one of the hottest topics on Weibo and WoS</title><p id="p0360">According to UNWTO (2022), safety is a critical factor in the quality of tourism. The success or failure of a tourism destination depends on its ability to provide a safe, secure, and high-quality place for visitors. According to keyword analyses, “quality” was a popular keyword on WoS. By analysing the content on WoS, it was found that the research on quality covered all aspects of tourism safety, including quality of service, environment, human activity, infrastructure, facilities, residential living standards, destinations, brands, culture, etc. Cambra-Fierro et al. [<xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] analysed the impact of what was considered a health risk on a certain quality destination. The Brazilian medical tourism market was subject to tight legislation on facilities and continued the development of medical facility accreditation standards, demonstrating a commitment to patient safety and high-quality care [<xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Tourism safety is critical in ensuring both the tourism experience for tourists and the quality of life for residents are good. Therefore, many scholars have studied tourism safety in combination with quality and there is research available on the quality and safety issues associated with medical treatment in medical tourism that proves this [<xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Under government policies, a “bubble zone” was established in China to ensure tourism safety and quality [<xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Adventure tourism activities are safe and involve a high-quality experience, therefore Chinese tourists who follow the rules are willing to participate in these activities [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. By comparing the most influencing documents and posts that are related to “quality” in tourism, it was found that the focus on “quality” from WoS appeared earlier than on Weibo. Yuksel and Yuksel [<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] suggest that the quality of tourism safety is one of the factors that impact tourists’ shopping behaviour. Furthermore, the most popular microblog on the topic with the highest reposting numbers on Weibo appeared in 2015 (<xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Quality-related content on Weibo with a larger reposting number.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0120">Table 7</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time Published</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Account_Name</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Content</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reposting_<break/>Number</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comment_<break/>Number</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Like_<break/>Number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2015/4/2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">China ∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[Ten 5 A tourist sites, including Mount Wutai, were warned]<break/>The person in charge of the National Tourism Administration said some 5 A tourist sites did not meet the standards of tourist safety management, environmental sanitation, service quality, market order, etc. Tourist rip-offs were common there.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">124</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017/2/2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Released by ∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[Incredible! During the Spring Festival, 2.98 million Chinese and foreign tourists came to Wuxi for the New Year, the city's tourism revenue was close to 3.3 billion RMB.] within the seven days from January 27 to February 2, 2017, there were no tourism accidents or major tourism quality complaints in the city.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017/2/28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Release by ∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[@Tianfu New District, Dalin Town, “Three Grasps and Three Majors” to Create a Soft Environment Perfect for Spring Tourism safety]<break/>Adhering to the goal of “safety, order, quality and efficiency” and the policy of “safety first, prevention first, and comprehensive management”, Dalin neighbourhood strived to create a safe soft environment for tourism in the “Cuihu Pear Township” scenic spot. In this way, a solid foundation was laid for the smooth development of the pear blossom viewing events in March.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017/10/25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Released by ∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[Shuangqiaohe Town actively conducts tourism safety inspections on the scenic spots and hotels in Baocheng]<break/>A few days ago, to ensure the stability of the tourism industry's safety situation in Shuangqiaohe Town during the 19th National Congress of the Communist Party of China, the local tourism bureau organized a joint inspection team to carry out safety inspections on the tourism industry in the Baocheng Qishiyuan Scenic Spot and Baocheng Hotel in the town, providing a safe tourism environment for tourists.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017/2/3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Released by ∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[We won't rest until the universe does not restart!]<break/>During the Golden Week of the Spring Festival, there were no travel accidents or complaints in the whole industry in Binhai New Area, and the goal of safety, order, quality and efficiency were achieved.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2016/5/18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">www.T∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[The 6 restaurants and hotels in Taiwan's Sun Moon Lake overwhelmed by mainland tourists are all unqualified]<break/>To maintain the safety and quality of tour groups coming to Taiwan, the relevant Taiwan management departments have jointly inspected Sun Moon Lake in Nantou County, a key tourist destination for mainland tour groups.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2012/10/29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cultural T∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[Draft of the Tourism Law submitted for deliberation, and forced shopping by travel agencies will be curbed]<break/>To diversify tourism products, improve the quality of tourism services, and promote tourism development, it is urgent to enact a tourism law. This time, the draft of Tourism Law submitted for deliberation comprises ten chapters and 98 articles, including corresponding regulations on tourism safety, zero-negative group fees, scenic spot ticket prices, forced shopping, and difficulties for tourists to protect their rights of concern to the people.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2017/10/9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ru∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[Overview of Golden Week Tourism]<break/>Last November, the city's tourist reception and tourism revenue increased significantly. The occupancy rate of guest rooms and the income from house prices were considerably high. Public services such as tourism and transportation have improved, and civilized tourism has become popular without accidents.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2013/5/3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sich∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">[During the Labor Day holiday, tourism in Chengdu had a revenue of over 2.7 billion RMB]<break/>During the three-day holiday, there were no major complaints about the quality of tourism services nor any tourism safety liability accidents in the city.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0365">As shown in Figs. <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> and <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, “quality” was the keyword with the biggest number of comments and reposts in tourism safety research, especially on Weibo in 2011 and 2022. From Weibo user information, “quality” was a popular topic regarding tourism safety. In China, the government has issued some formal documents on the topic. In the document titled “Guiding Opinions of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism on Implementing the Plan to Improve the Quality of Tourism Services” [<xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>], a high-quality plan for tourism services was proposed to address safety measures, hygiene and safety risks in the tourism market. As suggested in “The Opinions on Deepening the Internet ​+ ​Tourism to Promote the High-quality Development of the Tourism Industry released” [<xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], it is necessary to ensure the safety of tourism data, fulfil the duty of data safety management, and conduct regular inspections in case there are security risks and hidden dangers. Safety risk warnings and instructions should be highlighted in advertising and sales for self-guided tours that involve high-risk activities, such as rock climbing, surfing, and snorkelling.<fig id="fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>The number of comments, likes and reposting about the keywords related to tourism safety on Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 10</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr10.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Annual occurrence of keywords about comment number, like number and reposting number related to tourism safety on Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Fig. 11</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr11.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0370">Many policy documents have been issued to promote the high-quality development of cultural tourism. For example, “Voice of Culture and Tourism”, the official Weibo account under the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the People's Republic of China (MCTPRC), reprinted “Promoting the High-Quality Development of Culture and Tourism from People's Daily” on April 9, 2022. The tourist system is supposed to promote the high-quality development of culture and tourism nowadays [<xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. As a result, governmental Weibo accounts have begun to publish and implement plans for high-quality tourism developments. The content related to high-quality tourism safety on Weibo is listed below. Most of the quality-related posts come from government agencies. As shown in <xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>, tourism quality is also often related to tourism safety.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6.3"><label>6.3</label><title>Users/organisations</title><p id="p0375"><xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref> shows that China's Tourism Network of Integrity (with 7158 fans) is the most influential user on tourism safety on Weibo. Sponsored by the National Tourism Administration, China's Tourism Network of Integrity aims to promote the construction of the credit system in the tourist industry, the culture of integrity and the development of high-integrity enterprises in China. It is a “tourism safety platform” for tourists to complain, protect their rights and communicate with travel companies and other tourists. Tourists can also record and inquire about the professional credit of tourism practitioners. Therefore, the platform combines a complaint and reporting option for the travel network, a leading management system, a travel agencies' statistics management system, a hotel statistical investigation management system, and a quality inspection and complaint management system (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://s.weibo.com" id="intref0010a">https://s.weibo.com</ext-link>, January 13, 2022). Other users with most followers on Weibo include Sishui Public Security in Jinan (with 19,000 fans), Culture and Tourism Department in Gansu Province (with 36,000 fans), China Tourism News (with 390,000 fans), and Ji Zhou (with 15,000 fans), etc, all of which are government agencies. It was found that government agencies, especially those located in tourism destinations, can use Weibo to raise concerns about and improve tourist safety rules in China. On WoS, universities and research institutes published most.<fig id="fig12" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Annual occurrences of accounts related to tourism safety on Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Fig. 12</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr12.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec6.4"><label>6.4</label><title>The connection between Weibo and academia in tourism safety research</title><p id="p0380">Social media are playing an increasingly important role in scholarly communication. More and more academic journals have established social media accounts on Twitter, Facebook, and other platforms to share knowledge and publish research results, including their latest articles. This way, collaborations between researchers can be facilitated to enhance the exchange of the latest research results and promote the application of science and technology, thus making it easier for users to raise awareness and outreach to academic journals.</p><p id="p0385">On Weibo, the content of academic research on tourism safety mainly focuses on marine ecological safety, outbound tourist safety, high-quality development and safety of rural tourism, development of tourism safety and health, China's tourism safety report, and tourist safety for the elderly. Below are some examples of such posts on Weibo (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://weibo.com/" id="intref0010">https://weibo.com/</ext-link>).<list list-type="simple" id="olist0075"><list-item id="o0075"><label>1)</label><p id="p0390">The blue book on tourism safety, “China Tourism Safety Report” <italic toggle="yes">(2013)</italic>, has recently been published by an academician from the Institute of Public Security of Tsinghua University and an academician from the Chinese Academy of Engineering.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0080"><label>2)</label><p id="p0395">In 2015, China's first Argus coastal observation system was completed. The Argus video monitoring system was launched successfully on Zhujiajian Island, Zhoushan City, Zhejiang Province, recently. The system would be mainly used for research on the dynamic geomorphological process of Dongsha beach, tourist safety, and carrying capacity, and the research results will provide a scientific basis for the protection and development of the beach and the evaluation of coastal engineering.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0085"><label>3)</label><p id="p0400">A user conducted an empirical study on June 14, 2016 on the safety needs and constraints of outbound tourism for the elderly in China.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0090"><label>4)</label><p id="p0405">During the post-pandemic period in 2020, tourism safety and crisis management against the pandemic, tourism integration and local image in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area became priorities, along with high-quality development of rural tourism. From November 7th to 8th, the China Tourism Research Annual Conference of “Tourism Journal” was held in Guangzhou, where people from academic circles of tourism discussed China's high-quality tourism development and social well-being.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0095"><label>5)</label><p id="p0410">In 2021, China's tourism industry accelerated the formation of a new pattern where tourism would be integrated into the comprehensive development layout of the “14th Five-Year Plan”. In 2022, the tourism industry will better adapt to the changing trend of supply and demand in the tourism market to grasp new opportunities for the industry's recovery. With the normalisation of the pandemic prevention measures and ways of control, tourism will develop safely and healthily, and the two-way adjustment of supply and demand will promote the recovery of tourism.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0415">However, the number of comments, reposts, and likes of these Weibo posts sharing academic information was close to 0. It can be speculated that compared with other social platforms (such as Twitter), Weibo plays a minor role in or has just entered the initial stage of promoting and publishing academic research. For example, Nature has a Twitter account to share its newly published articles. The Tweet's report link is a short link or URL (go.nature.com/2CD3ovO), which is more convenient for mobile users than the original browser tabs [<xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec6.5"><label>6.5</label><title>Artificial intelligence (AI) sentiment analysis on Weibo</title><p id="p0420">Some scholars have explored sentiment analyses in tourism safety research, for example, detecting safety issues mentioned in the videos on the world's most popular video-sharing platform, YouTube [<xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. According to the analysis of the keywords' occurrence on Weibo, there were more microblogs with positive than negative sentiment. To further discuss the tourism safety-related content on Sina Weibo, it is necessary to conduct a sentiment analysis on 7293 Weibo posts about tourism safety.</p><p id="p0425">Based on the study of Nasri et al. [<xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], the AI Sentiment from CX Data Science was used in analysing the tourism safety-related content on Weibo. There were more microblogs with positive sentiments than those with negative sentiments. The positive and negative sentiments account for 52.0% and 39.5% of all the analysed Weibo posts (<xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>). The most frequently occurring keyword of positive sentiment is “good” (<xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>).<fig id="fig13" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Distributions of words’ sentiments mentioned in Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Fig. 13</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr13.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig14" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Tag clouds-all sentiments in Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Fig. 14</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr14.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0430">“Safe”, “relevant”, “improved”, “comprehensive”, “effective”, “help”, and “rectification” was more influential than other keywords with positive sentiments (<xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>). On the contrary, the top 3 negative sentiments in occurrence frequency were “accident”, “epidemic”, and “complaints” (<xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref>). The total count of keywords about “good” is 1,328, while the total count of keywords about “accident” is 981. The total count of “epidemics” and “complaints” are 842 and 486, respectively. Laypersons focused more on positive keywords than on negative keywords, while the negative ones, including “accident”, “epidemic”, and “complaint”, were the focus of tourist organisations, managers, and government agencies. Thus, these negative words indicated identical results with the co-occurrence of keywords and keywords with an emerging trend on the Web of Science.<fig id="fig15" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Most mentioned keywords with positive sentiments in Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Fig. 15</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr15.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig16" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>Most mentioned keywords with negative sentiments in Weibo.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0085">Fig. 16</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr16.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>7</label><title>Conclusion</title><sec id="sec7.1"><label>7.1</label><title>Theoretical implications</title><p id="p0435">Based on bibliometrics and informatics, this study analysed 2018 documents on WoS and 7293 posts on Weibo with VOSviewer, Citespace, Python and Tableau. Organisations, sources, keywords, countries, etc., were analysed using a science mapping approach. The theoretical implications of this study are described below.</p><p id="p0440">The first publication on tourism safety in WoS appeared in 1977, while the first information on tourism safety on Weibo is dated back to 2011. Compared with information posted on Weibo, the annual publications about tourism safety experienced a relatively stable increase on WoS. Weibo users are subject to emotional variation, entertainment, policies, etc., quickly influencing popular topics on Weibo. Thus, the annual number of posts on tourism safety can vary from time to time.</p><p id="p0445">In addition, on WoS, the most influential organisation in the study of tourism safety is the Chinese Academy of Sciences and Hong Kong Polytechnic University. However, on Weibo, the most productive organisations in posting blogs on tourism safety are government agencies, such as China's Tourism Network of Integrity, the Sishui Public Security in Jinan, and the Culture and Tourism Department of Ji Zhou in Hebei. Most of these government agencies are in tourist destinations. Thus, the focus of the public will be detected by comparing the content about tourism safety on Weibo and WoS. New research trends from universities and academic institutions can be identified on WoS, while Weibo provides the latest information from government agencies.</p><p id="p0450">Furthermore, “accident”, “quality”, and other health-related keywords are equally popular on Weibo and WoS. Weibo users place their emphasis on visitors’ risks and hazards, such as drowning risks, traffic risks, etc. Researchers on WoS focus more on tourist safety management.</p><p id="p0455">Moreover, academic studies focus more on artificial intelligence (AI). Nevertheless, the public might not know of or make use of AI in tourism. On the other hand, the top 10 Weibo search terms were more related to dangers and risks of travelling, such as drowning accidents and traffic risks. Institutional differences in academic levels and information asymmetry due to different exposure to information technology can lead to a digital divide. That also explains the gap in comparative analysis between the Web of Science (WoS) and Sina Weibo on tourism safety, and the fact that academic elites benefit more from technology than the public does.</p><p id="p0460">What is more, according to the AI sentiment analyses on Weibo, the public used more positive keywords than negative ones. At the same time, “accidents”, “epidemics”, and “complaints” should be the focal points for tourist organisations, managers, and governments. Additionally, Weibo played a minor role or has just started to play a role in promoting and publishing academic studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec7.2"><label>7.2</label><title>Practical implications</title><p id="p0470">Tourism safety is of practical importance for industry practitioners. Comparing WoS and Weibo in tourism safety can benefit governments and enterprises. This study provided some important information for tourism industry players and the government.</p><p id="p0475">Tourism safety is increasingly related to health problems, such as a pandemic, food safety, mental health issues etc. Besides, academia pays more attention to the role of AI in tourism safety as there is an opportunity for tourists to solve health problems using AI and intelligent tools when they are on a journey.</p><p id="p0480">On top of that, Weibo is more pragmatic. Social media play a crucial role in tourism safety communication by capturing the earliest information about accidents the first time, as was the case in the earthquake in Japan in 2011.</p><p id="p0485">Sina Weibo has played an essential role in signal amplification. It creates sensation and promotes information sharing to a certain extent while facilitating the exchange of different viewpoints and providing early warning of sudden tourist accidents for government authorities. On social media, people conduct human-machine interaction and group communication through comments, likes, sharing, etc.</p><p id="p0490">Finally, it is possible to publish academic research articles on WoS and other academic platforms via Weibo, and that is convenient for users to access that content and increase their influence.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>8</label><title>Limitations and further research direction</title><p id="p0495">There are still a few limitations to this study. First of all, it may fail to include some older people who cannot be Weibo users as they do not use the internet to communicate with others. In addition, the results would have been different if other blogging or academic platforms had been the target basis of this research. Thus, a questionnaire or interview might be helpful in further research.</p><p id="p0500">The research could be extended in several ways. There may be a comparison between Sina Weibo and other social media, including Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, etc. Other researchers could compare Sina Weibo's role in promoting and publishing academic research by using different social media platforms. Finally, some researchers could study academic platforms other than WoS, such as Scopus, Google scholar, etc., to research tourism safety.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec9.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0505">Liyun Zeng: Conceived and designed the research, wrote the paper, analysed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0510">Rita Yi Man Li: Conceived and designed the research, wrote the paper, analysed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0515">Huiling Zeng: Conceived and designed the research, wrote the paper, analysed and interpreted the data.</p></sec><sec id="sec9.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0520">This work was supported by Ph.D. Starting Research Fund from the <funding-source id="gs1">Panzhihua University</funding-source> (No. 035200153); <funding-source id="gs2">Panzhihua University</funding-source> Scientific Research Project (Economic Environmental Impact Assessment of Rural Ecotourism (No. 035001411); <funding-source id="gs3">Panzhihua City’s Municipal Science and Technology Program</funding-source> Project (No. 2021ZD-S-1).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec10"><title><italic toggle="yes">Additional information</italic></title><p id="p0525">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title><italic toggle="yes">Declaration of interest's statement</italic></title><p id="p0535">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive evolution analysis of public perceptions related to pediatric care: a Sina Weibo case study (2013–2020)</article-title><source>Sage Open</source><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/21582440221087260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>C.C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grépin</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><x xml:space="preserve">…</x><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title># WuhanDiary and# WuhanLockdown: gendered posting patterns and behaviours on Weibo during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>BMJ global health</source><volume>7</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2021-008149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9006193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35414567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time identification of urban rainstorm waterlogging disasters based on Weibo big data</article-title><source>Nat. Hazards</source><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11069-018-3427-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disaster management 2.0: a real-time disaster damage assessment model based on mobile social media data—a case study of Weibo (Chinese Twitter)</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>115</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2019.02.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The London School of Economics and Political Science</part-title><year>2020</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2020/03/26/weibo-how-is-chinas-second-largest-social-media-platform-being-used-for-social-research/" id="intref0015">https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2020/03/26/weibo-how-is-chinas-second-largest-social-media-platform-being-used-for-social-research/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction safety and health hazard awareness in Web of Science and Weibo between 1991 and 2021</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>152</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2022.105790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref103"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Esteller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tax collection in the Roman Empire: a new institutional economics approach</article-title><source>Constitutional Political Economy</source><volume>33</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10602-021-09355-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceptions of risk from nanotechnologies and trust in stakeholders: a cross sectional study of public, academic, government and business attitudes</article-title><source>BMC Publ. Health</source><volume>15</volume><issue>424</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-1795-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4417265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25928741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreiras</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Planning tourism in protected natural areas: safety, soft law and conflict management between beach users. The case of surf in aljezur, Portugal</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>13</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su131910739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A summary of the domestic research and characteristics on tourism security in 1990-2016</article-title><source>Econ. Geogr.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>219</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinese tourists? sense of safety: perceptions of expected and experienced destination safety</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>23</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500.2019.1681382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chingarande</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saayman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical success factors for tourism-led growth</article-title><source>Int. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jtr.2233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing tourism safety and risk: using the Delphi expert consensus method in developing the event tourism security self-beliefs scale</article-title><source>J. Hospit. Tourism Manag.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhtm.2021.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LinLiu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Slopeland disaster risk management in tourism</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500.2016.1165187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accidents in the New Zealand adventure tourism industry</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-7535(00)00053-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death in paradise: tourist fatalities in the tsunami disaster in Thailand</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500802531141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Impacts of tourism development on the spreading of zoonosis</part-title><comment>AUG 29-30, 2014</comment><source>Paper Presented at the 10th Euro-Asia Conference on Environment and Corporate Social Responsibility - Tourism</source><year>2014</year><publisher-name>Society and Education Session</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mountain tourism planning served engineering geology and its application</article-title><source>J. Eng. Geol.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Communication and Aso Tourism Revival Post-Earthquake 2016 (Using Web Technology for English Information Spread). Paper Presented at the Pacific Neighborhood Consortium Annual Conference and Joint Meetings (PNC)</part-title><year>2017</year><publisher-name>Natl Cheng Kung Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vairo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quagliati</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Giudice</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbucci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabiano</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From land- to water-use-planning: a consequence based case-study related to cruise ship risk</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>97</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2016.03.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolkach</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Travel preferences of Asian gay men</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10941665.2017.1308396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unpacking millennial Chinese women's risk perceptions in outbound travel: an intersectional perspective</article-title><source>J. Hospit. Tourism Manag.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhtm.2021.10.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tourists' spatio-temporal behaviour and concerns in park tourism: giant panda national Park, sichuan, China</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10941665.2019.1653336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witting</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filimon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kevork</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carry along or not? Decision-making on carrying standard avalanche safety gear among ski tourers in a German touring region</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>143</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2021.105406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cycling in Tibet: an analysis of tourists' spatiotemporal behavior and infrastructure</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2021.104418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murgante</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pishgahi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarghamfard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahaki</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting the lut desert tourism in Iran: developing an interpretive-structural model</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>13</volume><issue>13</issue><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su13137245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennington-Gray</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tourism crisis management: can the Extended Parallel Process Model be used to understand crisis responses in the cruise industry?</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>55</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2016.02.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motivation and involvement in adventure tourism activities: a Chinese tourists' perspective</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10941665.2019.1666152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive evaluation and prediction of tourism ecological security in droughty area national parks-a case study of Qilian Mountain of Zhangye section, China</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Control Ser.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>13</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>16816</fpage><lpage>16829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-12021-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33394393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.Y.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuttapong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic development and mountain tourism research from 2010 to 2020: bibliometric analysis and science mapping approach</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su14010562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microclimate tourism and microclimate tourism security and safety in China</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>74</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2018.12.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weibo</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Weibo Reports First Quarter 2022 Unaudited Financial Results</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Beijing</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ir.weibo.com/static-files/dde1f6a8-1ed6-4e6b-8e75-4764b1685adf" id="intref0020">http://ir.weibo.com/static-files/dde1f6a8-1ed6-4e6b-8e75-4764b1685adf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weibo</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Business Overview</part-title><year>2022</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ir.weibo.com/corporate-profile" id="intref0025">http://ir.weibo.com/corporate-profile</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goerlandt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reniers</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of scientometric mapping for the safety science community: methods, tools, and framework</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>134</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2020.105093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining the effects of AI contactless services on customer psychological safety, perceived value, and hospitality service quality during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J. Hospit. Market. Manag.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19368623.2021.1934932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.Y.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crabbe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic development and construction safety research: a bibliometrics approach</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>145</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2021.105519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrobel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montewka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goerlandt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A bibliometric analysis and systematic review of shipboard Decision Support Systems for accident prevention</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>128</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2020.104717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goerlandt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Y.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arctic shipping risk management: a bibliometric analysis and a systematic review of risk influencing factors of navigational accidents</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>139</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2021.105254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Blue Book of Social Mentality</series><volume>vol. 2022</volume><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Social Science Literature Press</publisher-name><comment>(in Chinese)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weibo</surname></name></person-group><article-title>2016 Sina user media value report</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.weibo.com/report/reportDetail?id=344&amp;sudaref=cn.bing.com" id="intref0030">https://data.weibo.com/report/reportDetail?id=344&amp;sudaref=cn.bing.com</ext-link><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>LPSOS</collab></person-group><part-title>Inventory of Weibo Travel Data in 2017</part-title><year>2017</year><comment><italic toggle="yes">Tencent</italic></comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cloud.tencent.com/developer/news/80113" id="intref0035">https://cloud.tencent.com/developer/news/80113</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weibo</surname></name></person-group><part-title>2018 White Paper on Tourism Consumer Rights and Interests</part-title><year>2018</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.weibo.com/report/reportDetail?id=419" id="intref0040">https://data.weibo.com/report/reportDetail?id=419</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikanchai</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Look at the 2019 Weibo Night for the Strongest Annual Inventory</part-title><year>2019</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://baijiahao.baidu.com/s?id=1653154862147105955" id="intref0045">https://baijiahao.baidu.com/s?id=1653154862147105955</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconnecting tourism after COVID-19: the paradox of alterity in tourism areas</article-title><source>Tourism Geogr.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14616688.2020.1762115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref102"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atadil</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do you dare to travel to China? An examination of China's destination image amid the COVID-19</article-title><source>Tourism Manag. Perspect.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmp.2021.100881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8480968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34608430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref109"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chaomei</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>CiteSpace: a practical guide for mapping scientific literature</part-title><year>2016</year><publisher-name>Nova Science Publishers Hauppauge</publisher-name><publisher-loc>NY, USA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chaomei</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CiteSpace II: Detecting and visualizing emerging trends and transient patterns in scientific literature</article-title><source>J Journal of the American Society for information Science, and Technology</source><volume>57</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>377</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bursty and hierarchical structure in streams</article-title><source>Data Min. Knowl. Discov.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>397</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracking traffic congestion and accidents using social media data: a case study of Shanghai</article-title><source>Accid. Anal. Prev.</source><volume>169</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aap.2022.106618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35231867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doucet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortlage</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><x xml:space="preserve">…</x><name name-style="western"><surname>Coimbra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unrecognized danger of a new transportation mechanism of injury - Pedicabs</article-title><source>J. Saf. Res.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsr.2011.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21569895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yannis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golias</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accident risk of foreign drivers in various road environments</article-title><source>J. Saf. Res.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsr.2007.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Manzano</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Nuno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Valpuesta</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassallo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An assessment of road traffic accidents in Spain: the role of tourism</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500.2018.1548581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regmi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudhia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maharjan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-Scale gravity current over the middle hills of the Nepal himalaya: implications for aircraft accidents</article-title><source>J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.</source><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/JAMC-D-16-0073.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk assessment of seaplane operation safety using bayesian network</article-title><source>Symmetry-Basel</source><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/sym12060888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Procopiuck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segovia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Procopiuck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urban cycling mobility: management and urban institutional arrangements to support bicycle tourism activities-case study from Curitiba, Brazil</article-title><source>Transportation</source><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2055</fpage><lpage>2080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11116-020-10121-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiatkawsin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining Vietnamese hard-adventure tourists' visit intention using an extended model of goal-directed behavior</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12051747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcintosh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grissom</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mountaineering fatalities on Denali</article-title><source>High Alt. Med. Biol.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ham.2008.1047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18331224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhetri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherpa</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherpa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanati</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Work-health needs of high-altitude mountain guides (Sherpas) in Nepal - a pilot study</article-title><source>Int. J. Occup. Saf. Ergon.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10803548.2015.1017945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26327257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruedl</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rein</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burtscher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes and risk factors of injuries during winter sport holidays</article-title><source>Deutsche Zeitschrift Fur Sportmedizin</source><volume>64</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5960/dzsm.2012.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of a complex recreational scuba diving accident: French Pass, New Zealand, 2000</article-title><source>Diving and Hyperbaric Medicine</source><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22753164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durrheim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leggat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk to tourists posed by wild mammals in South Africa</article-title><source>J. Trav. Med.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1708-8305.1999.tb00856.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10467154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goffredo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Airi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radetic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaccanti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual reproduction of the solitary sunset cup coral Leptopsammia pruvoti (Scleractinia, Dendrophylliidae) in the Mediterranean. 2. Quantitative aspects of the annual reproductive cycle</article-title><source>Mar. Biol.</source><volume>148</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00227-005-0137-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kružić</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popijač</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass mortality events of the coral Balanophyllia europaea (Scleractinia, Dendrophylliidae) in the Mljet National Park (eastern Adriatic Sea) caused by sea temperature anomalies</article-title><source>Journal of the International Society for Reef Studies</source><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00338-014-1231-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.Y.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable Mountain-based health and wellness tourist destinations: the interrelationships between tourists' satisfaction, behavioral intentions, and competitiveness</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>13</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su132313314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rittichainuwat</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tourists' and tourism suppliers' perceptions toward crisis management on tsunami</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2012.03.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilks</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faulks</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>International tourists and road safety in Australia: developing a national research and management programme</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0261-5177(99)00034-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of tourism risk perception</article-title><source>Nat. Hazards</source><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11069-016-2208-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rantala</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valkonen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complexity of safety in wilderness guiding in Finnish Lapland</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500.2010.548548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How smart is your tourist attraction?: measuring tourist preferences of smart tourism attractions via a FCEM-AHP and IPA approach</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2015.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erfurt-Cooper</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geotourism in volcanic and geothermal environments: playing with fire?</article-title><source>Geoheritage</source><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12371-010-0025-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Policy suggestion and implications for the use and management of bathing beaches</article-title><source>J. Coast Res.</source><year>2014</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2112/SI72-019.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cater</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adventure and ecotourism safety in Queensland: operator experiences and practice</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2009.03.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>York</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brannon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Travel for treatment: students' perspective on medical tourism</article-title><source>Int. J. Tourism Res.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jtr.769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Health-Tourism.com</collab></person-group><part-title>Medical Tourism Statistics and Facts</part-title><year>2022</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health-tourism.com/medical-tourism/statistics/" id="intref0050">https://www.health-tourism.com/medical-tourism/statistics/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camberos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ascherman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><comment>JAN 19-23, 2004)</comment><source>Mycobacteria abscessus outbreak in US patients linked to offshore surgicenter</source><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><comment>Paper Presented at the 21st Annual Meeting of the Northeastern-Society-Of-Plastic-Surgeons</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/01.sap.0000168030.87804.93</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15985802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>p.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical tourism: assessing the evidence on treatment abroad</article-title><source>Maturitas</source><volume>66</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2010.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20185254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hee-seog</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An exploratory study on the invigoration of inbound tour through a survey on the awareness of Korean medical tourism toward American prospects customers</article-title><source>Journal of Tourism and Leisure Research</source><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>531</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conceptualizing and measuring recreation safety climate</article-title><source>Saf. Sci.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2016.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hengstmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthropogenic litter in freshwater environments – study on lake beaches evaluating marine guidelines and aerial imaging</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><volume>189</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.109945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32980020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valeri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards A framework for the global wine tourism system</article-title><source>J. Organ. Change Manag.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/JOCM-11-2020-0362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable development of rural tourism in an giang Province, vietnam</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su10040953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uysal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirgy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How does tourism in a community impact the quality of life of community residents?</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2012.09.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crime research in hospitality and tourism</article-title><source>Int. J. Contemp. Hospit. Manag.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/IJCHM-09-2019-0750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansfeld</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizam</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Tourism Security and Safety: from Theory to Practice</part-title><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Novotna</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubickova</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunc</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outdoor excitement in homeland? Opportunities and threats to balloon tourism in the Czech Republic during the coronavirus outbreak</article-title><source>Journal of Outdoor Recreation and Tourism-Research Planning and Management</source><volume>36</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jort.2021.100424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalhinho</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Security and risk management in outdoor sports - an exploratory systematic review</article-title><source>Sport TK-Revista Euroamericana de Ciencias del Deporte</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Mediation Analysis</series><volume>vol. 58</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.psych.58.110405.085542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2819368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khandakar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mediating effect of tourists' emotional involvement on the relationship between destination attributes and tourist satisfaction</article-title><source>Journal of Hospitality and Tourism Insights</source><volume>1</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/JHTI-05-2020-0075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref85"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarfraz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivascu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albasher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease 2019 safety measures for sustainable tourism: the mediating effect of tourist trust</article-title><source>Front. Psychol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">784773</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.784773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8919979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35295379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref86"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durgun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davras</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determining the antecedents influences on travel intention and willingness to pay during the pandemic</article-title><source>Int. J. Hospit. Tourism Adm.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15256480.2022.2073494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref87"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonmez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apostolopoulos</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karwowski</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complexity of occupational health in the hospitality industry: dynamic simulation modeling to advance immigrant worker health</article-title><source>Int. J. Hospit. Manag.</source><volume>67</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijhm.2017.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref88"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonmez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apostolopoulos</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the effects of COVID-19 on the health and safety of immigrant hospitality workers in the United States</article-title><source>Tourism Manag. Perspect.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmp.2020.100717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7358760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32834958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref89"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the causes of negative tourism experiences</article-title><source>Curr. Issues Tourism</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13683500.2020.1711711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An exploratory inquiry into destination risk perceptions and risk reduction strategies of first time vs. repeat visitors to a highly volatile destination</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2010.01.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref91"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shopping risk perceptions: effects on tourists' emotions, satisfaction and expressed loyalty intentions</article-title><source>Tourism Manag.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2006.04.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref92"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonmez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graefe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of terrorism risk on foreign tourism decisions</article-title><source>Ann. Tourism Res.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0160-7383(97)00072-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref93"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cambra-Fierro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes-Blasco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta-Alvarez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olavarria-Jaraba</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Destination recovery during COVID-19 in an emerging economy: insights from Peru</article-title><source>European Research on Management and Business Economics</source><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.iedeen.2021.100188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref94"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ambulatory anesthesia for cosmetic surgery in Brazil</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Anesthesiology</source><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACO.0000000000000361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27362477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref95"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Runnels</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why do patients engage in medical tourism?</article-title><source>Maturitas</source><volume>73</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2012.08.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23007007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref96"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the tourism industry: applying TRIZ and DEMATEL to construct a decision-making model</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>13</volume><issue>14</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su13147610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref97"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MCTPRC</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Guiding Opinions of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism on Implementing the Tourism Service Quality Improvement Plan</part-title><year>2019</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/zhengceku/2019-09/25/content_5433033.htm" id="intref0055">http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/zhengceku/2019-09/25/content_5433033.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref98"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MCTPRC</surname></name></person-group><part-title>Opinions on Deepening "Internet + Tourism" to Promote High-Quality Development of Tourism</part-title><year>2020</year><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zwgk.mct.gov.cn/zfxxgkml/zcfg/zcjd/202012/t20201205_915494.html" id="intref0060">http://zwgk.mct.gov.cn/zfxxgkml/zcfg/zcjd/202012/t20201205_915494.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref99"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Promote High-Quality Development of Culture and Tourism</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Weibo</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://weibo.com/ttarticle/p/show?id=2309404755183904096891" id="intref0065">https://weibo.com/ttarticle/p/show?id=2309404755183904096891</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Quantitative Analysis of the Impact of Social Media Sharing of Academic Papers</part-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>Wuhan University</publisher-name><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/Kw065jh7hXofDFzcgc3KUA" id="intref0070">https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/Kw065jh7hXofDFzcgc3KUA</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref101"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baghersad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruss</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marucchi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahams</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehsani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation into online videos as a source of safety hazard reports</article-title><source>J. Saf. Res.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsr.2018.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29776534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref104"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tourist's perceptions of safety and security while visiting Cape Town</article-title><source>Tourism Management</source><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0261-5177(03)00003-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib107"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevenka</surname><given-names>Cavlek</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tour operators and destination safety</article-title><source>Annals of Tourism Research</source><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0160-7383(01)00067-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib108"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref106"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cláudia</surname><given-names>Seabra</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolnicar</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrantes</surname><given-names>José Luís</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastenholz</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterogeneity in risk and safety perceptions of international tourists</article-title><source>Tourism Management</source><volume>36</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2012.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib109"><label>109</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref107"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visitor perceptions of crime-safety and attitudes towards risk: The case of Table Mountain National Park, Cape Town</article-title><source>Tourism Management</source><volume>31</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tourman.2009.08.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib110"><label>110</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref108"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Albuquerque</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerome</surname><given-names>McElroy</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tourism and crime in the Caribbean</article-title><source>Annals of Tourism Research</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0160-7383(99)00031-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>