
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2757</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101596737</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11232474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11232474.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11232474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11232474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38983800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.42304</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Preventive Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Quality Improvement</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of Knowledge, Attitude, and Adherence to National Guidelines for Preventing Central Line-Associated Bloodstream Infections Among ICU Nurses of Adult Patients in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia: A Cross-Sectional Survey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names initials="JR">John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names initials="AI">Abdulrahim I</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names initials="HA">Hani A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tashkandy</surname><given-names initials="NA">Nidal A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Preventive Medicine Postgraduate Program, Ministry of Health, Jeddah, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Preventive Medicine Department, Ministry of Health, Jeddah, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Infection Prevention and Control, Public Health Department, Directorate of Health Affairs, Ministry of Health, Jeddah, SAU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Abdulrahim I. Almalki <email>abdulraheem216@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">439662</issue-id><elocation-id>e42304</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-10 17:25:38.797"><day>10</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2023, Almalki et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Almalki et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000042304.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/171178-assessment-of-knowledge-attitude-and-adherence-to-national-guidelines-for-preventing-central-line-associated-bloodstream-infections-among-icu-nurses-of-adult-patients-in-jeddah-saudi-arabia-a-cross-sectional-survey">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/171178-assessment-of-knowledge-attitude-and-adherence-to-national-guidelines-for-preventing-central-line-associated-bloodstream-infections-among-icu-nurses-of-adult-patients-in-jeddah-saudi-arabia-a-cross-sectional-survey</self-uri><abstract><p>Background: Central line-associated bloodstream infections (CLABSIs) pose a significant burden on patient outcomes in intensive care units (ICUs). Adherence to evidence-based guidelines for CLABSI prevention is crucial in reducing healthcare-associated infections. This study aimed to assess the knowledge, attitude, and practice adherence to national guidelines for preventing CLABSIs among adult ICU nurses in Ministry of Health (MOH) hospitals in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. </p><p>Methods: This cross-sectional survey included all adult ICU nurses with a minimum of one year of experience from the four major MOH hospitals in Jeddah with operational adult ICUs. A self-administered online questionnaire was utilized for data collection. Descriptive statistics, t-tests, ANOVA, and Pearson correlation were employed for data analysis. </p><p>Results: A total of 203 nurses completed the questionnaire (response rate: 91.5%). The overall knowledge score was 71%. Only 20% of nurses answered over 90% of the knowledge questions correctly, and merely 8% answered all questions correctly. Higher knowledge levels were significantly associated with older age, longer ICU nursing experience, higher education, holding a head nurse position, and attending educational courses on CLABSI prevention. Regarding attitudes, 58% of respondents had a positive perception of guideline utility for CLABSI prevention. In terms of adherence, the overall score was 65%, with only 5% reporting complete adherence to evidence-based practices for preventing CLABSIs. </p><p>Conclusion: This study highlights knowledge gaps, suboptimal adherence, and the need for targeted interventions to enhance nurses' understanding of and adherence to evidence-based guidelines for preventing CLABSIs among adult ICU nurses in Jeddah's MOH hospitals. Enhancing knowledge, attitudes, and practice adherence is crucial for reducing CLABSI risks and improving patient outcomes. Further research investigating the factors influencing nurses' knowledge, acceptance, and application of evidence-based guidelines is warranted to inform the development of tailored interventions and educational strategies. </p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>healthcare-associated infection</kwd><kwd>infection control guidelines</kwd><kwd>infection control and prevention</kwd><kwd>central line-associated bloodstream infections (clabsi)</kwd><kwd>central venous catheter infection</kwd><kwd>icu nursing</kwd><kwd>adult intensive care unit</kwd><kwd>jeddah saudi arbia</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Central line-associated bloodstream infections (CLABSIs) are a common and avoidable complication of central venous catheters (CVC) ​[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]​. CLABSIs lead to significant morbidity, mortality, prolonged hospital stays, and increased healthcare costs ​[<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]​. Patients with CLABSIs are at a higher risk of in-hospital mortality and readmission compared to those without CLABSIs ​[<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]​. The average cost of treating a single case of CLABSI is approximately $46,000 ​[<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]​. </p><p>A prospective surveillance study conducted in 109 Ministry of Health (MOH) hospitals in Saudi Arabia reported an overall CLABSI rate of 3.24 per 1,000 central line-days, which is higher than rates observed in developed countries ​[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]​. For example, in the United States (US), the intensive care unit (ICU) CLABSI rate is estimated to be 0.8 per 1,000 central line-days ​[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]​. These findings emphasize the need to address CLABSI prevention strategies in Saudi Arabia and implement effective measures aligned with international standards, following evidence-based guidelines for CVC insertion and maintenance. </p><p>ICU nurses play a crucial role in providing quality care and ensuring patient safety in the ICU setting [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, studies from various countries have revealed a lack of knowledge and adherence to best practices among ICU nurses, as outlined by guidelines from agencies like the US CDC ​[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]​. </p><p>Assessing the knowledge and adherence of nursing staff to national guidelines for CLABSI prevention is crucial for identifying areas of improvement. Targeted educational interventions can then be implemented to enhance adherence, reduce the incidence of CLABSI, and improve patient outcomes. Limited research exists on this issue in Saudi Arabia, particularly concerning ICU nursing staff in MOH hospitals in Jeddah. Therefore, this study aimed to assess the knowledge, attitude, and practice adherence of adult ICU nursing staff in MOH hospitals in Jeddah, regarding national evidence-based guidelines for preventing CLABSIs. </p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Study design and study population</p><p>This cross-sectional survey was conducted between April and June 2023. All ICU nurses (n=222) working in adult ICUs for at least one year in the major four MOH hospitals in Jeddah with operational adult ICUs were invited to participate. The inclusion criteria were selected based on the experience level of the nurses to ensure an adequate understanding of CLABSI prevention guidelines. </p><p>Data collection</p><p>Data was collected using an online self-administered questionnaire based on Saudi MOH guideline recommendations for the prevention of CLABSIs, which are identical to the CDC guidelines. The questionnaire, originally designed and validated by Luciana Albano et al., underwent a modification in which all references to the CDC guidelines were changed to the Saudi MOH guidelines [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]​. This change was made to ensure alignment with the guidelines familiar to the nursing staff in the participating hospitals, as they commonly refer to the Saudi MOH guidelines instead of the CDC guidelines. </p><p>The questionnaire consisted of five sections: demographic and professional data, knowledge of healthcare-associated infections and CLABSI prevention based on the Saudi MOH guidelines, attitudes toward the utility of guidelines, behaviors and practices related to CVC insertion and management, and sources of information and educational needs. The knowledge assessment section comprised 11 multiple-choice questions (MCQs) related to knowledge about the CDC's main recommendations for preventing CLABSI. The questionnaire demonstrated a high degree of internal consistency, as evidenced by a Cronbach's α value of 0.83 and an inter-item correlation coefficient (r) of 0.46 ​[<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]​. </p><p>Statistical analysis</p><p>Continuous variables were summarized using mean, standard deviation, or range (for age), while categorical data were presented as numbers and percentages. The knowledge score for each respondent was calculated by assigning one point for every correct answer. These scores were then summed up to represent the total number of correct answers out of a maximum score of 11. The overall knowledge score for the knowledge section was reported as a percentage, representing the proportion of correct answers achieved out of the total possible correct answers for all respondents. Adherence and attitude rates were presented as percentages. Total scores between two groups were compared using an independent t-test, and for comparisons among three or more groups, a one-way ANOVA was conducted followed by Bonferroni post-hoc pairwise comparisons. Data analysis was performed using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 24.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY). A two-tailed p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p><p>Ethical considerations</p><p>Ethical approval was obtained from the Ministry of Health Institutional Review Board in Jeddah (code A01604) prior to data collection. Informed consent was obtained from all participants, and confidentiality of data was ensured throughout the study. </p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 203 nurses completed the questionnaire (response rate: 91.5%). Among them, 164 (80.8%) were female, with a mean age of 33 (range: 23-54). The majority held a bachelor's degree (78.3%, n=159), and a significant portion had attended educational courses on CVC maintenance (79.3%, n=161). Details of participants' characteristics are presented in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. </p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the respondents (N=203).</title><p><sup>a </sup>Age reported as mean and range</p><p>ICU, intensive care unit; MOH, Ministry of Health; CVC, central venous catheter</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (19.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (80.8%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years<sup>a</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (23-54)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Highest educational level</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (18.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor's degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (78.3%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master's degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursing level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189 (93.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head Nurse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (6.9%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Length of ICU nursing experience, years</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 – &lt;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (19.2%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 – 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (15.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 – 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (38.4%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (26.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Have you ever attended educational courses on the maintenance of CVCs?</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161 (79.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (20.7%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is there an internal care protocol in your hospital for the prevention of intravascular catheter-related infections?</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (96.1%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you follow the Saudi MOH Guidelines for the prevention of intravascular catheter-related infections as a source of information?</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 (98.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1.5%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you feel that you need more information regarding the prevention of CVC-related infections?</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (65.5%)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (34.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The knowledge section of the questionnaire had an overall correct response rate of 71%. The mean score for the 11 questions in this section was 7.84, with a standard deviation of 1.82. Scores ranged from 4 to 11. Only 20% (n=41) of participants answered more than 90% (10 or more questions) correctly, while a mere 7.9% (n=16) answered all questions correctly. The distribution of knowledge scores is presented in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. </p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Distribution of knowledge of national guideline recommendations for preventing CLABSI scores among respondents.</title><p>CLABSI, central line-associated bloodstream infections</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000042304-i01.jpg"/></fig><p>Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref> provides a breakdown of the questions in the knowledge of guideline recommendations for preventing CLABSI section of the questionnaire, along with the corresponding correct response rates. </p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Responses to the "Knowledge of national guideline recommendations for preventing CLABSI" section of the questionnaire. </title><p>CVC, central venous catheters; CLABSI, central line-associated bloodstream infections</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of correct  responses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of correct responses</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The routine replacement of CVCs is a recommended strategy to prevent infection?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.50%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The use of antibiotic ointment at the CVC insertion site is recommended for reducing infections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.20%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often should administration sets used for standard infusions be replaced?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.60%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often should a clean and intact sterile gauze on the catheter insertion site be replaced?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.60%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">If the adherence to aseptic technique cannot be ensured during the CVC insertion, the catheter should be replaced within 48 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often should a clean and intact transparent dressing on the catheter insertion site be replaced?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.50%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is recommended to be used for cleaning the skin before CVC insertion and during dressing changes?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.90%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have you ever attended educational courses about the maintenance of CVCs?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.30%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often should the administration sets used to administer blood, blood products, or fat emulsions be replaced?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.60%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insertion and maintenance of CVCs must be preceded by hand hygiene procedures</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.00%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insertion of CVCs must be performed using sterile gloves</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.50%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Higher levels of knowledge were found to be significantly associated with age (Pearson’s r=0.5), higher education (master's degree), holding the position of a head nurse, having a longer length of ICU nursing experience, and attending educational courses on CVC maintenance. Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents a summary of the results from subgroup analyses, which were stratified by demographic and other variables. </p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Subgroup analysis of knowledge scores. </title><p>Post-hoc comparisons utilized the Bonferroni test following significant one-way ANOVA results</p><p>ICU, intensive care unit; CVC, central venous catheter; SD, standard deviation</p><p> </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significantly different from group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t/F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cohort (N=302)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.84±1.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (n=39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9±1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (n=164)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8±1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest educational level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma (n=37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bachelor's degree (n=159)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62±1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Master's degree (n=7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10±0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A, B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursing level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-12.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse (n=189 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6±1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head nurse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head nurse (n=14 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2±0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Length of ICU nursing experience, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A. 1 – &lt;3 (n=39 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1±1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B, C, D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B. 3 – 5 (n=32 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 – 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A, D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C. 6 – 10 (n=78 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.95±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A, D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D. &gt;10 (n=54 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A, C, D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Attendance of educational courses on CVC maintenance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attended courses (n=161 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2±1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never attended courses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never attended courses (n=42 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3±1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 – 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attended courses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The overall correct response rate regarding the utility of guideline recommendations in preventing CLABSI was 65%. Only 58% of respondents perceived the utility of guidelines positively for CLABSI prevention. </p><p>In terms of adherence to recommended evidence-based practices for CVC maintenance, the overall rate of correct responses was 65.5%. However, it is important to note that none of the participants reported performing CVC insertion, as this procedure is almost always conducted by a physician in MOH hospitals. Therefore, no responses related to the practice adherence to CVC insertion were received. Only a small 5% of respondents reported complete adherence, scoring a maximum of 5 out of 5, to guideline recommendations in other aspects of CVC maintenance. </p><p>Table <xref rid="TAB4" ref-type="table">4</xref> provides a breakdown of the questions in the "adherence to recommended evidence-based practices for CVC maintenance" section of the questionnaire, along with the corresponding correct response rates. </p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Responses to the "Adherence to recommended evidence-based practices for CVC maintenance" section of the questionnaire. </title><p>CVC; central venous catheters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of correct  responses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of correct responses</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before replacing catheter site dressing, do you perform hand hygiene?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often do you visually monitor the catheter site when changing the dressing?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.70%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often do you perform the palpation of the site through the intact dressing on a regular basis?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.70%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">How often do you remove the site dressing if patients have tenderness to allow a thorough examination of the site?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.30%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">If a patient with a central line catheter has a fever, what is the best next step?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.30%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Knowledge scores showed a weak positive correlation with the perception of guideline utility for CLABSI prevention (r=0.256) and practice adherence scores (r=0.147). </p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study included adult ICU nurses from the four major MOH hospitals in Jeddah city with operational adult ICUs. Our findings show a moderate overall knowledge level of CDC guideline recommendations, with an average score of 71%. Notably, only 20% of participants answered over 90% of the questions correctly, and just 7.8% answered all questions correctly. Compared to the study conducted by Almahmoud et al. at King Abdul-Aziz Medical City in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, our participants demonstrated a lower knowledge level (82% in Riyadh) ​[<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]​. It is important to consider that their study used a different questionnaire and was conducted in a specialized tertiary medical center. Interestingly, the knowledge level in our study is higher than the average reported in similar studies from various countries ​[<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]​. </p><p>Multiple questions in the CDC guideline recommendations knowledge section of the questionnaire received remarkably low rates of correct responses, indicating notable knowledge gaps. For instance, a mere 36.5% of nurses were aware that routine replacement of CVC is not recommended for infection prevention. Similarly, only 55.2% of participants knew that using antibiotic ointment at the CVC insertion site is not recommended. Additionally, just 57% accurately identified the proper timing for replacing administration sets and clean, sterile gauze at the insertion site. </p><p>Older age, having a longer length of ICU nursing experience, higher education (master's degree), holding the position of a head nurse, and attending educational courses on CVC maintenance were significantly associated with higher levels of knowledge scores. These results are consistent with prior research, highlighting that increased nursing experience, along with formal education and training, can enhance familiarity with evidence-based guidelines for preventing CLABSIs ​[<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>-<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]​. </p><p>Only 58% of the respondents had a positive perception of the guidelines' utility in preventing CLABSI, indicating a considerable proportion with unfavorable views on their effectiveness. This highlights a notable gap between knowledge and perception among the participants, underscoring the importance of exploring factors influencing healthcare professionals' acceptance of guidelines. Investigating these factors is crucial to ensure successful implementation and adherence to CLABSI prevention guidelines. </p><p>The study found an overall adherence rate of 65.5% to evidence-based practices for CVC maintenance. However, only 5% of respondents reported complete adherence, scoring a maximum of 5 out of 5, highlighting a significant gap between knowledge and practice. Ongoing education and targeted interventions are needed to improve adherence among nursing staff, minimize CVC-related infection risks, and enhance patient outcomes. Further research should explore factors influencing adherence to guide the development of effective interventions and educational strategies. </p><p>Limitations of this study include its limited generalizability to other regions or practices beyond MOH hospitals in Jeddah. Additionally, focusing solely on ICU nurses may not capture the full spectrum of CVC procedures in various departments. The reliance on self-reporting introduces potential bias, and the unsupervised nature of data collection raises concerns about participants looking up answers. Furthermore, the cross-sectional design restricts causal interpretations. Future research should address these limitations by considering diverse settings, employing objective assessment methods, and utilizing longitudinal designs. </p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, this study highlights knowledge gaps, negative perceptions, and inadequate adherence to evidence-based guidelines for preventing CLABSIs among ICU nurses in Jeddah's MOH hospitals. To address these issues and enhance patient safety, targeted educational interventions, continuous training programs, and regular guideline updates are recommended. Further research is needed to understand the factors influencing nurses' acceptance and application of the guidelines, facilitating the development of effective strategies for improving adherence and promoting infection prevention practices in the ICU. </p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ministry of Health Institutional Review Board in Jeddah issued approval A01604.</p><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>International Nosocomial Infection Control Consortium report, data summary of 50 countries for 2010-2015: device-associated module</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Abdely</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kholy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1495</fpage><lpage>1504</lpage><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27742143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajic.2016.08.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Attributable mortality of central line associated bloodstream infection: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Infection</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Safdar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><volume>43</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25331552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s15010-014-0689-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Preventing central line-associated bloodstream infections</article-title><source>J Nurs Care Qual</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kusek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><volume>27</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22929645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/NCQ.0b013e31825733d1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Association of CLABSI with hospital length of stay, readmission rates, and mortality: a retrospective review</article-title><source>Worldviews Evid Based Nurs</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chovanec</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arsene</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><volume>18</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34779128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/wvn.12548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Central line associated blood stream infections</article-title><source>Healthcare-Associated Infections in Children</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holzmann-Pazgal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Burden of central-line-associated bloodstream infections in 106 Ministry of Health hospitals of Saudi Arabia: a 2-year surveillance study</article-title><source>Int J Infect Control</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alqahtani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Humayun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>20978</fpage><volume>17</volume><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Nurse staffing and healthcare-associated infections in a national healthcare system that implemented a nurse staffing directive: Multi-level interrupted time series analyses</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Annis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yosef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>103531</fpage><volume>104</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32062053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Nurses' compliance with central line associated blood stream infection prevention guidelines</article-title><source>Saudi Med J</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aloush</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaraireh</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29543306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15537/smj.2018.3.21497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5893917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevention of central line-associated bloodstream infections: a survey of ICU nurses' knowledge and practice in China</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>186</fpage><volume>9</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33198796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13756-020-00833-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7667726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Educating intensive care unit nurses to use central venous catheter infection prevention guidelines: effectiveness of an educational course</article-title><source>J Res Nurs</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aloush</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34394451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1744987118762992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7932335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Knowledge, attitudes, and practice on the prevention of central line-associated bloodstream infections among nurses in oncological care: a cross-sectional study in an area of southern Italy</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guillari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Angelillo</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0180473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5493401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28665993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The adherence to guidelines for preventing CVC-related infections: a survey among Italian health-care workers</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Albano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>606</fpage><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30509200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12879-018-3514-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6276178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Assessment knowledge and practices of central line insertion and maintenance in adult intensive care units at a tertiary care hospital in Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>J Infect Public Health</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Almahmoud</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alfarhan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1694</fpage><lpage>1698</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32741732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jiph.2020.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7606903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Oncology nurses' knowledge of guidelines for preventing catheter-related bloodstream infections</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Al Qadire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><volume>45</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajic.2017.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28502638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevention of central venous catheter infections: a survey of paediatric ICU nurses' knowledge and practice</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ullman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><volume>34</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24070818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nedt.2013.09.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Guidelines for preventing catheter infection: assessment of knowledge and practice among paediatric and neonatal intensive care healthcare workers</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guembe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bustinza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez Luna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo-Álvarez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Sheriff</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bouza</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><volume>81</volume><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhin.2012.02.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention guidelines for preventing central venous catheter-related infection: results of a knowledge test among 3405 European intensive care nurses</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Labeau</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vandijck</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rello</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19050628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/CCM.0b013e3181926489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevention of central venous catheter-associated bloodstream infections: a questionnaire evaluating the knowledge of the selected 11 evidence-based guidelines by Polish nurses</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dedunska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1368</fpage><lpage>1371</lpage><volume>43</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26307045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajic.2015.07.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>