
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Natl J Maxillofac Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Natl J Maxillofac Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1762</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">njmaxsurg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101578767</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NJMS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Natl J Maxillofac Surg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>National Journal of Maxillofacial Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0975-5950</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2229-3418</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13342732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC13342732.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13342732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13342732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42422800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/njms.njms_29_24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">NJMS-17-316</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Utility of tooth as an autogenous graft material in the management of intraoperative alveolar bony defects—A clinical trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datarkar</surname><given-names initials="A">Abhay</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhawalkar</surname><given-names initials="A">Amit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names initials="V">Vartik</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daware</surname><given-names initials="S">Surendra</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Government Dental College and Hospital, Nagpur, Government Medical College Premises, Medical Square, Nagpur, Maharashtra, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
<bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Vartik Shah, Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Government Dental College and Hospital, Nagpur, Government Medical College Premises, Medical Square, Nagpur - 440 003, Maharashtra, India. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="vartikm@gmail.com">vartikm@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Aug</season><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>6</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">517250</issue-id><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-07-09 09:25:20.113"><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2026 National Journal of Maxillofacial Surgery</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 License (CC BY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Autogenous bone grafts, though considered the gold standard in maxillofacial surgery defects, involve a separate surgery and can cause donor site morbidity. Using autogenous tooth grafts can reduce such issues, offering a potential alternative with less morbidity.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives:</title><p>To find out the utility of freshly extracted teeth as an autogenous graft material in the management of intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defects.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>We performed a non-randomized clinical trial including 25 patients with mild (&lt;1 cm<sup>3</sup>)- to moderate (1-2 cm<sup>3</sup>)-sized odontogenic pathology including cyst or tumor, and impacted third molar and canine indicated for extraction and patients with cleft lip and palate requiring secondary alveolar bone grafting. All patients were evaluated intraoperatively, clinically, and radiographically for the following parameters—volume of the processed autogenous graft from the teeth, size of the intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defect, post-operative healing at 3<sup>rd</sup> month and 6<sup>th</sup> month, and post-operative infection rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Of 25 patients, 16 patients had relative bone healing (RBH) score at 6 months (RBH 6M) greater than 0.97 (score 0), suggesting ideal healing of the surgical defect after 6 months postgrafting. Seven patients had RBH 6M between 0.96 and 0.80 (score 1), suggesting good healing. Two patients had RBH 6M less than 0.80 (score 2), suggesting poor healing. Post-operative infection was found in one patient of the 25 patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Autogenous tooth graft is an excellent and equally effective option to the conventional autogenous bone graft with the added advantage of no donor site morbidity.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Autogenous tooth graft</kwd><kwd>maxillofacial surgical defects</kwd><kwd>osteoinductive</kwd><kwd>osteoconductive</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>
Nil.
</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Various surgical procedures are performed in the oral and maxillofacial region to treat odontogenic cysts, odontogenic tumors, alveolar cleft, and impacted teeth. Some kind of defect is always created after these surgical procedures. In these surgical defects, various bone graft materials are used. These include autografts, allografts, xenografts, and alloplasts. Autogenous bone graft is considered the gold standard.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p><p>Dentin matrix has long been proven to be osteoinductive and rich in bone morphogenetic protein (BMP).[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Also, the concentration of transforming growth factor (TGF-β), insulin growth factor-I (IGF-I), and insulin growth factor-II (IGF-II) was detected in human dentin matrix by various studies.[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] It is well known that jaw bones, alveolar bone, and teeth develop from cells of the neural crest and that many proteins are common to bone, dentin, and cementum.[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p><p>Currently, all extracted teeth are considered a clinical waste and therefore are simply discarded. Recently, several studies reported that extracted teeth from patients that undergo a process of cleaning, grinding, demineralization, and sterilization are a very effective graft to fill alveolar bone defects of the same patient. When the autogenous tooth grafting is conducted in the patients, there is little immune rejection response.[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] The autogenous bone grafting is still the gold standard in grafting the maxillofacial defects.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] The autogenous bone can be harvested intra-orally from the chin, lateral ramus, maxillary tuberosity, maxillary buttress, palate, etc., and extra-orally from the iliac crest, calvarium, tibia, rib, etc.[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] However, there are problems with autogenous bone grafting, which include donor site morbidity, infection at the donor side, limited amount of available bone mass, and marked resorption of the grafted bone.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] The use of autogenous tooth graft in such defects can certainly reduce the donor site morbidity and other issues associated with autogenous bone grafting. The few studies published in the literature regarding the use of autogenous tooth graft are mostly based on augmenting peri-implant defects with excellent success.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] At present, there is scarcity of the literature regarding the use of this novel technique in alveolar jaw defects created by odontogenic pathologies and alveolar cleft.</p><p>This study was planned in our department to find out the utility of tooth as an autogenous graft material in the management of intraoperative alveolar bony defects.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>This study was planned in the Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery to find out the utility of tooth as an autogenous graft material in managing the intraoperative alveolar bony defects. This study included 25 patients with mild (&lt;1 cm<sup>3</sup>)- to moderate (1-2 cm<sup>3</sup>)-sized odontogenic pathology including cyst or tumor, and impacted third molar and canine indicated for extraction and patients with cleft lip and palate requiring secondary alveolar bone grafting. Exclusion criteria included patients with systemic disease contraindicating any invasive procedures, patients with root pieces and absent third molars, patients with endodontically treated teeth, and patients with frank infection. Ethical Clearance was obtained from Ethics Committee with Ref no MUHS/PG-T/E2/09/18 dated 28/10/2018.</p><p>The procedure to be performed was explained, followed by written informed consent. The Institutional Ethical Committee approved the clinical trial, and all subjects gave informed consent. A detailed case history was recorded in a specially prepared case history proforma.</p><sec><title>Surgical procedures</title><p>
<bold>I. Exposure of the surgical site</bold>
</p><p>a) Mild to moderate odontogenic pathology:</p><p>The patients were maintained under local anesthesia. About 2% lignocaine with epinephrine was given intra-orally along the planned surgical site. A full-thickness mucoperiosteal flap was reflected after giving a crevicular incision with two releasing incisions. The buccal cortical plate over the affected part was removed to expose the odontogenic pathology completely. Enucleation was conducted carefully, all the teeth associated with cysts or tumors were extracted, and sharp edges were smoothened using the bone file.</p><p>b) Alveolar cleft:</p><p>The patients were intubated with south pole tube endotracheal tube. The surgical site was infiltrated with 2% lignocaine with epinephrine. The labiobuccal mucoperiosteal flap was elevated after incising around the cleft margins. The incision was then extended along the gingival margins, from the upper first molar on the cleft side to the opposite side canine for the patients with unilateral cleft alveolus and to the opposite upper first molar tooth for the patients with bilateral cleft alveolus [Figures <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>]. In the patients having a bilateral alveolar cleft, the dissection in the pre-maxillary region was limited to preserve its blood supply. Elevation of the palatal mucoperiosteal flaps was performed to adequately visualize the cleft with the piriform aperture and the anterior nasal spine in the site.</p><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f001" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Alveolar Cleft Pre-operative image and OPG</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f002" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Alveolar Cleft- Intraoperative Images. A) Exposure of surgical defect, B) Extraction of impacted 45, C) Extracted teeth ready for processing, D Grafting of autogenous tooth graft</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>c) Impacted third molar indicated for prophylactic removal:</p><p>The patients were maintained under local anesthesia. Inferior alveolar nerve block along with the lingual nerve block and long buccal nerve blocks were given on the side of the impacted tooth with 2% lignocaine with 1:80000 epinephrine. Ward’s I or modified Ward’s incisions were taken. The distal and buccal bone was guttered, and the extraction was conducted as atraumatic as possible. In cases, which required tooth sectioning, it was conducted.</p><p>d) Impacted canine indicated for orthodontic extraction:</p><p>The patients were maintained under local anesthesia. Required nerve blocks were given based on the site of the impacted canine with 2% lignocaine with 1:80000 epinephrine. Crevicular or vestibular incisions were made and full-thickness mucoperiosteal flaps were reflected. Buccal or palatal bone was removed based on the location of the canine to expose the crown. The crown of the impacted canine was exposed up to the cementoenamel junction (CEJ), and the tooth was extracted in toto or by sectioning the canine [Figures <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f003" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Impacted Canine Pre-operative image and OPG</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f004" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Impacted Canine- Intraoperative images, A) Exposure of impacted canine, B) Exposure of surgical defect, C) Extracted tooth ready for processing, D) Grafting of autogenous tooth graft</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>
<bold>II. Preparation of the autologous tooth graft: [<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>]</bold>
</p><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f005" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Preparation of autologous tooth graft</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Immediately after the extraction, the discolored dentin or remnants of periodontal ligament (PDL) and calculus were reduced by tungsten bur. Clean teeth including crown and root dentin were dried by air syringe and then inserted into a grinding sterile chamber of a newly designed KometaBio Smart Dentin Grinder. The particulate dentin from the drawer was immersed in basic alcohol for 10 minutes, in a small sterile glass container. The alcohol cleanser consists of 0.5M of NaOH and 30% alcohol (v/v), for defatting, dissolving all organic debris, bacteria, and toxins of the dentin particulate.</p><p>After decanting the basic alcohol cleanser, the particulate was washed twice, in sterile phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). The PBS was then decanted leaving wet particulate dentin ready to graft into the defect.</p><p>
<bold>III. Insertion of graft and final closure:</bold>
</p><p>The autogenous tooth graft was inserted in the surgical defect and was evenly filled. As we used autogenous tooth graft material for mild- to moderate-sized defects, the amount of graft material obtained was sufficient to completely fill the defect. Hemostasis was achieved, and final closure was conducted with 3-0 and 4-0 vicryl. However, in patients with mandibular odontogenic pathology or deeply seated impacted canine where considerable amount of bone was removed, pressure dressing was given to the patients to prevent hematoma and swelling over the operated region.</p><p>The patients were evaluated intraoperatively and post-operatively for various parameters. Post-operatively, patients were evaluated clinically at 7<sup>th</sup> day, 3<sup>rd</sup> month, and 6<sup>th</sup> month, while radiographically at 3<sup>rd</sup> month and 6<sup>th</sup> month on panoramic radiographs.</p></sec><sec><title>Parameters assessed</title><p>All patients were evaluated intraoperatively, clinically, and radiographically for the following parameters:</p></sec><sec><title>Intraoperative parameters</title><p>1. Volume of the processed autogenous graft from the teeth[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]:</p><p>The volume of the processed autogenous graft from the teeth was measured in cubic centimeters (cc) by placing the graft in a graduated sterile 10-ml syringe with markings. After inserting the graft inside the syringe, a compacting pressure of 100 g was applied, and saline solution (1 mL) was added to fill the voids. To account for the previous saline addition, 1 mL was subtracted from the final measured volume. Then, the average volume was calculated from the measured volumes of processed autogenous tooth graft from each patient.</p><p>2. Size of the intraoperative alveolar bony defect[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><p>The size of the intraoperative alveolar bony defect was measured by the same operating surgeon in cubic centimeters (cm<sup>3</sup>) by multiplying the longest height in cm, width in cm, and depth in cm after the surgical site was opened. It was classified as mild when the defect was 0–1 cm<sup>3</sup>, moderate when it was 1–2 cm<sup>3</sup>, and severe when the defect was more than 2 cm<sup>3</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Post-operative parameters</title><p>1. Post-operative healing at 3<sup>rd</sup> month and 6<sup>th</sup> month:</p><p>Post-operative bone healing was assessed by comparing the Orthopantomogram (OPGs) (SIRONA ORTHOPHOS XG 3D) before grafting the surgical defect, at 3<sup>rd</sup> month and 6<sup>th</sup> month postgrafting [Figures <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>-<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-f008" ref-type="fig">8A-C</xref>]. OPG was taken at settings of 60 KVp, 7 mA, and 0.25 seconds. The OPGs were digitalized and then analyzed using the computer software (SIRONA SIDEXIS XG System).</p><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f006" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Alveolar cleft Post-operative OPG, A) 3 months Post-Op OPG, B) 6 months Post-Op OPG</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g006.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f007" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Impacted Canine Post-operative OPG, A) 3 months Post-Op OPG, B) 6 months Post-Op OPG</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g007.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-f008" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Measurement of relative bone density of surgical defect and surrounding normal bone (A) Pre-grafting, (B) At 3 months, (C) At 6 months</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="NJMS-17-316-g008.jpg"/></fig><p>The area of defect projection on the OPGs was determined as well as the area of surrounding bone without other anatomical structures such as spongiform bone. Then, relative bone density of the surgical defect and the area around them were then measured in percentage of the pixels.</p><p>Indexes of relative bone healing (RBH) at 3<sup>rd</sup> and 6<sup>th</sup> month were calculated as the quotients of bone density of pixel percentage in the area of the surgical defect and the area of the surrounding bone on the same OPG as given by Hren and Miljavec.[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Ideal healing occurs when the bone density of the surgical defect becomes the same as that in the surrounding bone. Therefore, the maximal index of RBH was 1, and an index between 0.97 and 1 was considered an ideal healing.[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] If the index of RBH was between 0.96 and 0.80, it was considered a good healing. Based on the data from various studies, panoramic-based mandibular and maxillary indices of dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry for diagnosing osteoporosis, mean density of the bone approximately less than 20% of the normal bone was considered osteopenic;[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] therefore, if the index of RBH was less than 0.80, it was considered poor healing.</p><p>2. Post-operative infection:</p><p>Any infection of the grafted site was evaluated on 7<sup>th</sup> day, 3<sup>rd</sup> month, and 6<sup>th</sup> month post-operatively. Criteria for infection were based on either of the following conditions:</p><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Purulent discharge from the incision.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pain in the operated region.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Serosanguinous drainage and a positive wound culture for a known pathogen.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>If the infection was absent, a score of 0 was assigned, while the presence of infection was denoted by score 1.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Data obtained were compiled on an MS Office Excel Sheet (v 2019, Microsoft Redmond Campus, Redmond, Washington, USA). Data were subjected to statistical analysis using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS v 26.0, IBM). Descriptive statistics, such as frequencies and percentage for categorical data, and mean and standard deviation (SD) for numerical data, have been depicted. The intragroup comparison was conducted using paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test (up to two observations). The intragroup comparison was conducted using repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) (for &gt;2 observations) followed by the <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> test.</p><p>For all the statistical tests, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant, keeping α error at 5% and β error at 20%, thus giving a power to the study as 80%.</p><p>The results of parameters are given in Tables <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t001" ref-type="table">1</xref>-<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t011" ref-type="table">11</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25) according to age (years)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. deviation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.928</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25) according to gender</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25) according to the category of diagnosis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alveolar cleft</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impacted canine</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impacted third molar</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odontogenic pathology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Distribution as per teeth used for autogenous tooth grafting (FDI system)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth no (FDI)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 and 13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 and 23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 and 18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25, 26, and 27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31, 32, 41, 42, and 43</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 and 38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 and 38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37, 38, and 18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,48, and 24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 and 42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44, 45, and 46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 and 46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 47, and 17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t005" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics of the total volume of the processed autogenous tooth graft (cc)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. deviation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total volume of graft (cc)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.485</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t006" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Distribution as per category of the intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defect</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category of the defect</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t007" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of relative bone density of the intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defect (RIMD) and relative bone density of the surrounding normal bone (RNB) between time intervals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Dependent variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Time</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Std. deviation</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Std. error</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% confidence interval for mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mini mum</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Maxim um</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of RM ANOVA</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower bound</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper bound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(RIMD) (%) Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60456</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32091</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1338</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5862</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.5000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.37780</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67556</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0418</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9582</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.806</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.20184</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44037</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5533</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6267</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6500</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.74300</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58690</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4880</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8120</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(RNB) (%) Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4300</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.35552</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47110</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3299</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5301</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.36353</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.4234</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.43887</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48777</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4255</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6945</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1033</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.22730</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41189</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2901</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>**Statistically significant, <sup>#</sup>Statistically insignificant</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t008" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Pairwise comparison of RIMD and RNB between time intervals</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Dependent variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">(I) Time</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">(J) Time</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Mean difference (I-J)</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Std. error</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% confidence interval</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower bound</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper bound</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(RIMD) (%) Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-13.64000*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64672</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-19.9739</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.3061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-24.73000*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64672</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-31.0639</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-18.3961</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.09000*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64672</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-17.4239</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.7561</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(RNB) (%) Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.89000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50330</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965<sup>#</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.2738</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4938</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.13000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50330</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944<sup>#</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.5138</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2538</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.24000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50330</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.997<sup>#</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.6238</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1438</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Significant, **Statistically significant, #Statistically insignificant</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t009" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Comparison of relative bone healing (RBH) 3<sup>rd</sup> month (M) vs 6<sup>th</sup> month (M) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=25)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. deviation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. error mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean diff</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD of diff</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7012</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12293</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02459</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.2204000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1179859</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.340</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.921600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1080771</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0216154</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>**Statistically significant</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t010" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics (mean and standard deviation) for score of relative bone healing (RBH) at 6<sup>th</sup> month postgrafting</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score of RBH 6M</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="njms.njms_29_24-t011" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 11</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics (mean and standard deviation) for post-operative infection score</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-operative infection score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The mean age of the cases was 27.12 ± 7.928 years. Twelve (48.0%) of the total cases were females, and 13 (52.0%) were males. Of the 25 patients, there were two patients (8%) with alveolar cleft, three patients (12%) with impacted canine, three patients (12%) with impacted 3<sup>rd</sup> molar, and 17 patients (68%) with odontogenic pathology [Tables <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t001" ref-type="table">1</xref>-<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t003" ref-type="table">3</xref>].</p><p>The total number of molars used for processing autogenous tooth graft was 20 (45%), of premolars was 6 (14%), of canines was 6 (14%), and of incisors was 12 (27%), suggesting that the molars were used the most in preparing autogenous tooth graft in this study. The mean total volume of the processed autogenous graft from the teeth in cubic centimeters (cc) was 3.04 cc ± 1.485 with the maximum volume of 6 cc and minimum volume of 1 cc. The data show that the total volume of the autogenous tooth graft was based on the number of teeth used and the size of teeth used with posterior teeth giving more volume than the anterior teeth. Of the 25 patients, nine patients (36%) had mild defects and 16 patients (64%) had moderate defects [Tables <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t004" ref-type="table">4</xref>-<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t006" ref-type="table">6</xref>].</p><p>The relative bone density of the intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defect (RIMD) (%) mean before grafting was 19.8600 ± 6.60456 (std. error = 1.32091), 33.5000 ± 8.37780 (std. error = 1.67556) for 3<sup>rd</sup> month postgrafting, and 44.5900 ± 12.20184 (std. error = 2.44037) for 6<sup>th</sup> month postgrafting. The relative bone density of the surrounding normal bone (RNB) (%) mean before grafting was 47.4300 ± 12.35552 (std. error = 2.47110) and 48.3200 ± 12.36353 (std. error = 2.47271). Using repeated-measures ANOVA test, there was a statistically highly significant difference seen for the values between the time intervals for RIMD with higher values at 6M, with the data showing increase in the bone density of the defect postgrafting (f = 43.806, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, 95% confidence interval for mean). Using the <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> tests, there was a statistically highly significant difference seen for the values for RIMD between all the time pairs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, 95% confidence interval), while there was a statistically non-significant difference seen for the values between all the time pairs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05, 95% confidence interval) for (RNB) (%) mean. Using paired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, there was a statistically highly significant difference seen for the values between the time intervals with higher values of RBH at 6<sup>th</sup> month postgrafting [Tables <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t007" ref-type="table">7</xref>-<xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t009" ref-type="table">9</xref>].</p><p>Of 25 patients, 16 patients had RBH 6M (RBH at 6 months) greater than 0.97 (score 0), suggesting ideal healing of the surgical defect after 6 months postgrafting. Seven patients had RBH 6M between 0.96 and 0.80 (score 1), suggesting good healing. Two patients had RBH 6M less than 0.80 (score 2), suggesting poor healing. The mean post-operative infection score was 0.04 with minimum of 0 and maximum of 1. The data show that of 25 patients, only one patient had a score of 1, suggesting that there was an infection of the grafted site in that patient [Tables <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t010" ref-type="table">10</xref> and <xref rid="njms.njms_29_24-t011" ref-type="table">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The science of autogenous grafting in oral and maxillofacial defects has come a long way from its beginning years in the early 1900s.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Initially, Wolff[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] had defined osteoplasty as a procedure in which bone or bone-stimulating tissue is grafted in the body to effect the permanent existence of bone at that site and thus predicted on his animal experiments that in future, autogenous bone grafting can be used in treating acquired and congenital defects of the jaw. Burri[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] highlighted the role of autogenous cancellous bone as the substance of choice for bridging and filling defects. Later, Spiessl[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] confirmed that autogenous graft has all the characteristics of living bone.</p><p>There are various clinical reports and studies regarding the application of autogenous tooth graft in the augmentation of peri-implant defects, sinus bone graft, ridge augmentation, guided bone regeneration, and socket preservation or graft, and they have proven to be useful materials for hard tissue defect restoration.[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] But no comprehensive study is present in the literature to assess the utility of tooth graft in defects created by odontogenic pathology, cleft alveolus, or impacted tooth.</p><p>In this study, we have broadened the spectrum of the autogenous tooth graft application by using it in the defects created by odontogenic pathology, alveolar clefts, impacted canine, and third molars.</p><p>In this study, the consistency of the processed autogenous tooth graft was particulate in nature which could be readily incorporated into the alveolar defects. Also, the edge-to-edge inset of the graft in the defect was quite possible based on the nature of the graft. This is in contrast with the autogenous cortical bone grafts where the edge-to-edge inset of the graft is not possible. Murata <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] found that handling of the autogenous tooth graft was quite easy compared with autogenous cancellous bone graft.</p><p>In this study, overfilling of the graft into the defect was achieved in all the cases. No other autograft or allograft was required in this study as the autogenous tooth graft was sufficient to fill the defect.</p><p>Molars were used the most in preparing autogenous tooth graft in this study. The average volume of graft processed from a single molar was approximately 2 cc, from a single premolar and canine was 1.5 cc, and from a single incisor, it was 1 cc. Thus, a single-molar tooth, which is indicated for extraction, should be the first choice for processing autogenous tooth graft if the defect size is less than 2 cm<sup>3</sup> for better overfilling of the defect. According to Jeong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>,[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] the volume of autogenous graft acquired from the incisors, canines, and premolars ranged from 0.2 cc to 0.6 cc while that from molars ranged from 0.6 cc to 1.0 cc.</p><p>In this study, for ease of measuring the size of the intraoperative oral and maxillofacial surgical defect, we have proposed a classification of defect as mild when the defect was 0–1 cm<sup>3</sup>, moderate when it was 1–2 cm<sup>3</sup>, and severe when the defect was more than 2 cm<sup>3</sup>. Patients with severe defects were not included in this study.</p><p>In this study, the density of the surrounding normal bone remained relatively unchanged and a stable reference point for comparison with the grafted surgical defect. Of 25 patients, 16 patients had RBH 6M greater than 0.97, suggesting ideal healing of the surgical defect after 6 months postgrafting. Seven patients had RBH 6M between 0.96 and 0.80, suggesting good healing. Two patients had RBH 6M less than 0.80, suggesting poor healing.</p><p>In this study, we have used the novel relative bone densitometry method according to Hren and Miljavec.[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] In their study on spontaneous healing of mandibular cysts, the mean final bone density in the bone defects was 88% of the bone density of the surrounding healthy bone. The drawback of their study was that to get a spontaneous and ideal bone healing for smaller defects, they had to wait for 2 years, while in our study, the mean bone density of the defects was 92% of the surrounding healthy bone with 64% of the patients with ideal bone healing and 28% of the patients with good bone healing. We have got this result just 6 months postgrafting, proving the effectiveness of autogenous tooth grafting in bony defects of the maxillofacial region.</p><p>In this study, over a period of time, the grafting materials underwent gradual resorption. There was reduction in the amount and shape of the material, and the graft became less visible. There was an increase in the volume of new bone, and the graft became interconnected with the surrounding bone, thus forming a more stable structure. At 6 months postgrafting, the new bone had undergone trabecular bone formation and most of the grafting material had been resorbed which was clearly visible in the panoramic radiographs.</p><p>In this study, we had an excellent uptake of autogenous tooth graft. The reason for this is the osteoinductive and osteoconductive nature of the tooth graft. Studies performed by Chung <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>,[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] Murata <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>,[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and Lee HJ[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] have confirmed the osteoinductive capacity of the autogenous tooth graft.</p><p>In this study, the reason for one of the two patients with low RBH was infection of the grafted site after 10 days post-operatively. The patient did not maintain good oral hygiene post-operatively and continued with smoking in spite of informing him with the ill effects. Ultimately, we had to remove the infected graft and allow the defect to heal spontaneously. Another patient with low RBH had a recurrence of the odontogenic keratocyst which was managed again by enucleation followed by peripheral ostectomy, mechanical curettage, and chemical cauterization with Carnoy’s solution. The defect was allowed to heal spontaneously as it was small in size (&lt;1 cm3).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The novel technique of using autogenous tooth graft is successful in terms of clinical utility and outcome in augmenting defects of the alveolus created by odontogenic pathologies, impacted canine, impacted third molars, and cleft alveolus in this study. The neural crest cells play an important part in the development of teeth, alveolar bone as well as other jaw bones; thus, using autogenous tooth graft in such bony defects is a perfect example of “like replacing like.” The processing and handling of the autogenous tooth graft are quite easy. The edge-to-edge inset of the autogenous tooth graft at the surgical defect was possible. Previous studies have mostly used the autogenous tooth graft in peri-implant defect augmentation, but we have broadened the spectrum using the autogenous tooth graft in a novel way. Based on the results of this study, autogenous tooth graft is an excellent and equally effective option to the conventional autogenous bone graft with the added advantage of no donor site morbidity. Though further research in this direction is still required, autogenous tooth graft has many potential applications in the field of craniomaxillofacial surgery in the upcoming years.</p><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Ethical Approval was given, by the Institutional Ethical Committee Govt. Dental College and Hospital, Nagpur.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nampo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watahiki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>A new method for alveolar bone repair using extracted teeth for the graft material</article-title><source>J Periodontol</source><year>2010</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20476887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1902/jop.2010.100016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsugi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Human Dentin as Novel Biomaterial for Bone Regeneration [Internet</article-title><source>Biomaterials - Physics and Chemistry. InTech</source><year>2011</year><comment>doi: 10.5772/25071</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bone graft material using teeth</article-title><source>Journal of the Korean Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons</source><year>2012</year><comment>doi: 10.5125/jkaoms.2012.38.3.134</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5125/jkaoms.2013.39.3.103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24471027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Binderman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hallel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nardy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sapoznikov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A novel procedure to process extracted teeth for immediate grafting of autogenous dentin</article-title><source>J Interdiscipl Med Dent Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khojasteh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeelinejad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aghdashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Regenerative techniques in oral and maxillofacial bone grafting</article-title><source>In A Textbook of Advanced Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery. IntechOpen</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>22</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verdugo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simonian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>McDonald R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nowzari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Quantitation of mandibular symphysis volume as a source of bone grafting</article-title><source>Clin Implant Dent Relat Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19220848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1708-8208.2008.00140.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hren</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miljavec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Spontaneous bone healing of the large bone defects in the mandible</article-title><source>Int J Oral Maxillof Surg</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijom.2008.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18760900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vignesh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howlader</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Bone marrow aspirate in cystic maxillofacial bony defects</article-title><source>J Craniofac Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>e247</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30845084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SCS.0000000000005200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ledgerton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A comparison of maxillary and mandibular bone mineral densities</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1998</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0022-3913(98)70245-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Drozdzowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pluskiewicz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tarnawska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Panoramic-based mandibular indices in relation to mandibular bone mineral density and skeletal status assessed by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry and quantitative ultrasound</article-title><source>Dentomaxillofac Radiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12424634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.dmfr.4600729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meeder</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>1. The history of autogenous bone grafting</article-title><source>Injury</source><year>1994</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>SA2</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0020-1383(94)90254-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7927653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Die Osteoplastik in ihren Beziehungen zur Chirurgie und Physiologie</article-title><source>Hirschwald</source><year>1863</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Die Behandlung der sekundar-chronischen Osteomyelitis, bucherei d</article-title><source>Orthopaden</source><year>1974</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spiessl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Grundsätzliches zur Knochentransplantation [Basic principles of bone transplantation</article-title><source>Fortschr Kiefer Gesichtschir</source><year>1976</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">770275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Clinical study of graft materials using autogenous teeth in maxillary sinus augmentation</article-title><source>Implant Dent</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22067601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ID.0b013e3182386d74</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Healing mechanism and clinical application of autogenous tooth bone graft material</article-title><source>Advances in Biomaterials Science and Biomedical Applications</source><year>2013</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Retrospective cohort study of autogenous tooth bone graft</article-title><source>Oral Biol Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Autogenous teeth used for bone grafting: A comparison with traditional grafting materials</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>e39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22939321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.oooo.2012.04.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Method for extracting tooth protein from extracted tooth</article-title><source>Korea Intel-lectual Property Rights Information Service. Patent. Application 2002</source><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>2002</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tooth protein extracted from extracted tooth and method for using the same</article-title><source>Korea Intellectual Property Rights Information Service. Patent. Application 2004</source><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>2004</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Quantitative analysis of proliferation and differentiation of MG-63 cell line on the bone grafting material using human tooth</article-title><source>PhD thesis. School of Dentistry, Seoul National University</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>