
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3886883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3886883.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3886883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3886883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24416097</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-02228</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium oxysporum gnt2</italic>, Encoding a Putative <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Acetylglucosamine Transferase, Is Involved in Cell Wall Architecture and Virulence</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Fusarium oxysporum N-acetylglucosamine Transferase</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Fernández</surname><given-names initials="L">Loida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Roldán</surname><given-names initials="C">Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pareja-Jaime</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yolanda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names initials="A">Alicia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khraiwesh</surname><given-names initials="H">Husam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names initials="MIG">M. Isabel G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Genética, Universidad de Córdoba, Córdoba, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Campus de Excelencia Agroalimentario (ceiA3), Córdoba, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas-CSIC, Madrid, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Biología Celular, Fisiología e Inmunología, Universidad de Córdoba, Córdoba, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skurnik</surname><given-names initials="M">Mikael</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Helsinki, Finland</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>roncero@uco.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LLF CRR YPJ AP HK MIGR. Performed the experiments: LLF CRR YPJ AP HK MIGR. Analyzed the data: LLF CRR YPJ AP MIGR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LLF CRR YPJ HK MIGR. Wrote the manuscript: LLF CRR MIGR. </p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ecorrected"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">230490</issue-id><elocation-id>e84690</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-21 23:25:09.980"><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 López-Fernández et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>López-Fernández et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0084690.pdf"/><abstract><p>With the aim to decipher the molecular dialogue and cross talk between <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersci</italic> and its host during infection and to understand the molecular bases that govern fungal pathogenicity, we analysed genes presumably encoding <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosaminyl transferases, involved in glycosylation of glycoproteins, glycolipids, proteoglycans or small molecule acceptors in other microorganisms. <italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> analysis revealed the existence of seven putative <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycosyl transferase encoding genes (named <italic toggle="yes">gnt</italic>) in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> genome. <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> deletion mutants showed a dramatic reduction in virulence on both plant and animal hosts. Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutants had αalterations in cell wall properties related to terminal αor β-linked <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetyl glucosamine. Mutant conidia and germlings also showed differences in structure and physicochemical surface properties. Conidial and hyphal aggregation differed between the mutant and wild type strains, in a pH independent manner. Transmission electron micrographs of germlings showed strong cell-to-cell adherence and the presence of an extracellular chemical matrix. Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> cell walls presented a significant reduction in <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked oligosaccharides, suggesting the involvement of Gnt2 in <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation of cell wall proteins. Gnt2 was localized in Golgi-like sub-cellular compartments as determined by fluorescence microscopy of GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein after treatment with the antibiotic brefeldin A or by staining with fluorescent sphingolipid BODIPY-TR ceramide. Furthermore, density gradient ultracentrifugation allowed co-localization of GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein and Vps10p in subcellular fractions enriched in Golgi specific enzymatic activities. Our results suggest that <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosaminyl transferases are key components for cell wall structure and influence interactions of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> with both plant and animal hosts during pathogenicity.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnologia (BIO2010-015505) of Spain, and Junta de Andalucía (P08-CVI-3847). L.L.F. was supported by a PhD fellowship from the former Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnologia.L.L.F. was supported by a PhD fellowship from the former Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnología. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The amino sugar <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetylglucosamine (GlcNAc) plays important roles in a wide range of organisms from bacteria to humans. One major role for GlcNAc is shaping the structure of the extracellular cell surface. GlcNAc is converted to UDP-GlcNAc, which is a substrate for the transfer of the GlcNAc moiety to macromolecules. In fungi, UDP-GlcNAc is the substrate for chitin synthases that form the cell wall chitin, a β-(1→4) GlcNAc polymer. </p><p>In the fungal plant pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, integrity of the cell wall structure has been associated with plant interaction [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Chitin plays an important role in the pathotypic behaviour toward tomato plants (<italic toggle="yes">Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>). Deletion of the Chs V class V chitin synthase demonstrated that this enzyme plays different roles in fungal pathogenesis on plants [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and mammalian systems [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Evidence has been obtained showing that perturbation of fungal cell wall biosynthesis causes avirulence by elicitation of the induced plant defence-response leading to the restriction of fungal infection [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>UDP-GlcNAc is also used in eukaryotes to initiate <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>linked glycosylation and for the synthesis of glycosyl-phosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchors on membrane proteins. In addition to its structural roles, GlcNAc is an important signalling molecule in bacteria, fungi and animal cells. The glycosylation reaction is catalysed by the action of glycosyl transferases, which transfer different mono-saccharides from nucleotide activated sugar donors in α-conformation to various glycans on glycoproteins, glycolipids, proteoglycans or small molecule acceptors [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Oligosaccharide structures attached to proteins are conserved in eukaryotes, being one of the most abundant post-translational modification reactions [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Glycosylation plays numerous roles in protein folding and conformation, targeting, recognition, and other biological functions. Changes in glycan structures are associated with many physiological and pathological events, including cell adhesion, migration, cell growth, cell differentiation, and tumour invasion [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Oligosaccharides of glycoproteins are classified as <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycans and <italic toggle="yes">O-</italic>glycans [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>linked protein glycosylation, present in all domains of life, has two characteristics in common: the oligosaccharide is preassembled on a lipid carrier (dolichyl pyrophosphate), and then transferred in bloc to an asparagine residue within the consensus sequence Asn- X- Ser/Thr of the protein, as opposed to <italic toggle="yes">O-</italic>glycans which are attached to a subset of Ser and Thr [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Once the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycoproteins have been correctly folded and passed the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) quality control mechanism, they are transported to the Golgi where they are further modified [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Among the enzymes involved in the glycosylation process, the <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosaminyl transferases (GnTs) transfer <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetyl glucosamine residues from UDP-GlcNAc to the specific acceptor protein<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>linked structures, converting them into hybrid or complex glycan types.</p><p>Protein glycosylation pathways of 12 filamentous fungal species were investigated using a systems biology approach and developing a composite representation [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycosylation pathway in the cytoplasm and ER was evolutionarily conserved across the species studied, and highly specialized <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycan structures with galactofuranose residues, phosphodiesters, and other insufficiently trimmed structures were identified.</p><p>In the basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Coprinopsis cinerea, N-</italic>glycans of cell wall proteins from the fruiting body have been characterized [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The authors identified a novel oligosaccharide structure with at least five mannoses and a bisecting α, 1→4 <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosamine linked to the -mannose of the <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycan core, resembling a bisecting-hybrid-type glycan as in higher eukaryotes. The transferase responsible for this modification, CcGnt1, was described as a retaining glycosyltransferase from family 8 (GT8), as classified in the CaZY database [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and predicted to be a type II membrane protein. </p><p>In the model fungus <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic>, protein glycosylation has been extensively studied for decades, revealing much of the enzymology of both Golgi and ER glycosylation pathways. Several authors examined the oligosaccharides attached to endogenous proteins, including invertase, exoglucanase and carboxypeptidase Y [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These studies indicated that the structure of yeast <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>linked glycans is based solely on mannose and phosphomannose, without evidence for the addition of further <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylhexosamine residues beyond the two GlcNAc residues of the core structure. Nevertheless, an ortholog of the <italic toggle="yes">GNT1</italic> gene (<italic toggle="yes">YOR320c</italic>) encoding an open reading frame related to known <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosaminyl transferases has been identified. Deletion of this ORF resulted in loss of the extra mass on the <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>linked glycans and of lectin binding [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The phenotype of yeast mutants lacking <italic toggle="yes">GNT1</italic> provided few clues for its likely function. The <italic toggle="yes">gnt1</italic> mutants showed no change in sensitivity to caffeine, calcofluor white, or hygromycin, all of which have increased toxicity toward strains with cell wall defects [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and there was no change in the mobility of invertase, or increased secretion of the ER resident protein Kar2p. </p><p>In the human pathogens <italic toggle="yes">Candida albicans</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, glycosylation is essential for virulence [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Although the role of glycosylation is poorly understood in plant pathogens, it was recently shown to be crucial for virulence in <italic toggle="yes">Ustilago maydis</italic> [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic> [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p><p>The present study was initiated following an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosylation pathway components of the tomato pathogen <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic>. As a result, a family of seven members of genes presumably encoding for <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetyl glucosamine transferases (Gnts) was identified. Targeted gene disruption generated a double knock out mutant lacking a Golgi-localized Gnt, that displayed altered physico-chemical cell wall properties indicating severe structural changes, and a significant decrease in virulence on tomato plants. These conclusions were corroborated by functional complementation of the deletion mutant. This work opens the question to advance in the characterization of the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosylation as key enzymes decorating the outer cell surface of fungal plant pathogens. </p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>Fungal isolates, culture conditions and treatments</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. lycopersici wild type strain 4287 (race 2) was obtained from J. Tello, Universidad de Almería, Spain, and stored at -80°C with glycerol as a microconidial suspension. The pathotype of the isolates was periodically confirmed by plant infection assays. For extraction of DNA and microconidia production, cultures were grown in potato dextrose broth (PDB) (Difco) at 28°C as described previously [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. For inhibition assays in axenic cultures freshly obtained microconidia from the wild type, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant resistant to hygromycin (Hyg<sup>R</sup>) [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and the cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strain resistant to phleomycin (Phl<sup>R</sup>) [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] were transferred on 1.5% (w/v) agar plates of synthetic medium (SM) [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] containing 1% (w/v) glucose. For phenotypic analysis of colony growth, water droplets containing 5 x10<sup>3</sup>, 5 x10<sup>2</sup> or 50 freshly obtained microconidia were spotted onto SM plates containing the indicated compounds. Plates were incubated at 28 °C for 3 days, or at 35°C for 6 days for heat stress assessment, before being photographed. For determination of sensitivity to cell wall-degrading enzymes, germlings were incubated with protoplasting enzyme (Glucanex G100, Denmark) at 30 °C, and protoplast release over time was determined microscopically as described previously [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. To test sensitivity to Brefeldin A (BFA, Sigma) treatment, germlings grown for 12 h in PDB were washed with sterile water and incubated for 5 min in the presence of BFA (dissolved in ethanol) at 100 g mL<sup>-1</sup> final concentration. Cells were then subjected to fluorescence and light microscopy analyses. </p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>Nucleic acid manipulations and cloning</title><p>Total RNA and genomic DNA (gDNA) were extracted from <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> mycelium according to previously reported protocols [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Southern analyses and probe labelling were carried out as described previously [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] using the non-isotopic digoxigenin labelling kit (Roche Applied Science). <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> cDNA from duplicated genes FOXG_12436/FOXG_14101 including the complete ORFs, was amplified from total RNA using primers gnt2-31N corresponding to the eight initial codons of the ORF plus the <italic toggle="yes">Nsi</italic> I restriction site and an additional cytosine, and gnt2-33X corresponding to the reverse complement of the last eight codons of the ORF plus the <italic toggle="yes">Xma</italic> I restriction site and an additional cytosine (<xref rid="pone-0084690-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), derived from <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> genome sequence database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broad.mit.edu/annotation/genome/fusarium_group"><underline>http://www.broad.mit.edu/annotation/genome/fusarium_group</underline></ext-link>). The resulting amplified band was cloned into pGEMT vector (Promega, Madison<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>WI) and then subcloned in frame into the appropriate sites of the <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus nidulans</italic> vector p1902 (kindly provided by Dr. M.A. Peñalva, CIB-CSIC, Spain), resulting in a GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein under the transcriptional control of the <italic toggle="yes">gpdA</italic> promoter and terminator. Sequencing of both DNA strands of the obtained clones was performed at the Servicio de Secuenciación Automática de DNA (Universidad de Córdoba, Spain) using the Dyedeoxy Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City-CA) on an ABI Prism 377 Genetic Analyser apparatus (Applied Biosystems, Foster City-CA). DNA and protein sequence databases were searched using the BLAST algorithm [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] at the National Centre for Biotechnology Information (Bethesda, MD).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0084690-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Oligonucleotides used in this study.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NaName</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sequence (5´→ 3´)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Position AT</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Experimental use</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXG_12436F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GTTCGACATAAGGATAATACGGA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+350 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXG_12436R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TATTTCGGAGCCCAGATACTTG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+824 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chs V-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ACAGCTCCAACGAACTCT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2910 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal quantification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chs V-26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GGAGGTACTTGGTCATGT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3402 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal quantification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tomQB-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CCTCATCAACCAATCCTCCAA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal quantification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tomQB-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TCATTCACAACAACTCCAGGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal quantification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GAGGGACCGCTCTCGTCGT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">898 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actin-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GGAGATCCAGACTGCCGCTCAG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">674 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-sceIF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">tagggataacagggtaatCCTCGTGAGTTTATCCAGCAG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-821 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delsgate disruption vector/ probe</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-sceIR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">attaccctgttatccctaCCCAGAAATCCAACAAGATAGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2030 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delsgate disruption vector</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-attB1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ggggacaagtttgtacaaaaaagcaggctaaCAGGTACTCGCTATTGGTCAC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+166 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delsgate disruption vector</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-attB2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ggggaccactttgtacaagaaagctgggtaGACTTCCAAATGAAACGCAAGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1032 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delsgate disruption vector</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AGTGAAGTTGTTGATTTTTGGTGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1461 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complementation </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GTGATCCTCTCGACGCAGAC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1201 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complementation </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTATTCAGCTACCTGCGCCAT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-232 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complementation/Probe</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-18B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">cgcggatccATGATAGGTGTCGCCCGATTA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> ORF amplification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-19S </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">acgcgtcgacCTAGTTCAGCTGCAGATTTCC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1110 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> ORF amplification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-31N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">catgcatATGATAGGTGTCGCCCGATTACTC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> ORF amplification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gnt2-33X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ccccgggCTAGCTGCAGATTTCCTTGCGTTTCAT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1110 (as)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> ORF amplification</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gpdA-15B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AATAGTGGTGAAATTGATCGTGT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gpdA Promoter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP fusion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tripter-8B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TCGACCATCCGGTGCTCTG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gpdA Terminator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP fusion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chi3-5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TCTTGTCTCTTTTTCTTGTTCC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chi3-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GCAGTATCATCACCAGCAGT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chi9-5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GCCTTCTTGTCACGATGTCA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">chi9-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTCCAAGAATTCCGCAATACC</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gluB-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">ATTCTGTTTATGCTGCGATGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gluB-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTTTCTCGGACTACCTTCTTT</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pr1-7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GCATCCCGAGCACAAAACTA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pr1-8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGGTAGCGTAGTTATAGTCTG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">efα1-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TACTGGTGGTTTTGAAGCTGG</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">efα1-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AACTTCCTTCACGATTTCATCA</named-content>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">qRTPCR plant-defence</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Italics and lower case indicate restriction sites and nucleotide sequences added for cloning purposes. Positions are referred to the start codon, (+) downstream or (-) upstream of ATG. Orientation is indicated, (s) sense, (as) antisense.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>Quantification of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> biomass during plant infection</title><p>Plant roots were maintained immersed in microconidial suspensions of the different strains (5 x 10<sup>6</sup> microconidia mL<sup>-1</sup>), for five days. To avoid amplification of gDNA from external fungal mycelium that had not penetrated the roots, only the stems were collected for DNA analysis 5 plants were used per treatment. Real-time PCR assays for the quantification of fungal gDNA from infected stems were performed using primer pair chs V-3 and chs V-26 (<xref rid="pone-0084690-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Reaction mixtures contained 7.5 μL of FastStart Essential DNA Green Master (Roche Diagnostics), 300 nM of each primer and 60 ng of total DNA extracted from stems in a final volume of 15 L. Three simultaneous replicated amplifications were carried out for each DNA sample, using 15-μL aliquots from a 50-μL mixture. Amplification reactions were performed in 96-well microtitre plates (Bio-Rad). PCRs were performed in an iCycler apparatus (Bio-Rad) using the following cycling protocol: an initial step of denaturation (5 min, 94 °C) followed by 40 cycles of 30 s at 94 °C, 30 s at 62 °C, 45 s at 72 °C and 20 s at 80 °C for measurement of the fluorescence emission. After this, a melting curve programme was run for which measurements were made at 0.5 °C temperature increases every 5 s within a range of 55-95 °C. The DNA concentration of each sample was extrapolated from standard curves, which were developed by plotting the logarithm of known concentrations (10-fold dilution series from 100 ng to 1 ng/15 μL reaction) of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> gDNA against the Ct values. In order to normalize the amplification conditions of the serially diluted DNA samples, 100 ng of DNA from non-inoculated plants were added to each sample in the dilution series. Additionally, tomato gDNA concentration was extrapolated from standard curves developed by plotting the logarithm of known concentrations (10-fold dilution series from 200 ng to 1 ng/15 μL reaction) of plant gDNA against the Ct values, using a primer pair corresponding to <italic toggle="yes">Solanum lycopersicum tomQB</italic> gene (β, 1-3 glucanase) (<xref rid="pone-0084690-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Graphs represent the amount of fungal gDNA relative to 100 ng tomato gDNA. The experiment was repeated three times using independent infected tissues. Data were analysed with the software SPSS 15.0 for Windows® (LEAD Technologies, Inc.). ANOVA was performed and the Duncan <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> test was executed to assess the differences among treatments within each day at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05. </p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR of defence-related genes</title><p>Real-time RT-PCRs were performed in an iCycler apparatus (Bio-Rad) using 7.5 μL FastStart Essential DNA Green Master (Roche Diagnostics), 6.9 μL of cDNA template and 300 nM of each gene-specific primer (<xref rid="pone-0084690-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) in a final reaction volume of 15 μL. All primer pairs amplified products of 200-250 bp. The following PCR program was used for all reactions: an initial step of denaturation (5 min, 94 °C), followed by 40 cycles of 30 s at 94 °C, 30 s at 60 °C, 30 s at 72 °C and 20 s at 80 °C for measurement of the fluorescence emission. A melting curve program was run for which measurements were made at 0.5 °C temperature increments every 5 s within a range of 55-95 °C. Each sample reaction was performed in duplicate for each gene assay. Relative levels of the RT-PCR products were determined using the <named-content content-type="gene">DDCt</named-content> method [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Ct values were normalized to the Ct value of the elongation factor (<italic toggle="yes">EF</italic>α<italic toggle="yes">1</italic>) housekeeping gene. Normalized transcript levels of each gene in infected samples were compared with levels in non-inoculated samples. The experiments were repeated three times with independent infected tissues. Data were analysed with the software SPSS 15.0 for Windows® (LEAD Technologies, Inc.). ANOVA was performed to assess differences among treatments for each gene at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title>Targeted gene replacement and complementation</title><p>Simultaneous targeted replacement of the duplicated <italic toggle="yes">FOXG_12436/FOXG_14101</italic> alleles (<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic>) was performed using the DelsGate technique [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The 5´and 3’ <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> genomic flanking sequences, were obtained by PCR amplification of wild type gDNA, and the resulting 1025 bp and 1020 bp fragments, 5´and 3´ respectively, were cloned into pDONR vector containing the Hyg<sup>R</sup> cassette (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). For each transformation, the <italic toggle="yes">Sce</italic> I lineal DNA deletion construct (6000 bp), was introduced into protoplasts of wild type strain 4287 as reported previously [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Complementation of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant was achieved by reintroducing the <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> wild type allele obtained by DNA amplification using primer pair gnt2-7/gnt2-3 (<xref rid="pone-0084690-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and co-transformation with the Phl<sup>R</sup> cassette as selective marker. In all cases, Hyg<sup>R</sup> or Phl<sup>R</sup> resistant transformants were selected and the homologous recombination or complementation events were confirmed by Southern analysis of gDNA using the indicated probe (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2.6"><title>Subcellular fractionation</title><p>Golgi-enriched fractions were isolated from fungal mycelia grown for 14h on PDB by ultracentrifugation on discontinuous sucrose gradients as previously described [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] with some modifications. Cells were thoroughly washed with water, disrupted by freezing liquid nitrogen and resuspended in 1 mL ice-cold HM buffer containing 10 mM HEPES, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> pH 7.5, 1 mM PMSF and 1% protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma). The cell homogenate was centrifuged at 4 °C during 5 min at 1,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> to remove un-lysed cells. The supernatant was recovered and centrifuged at 4 °C during 10 min at 10,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> to generate a pellet, corresponding to endoplasmic reticulum enriched fraction (P10) that was resuspended in 350 μL ice-cold HM and stored at -20 °C for further analyses, and a supernatant (S10) that was loaded on a 4 mL sucrose step gradient (26 to 54%). Sucrose solutions were prepared in HM buffer and the gradient column was incubated over night at 4 °C before use. Gradient was subjected to centrifugation at 4 °C for 90 min at 160,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> in a SW50.1 rotor (Beckmann Coulter, Fullerton, CA) and 14 fractions of approx. 350 μL each were collected from the top of the gradient. The remaining pellet (P160) was resuspended in 350 μL ice-cold HM and stored at -20 °C for further analyses. Sucrose concentration of each fraction was measured using a refractometer (Atago Co., LTD). Aliquots of each fraction were mixed with SDS sample buffer and proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE and detected by immunoblotting using the anti-GFP anti-body (Roche) or anti-Vps10p (Life Technologies). Guanidine diphosphate (GDP) hydrolysis and NADPH cytochrome c reductase assays were used to detect Golgi and endoplasmic reticulum enrichment, respectively, in the different fractions. Hydrolysis of GDP (GDPase) was measured as previously described [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] with some modifications. Five-μL aliquots of each fraction were mixed with 20 μL of reaction buffer containing 0.2 M imidazole pH 7.5, 10 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1% Triton X-100 and 2 mM GDP. The reactions were incubated in 96-well plates at 30 °C for 30 min and stopped by transferring them to ice and adding 2 μL of 10% SDS. Finally, 40 μL of water and 140 µL of AMES reagent (1:6 mixture of 10% ascorbic acid and 0.42% ammonium molybdate in 1 N sulfuric acid) were added to each well and the reactions were incubated at 42 °C for 20 min. GDPase activity of each fraction was determined as the absorbance at 660 nm.</p><p>To determine NADPH cytochrome c reductase activity, 10 µL aliquots of each fraction were assayed using the cytochrome c reductase (NADPH) Assay Kit (Sigma) following the manufacturer’s instructions, except that reactions were scaled to a final volume of 224 µL.</p></sec><sec id="s2.7"><title>Staining of Golgi complexes</title><p>For visualization of Golgi compartments, germlings from <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> were stained using the selective fluorescent sphingolipid BODIPY-TR (Molecular Probes) [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Aliquots containing 10<sup>5</sup> microconidia from the different strains were inoculated on 1 % agarose plates containing 0.5 % casamino acids, and incubated at 28 °C for 14 h before treatment at RT with 2.5 % glucanex during 10 min. After washing three times with Hanks´ Balance Salt Solution (sodium chloride 8 g L<sup>-1</sup>; potassium chloride 0.4 g L<sup>-1</sup>; potassium phosphate monobasic 0.06 g L<sup>-1</sup>; glucose 1 g L<sup>-1</sup>; sodium phosphate dibasic 0.048 g L<sup>-1</sup>; magnesium sulphate 0.098 g L<sup>-1</sup>; calcium chloride 0.14 g L<sup>-1</sup>; sodium bicarbonate 0.35 g L<sup>-1</sup>) containing 10mM HEPES pH 7.4 (HBSS/HEPES), samples were stained during 30 min at 4 °C with 5 μM BODIPY-TR complexed with defatted BSA. Following three washes with HBSS/HEPES samples were flooded with liquid SM and further incubated at 28 °C during 60 min. Fixation of samples was achieved by treatment during 40 min at RT with fixation solution (50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0; 3.7 % formaldehyde; 0.2 % Triton X-100), followed by two washes with PBS buffer containing 0.0125 mM manganesium chloride and 0.0125 mM calcium chloride. Finally, samples were observed under optical and fluorescence microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="s2.8"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Amino acid sequences were aligned using the CLUSTALW algorithm [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] with the Bioedit 7.0.0 program [<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and cleaned by GBlocks v0.91b [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The PHYML 3.0 program [<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] was used to perform a 1,000 nonparametric bootstrap phylogenetic analysis of the resulting alignment with the maximum likelihood method after optimization of the settings by the MODELGENERATOR program, version 0.85 [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Phylogenetic relationships among sequences were depicted in a phylogenetic tree constructed using <italic toggle="yes">MEGA</italic> version 4 [<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2.9"><title>Alcian Blue staining</title><p>Alcian Blue binding assay was carried out using the method of Herrero et al. [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. A series of solutions containing different amounts of Alcian Blue (Sigma) was prepared in HCl 0.002 N, and the optical density at 620 nm (OD<sub>620</sub>) of each solution was determined. A standard curve was plotted of the OD values versus amounts of Alcian Blue. To quantify Alcian Blue bound to the cell surface, fresh aliquots containing 5 x 10<sup>8</sup> microconidia were centrifuged, and the cells were washed with 0.002 N HCl, resuspended in 0.025 % Alcian Blue (w/v), incubated 20-30 min at RT, and then centrifuged for 2 min to pellet the cells. The OD<sub>620</sub> of the supernatant was measured and the amount of Alcian Blue was determined by using the standard curve. The percentages of dye bound to the cells were calculated from the total values. </p></sec><sec id="s2.10"><title>Cell surface labelling with GS II-FITC lectin and flow cytometry analysis</title><p>The lectin GSII from <italic toggle="yes">Grifonia simplifolia</italic> labelled with Fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) was used in this study due to its specific binding capacity to terminal <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosamine residues [<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Lectin GSII-FITC stock was prepared at 1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup> in 10 mM phosphate buffer, containing 15 mM NaCl and 50 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Aliquots containing 10<sup>7</sup> fresh microconidia or germlings grown for 3 h on PDB were collected, centrifuged at 5,000 g for 5 min, washed twice with water and twice with labelling buffer (50 mM phosphate buffer pH7.5, containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 0.1 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>) and then resuspended in 180 μL of the same buffer. Samples were stained by adding 20 μL GS II-FITC (F-2402-2, EY laboratories, USA) at final concentration 0.1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup> and incubated for 30 min at 28 °C, 170 rpm, in the dark. After washing twice with labelling buffer, samples were resuspended at 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> cells mL<sup>-1</sup>. The fluorescent emission of cell surface labelling was determined by flow cytometry analysis. Fluorescence intensity measurements were performed by flowing labelled cells at a rate of 200-300 sec<sup>-1</sup>, excited at 488 nm, through a FACScan (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA) equipped with an Innova 90 argon laser at the Department of Cell Biology, Immunology and Physiology (University of Cordoba, Sian). The green emission (550 nm) was collected by a FL1 detector. For each strain, a total number of 20,000 FITC event data files were collected and analysed with Lysis II on a Hewlett-Packard 340 computer. The data of independent fluorescence emission were processed as frequency distribution histograms and the flow cytometer light scattering measurement, corresponding to the size and shape of cell population, were represented by a two-parameter, forward and side light scatter histogram, FSC and SSC, respectively. </p><p>Single-cell and aggregated conidia in the whole population were identified by plotting all FITC events and representing their relative fluorescence intensity (FL1 channel) vs. their lineal fluorescence intensity (auxiliary channel) values. Single cell populations were classified as those positive events (H3) that fell below the relative fluorescence value of 10<sup>1</sup> considered as a single cell maximal emission, as deduced from the flat slope observed in the strain graphs. Thus, aggregated cell population (H4) was identified as scattered values showing higher lineal fluorescence intensities. This approach was further supported by morphological analyses using light scattering assessments. All experiments were performed at least three times.</p></sec><sec id="s2.11"><title>Cell wall material preparation and fractionation</title><p>Glycans linked to cell wall glycoproteins were extracted from fungal mycelium, grown for 3 days in minimal medium containing 1 % sucrose as the carbon source, following the previously described protocol [<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] with minor modifications. Freeze-dried mycelium (3 g) was ground using an IKA 10A grinder and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-linked glycans were released after four consecutive extractions at 20 °C with 40 mL 0.1 M NaOH containing 0.3 M NaBH<sub>4</sub>, with shaking during 8 h. After centrifugation at 10.000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 min at 10 °C, the supernatants were combined and two volumes of absolute ethanol were added. The samples were incubated at 4 °C over night and the precipitate was collected by centrifugation, resuspended in 30 mL of water and dialyzed (3.5 kDa cut-off) against distilled water for 4 days. The resulting insoluble (F1) and water-soluble fractions were freeze-dried and the latter was again fractionated by ethanol-water 1:1 (v/v) solubility followed by centrifugation. The resulting insoluble fraction (F2) was freeze-dried, and the soluble fraction, containing <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-linked glycans, was dialyzed against distilled water for 8 h and freeze-dried (F3). <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans were released from the solid residue obtained after the fourth treatment with 0.1 M NaOH/0.3 M NaBH<sub>4</sub>, by four consecutive extractions with 40 mL 1 M NaOH at 20 °C with shaking during 8 h, followed by centrifugation at 15,300 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 min at 10 °C. The resulting solid residue, containing the β-glucan-chitin complex (F4), was dialyzed (12 kDa cutoff) and freeze-dried, and the supernatants were subjected to precipitation with absolute ethanol followed by consecutive solubilisation with water and ethanol: water 1:1 (v/v), as described above. The resulting water and ethanol: water insoluble fractions (F5 and F6, respectively), as well as the ethanol: water soluble fraction, containing <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans (F7), were dialyzed against distilled water for 8 h, and freeze-dried. Finally, the dry-weight of each fraction was quantified, and the amount of <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans was determined relative to the cell wall total dry weight (fractions F1 to F7). Experiments were repeated three times. </p></sec><sec id="s2.12"><title>Aggregation and cell-to-cell adhesion assays</title><p>Spore and hyphal aggregation ability was assessed at different pH values following a method previously described [<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Briefly, 50 mL of liquid SM were adjusted to pH 2.0, 3.5 or 6.0, inoculated with 10<sup>6</sup> microconidia mL<sup>-1</sup>, incubated at 28 °C and 80 rpm for 5 to 7 h. To quantify spore aggregation, aliquots of each culture were observed under a light microscope and 15-20 random pictures of every strain were taken, resulting in 300-500 cell counts. To avoid errors caused by non-spore particles, all images were controlled and false measurements erased. In parallel, GSII-FITC labelled cells were observed under the fluorescence and light microscope, and a number of random pictures were taken, resulting in 300-500 cell counts. </p></sec><sec id="s2.13"><title>Optical, fluorescence and transmission electron microscopy</title><p>For optical and fluorescence microscopy analyses cell aliquots were embedded in 1% agarose blocks, and observed using the Nomarsky technique or the appropriate filter set, respectively, in a Zeiss Axio Imager M2 microscope (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging GmbH, Göttingen, Germany). Images were captured with an Evolve Photometrics digital camera using the Axiovision 4.8 software. Images were processed using Adobe Photoshop C5 (Adobe Systems, Mountain View, CA, USA).</p><p>For transmission electron microscopy (TEM), germlings grown on PDB for 14 h at 28 °C and 150 rpm were initially fixed overnight at 4 °C, in a mixture of 2.5 % glutaraldehyde and 2 % paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer pH 7.0, then washed in buffer and post-fixed in 1 % osmium tetroxide at 4 °C. After dehydration in an ethanol series, the samples were treated with propylene oxide and embedded in EMBed 812. After curing, the blocks were sectioned with a thickness of about 80 nm in an ultramicrotome and mounted on Cu grids. The samples were stained in 2 % aqueous uranyl acetate for 2 min at 37 °C, and then transferred to Reynold’s lead citrate for 3 min at room temperature. Micrographs were obtained using a Philips CM 10 electron microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s2.14"><title>Plant and animal infection assays</title><p>Tomato root inoculation assays were performed as described [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], using 2-week-old tomato seedlings (cultivar Monika, seeds kindly provided by Syngenta, Spain) and <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> strains, by immersing the roots in a suspension of 5 × 10<sup>6</sup> spores mL<sup>-1</sup> for 30 min, planted in vermiculite and maintained in a growth chamber. Ten plants were used for each treatment. Severity of disease symptoms and plant survival was recorded daily for 30 days as previously described [<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. </p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> larvae in the final larval stage were obtained from the company Animal Center S.C.P. (Valencia, Spain), and inoculated as previously described [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Fifteen larvae per treatment between 0.2 to 0.3 g in weight were employed in all assays. A Burkard Auto Microapplicator (0.1-10 µL; Burkard Manufacturing Co. Limited, Hertfordshire, UK) with a 1 mL syringe was used to inject 8 µL of a microconidial suspension, containing 1.5 x 10<sup>5</sup> spores resuspended in sterile phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), into the hemocoel of each larva through the last left proleg. The area was cleaned using an alcohol swab before injection. Larvae injected with 8 µL PBS served as controls. After injection, larvae were incubated in glass containers at 30 °C, and the number of dead larvae was scored daily. Larvae were considered dead when they displayed no movement in response to touch.</p><p>The Mantel-Cox method was used to assess statistical significance of differences in survival among groups. Data was plotted using Graph Pad Prism software version 4 for Windows. Differences showing a P value &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. Experiments were repeated three times with similar results. Data presented are from one representative experiment.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Identification and sequence analysis of glycosylation-decorating enzymes in the Fusarium oxysporum genome</title><p>Since glyco- structures are excellent targets for host recognition in animal and plant model systems, we conducted an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosylation pathway components of the tomato pathogen <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> strain 4287 genome sequence database. The results of the protein blast search revealed that the <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> genome contains homologous sequences to 49 <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> genes involved in <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- protein glycosylation. Remarkably, we detected the existence of seven α-1-4,<italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetylglucosamine transferase paralogs and the apparent absence of 17 orthologs to yeast genes in this pathogenic fungus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s004">Table S1</xref>). We were conservative in our selection, requiring <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> values ≤ than e<sup>-9</sup> to consider candidate sequences as putative <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> protein homologs. </p><p>The family of seven members encoding for N-acetyl glucosamine transferases (all named <italic toggle="yes">gnt</italic> in this work) was further studied: FOXG_12436 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic>) and FOXG_14101 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt5</italic>) are identical copies located within duplicated genomic regions on chromosomes 3 and 6, respectively (here after <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic>); FOXG_01495 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt1</italic>) on chromosome 5; FOXG_12874 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt3</italic>) and FOXG_12897 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt4</italic>) both on chromosome 9; FOXG_14149 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt6</italic>) and FOXG_16408 (<italic toggle="yes">gnt7</italic>) both on chromosome 14. The deduced amino acid sequences from FOXG_12436, FOXG_14101 and FOXG_14149 genes presented 31-33% identities to <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> GNT1 [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], a fungal enzyme belonging to the glycosyl transferases family 8 that catalyses the addition of <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetyl-D-glucosamine to mannose side chains by high mannose N-glycan synthesis [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Cloning and sequencing of the complete cDNAs from <italic toggle="yes">gnt2, gnt4, gnt6</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">gnt7</italic> allowed manual curing of the genomic sequences in the <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> genome database using BLAST and the non-redundant database of NCBI. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt2</italic> consists of an ORF of 987 bp organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns: exon I starts 264 nucleotides upstream from the annotated start codon and the first intron of 81 bp is 376 bp downstream of this putative start codon. Exon II is interrupted by a previously not annotated 58 bp intron, causing a frame shift and giving rise to a new exon III which ends 5 nucleotides upstream from the previously annotated stop codon, resulting in a 328 amino acid protein with a predicted trans-membrane domain between amino acids 12 to 34. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt4</italic> contains an ORF of 1023 bp organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns. Intron 2 is 55 bp shorter than in the annotated version, followed by a new exon 3 of 63 bp and a stop codon 158 bp upstream of the previous annotation, resulting in a new open reading frame that codes for a 341 amino acid protein with a predicted trans-membrane domain between amino acids 7 to 24. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt6</italic> contains an ORF of 990 bp organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns. Exon I starts 267 nucleotides upstream from the annotated start codon and the first intron of 81 bp is 379 bp downstream of this putative start codon, Exon II is interrupted by a new 58 bp-long intron, causing a frame shift and giving rise to a new exon III which ends 26 nucleotides upstream from the previous stop codon, resulting in a 329 amino acid protein with a predicted trans-membrane domain between amino acids 12 to 34. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt7</italic> contains an ORF of 1077 bp organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns. The first intron is 126 bp shorter than the annotated one, giving rise to a 126 bp longer exon II and resulting in a 358 amino acid deduced protein.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Gnt1</italic> has an ORF of 1065 bp encoding a 354 amino acid polypeptide organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns. The first intron of 75 bp is 415 bp downstream of the putative start codon, and the second of 53 bp is 54 bp upstream of the stop codon. The putative trans-membrane domain comprises amino acids 22 to 44. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt3</italic> has an ORF of 1269 bp encoding a 422 amino acid polypeptide organized in 3 exons interrupted by 2 introns. The first intron of 49 bp is 607 bp downstream of the putative start codon, and the second of 53 bp is 69 bp upstream of the stop codon.</p><p>The deduced six proteins (Gnt1, Gnt2, Gnt3, Gnt4, Gnt6 and Gnt7) show an overall identity among each other ranging from 53 to 97 %. Alignment of the <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> putative Gnts with other orthologs revealed identities of 31-33 % to S. cerevisiae GNT1 [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and of 16-19 % to <italic toggle="yes">Coprinopsis cinerea Ccgnt1</italic> [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). All seven deduced proteins present the main features described for <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycosyltransferases, located at highly conserved positions: a single pass trans-membrane domain (type II) near the N-terminus characteristic of a Golgi localized enzyme [<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and two/three DXD motifs essential for the coordination of the catalytic cations, most commonly Mn<sup>2+</sup>, and cysteine residues for establishment of disulfide bridges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g001">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Fusarium oxysporum</italic> contains six putative <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetyl glucosaminyltransferase genes.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Alignment of the conserved domains of six predicted Gnts encoded by <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> genes FOXG_<italic toggle="yes">01495</italic> (Gnt1), FOXG_<italic toggle="yes">12436/FOXG</italic>_<italic toggle="yes">14101</italic> (Gnt2), FOXG_<italic toggle="yes">12874</italic> (Gnt3), FOXG_<italic toggle="yes">12897</italic> (Gnt4), FOXG_<italic toggle="yes">14149</italic> (Gnt6), and <italic toggle="yes">FOXG-16408</italic> (Gnt7), with the corresponding orthologs from <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Gnt1 (YOR320c) and <italic toggle="yes">Coprinopsis cinerea</italic> Gnt1 (CC1G 14119). Identical amino acids are highlighted on a grey background. Conserved motifs: DXD triads (black rectangle), Asp residues involved in ion binding (filled black circle), and conserved Cys residues (open triangles) are indicated. Amino acid sequences were aligned using Clustal W. (<bold>B</bold>) Scaled diagrams with conserved features of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> Gnt proteins. Positions of the conserved DXD domains, Cys residues (C), and transmembrane domains (dashed boxes) are indicated. </p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Gnt representation in multiple family members is unique for F. oxysporum</title><p>To investigate the representation of <italic toggle="yes">gnt</italic> genes among <italic toggle="yes">Fusaria</italic> and other fungal species, we performed an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> search of the <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> comparative database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/"><underline>http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/</underline></ext-link>) <underline>using</underline> the six deduced Gnt amino acid sequences identified in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>. This search detected two or three orthologs in the majority of the species analysed, whereas <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> contained only one (GNT1), indicating low genomic redundancy in all species, in contrast to the six genes located in seven loci at five different chromosomes in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> Gnts were aligned together with other Gnts available at the National Centre for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast.cgi?program=blastp"><underline>http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?PROGRAM=blastp</underline></ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s002">Figure S2</xref>). The phylogram revealed that <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> Gnts are grouped in two clades, one containing Gnt1, Gnt2, Gnt4, Gnt6 and Gnt7 and the other containing Gnt3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g002">Figure 2</xref>). It is remarkable that four of the loci are located on three dispensable <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> chromosomes [<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. And thus, it could be assumed that genes <italic toggle="yes">gnt1</italic> (on chromosome 5), <italic toggle="yes">gnt3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">gnt4</italic> (both on chromosome 9) were the ancestors of the other four genes which might be originated by genomic-duplication. This hypothesis is also supported by the number of orthologues found in the close related species <italic toggle="yes">F. verticillioides</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">F. graminearum</italic> (three and two genes, respectively).</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> is part of a gene family expanded in the pathogenic fungus <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>.</title><p>Phylogenetic tree constructed using the neighbour-joining method from Clustal W multiple-sequence alignment of 146 aa of GT8 proteins. Numbers at the branch points represent percentage bootstrap values based on 1,000 replicates. <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> (FOXG_01495; FOXG_12436/FOXG_14101; FOXG_12874; FOXG_12897; FOXG_14149; FOXG_16408)<italic toggle="yes">, F. graminearum</italic> (FGSG_10936; FGSG_10956*)<italic toggle="yes">, F. verticillioides</italic> (FVEG_07859; FVEG_11624; FVEG_11649*), <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> (AFUB_08390), <italic toggle="yes">A. niger</italic> (An11g10206; An03g02990), <italic toggle="yes">A. oryzae</italic> (AO09001000), <italic toggle="yes">Chaetomium globosum</italic> (CHGG_09837; CHGG_08452), <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (GNT1, YOR320C), <italic toggle="yes">Nectria haematococca</italic> (NHA_39806; NHA_79931; NHA_79932), <italic toggle="yes">Verticillium dahliae</italic> (VDBG_01023; VDBG_03984), <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium chrysogenum</italic> (PC_16g00820; PC_22g12650).</p><p>*These genes were manually cured as follows: FGSG_10956, 120 amino acids were added upstream of the annotated start codon; FVEG_11649, 78 amino acids were added upstream of the annotated start codon.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>Targeted disruption of F. oxysporum gnt2 genes</title><p>To determine whether Gnts are necessary for pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic>, we performed double targeted replacement of the <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> genes <italic toggle="yes">FOXG_12436</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">FOXG_14101</italic>. The disruption vector was introduced into wild-type protoplasts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1A</xref>), and homologous recombination events were confirmed by Southern analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). The wild type strain showed a 2 kb <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>R I/<italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic> I hybridizing band corresponding to <italic toggle="yes">gnt6</italic> plus a 3.5 kb double hybridizing band corresponding to the duplicated <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> allele. The 3.5 kb band was replaced by a 7 kb fragment in the homologous integrative transformant #55, indicating that it has undergone simultaneous disruption of both <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> alleles (<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). Transformant #46 displayed the original 3.5 and 2 kb <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>R I-<italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic> I hybridizing bands plus an additional band, indicating ectopic insertion of the disruption construct (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1B</xref>).</p><p>Complementation of mutant Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> was done by cotransformation with the <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> wild type allele and the Phl<sup>R</sup> cassette as the selective marker. Cotransformants were identified by Southern analysis of gDNA digested with <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>R I and <italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic> I (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s001">Figure S1B</xref>). In the case of complemented strain 6 (cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic>), the hybridizing patterns allowed the verification of the integration events.</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>Gnt2 is essential for virulence of Fusarium oxysporum</title><p>The role of Gnt2 in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> virulence was determined by plant infection assays, performed by immersing the roots of 2-week-old tomato plants in microconidia suspensions of the fungal strains. Severity of wilt symptoms in plants inoculated with the wild type strain, the ectopic transformants (not shown) and the complemented cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> strain increased steadily throughout the experiment, showing characteristic wilt symptoms 10 days after inoculation with most plants dead 8 days later. By contrast, plants inoculated with the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed a significant delay in symptom development with most plants alive (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and healthy 25 days after inoculation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Virulence experiments were performed three times with similar results. </p><fig id="pone-0084690-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Gnt2 contributes to virulence of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> on plant and animal systems.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Groups of ten plants (cultivar Monika) were inoculated by immersing the roots into a suspension of 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> freshly obtained microconidia mL<sup>-1</sup> of the wild type (wt), the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strains, and planted in minipots. Percentage survival was recorded after different time points. All experiments were performed at least three times with similar results. The data shown are from one representative experiment. (<bold>B</bold>) Mantel-Cox plots of <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> larvae survival after injection of 1.6 x 10<sup>5</sup> microconidia of the indicated strains into the hemocoel and incubation at 30 °C. Data shown are from one representative experiment. Experiments were performed three times with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>In order to examine the role of Gnt2 in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> virulence on animals, we performed infection experiments using the greater wax moth <italic toggle="yes">Galleria mellonella</italic> as host, which has been recently described as an useful non-vertebrate infection model for studying virulence mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> on animal hosts [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Injection of microconidia of the wild type strain into the hemocoel of <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic> resulted in rapid killing of the larvae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). By contrast, the <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed a moderate but significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) reduction in killing. The complemented strain cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> did not show significant differences in killing efficiency compared to the wild type strain.</p><p>To determine the ability of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant to colonize tomato plants, we performed quantification of specific fungal DNA within stems using real-time PCR. The amount of fungal biomass present in tomato stems increased during the course of infection in wild type-inoculated plants (up to 5 % of total DNA from infected tissues five days post-inoculation) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). A significant decrease in the amount of fungal DNA was observed in plants inoculated with the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant (up to 1 % of total DNA from infected tissues five days post-inoculation). These data suggest that Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant colonizes the stem tissues with strong reduced efficiency in comparison with wild type strain. No significant differences were observed in complemented strain cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> compared to wild type. No DNA amplification was observed in the un-inoculated controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g004">Figure 4A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutants have reduced colonization ability and induce higher defence response of tomato plants.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Comparative analysis of fungal biomass using quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction during disease progression caused by the wild type (wt), the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and the complemented cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> strains. Data represent nanograms of fungal DNA amplified from 100 ng of DNA extracted from infected stems. Each column represents the mean from three independent inoculation experiments with three replicates each. Standard error bars are indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Expression of defence-response genes in tomato plants three days after inoculation with the indicated strains. Transcript abundance was determined by quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction. Expression levels in each sample were normalized to the expression of the tomato <italic toggle="yes">efα</italic> gene and were calculated relative to the uninfected control plants by the <named-content content-type="gene">DDCt</named-content> method. Error bars indicate the standard error calculated from three independent inoculation experiments with three replicates each.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>The plant defence reaction in response to infection with the wild type and non-virulent Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> strains was analysed by the quantification of transcript levels of defence-related genes encoding basic glucanase (<italic toggle="yes">gluB</italic>) [<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], acidic chitinase 3 (<italic toggle="yes">chi3</italic>), basic chitinase 9 (<italic toggle="yes">chi9</italic>) [<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and pathogenesis-related protein 1 (<italic toggle="yes">pr-1</italic>) [<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] in tomato plant roots at three days post-inoculation, using quantitative real-time RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). The expression level of each defence-related gene was compared among plants infected with the wild-type strain, non-virulent Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, or the complemented strain cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> as well as non-inoculated control plants, and referred to the relative levels of the constitutive reference gene <italic toggle="yes">efα1</italic> encoding elongation factor alpha 1 [<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The expression levels of the four genes detected in plants inoculated with the mutant were significantly higher than those observed in plants inoculated with either the wild type or the complemented strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). </p></sec><sec id="s3.5"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Δgnt2</italic> mutant cell wall has altered physico-chemical properties</title><p>The role of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> Gnts on cell wall structure and integrity was investigated by determining the sensitivity to membrane or cell wall interfering agents and to heat stress conditions. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g005">Figure 5A</xref>, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant exhibited higher sensitivity to Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate (SDS) and Calcofluor white (CFW), as well as to heat stress (35 °C), than the wild type strain. As expected, reintroduction of the wild type allele completely restored the resistance to the cell wall interfering agents tested, suggesting that these phenotypes may be a general consequence of compromised cell wall integrity.</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Gnt2 mutants show increased sensitivity to stress conditions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Fungal colonies from the wild type (wt), the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and the complemented cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> strains grown for 3-4 days at 28 °C on SM plates containing Sodium Dodecyl Sulphate (SDS) or Calcofluor white (CFW), or on SM plates under heat stress conditions (120 h at 35 °C). The number of inoculated spores is indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Alcian Blue binding affinity of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> wild type (wt), Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strains. Microconidial suspensions (5 x 10<sup>8</sup> mL<sup>-1</sup>) from the indicated strains were added to an Alcian Blue containing suspension (0.025% w/v), incubated 20 min at RT, and centrifuged. The ability to bind the dye was determined by measuring the absorbance at 620 nm of the remaining supernatant after centrifugation, and represented as % of Alcian Blue bound to the cells. Photographs above the diagram show the remaining colour in the supernatants of the different strains. (<bold>C</bold>) Sensitivity of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> wild type (wt), Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strains to the treatment with 50 mg mL<sup>-1</sup> Glucanex lytic enzyme. The graph shows the number of protoplasts released from each strain during incubation for the indicated time period in min. Bars indicate the standard error from three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>The tetra-cationic compound Alcian Blue is able to detect negatively charged heteropolysaccharides, such as sulfated and carboxylated muco-polysaccharides and sialomucins (glycoproteins) in fungal cell surfaces. Reversible electrostatic bonds are formed between this cationic dye and the negative sites on the polysaccharides [<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. To further identify possible structural differences in the cell wall of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, microconidial suspensions were added to Alcian Blue solution and the absorbance of the remaining supernatant was measured at 620 nm. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g005">Figure 5B</xref>, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant displayed a 33% decreased binding affinity to Alcian Blue compared to the wild type or the complemented strains. These phenotypes prompted us to further examine the cell wall properties of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant. Germinated microconidia were exposed to a mixture of cell wall-degrading enzymes and the release of protoplasts was monitored over time. The extent of protoplast formation was followed by microscopic observation of the cell suspension at timed intervals and standardized to viable cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g005">Figure 5C</xref>, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed dramatically decreased sensitivity to the activity of the protoplasting enzyme in comparison. </p></sec><sec id="s3.6"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> deficient mutant exhibits altered aggregation behaviour</title><p>Plant lectins are used extensively in purification, detection and structural characterization of glyco-conjugates, investigation of cell-surface architecture, blood typing and fractionation of cells [<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Especially plant and invertebrate lectins have proved to be valuable for the detection of specific carbohydrate sequences [<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Lectin GS II from <italic toggle="yes">Griffonia simplicifolia</italic>, a tetrameric protein with an aggregate molecular weight of ~113 kDa with each site binding a single carbohydrate, is the only known lectin that binds with high selectivity to terminal non-reducing α- and β-<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetyl-D-glucosamine residues of glycoproteins [<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Because of its affinity, lectin GS-II conjugates are useful to identify GlcNAc-containing oligosaccharides. The ability of pre-germinated microconidia (3 h) to bind GS II-FITC conjugate was determined using flow cytometer separation and fluorescence detection. Unexpectedly, in all the experiments the mean values corresponding to the fluorescence emission in Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant cells were significantly higher than those for wild type or the complemented strain (10.5, 7.1, and 4.4 in microconidia, or 12.3, 7.1 and 4.2 in germlings, respectively). To discover the basis for the increased binding capacity, we performed fluorescence analysis using the auxiliary channel adjusted to allow discrimination between single and aggregated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Additionally, the abundance of each cell population was determined for the three strains, by microscopic observation and cell counting. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g006">Figure 6A</xref> the percentage of aggregated microconidia in Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> was about 25%, while in the wild type and the complemented strains it was significantly lower (12 and 4%, respectively, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Analyses of separate cell populations, single (H3), or aggregated cells (H4) for the three strains are shown in the histograms of relative fluorescence determined by FL1 channel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). The relative fluorescence medium values observed in each segregated cell population were similar for the three strains, around 4 to 6 for single cells and 19 to 25 for aggregated cells. Morphological analysis of cell populations was performed by cytometer light scattering detection, using the forward and side scattered light shape (FSC and SSC, respectively). As represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g006">Figure 6C</xref>, the shapes of the three populations are in accordance to the relative fluorescence value analyses (FL1 channel), showing less uniformity in strains with more aggregated cells. These results were further supported by optical and fluorescence microscopy analysis of GS II-FITC bound cell populations, where we observed a slightly higher number of aggregated cells in the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant in comparison with the wild type and the complemented strains, resulting in a slightly higher fluorescence intensity of the mutant samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). </p><fig id="pone-0084690-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>GS II-FITC lectin binding affinity of the indicated <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> strains.</title><p>Intensity of fluorescence emitted by GS II-FITC bound to cell surface was measured for 20,000 events in microconidia from wild type (wt), Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strain, using flow cytometer separation and fluorescence detection. (<bold>A</bold>) Fluorescence analysis using the auxiliary channel adjusted to allow discrimination of single cell population (H3 in the histograms and white columns in the graph) from aggregated cells population (H4 and stripped columns). The percentages of each cell population are represented for the three strains. (<bold>B</bold>) Histograms showing relative fluorescence determined by FL1 channel for single cells (H3) or aggregated cells (H4) from the three strains. Columns in the graph represent the relative fluorescence medium values observed for single cells (white) and aggregated cells (stripped). The standard errors from three independent experiments are indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) Morphological analyses of cell populations from the different strains by cytometer light scattering detection. Forward and side scattered light shape (FSC and SSC, respectively) is represented.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g006.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0084690-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> gene results in increased cell aggregation and aberrant septum morphology.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Light (upper panels) and fluorescence (lower panels) micrographs of GS II-FITC labelled swollen spores (after 3 h incubation in PDB) from wild type (wt), Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strains. Scale bars, 10 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Transmission electron micrographs showing aggregation and ultra-structure characteristics of 14 h-old germlings from the indicated strains. Black arrows, septa; white arrows, cell-to-cell contact area; black star, extracellular matrix.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g007.jpg"/></fig><p>Recently, it has been reported that changes of the physico-chemical properties of the spore surface may be related to the zeta potential of spores at different pH values [<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. To further analyse the altered aggregation pattern of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, we compared the spore aggregation ability of the different strains in glucose-containing SM at pH values 2.0, 3.5 and 6.0. Conidial aggregation was inhibited at pH 2.0 in all strains, while aggregation was comparable at pH values 3.5 and 6.0. The wild type strain showed around 15-20% aggregation after seven hours incubation at pH 6.0, while this value was up to 40% in the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant (data not shown).</p><p>Comparative TEM analysis of sections through 14 h-old germlings from the wild type strain and the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed abnormally aggregated mutant hyphae, supporting an altered aggregation phenotype in this strain in comparison with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g007">Figure 7B</xref>). Furthermore, Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> hyphae in close proximity appeared to be fixed to each other by a newly existing extracellular matrix of unknown nature, which was not detected in the wild type strain, whose hyphae were not adhered to each other. Detailed analysis of TEM micrographs revealed that Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> hyphae contained aberrant twisted septa compared to those of the wild type, suggesting defects in septum architecture. Despite these findings, no obvious consistent differences in overall cell wall structure were detected.</p></sec><sec id="s3.7"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant cell walls contain reduced levels of N-linked glycans</title><p>To demonstrate the role of Gnt2 in protein glycosylation, <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans were released from cell wall glycoproteins by alkali treatment in the wild type strain, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and the cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strain, and estimated relative to total cell wall dry weight. Similar amount of <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-linked glycans were detected in the three strains, representing 1.2 to 1.25% of the total cell wall biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g008">Figure 8</xref>). By contrast, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed a 30% reduction of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans in comparison with the wild type strain, suggesting a deficient <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation pattern in the mutant strain. The complemented strain partially restored the wild type phenotype.</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Gnt2 is required for efficient N-glycosylation of cell wall proteins.</title><p>Protein-associated glycans were released from fungal cell walls in the wild type strain (wt), and the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant and the cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> complemented strain by alkali treatment, and the amount of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- (grey bars) and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-linked glycans (white bars) was calculated relative to cell wall total dry weight. The standard errors from three independent experiments are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g008.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3.8"><title>GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein localizes in Golgi-like compartments</title><p>Gnt2 comprises an N terminal trans-membrane domain and a Golgi retention signal, suggesting that it may be localized to Golgi-like compartments. To investigate its subcellular localization we fused the <italic toggle="yes">GFP</italic> gene encoding the green fluorescent protein in frame to the 5’-end of the <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0084690.s003">Figure S3</xref>). This construct was used to transform protoplasts of both the wild type strain and the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, resulting in wt (GFP::Gnt2) and Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> (GFP::Gnt2) strains, respectively. Microscopic analysis revealed a strong GFP fluorescence that was enriched in distinct intracellular compartments of both strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g009">Figure 9A</xref>). These large spot-like structures disaggregated into smaller fluorescent spots after treatment with Brefeldin A, which is known to disrupt the Golgi apparatus [<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].</p><fig id="pone-0084690-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084690.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Gnt2 co-localizes with Golgi sub-cellular compartment proteins.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Light (left panels) and fluorescence (right panels) micrographs of germlings from the wild type (wt) and the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, both harbouring the GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein, after 5 min treatment with (+) or without (-) Brefeldin A (BFA). Scale bars, 10 µm. (<bold>B</bold>) Enzymatic activities of sub-cellular fractions (1 to 14) obtained after velocity sucrose gradient ultracentrifugation of cell lysates from the indicated strains. Aliquots of the 10,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> x 10-min pellet (P10) and the 160,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> x 90-min pellet (P160) were also included in the analyses. Dashed line, sucrose concentration; black diamonds, NADPH cytochrome c reductase activity (endoplasmic reticulum marker); white diamonds, GDPase activity (Golgi marker). (<bold>C</bold>) Proteins contained within the indicated fractions were resolved by SDS-PAGE and detected by Western blotting analyses using anti-GFP or anti-Vps10p antibodies, as indicated. (<bold>D</bold>) Colocalization of GFP::Gnt2 (green) with the Golgi apparatus (red) as stained with BODIPY TR ceramide in the indicated strains. Bar, 10 μm. </p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0084690.g009.jpg"/></fig><p>To further confirm its localization, mixed vesicle populations from both, the wt (GFP::Gnt2) and Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> (GFP::Gnt2) strains were subjected to centrifugation in a sucrose gradient. Enzymatic activities of specific Golgi and ER markers, GDPase [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and NADPH cytochrome c reductase, respectively, allowed determination of the enriched Golgi fractions, 1, 2 and 3, as well as the ER enriched fraction P10, in both strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g009">Figure 9B</xref>). Western analyses of those fractions using the specific antibody against the trans-Golgi resident membrane protein Vps10 from <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> [<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] or the anti-GFP antibody confirmed the co-localization of both proteins in the Golgi-enriched fractions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g009">Figure 9C</xref>). Localization of Gnt2 was further confirmed by selective staining of Golgi compartments using the red fluorescent BODIPY-TR ceramide in both wt (GFP::Gnt2) and Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> (GFP::Gnt2) strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g009">Figure 9D</xref>). All together these results support the hypothesis that Gnt2 is retained in Golgi-like structures of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>During most host-pathogen interactions, a complex crosstalk between the pathogen and its host is established. In the case of fungal pathogens many infection processes involve two important features: secretion of fungal effector proteins, which interact with a variety of plant responses, and recognition of fungal cell wall proteins during host invasion, which modulates the plant immune response [<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>–<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Both fungal secreted effectors and cell wall proteins are generally subjected to post-translational modifications in the endoplasmic reticulum and Golgi apparatus. Protein glycosylation is the most common post-translational modification in eukaryotes and confers the appropriate stability, functionality and localization of cellular proteins [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, glycosylation is likely to have an important role in modulating the interaction between <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> and its hosts.</p><p>In this study we performed an <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glycosylation pathway components from the tomato pathogen <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. lycopersici. As reported for the plant pathogen <italic toggle="yes">U. maydis</italic> [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], glycosylation in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> appears to be simpler, involving less components [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] than the large families described for <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">C. albicans</italic> [<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Nevertheless, it was remarkable to find seven members of putative <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>acetyl glucosaminyl transferases (Gnts) in the genome of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic>. This feature appears to be unique for a fungal species, as demonstrated by comparative genomic analysis with the two closely related species <italic toggle="yes">F. graminearum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">F. verticilloides</italic>, and other related species. This putative glycosyltransferase ‘family’ may have arisen through exon shuffling, or by gene duplication and subsequent divergence. The different number and chromosome location of Gnt encoding genes in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> in comparison with the two other <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">spp.</italic> may point to divergent evolutionary mechanisms during adaptation of the infection process in root and aerial plant pathogens, due to the specific requirements encountered during host colonization [<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Similar results have been previously reported for cutinolytic encoding genes, in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> with one single cutinase gene [<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], as opposed to three in <italic toggle="yes">F. solani</italic> [<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. </p><p>Gnts are Golgi-localized membrane-bound enzymes involved in key steps of biosynthesis of complex and hybrid <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycans from oligomannose-type <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycans [<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Gnt</italic> genes were cloned from various eukaryotic species including mammals, insects, nematodes [<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] and higher plants [<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. All Gnt proteins have N-terminal transmembrane and conserved central catalytic domains. Since most Gnts are resident and anchored in the membranes lining the ER and the trans-Golgi network (<italic toggle="yes">cis-, medial- trans</italic>-), they contain sequences, in or around their trans-membrane region, for targeting or retention in the Golgi apparatus (mostly unknown) analogous to the K(H)DEL for ER location signal. The <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycans from glycoproteins that move to and through the Golgi may be processed into complex type <italic toggle="yes">N-</italic>glycans by trimming of mannose residues and/or addition of specific sugar residues, before they get to other subcellular organelles, the plasma membrane, the cell wall, or the extracellular space. <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> Gnts share conserved structural motifs including a transmembrane domain, a Golgi targeting or retention signal, C residues for establishing di-sulfide linkages, and the so-called DXD motifs thought to play a role in metal ion binding and catalysis, and/or DSD as their catalytic active sites for sugar-donor/receptor molecules [<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. We have localized a GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein in intracellular compartments that are sensitive to Brefeldin A and accumulate the fluorescent sphingolipid BODIPY-TR, strongly suggesting that they correspond to <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> Golgi-like structures. Localization of the fusion protein was further verified by immune-detection in subcellular compartments enriched in GDPase enzymatic activity, described as a Golgi located enzyme in <italic toggle="yes">C. albicans</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">S.</italic> cerevisiae and <italic toggle="yes">Kluyveromyces lactis</italic> [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], which also contained Vps10, a membrane protein that resides in late-Golgi compartments [<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. </p><p>In order to address the role of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation in pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic>, we constructed a disruption mutant lacking functional Gnt2. The resulting Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> strain showed a dramatic reduction of its infection capacity on tomato plants, suggesting that correct protein glycosylation may be influencing virulence in this pathogenic fungus. The increased defence-reaction detected in tomato plants inoculated with the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant might be reflecting recognition of the altered glycosylation pattern of the fungal cell wall surface and/or secreted effectors. Additionally, the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant showed attenuated virulence on <italic toggle="yes">G. mellonella</italic>, an invertebrate model host that is widely used for the study of microbial human pathogens and has been described as a useful infection model for studying virulence mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> on animal hosts [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Protein glycosylation has been identified as an important process for the virulence of various fungal pathogens of animals. To date, most reports have described the importance of <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-linked glycosylation, frequently <italic toggle="yes">O-</italic>mannosylation. For example, the role of PMTs has been well established to support both morphological transitions and animal host infection by <italic toggle="yes">C. neoformans</italic> [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">C. albicans</italic> [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">A. fumigatus</italic> [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Other studies have also revealed a role of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation in virulence of <italic toggle="yes">C. albicans</italic> through the analysis of mutants affected in the subsequent processing of high mannose-type glycans, following the initial transfer of the core oligosaccharide structure onto proteins [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. For plant infecting fungi, to date there are only three examples where defects in protein glycosylation had an effect upon pathogen development and virulence. In the basidiomycete fungus <italic toggle="yes">U. maydis</italic>, mutants lacking an ER associated glycan processing enzyme Glucosidase II grew normally <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> but failed to effectively establish a host–pathogen interface with the plant [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and the <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-mannosyltransferase PMT4 was found to be essential for appressorium formation and penetration [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Recently, in the wheat leaf infecting fungus <italic toggle="yes">M. graminicola</italic>, the α-1,2-mannosyltransferase MgAlg2, which functions in the early stages of asparagine-linked protein <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation, was shown to play an important role in the virulence of this fungus. Loss of MgAlg2 function gave rise to an inability of spores to extend hyphal filaments, which normally permit leaf penetration by the fungus through stomata [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Recently it was found that <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation might also play a role in plant pathogen interactions through functional pattern recognition receptors [<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. In mammalian cells the glycans on the glycoproteins have been proven to be involved in a wide range of biological functions such as receptor binding, cell signalling, protein folding, subcellular distribution and localization, protein stability, endocytosis, immune recognition, inflammation and pathogenicity [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Our results on <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> putative <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetylglucosamine transferase Gnt2 suggest that <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation might represent a key virulence mechanism important for the interaction of the pathogen with both plant and animal hosts.</p><p>Phenotypic characterization of the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant indicated hypersensitivity to membrane and cell wall destabilizing agents, as well as to heat stress, and reduced binding affinity to the positively charged dye Alcian Blue. Additionally, septa in the mutant strain showed altered structure when compared with the wild type strain. Despite the fact that no detectable differences in cell wall structures were observed between the wild type and the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant by TEM, these data suggest that the cell wall and septa in the mutant strain lack the structural strength and/or the physical-chemical properties of wild type cells. This is supported by the observation that mutant cells show a high tendency to aggregate to each other, which could be mediated by the secretion of an extracellular matrix of unknown nature. On the other hand, quantification of cell wall protein-associated glycans revealed a hypo-glycosylated pattern in the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant, due to either a significant reduction or a different structure of the <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked oligosaccharides, suggesting that Gnt2 is required for efficient <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation of cell wall proteins in <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>. Studies on protein <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation mutants in <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> pointed that defects in cell wall strength might arise from alterations in the chemical composition of the glycans present in this structure. One hypothesis explaining this link was that under-glycosylated proteins led to incorrectly processed and localized proteins, with loss of enzymatic activities that were critical for biosynthesis of cell wall β1,6-glucan in the mutant strain [<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. A similar explanation was proposed for the <italic toggle="yes">M. graminicola N</italic>-glycosylation mutant Δ<italic toggle="yes">MgAld2</italic>. In this pathogenic fungus <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation plays key roles in regulating the switch to hyphal growth, possibly as a consequence of maintaining correct folding and localization of key proteins involved in this process [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The biochemical GlcNAc transferase activity on fungal cell wall proteins has been reported in <italic toggle="yes">C. cinerea</italic>, where depletion of <italic toggle="yes">CcGnt1</italic> gene expression by RNAi strongly reduced the GlcNAc modification in <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-linked glycans of the silenced transformants fruiting bodies [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>In conclusion, our results support that <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic toggle="yes">lycopersici</italic> contains a putative <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-Acetyl-glucosaminyl transferase located in Golgi-like compartments essential for virulence and cell wall strength. The precise mechanism underlying these phenotypes is still unknown, but it provides a useful base to analyse in more detail the role of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation in host-pathogen interactions. A complete comparative analysis of the structure and biosynthesis of cell wall glycans in the Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant will help to understand the immunological properties of the cell wall and the relation between <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-glycosylation and pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0084690.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Disruption of the predicted Gnt2 encoding gene (gnt2).</bold> (<bold>A</bold>) Targeted replacement strategy using the DelsGate technique and the hygromycin resistance cassette (Hyg<sup>R</sup>) as selective marker. Black arrowheads indicate the primer pairs used for amplification of DNA fragments. (<bold>B</bold>) Southern analysis of gDNAs from <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> wild type strain (wt), targeted Δ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant 55, ectopic transformant #45 and a cΔ<italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> mutant complemented with a <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> wild type allele (#6). DNAs were digested with EcoR I and <italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic> I and hybridized with the probe indicated in A (dashed bar). </p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0084690.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0084690.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Alignment of deduced amino acids from 25 N-acetylglucosamine transferases belonging to eleven fungal species.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> (FOXG_01495; FOXG_12436/FOXG_14101; FOXG_12874; FOXG_12897; FOXG_14149; FOXG_16408)<italic toggle="yes">, F. graminearum</italic> (FGSG_10936; FGSG_10956*)<italic toggle="yes">, F. verticillioides</italic> (FVEG_07859; FVEG_11624; FVEG_11649*), <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> (AFUB_08390), <italic toggle="yes">A. niger</italic> (An11g10206; An03g02990), <italic toggle="yes">A. oryzae</italic> (AO09001000), <italic toggle="yes">Chaetomium globosum</italic> (CHGG_09837; CHGG_08452), <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (GNT1, YOR320C), <italic toggle="yes">Nectria haematococca</italic> (NHA_39806; NHA_79931; NHA_79932), <italic toggle="yes">Verticillium dahliae</italic> (VDBG_01023; VDBG_03984), <italic toggle="yes">Penicillium chrysogenum</italic> (PC_16g00820; PC_22g12650). The alignment corresponds to the G-block used for construction of the cladogram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0084690-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p><p>*These genes were manually cured as follows: FGSG_10956, 120 amino acids were added upstream of the annotated start codon; FVEG_11649, 78 amino acids were added upstream of the annotated start codon.</p><p>(EPS)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0084690.s002.eps" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0084690.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Construction of the GFP::Gnt2 fusion protein.</bold> The <italic toggle="yes">gnt2</italic> cDNA fragment was amplified with the indicated primers, containing the <italic toggle="yes">Nsi</italic> I and <italic toggle="yes">Xma</italic> I restriction sites inserted at 5´or 3´ end of the ORF, respectively, and cloned into the corresponding restriction sites of the expression vector p1902. The resulting in-frame ORF fusion is under control of the <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus nidulans</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">gpdA</italic> promoter and terminator. Arrows indicate the transcriptional orientation.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0084690.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0084690.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium oxysporum</italic> orthologue genes</bold> involved in glycosylation pathways by comparison to those described in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. For protein blast search in the Broad Institute database <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/</ext-link>.</p><p>the S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic> proteins were used as query sequences. The systematic name for <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> genes and their function were obtained from <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic> genome database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.yeastgenome.org/">http://www.yeastgenome.org/</ext-link>). <italic toggle="yes">F. oxysporum</italic> gene numbers and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> value parameter after WUBLAST analysis were obtained directly from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/annotation/genome/fusarium_group/</ext-link>.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0084690.s004.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge Dr. A. Di Pietro for valuable suggestions and critical reading of the manuscript, Dr. J.A. González-Reyes for his advice with electron microscopy, Dr. J.M. Villalba for his helpful expertise with the cytometer experiments, and Esther Martínez Aguilera for technical assistance (all from Universidad de Cordoba). </p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schoffelmeer</surname><given-names>EAM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klis</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sietsma</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>BJC</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The cell wall of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/fgbi.1999.1153</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10441453">10441453</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10441453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Class V chitin synthase determines pathogenesis in the vascular kilt fungus <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic> and mediates resistance to plant defense compounds</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12492869">12492869</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03299.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ortoneda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guarro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caracuel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic> as a multihost model for the genetic dissection of fungal virulence in plants and mammals</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1760</fpage>-<lpage>1766</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.72.3.1760-1766.2004</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14977985">14977985</ext-link>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC356063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pareja-Jaime</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martín Urdíroz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>González Reyes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Roldán</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chitin synthase-deficient mutant of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic> elicits tomato plant defence response and protects against wild-type infection</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>-<lpage>493</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00624.x</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20618706">20618706</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20618706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6640515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turkenburg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charnok</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Insights into trehalose synthesis provided by the structure of the retaining glucosyl transferase OstA. Chem</article-title>. <source>Biol</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1337</fpage>-<lpage>1346</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1074-5521(02)00292-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermjakob</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>On the frequency of protein glycosylation, as deduced from analysis of the SWISS-PROT database</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1473</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4165(99)00165-8</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10580125">10580125</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>O-linked N-acetylglucosamine and cancer: messages from the glycosylation of c-Myc</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>
<volume>491</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4615-1267-7_26</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14533811">14533811</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14533811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crocker</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feizi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Carbohydrate recognition systems: Functional triads in cell-cell interactions</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>679</fpage>-<lpage>691</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-440X(96)80036-4</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8913692">8913692</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Protein glycosylation, conserved from yeast to man: a model organism helps elucidate congenital human diseases</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>6802</fpage>-<lpage>6818</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.200601645</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17024709">17024709</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17024709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The dolichol pathway of N-linked glycosylation</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1426</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4165(98)00127-5</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9878760">9878760</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9878760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Routier</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echtenacher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Approaching the secrets of N-glycosylation in <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">fumigatus</italic>: Characterization of the AfOch1 protein</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>e15729</fpage> PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21206755">21206755</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0015729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3012087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21206755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Protein glycosylation and its role in protein folding</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.69.1.69</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10966453">10966453</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Helenius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Roles of N-linked glycans in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1019</fpage>-<lpage>1049</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.73.011303.073752</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15189166">15189166</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15189166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lommel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Protein O-mannosylation: conserved from bacteria to humans</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>816</fpage>-<lpage>828</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwp066</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19429925">19429925</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nevalainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Protein glycosylation pathways in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>626</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwn044</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18504293">18504293</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18504293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Käser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Künzler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification, characterization, and biosynthesis of a novel N-Glycan modification in the fruiting body of the basidiomycete <italic toggle="yes">Coprinopsis</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cinerea</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>10715</fpage>-<lpage>10723</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.076075</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20061575">20061575</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20061575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2856279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rancurel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes database (CAZy): an expert resources for glycogenomics</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D233</fpage>-<lpage>D238</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn663</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18838391">18838391</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2686590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ballou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballou</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Revision of the oligosaccharide structures of yeast carboxypeptidase Y</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>3368</fpage>-<lpage>3372</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.87.9.3368</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2185468">2185468</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2185468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC53901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olivero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larriba</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Oligosaccharide structures of the major exoglucanase secreted by <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>9823</fpage>-<lpage>9831</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00155a039</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1390756">1390756</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1390756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballou</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Carbohydrate structure of yeast invertase. Demonstration of a form with only core oligosaccharides and a form with completed polysaccharide chains</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>254</volume>: <fpage>12209</fpage>-<lpage>12218</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/115881">115881</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">115881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yoko</surname></name>
<comment>oT</comment>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>CAR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peak-Chew</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A N-acetyl-glucosaminyl transferase of the Golgi apparatus of the yeast <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic> that can modify N-linked glycans</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwg063</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12651885">12651885</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12651885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Yeast glycosylation mutants are sensitive to aminoglycosides</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>1287</fpage>-<lpage>1291</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.5.1287</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7877969">7877969</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7877969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC42504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Timpel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strahl-Bolsinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegelbauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Multiple functions of Pmt1p-mediated protein O-mannosylation in the fungal pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>20837</fpage>–<lpage>20846</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.33.20837</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9694829">9694829</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Timpel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zink</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strahl-Bolsinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schröppel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Morphogenesis, adhesive properties, and antifungal resistance depend on the Pmt6 protein mannosyltransferase in the fungal pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>3063</fpage>–<lpage>3071</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.182.11.3063-3071.2000</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10809683">10809683</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10809683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC94490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prill</surname><given-names>SKH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klinkert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Timpel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schröppel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>PMT family of Candida <italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic>: five protein mannosyltransferase isoforms affect growth, morphogenesis and antifungal resistance</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15659169">15659169</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04401.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RTH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>MNN5 encodes an iron-regulated alpha-1,2-mannosyltransferase important for protein glycosylation, cell wall integrity, morphogenesis and virulence in Candida <italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.5.2.238-247.2006</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16467465">16467465</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1405895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>WPH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacCallum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Outer chain N-glycans are required for cell wall integrity and virulence of Candida <italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>281</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M510360200</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16263704">16263704</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16263704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rouabhia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corbucci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vecchiarelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prill</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Virulence of the fungal pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic> requires the five isoforms of protein mannosyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>4571</fpage>-<lpage>4580</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.73.8.4571-4580.2005</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16040968">16040968</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16040968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1201229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alspaugh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Role of protein O-mannosyltransferase Pmt4 in the morphogenesis and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptococcus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">neoformans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.00182-06</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17142566">17142566</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1797945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lengeler</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tielker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Protein O-mannosyl transferases in virulence and development</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>-<lpage>544</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-007-7409-z</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17975704">17975704</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17975704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11131616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mouyna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kniemeyer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jank</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loussert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Members of protein O-mannosyltransferase family in <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">fumigatus</italic> differentially affect growth, morphogenesis and viability</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1205</fpage>-<lpage>1221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07164.x</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20398215">20398215</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Álvarez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elías-Villalobos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibeas</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The O-mannosyltransferase PMT4 is essential for normal appressorium formation and penetration in <italic toggle="yes">Ustilago</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">maydis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3397</fpage>-<lpage>3412</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.065839</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19880800">19880800</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2782298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Álvarez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elías-Villalobos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibeas</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The requirement for protein O-mannosylation for <italic toggle="yes">Ustilago</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">maydis</italic> virulence seems to be linked to intrinsic aspects of the infection process rather than an altered plant response</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.5.4.10805</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20061799">20061799</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20061799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7080420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Álvarez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elías-Villalobos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibeas</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Protein glycosylation in the phytopathogen <italic toggle="yes">Ustilago</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">maydis</italic>: From core oligosaccharide synthesis to the ER glycoprotein quality control system, a genomic analysis</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>-<lpage>735</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2010.06.004</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20554055">20554055</ext-link>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20554055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schirawski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Böhnert</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snetselaar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adamikowa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum glucosidase II is required for pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">Ustilago</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">maydis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>3532</fpage>-<lpage>3543</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.036285</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16272431">16272431</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1315386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovegrove</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pirie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devonshire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Aberrant protein N-glycosylation impacts upon infection-related growth transitions of the haploid plant-pathogenic fungus <italic toggle="yes">Mycosphaerella</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">graminícola</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>-<lpage>433</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2011.07701.x</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21623954">21623954</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21623954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cloning, expression, and role in pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">pg1</italic> encoding the major extracellular endopolygalacturonase of the vascular wilt pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.1998.11.2.91</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9450333">9450333</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweigard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Improved vectors for selecting resistance to hygromycin</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Newsl</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Hondel</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Transformation of filamentous fungi based on hygromycin B and phleomycin resistance markers</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source>
<volume>216</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(92)16041-H</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1479914">1479914</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1479914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caracuel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Rocha</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic> gas1 encodes a β-1,3-glucanosyltransferase required for virulence on tomato plants</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1140</fpage>-<lpage>1147</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-18-1140</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16353549">16353549</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16353549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chomczynski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Single-step method of RNA isolation by acid guanidinium thiocyanatephenol- chloroform extraction</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>
<volume>162</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abio.1987.9999</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2440339">2440339</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2440339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aljanabi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Universal and rapid salt-extraction of high quality genomic DNA for PCR-based techniques</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4692</fpage>-<lpage>4693</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.22.4692</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9358185">9358185</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9358185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC147078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raeder</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Rapid preparation of DNA from filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.1985.tb01479.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>215</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2231712">2231712</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(–Delta Delta C(T)) method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>, <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11846609">11846609</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>García-Pedrajas</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baeza-Montáñez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Delsgate: a robust and rapid method for gene deletion</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<volume>638</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60761-611-5_5</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20238261">20238261</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20238261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Antebi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The yeast Ca2+-ATPase homologue, PMR1, is required for normal Golgi function and localizes in a novel Golgi-like distribution</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>-<lpage>654</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.3.6.633</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1379856">1379856</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1379856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC275619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uccelletti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeijon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Golgi GDPase of the fungal pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Candida</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">albicans</italic> affects morphogenesis, glycosylation, and cell wall properties</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>-<lpage>431</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.1.3.420-431.2002</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12455990">12455990</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12455990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC118022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haugland</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>A novel fluorescent ceramide analogue for studying membrane traffic in animal cells: accumulation at the Golgi apparatus results in altered spectral properties of the sphingolipid precursor</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1267</fpage>-<lpage>1279</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.113.6.1267</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2045412">2045412</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2045412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2289039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Clustal W improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>4673</fpage>-<lpage>4680</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7984417">7984417</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC308517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>BioEdit</article-title>. <comment>Available: </comment>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/bioedit/bioedit.html">http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/BioEdit/bioedit.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Selection of conserved blocks from multiple alignments for their use in phylogenetic analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>-<lpage>552</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026334</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10742046">10742046</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>696</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150390235520</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14530136">14530136</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Creevey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pentony</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naughton</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mclnerney</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Assessment of methods for amino acid matrix selection and their use on empirical data shows that ad hoc assumptions for choice of matrix are not justified</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-6-29</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16563161">16563161</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16563161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1435933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1596</fpage>-<lpage>1599</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17488738">17488738</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katsuyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression of N-acetylglucosamine residues in developing rat fundic gland cells</article-title>. <source>Histochem J</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1004051408239</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10841313">10841313</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10841313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Glycoconjugate expression during early mouse oculogenesis</article-title>. <source>Histochem J</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>-<lpage>827</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1003550612096</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9988349">9988349</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9988349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guillen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeijon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Mammalian Golgi apparatus UDP-N-acetylglucosamine transporter: molecular cloning by phenotypic correction of a yeast mutant</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>7888</fpage>-<lpage>7892</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.14.7888</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9653110">9653110</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9653110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC20899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrazem</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Miranda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabé</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Heterogeneity of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Myrothecium</italic> as revealed by cell wall polysaccharides</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>
<volume>173</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage>-<lpage>302</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002030000149</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10816049">10816049</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10816049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Priegnitz</surname><given-names>B-E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wargenau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The role of initial spore adhesion in pellet and biofilm formation in <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">niger</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2011.12.002</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22178638">22178638</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22178638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>López-Berges</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Capilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turrà</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schafferer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matthijs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>HapX-mediated iron homeostasis is essential for rhizosphere competence and virulence of the soilborne pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>3805</fpage>-<lpage>3822</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.098624</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22968717">22968717</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22968717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3480304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Velasco</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prados-Rosales</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortíz-Urquiza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quesada-Moraga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Galleria</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">mellonella</italic> as model host for the transkingdom pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1124</fpage>-<lpage>1129</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2011.08.004</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21907298">21907298</ext-link>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21907298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Inositol phosphorylceramidesynthase is located in the Golgi apparatus of <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2267</fpage>-<lpage>2281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.11.7.2267</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10888667">10888667</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10888667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC14918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Does</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borkovich</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daboussi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Comparative genomics reveals mobile pathogenicity chromosomes in <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>464</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>373</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08850</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20237561">20237561</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20237561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3048781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagemakers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Berg-Velthuis</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Differential accumulation of mRNAs encoding extracellular and intracellular PR proteins in tomato induced by virulent and avirulent races of <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">fulvum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00040610</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1421154">1421154</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1421154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Danhash</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagemakers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of four chitinase cDNAs obtained from <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">fulvum</italic>-infected tomato</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1017</fpage>–<lpage>1029</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00028974</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8400122">8400122</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8400122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Expósito-Rodríguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borges-Pérez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Selection of internal control genes for quantitative real-time RT-PCR studies during tomato development process</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-8-131</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19102748">19102748</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19102748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2629474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Odani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jigami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Mannosylphosphate transfer to cell wall mannan is regulated by the transcriptional level of the MNN4 gene in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>420</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(97)01513-5</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9459307">9459307</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9459307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Lectins: carbohydrate-specific proteins that mediate cellular recognition</article-title>. <source>Chem Rev</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>-<lpage>674</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr940413g</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11848911">11848911</ext-link>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11848911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peumans</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>EJM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Plant lectins: specific tools for the identification, isolation, and characterization of O-linked glycans</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Biochem Mol Biol</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9766939">9766939</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Lectins as molecules and as tools</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.55.070186.000343</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3527046">3527046</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3527046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashford</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Brefeldin A affects growth, endoplasmic reticulum, Golgi bodies, tubular vacuole system, and secretory pathway in <italic toggle="yes">Pisolithus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">tinctorius</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/fgbi.2000.1190</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10919378">10919378</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10919378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Wit</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>How plants recognize pathogens and defend themselves</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>2726</fpage>-<lpage>2732</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-007-7284-7</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17876517">17876517</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17876517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11136299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van de Veerdonk</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kullberg</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gow</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Netea</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Host-microbe interactions: innate pattern recognition of fungal pathogens</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>312</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2008.06.002</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18602019">18602019</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18602019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stukenbrock</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Population genetics of fungal and oomycete effectors involved in gene-for-gene interactions</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-22-4-0371</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19271952">19271952</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19271952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gemmill</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trimble</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Overview of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">O</italic>- linked oligosaccharide structures found in various yeast species</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1426</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4165(98)00126-3</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9878752">9878752</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9878752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Rocha</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Roldán</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>MIG</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ctf1, a transcriptional activator of cutinase and lipase genes in <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">oxysporum</italic> is dispensable for virulence</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2007.00463.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6640520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18705871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirakova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ettinger</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Regulation of constitutively expressed and induced cutinase genes by different zinc finger transcription factors in <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">solani</italic> f. sp. <italic toggle="yes">pisi</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Nectria</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">haematococca</italic>)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>7905</fpage>-<lpage>7912</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M108799200</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11756444">11756444</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mucha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Structural and functional features of glycosyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>-<lpage>718</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0300-9084(01)01298-6</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11530202">11530202</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11530202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Expression of three <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">elegans</italic> N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase I genes during development</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>274</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.1.288</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9867843">9867843</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9867843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mucha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwihla</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glössl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of cDNA coding for β1,2N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase I (GlcNAc-TI) from <italic toggle="yes">Nicotiana</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">tabacum</italic>
</article-title>
<comment>Glycobiology 9: 779–785</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/glycob/9.8.779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10406843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wenderoth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Schaewen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of plant N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase I (GntI) cDNA sequences: functional analyses in the <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cgl</italic> mutant and in antisense plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1097</fpage>-<lpage>1108</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.123.3.1097</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10889259">10889259</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC59073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeijon</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>A guanosine diphosphatase enriched in Golgi vesicles of <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>. Purification and characterization</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>265</volume>: <fpage>19351</fpage>–<lpage>19355</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2172253">2172253</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2172253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Avalos</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uccelletti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeijon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The UDPase activity of the <italic toggle="yes">Kluyveromyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> Golgi GDPase has a role in uridine nucleotide sugar transport into Golgi vesicles</article-title>. <source>Glycobiology</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>422</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/11.5.413</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11425802">11425802</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nothwehr</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The newly identified yeast <italic toggle="yes">GRD</italic> genes are required for retention of late-Golgi membrane proteins</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2700</fpage>–<lpage>2707</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8649377">8649377</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8649377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.16.6.2700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC231260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Häweker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rips</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koiwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saijo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Pattern recognition receptors require N-glycosylation to mediate plant immunity</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>: <fpage>4629</fpage>-<lpage>4636</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.063073</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20007973">20007973</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2836068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rekowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lennarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genetic, biochemical, and morphological evidence for the involvement of N-glycosylation in biosynthesis of the cell wall beta 1,6-glucan of <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>15381</fpage>-<lpage>15386</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2536561100</pub-id>. PubMed: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14676317">14676317</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14676317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC307576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>