
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">750</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">9882906</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3935559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3935559.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3935559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3935559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376255</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ert438</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Physiological and genetic analysis of CO<sub>2</sub>-induced breakdown of self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lao</surname><given-names initials="X">Xintian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names initials="K">Keita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names initials="S">Satoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakita</surname><given-names initials="M">Mitsuru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names initials="M">Megumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names initials="S">Seiji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>Graduate School of Biological Sciences, Nara Institute of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Ikoma, Nara 630-0192</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>Graduate School of Bioresources, Mie University</institution>, <addr-line>Tsu 514-8507</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><sup>3</sup><institution>Tohoku Seed Co. Ltd</institution>, <addr-line>Utsunomiya 321-3232</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">* To whom correspondencne should be addressed. E-mail: <email>takayama@bs.naist.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>65</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">234322</issue-id><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>26</day><month>02</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-06-23 01:25:18.430"><day>23</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ert438.pdf"/><abstract><p>Self-incompatibility (SI) of the Brassicaceae family can be overcome by CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment. This method has been used for decades as an effective means to obtain a large amount of inbred seeds which can then be used for F<sub>1</sub> hybrid seed production; however, the molecular mechanism by which CO<sub>2</sub> alters the SI pathway has not been elucidated. In this study, to obtain new insights into the mechanism of CO<sub>2</sub>-induced SI breakdown, the focus was on two inbred lines of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> (syn. <italic toggle="yes">campestris</italic>) with different CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity. Physiological examination using X-ray microanalysis suggested that SI breakdown in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line was accompanied by a significant accumulation of calcium at the pollen–stigma interface. Pre-treatment of pollen or pistil with CO<sub>2</sub> gas before pollination showed no effect on the SI reaction, suggesting that some physiological process after pollination is necessary for SI to be overcome. Genetic analyses using F<sub>1</sub> progeny of a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive×CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive cross suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is a semi-dominant trait in these lines. Analysis of F<sub>2</sub> progeny suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity could be a quantitative trait, which is controlled by more than one gene. Quantitative trait locus (QTL) analyses identified two major loci, <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>, which work additively in overcoming SI during CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. No QTL was detected at the loci previously shown to affect SI stability, suggesting that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is determined by novel genes. The QTL data presented here should be useful for determining the responsible genes, and for the marker-assisted selection of desirable parental lines with stable but CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive SI in F<sub>1</sub> hybrid breeding.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic></kwd><kwd>calcium</kwd><kwd>CO2</kwd><kwd>F1 hybrid</kwd><kwd>QTL</kwd><kwd>self-incompatibility.</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Self-incompatibility (SI) is a widespread genetic system in many flowering plants which serves to prevent self-fertilization and maintain genetic diversity. It is based on self/non-self pollen–pistil recognition interactions followed by inhibition of self-pollen hydration, germination, or pollen tube growth.</p><p content-type="indent">In the Brassicaceae, SI is sporophytically controlled by a multiallelic locus termed the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> locus (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Bateman, 1955</xref>). Male and female determinants have been identified as SP11/SCR (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus protein 11/<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus cysteine-rich) (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Schopfer <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Takayama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) and SRK (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic> receptor kinase) (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Takasaki <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>), respectively. When a compatible pollen grain lands on the stigma, it swells and a pollen tube is allowed to grow, whereas when self-pollen attaches to the stigma, SP11/SCR binds specifically to the extracellular domain of SRK of the same <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotype (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Takayama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), which triggers an SI signalling pathway to reject self-pollen. Another stigmatically expressed gene located at the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> locus, <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> locus glycoprotein (<italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic>) (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Nasrallah <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Takayama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>), has been shown to enhance the recognition process between self-pollen and stigma (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Takasaki <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>); however, this function of <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> remains controversial (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Silva <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). A recent study suggested that the plants in the Brassicaceae genus Levenworthia use paralogous <italic toggle="yes">SRK</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SP11/SCR</italic> genes, <italic toggle="yes">Lal2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Leavenworthia alabamica SRK-related 2</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">SCRl</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">SCR-like</italic>), for self/non-self recognition in SI, but the function of their orthologues in other Brassicaceae genera also remains unknown (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Chantha <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Many studies focusing on the downstream components involved in this type of SI signalling pathway have been performed and, thus far, two components have been identified as positive effectors. ARC1 (arm repeat containing 1) was identified by a yeast two-hybrid screen using the kinase domain of SRK as the bait (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Gu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Stone <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). ARC1 is a U-box protein with E3 ubiquitin ligase activity (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Stone <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), and has been shown to interact with Exo70A1, a putative component of the exocyst complex required for compatible pollination (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Samuel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). MLPK (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic>-locus protein kinase) was identified by positional cloning as the gene responsible for the self-compatible mutation of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> var. Yellow sarson (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Murase <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). MLPK is a membrane-anchored cytoplasmic protein kinase and interacts directly with SRK to transduce SI signalling (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Kakita <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). However, the importance of these two components in the Brassicaceae SI mechanism remains controversial (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Kitashiba <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Indriolo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">In the Brassicaceae, it has been known that SI can be overcome under some physiological and environmental conditions such as plant age (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Ockendon, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Horisaki and Niikura, 2008</xref>), stigmatic chemical treatments (e.g. ether, KOH, and NaCl) (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Tatebe, 1968</xref>; Tao and Yong, 1986; <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Monterio and Gabelman, 1988</xref>), and high temperature (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Matsubara, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Okazaki and Hinata, 1987</xref>). CO<sub>2</sub> gas (3–5%) treatment (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1969</xref>) is the most effective way to overcome SI. Today, most cultivated lines of crucifer vegetables, such as cabbage, broccoli, Chinese cabbage, and radish are F<sub>1</sub> hybrids whose seeds are produced by mix-planting two self-incompatible inbred parental lines. In this economical F<sub>1</sub> hybrid breeding system, CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment has been used to suppress SI and allow self-fertilization, thereby providing large-scale seed propagation of parental lines. This method has been used all over the world for many years, but the molecular mechanism leading to SI breakdown by CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment is entirely unknown.</p><p content-type="indent">Previous studies suggested that not all lines respond equally to CO<sub>2</sub>, and there are variations in SI response to CO<sub>2</sub> (CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity) in the Brassicaceae (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi and Hinata, 1973</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Niikura and Matsuura, 2000</xref>). Preliminary genetic analysis using lines with different CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity in radish (<italic toggle="yes">Raphanus sativus</italic>) suggested that high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity was controlled by a recessive gene independent of the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Niikura and Matsuura, 2000</xref>). In another genetic analysis using CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines of Chinese cabbage (<italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic>), high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity was suggested to be controlled by a dominant gene (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Hyun <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>); however, no responsible genes have been identified from these studies so far.</p><p content-type="indent">In this study, new inbred lines of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> with different CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity, a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (HA-11621) and a CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (HA-11623), were selected and analysed. X-ray microanalysis suggested that SI breakdown in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line was accompanied by significant calcium accumulation at the pollen–stigma interface. Independent pre-treatment of pollen or pistil with CO<sub>2</sub> gas before pollination showed no effect on the SI reaction, suggesting that some physiological process that occurs after pollination is necessary for SI to be overcome. Genetic analyses using F<sub>1</sub> and F<sub>2</sub> progeny of a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive×CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive cross suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is a semi-dominant and quantitative trait. Furthermore, quantitative trait locus (QTL) analyses identified two major responsible loci, <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>, which function additively in overcoming SI during CO<sub>2</sub> treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Two inbred lines of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> (2<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=20), a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (HA-11621) and a CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (HA-11623), were established at Tohoku Seed Co., Ltd, and grown in the greenhouse with 16h light and 8h dark conditions at 20 °C. Both lines show stable SI under normal (open-air) condition but have different CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity; SI in HA-11621 breaks down following treatment with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> whereas SI in HA-11623 is unaffected. HA-11621 and HA-11623 are reciprocally compatible, and their F<sub>1</sub> progeny were obtained under normal conditions. Buds (1–2 d before flowering) from a randomly chosen F<sub>1</sub> were used for F<sub>2</sub> production. Young petals and stamens were removed from the bud, and the immature pistil was pollinated with pollen grains from mature flowers of the same plant (bud pollination). Pollinated pistil was then covered with a paper bag for 3 d and seeds from the pistil were harvested. More than 20 pistils were pollinated, and harvested seeds were used as the F<sub>2</sub> population. A total of 110 F<sub>2</sub> plants were used for phenotypic and genetic analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Cryo-scanning electron microscopy and energy-dispersive X-ray analysis</title><p>Flowers were self- or cross-pollinated and incubated for 1.5h with or without 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> gas. These pollinated and non-pollinated pistils were submersed in liquid nitrogen slush and frozen under vacuum. While under vacuum, the sample was transferred to the microscope cryo stage (ALTO 1000, Gatan), and then the stage temperature was increased to –95 °C to remove frost that had settled on top of the specimen as a result of condensation. When all surface frost had been removed by sublimation, as verified by electron microscopy, the temperature was reduced to –140 °C. Imaging was performed using an ETD (Everhart–Thornley detector) by Quant 250 scanning electron microscopy (FEI). The chamber pressure was 30 Pa and the accelerating voltage was 15kV. EDX (energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy) analysis of the element assay was performed on selected papilla cells using INCA X-ray analysis software (Oxford Instruments, <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oxinst.com/Pages/home.aspx">http://www.oxinst.com/Pages/home.aspx</uri>, last accessed 14 December 2013), with the detector’s processing time set at 2. X-ray data were collected with 4.5 nA probe current for 2min. Each 2–3 pistils were used in one experiment and three individual experimental sets were performed.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Evaluation of reaction level of SI to CO<sub>2</sub> (RLSICO<sub>2</sub>)</title><p>Three to five flowers were cut at the peduncle and stood on a 1% (w/v) solid agar plate. Flowers were self-pollinated, placed into a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator, and treated with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 4h at 23 °C. After 1 d at room temperature, pistils were fixed in ethanol:acetic acid (3:1) overnight, softened in 1 N NaOH at 60 °C for 2h, then stained with 0.01% (w/v) decolorized aniline blue in 2% K<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> for 6h. Pollen tube behaviour was observed under a fluorescent microscope (Axiophot 2, Zeiss). CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity was measured using the RLSICO<sub>2</sub> index. RLSICO<sub>2</sub> was classified into five categories, based on the number of pollen tubes penetrating into the stigma: 1, 0 pollen tubes; 2, 1–5 pollen tubes; 3, 6–15 pollen tubes; 4, 16–30 pollen tubes; and 5, &gt;30 pollen tubes. Three replicates were performed on each plant on different days. Non-CO<sub>2</sub>-treated self-pollinated flowers were used as controls. In all cases, no pollen tubes penetrated into the control stigmas.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> were identified using primers PS5 (5′-ATGAAAGGCGTAAGAAAAACCTA-3′) and PS15 (5′-CCG TGTTTTATTTTAAGAGAAAGAGCT-3′) (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Nishio <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>) to amplify a fragment of the <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> gene. PCR-RFLP (restriction fragment length polymorphism) was used to distinguish the two <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes based on differential digest with the restriction enzyme <italic toggle="yes">Kpn</italic>I (TaKaRa, Japan). Digested DNA was electrophoresed on a 1.5% agarose gel.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Molecular markers and detection of DNA polymorphism</title><p>To screen for markers that show polymorphism between <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> lines, primers specific for simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers from different sources [UK, prefixes Ra, Na, Ol, and ENA (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Lowe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://brassica.bbsrc.ac.uk">http://brassica.bbsrc.ac.uk</uri>); Japan, prefixes BRMS, KBr, and EST (Suwabe et al., <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://vegmarks.nivot.affrc.go.jp">http://vegmarks.nivot.affrc.go.jp</uri>, NIVTS); China, prefix sau_um (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Ge <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>); and Korea, prefix AMCP (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Ramchiary <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>)] were used. SSR, RFLP, and insertion/deletion (InDel) markers (prefixes XT and Bra) were also designed based on the <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> database (BRAD) (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://brassicadb.org/brad/">http://brassicadb.org/brad/</uri>, last accessed 14 December 2013) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online).</p><p content-type="indent">Total genomic DNA was extracted from young leaves of two parental lines and F<sub>2</sub> progeny using the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) method (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Murray and Thompson, 1980</xref>). DNA polymorphism analysis with SSRs was carried out using PCR with fluorescent dyes, performed according to <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Suwabe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> with some modifications. The M13 (–21) universal primer sequence (18bp) was fused to the 5′ end of the original forward primer, and the M13 (–21) universal primer was labelled with 6-FAM, NED, VIC, or PET fluorescent dye (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA). PCRs were performed in a 10 μl reaction volume containing 10ng of template DNA, 4.7 μM of labelled M13 (–21) universal primer and reverse primer, 0.3 μM of forward primer, 1× PCR buffer, 1× dNTP, 1× MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.5U of rTaq (TOYOBO, Japan). Conditions for PCR were as follows: initial denaturation was carried out at 94 °C for 3min followed by 37 cycles at 94 °C for 30 s, 55 °C (slope of 0.5 °C s<sup>–1</sup>) for 30 s, 72 °C (slope of 0.5 °C s<sup>–1</sup>) for 30 s, and a final extension at 72 °C for 4min. A 1 μl aliquot of 50-fold diluted PCR product was added to 8.9 μl of Hi-Di™ Formamide and 0.1 μl of GeneScan™ 600 LIZ™ Size Standard (Applied Biosystems, USA) and applied to an ABI 3730 DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems). Data were analysed using ABI GeneMapper<sup>®</sup> software.</p><p content-type="indent">For polymorphism analysis with RFLP and InDel markers, PCR was carried out in a 10 μl reaction volume with 5 pmol of forward and reverse primers instead of fluorescent dyes. For RFLP markers, amplified fragments were digested using restriction enzymes for 1h. Fragments of digested DNA were separated on a 2–4% agarose gel.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Linkage map construction and QTL analysis</title><p>A genetic map was constructed using JoinMap<sup>®</sup> version 4 (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Van Ooijen, 2006</xref>) utilizing the double pseudo-testcross strategy with a log<sub>10</sub> of odds (LOD) threshold of 6.0 for linkage group identification. The best marker order was calculated with the regression mapping algorithm, and marker order was retained from the first round only. Map distance units in centiMorgans (cM) were converted from recombination frequencies using the Kosambi mapping function (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Kosambi, 1944</xref>). Interval mapping (IM) was performed to identify putative QTLs using the established linkage map and the observed phenotypic traits. This method was run using MapQTL<sup>®</sup> version 6 (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Van Ooijen, 2009</xref>). With this software, a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 LOD score significance threshold was calculated by creating a group-wide distribution of the data based on a 1000 permutation test. LOD peaks were used to estimate the position of QTLs on the map.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Box plots were prepared by Ekuseru-Toukei 2012 software (Social Survey Research Information Co., Ltd, Japan) to compare the phenotypic difference, as this plot type gives a good sense of environmental data distribution (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Upton and Cook, 1996</xref>). Kruskal–Wallis analysis of variance (ANOVA) by ranks was used between paired comparisons of markers to examine marker association.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Results</title><sec id="s11"><title>Phenotypic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> lines in response to CO<sub>2</sub> treatment</title><p>Two inbred lines of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> with different CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity, a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (HA-11621) and a CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (HA-11623), were used in this study. Flowers were self-pollinated by hand pollination and incubated in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator (4.5% CO<sub>2</sub>) for 4h. Both lines were self-incompatible under normal conditions (control) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">B</xref>), whereas they showed significantly different responses to CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">D</xref>). Specifically, in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line, many pollen tubes were seen to penetrate into papilla cells after CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. This pollination test confirmed that the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line had high sensitivity to CO<sub>2</sub> while the CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line hardly responded to 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cross-pollination was performed as a positive control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">F</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Phenotype of inbred <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> lines used in this study. (A, B) Pollen tube behaviour after self-pollination of CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive (HA-11621) and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive (HA-11623) lines under normal conditions (without CO<sub>2</sub> treatment). No penetrated or elongated pollen tubes are observed in either line. (C, D) Pollen tube behaviour after self-pollination of CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines under 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment. Pollen tubes could penetrate into the stigma and elongate through the style only in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line. (E, F) Cross-pollination as a positive control; the arrow shows pollen tubes which have penetrated. Pt, pollen tubes. Bar=1000 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Physiological changes in papilla cells after CO<sub>2</sub> treatment</title><p>Previous work using X-ray microanalysis has revealed the accumulation of calcium at the stigmatic surface following compatible cross-pollination in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica oleracea</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Elleman and Dickinson, 1999</xref>). X-ray mapping strongly indicated that a high concentration of calcium was localized at the points where the pollen grain made contact with the surface of the stigmatic papilla cell. The calcium accumulation was also observed in <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic>, especially in compatible pollination (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Iwano <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). To examine the physiological effect of CO<sub>2</sub> on pollination reactions, this calcium accumulation was examined by using cryo-scanning electron microscopy fitted with an X-ray microanalysis system. When the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line was cross-pollinated with the CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line, pollen grain hydrated and the pollen tube penetrated into the papilla cell, but when CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines were self-pollinated under normal conditions (without CO<sub>2</sub> treatment), few pollen grains hydrated, and no pollen tube germination was observed in either line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>, upper panel). After CO<sub>2</sub> treatment, the cross-pollinated pollen grains did not show a significant difference, neither did the self-pollinated CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line. However, the self-pollinated CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line showed obvious changes: pollen hydration and germination were observed under CO<sub>2</sub> treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>, lower panel). The emission of elements (Kα) in the tip of the papilla cells was then analysed after selecting the pollinated papilla cells which faced nearly the same direction in relation to the X-ray detector. Emissions of P-Kα, S-Kα, K-Kα, and Ca-Kα were detected together with C and O, which are constituent elements of biological materials. The detected emission of Al-Kα originates from the stub that held the samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). There was no significant difference in the elemental emissions between CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines before pollination. Ca<sup>2+</sup> accumulation was observed after cross-pollination as previously reported (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Iwano <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), and Ca-Kα emission was increased with CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. After self-pollination, Ca-Kα emission was slightly increased in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line in the normal CO<sub>2</sub> condition. This Ca-Kα increase became more pronounced (~6-fold) in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line when it was self-pollinated in the high CO<sub>2</sub> condition. In the CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line, no significant Ca-Kα increase was observed after self-pollination in normal or high CO<sub>2</sub> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Although the biological significance of the accumulation of calcium at the pollen–stigma interface is not clear, it has been suggested that calcium plays some role in the successful development of the pollen tube tip into the region of expanded stigmatic wall (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Elleman and Dickinson, 1999</xref>). The present results suggest that, in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line, high CO<sub>2</sub> activates a compatible pollination pathway or disturbs an SI signalling pathway leading to Ca<sup>2+</sup> accumulation at the pollen–stigma interface.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Electron micrographs and X-ray microanalysis of <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic>. (A) Cryo-scanning electron micrographs of pollinated papilla cells were taken 1.5h after pollination. Representative examples of the cross-pollinated (left column) and self-pollinated (middle column) CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line, and the self-pollinated (right column) CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line are shown. Without CO<sub>2</sub> treatment (upper panels), only cross-pollen is accepted, and self-pollen grains maintain a spheroid shape without swelling in both lines. With 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment (lower panels), pollen grains swell and germinate in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (lower middle) but not in the CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (lower right). Bar=25 μm. (B) Representative examples of energy-dispersive X-ray spectra of non-pollinated and pollinated papilla cell surfaces. Scanning positions for X-ray analyses are indicated by asterisks in (A). The emissions of Al-Kα, P-Kα, S-Kα, K-Kα, and Ca-Kα were detected at the papilla cell surfaces, and the intensity of Ca emission was increased after cross-pollination (left column). The increase of Ca emission was also observed after self-pollination with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (middle column) but not in the CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (right column). These spectrum patterns are reproducible in three individual experiment sets. The emission of Al-Kα is mostly derived from the stub that held the samples.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s13"><title>The efficiency of CO<sub>2</sub> treatment</title><p>A previous study suggested that the effect of CO<sub>2</sub> on SI breakdown depends on the timing of treatment (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi and Hinata, 1973</xref>). In the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line, when self-pollinated flowers were immediately treated with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 4h, SI could be overcome, and typically &gt;10 pollen tubes penetrated into the stigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). When CO<sub>2</sub> treatment started 3h after self-pollination, SI could still be overcome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, when CO<sub>2</sub> treatment started 6h after self-pollination, the number of penetrating pollen tubes was decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). These results indicate that self-pollen inhibition in SI is biostatic, as previously suggested (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Sarker <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>), and can be reversed at least at 3h after pollination. However, at 6h after pollination, SI inhibition enters an irreversible phase that cannot be overcome by CO<sub>2</sub> treatment.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>The efficiency of CO<sub>2</sub> treatment of the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line. (A) Self-pollinated stigmas were treated with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> immediately after self-pollination, and pollen tube penetration and elongation were observed. (B) Self-pollinated stigmas were treated with 4.5% CO<sub>2</sub> 3h after self-pollination. The pollen tube can still penetrate into papilla cells. (C) When CO<sub>2</sub> treatment began 6h after self-pollination, the number of penetrating pollen tubes was decreased. Pt, pollen tubes. Bar=1000 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0003.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">Next, in order to narrow down the stage of SI affected by CO<sub>2</sub> treatment, experiments with high CO<sub>2</sub>-pre-treated pollen or pistil from the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line were performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). SI could not be overcome by pre-treatment of either tissue, and no pollen tube penetration could be observed even when both pollen and pistil were treated separately prior to pollination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). SI could be overcome only when the self-pollinated pistil was treated with high CO<sub>2</sub>. These results suggest that some post-pollination physiological process is affected by high CO<sub>2</sub>, in the process of SI breakdown.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Pollination assay using CO<sub>2</sub>-treated non-pollinated flowers of the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line as either CO<sub>2</sub>-treated pistil or pollen. Pollen tube behaviour is observed after a 4h CO<sub>2</sub> treatment immediately after self-pollination. (A) A pistil from a non-pollinated flower treated with CO<sub>2</sub> for 4h was pollinated with pollen from the same plant which was not treated with CO<sub>2</sub>. (B) A pistil from a non-treated non-pollinated flower was pollinated with pollen from the same plant which was treated with CO<sub>2</sub> for 4h. (C) A pistil from a CO<sub>2</sub>-treated non-pollinated flower (CO<sub>2</sub>-treated) was pollinated with pollen from the same plant which was treated with CO<sub>2</sub> for 4h. (D) Self-pollinated flower treated with CO<sub>2</sub> after pollination, positive control. Pt, pollen tubes. Bar=1000 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s14"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-allele characterization and phenotype of CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity in F<sub>1</sub> and F<sub>2</sub>
</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes of the two parental inbred lines were first determined by amplifying their <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> genes (<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Nishio <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). The sequence data suggested that the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes of the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines were <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>, respectively. To dissect genetically the gene(s) that determines sensitivity to CO<sub>2</sub> treatment, six F<sub>1</sub> plants (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>) were produced by crossing CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines. These F<sub>1</sub> plants exhibited an intermediate CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity phenotype where self-pollen tubes penetrated into the stigma under high CO<sub>2</sub> treatment but there were fewer penetrating pollen tubes than observed in a self-pollination of the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive parent. An F<sub>2</sub> population of 110 individuals derived from a bud-pollinated F<sub>1</sub> plant was made and used for further genetic analyses of the CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity. F<sub>2</sub> individuals were genotyped using PCR-RFLP to distinguish <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> alleles (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>- and <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>-haplotypes were segregated in the F<sub>2</sub> population according to Mendelian transmission (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). Pollen tube behaviour after CO<sub>2</sub> treatment varied among individuals and, in order to quantify the strength of CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity, the modified RLSICO<sub>2</sub> (reaction level of SI to CO<sub>2</sub>) index was employed (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">Niikura and Matsuura, 2000</xref>), which calculates CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity based on the number of penetrating pollen tubes after self-pollination under high CO<sub>2</sub> conditions (see the Materials and methods). The RLSICO<sub>2</sub> of 110 F<sub>2</sub> individuals is presented in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>, and the summarized box-plot data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, together with the RLSICO<sub>2</sub> of F<sub>1</sub> and the parental inbred lines. F<sub>1</sub> had an RLSICO<sub>2</sub> score intermediate to the two parental lines, suggesting that the high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is a semi-dominant (incompletely dominant) trait in these inbred lines. Furthermore, the RLSICO<sub>2</sub> of F<sub>2</sub> individuals was continuously distributed and did not follow a simple one-locus biallelic Mendelian distribution (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>). These results suggest that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity in the inbred lines used here could be a quantitative trait which is controlled by more than one gene.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Box plots of CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity phenotypes. Data show the distribution of RLSICO<sub>2</sub> with 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles (horizontal bars), interquartile ranges (columns), and 1.5 interquartile ranges (error bars) of RLSICO<sub>2</sub> from six CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>) and six CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>), individuals, six F<sub>1</sub> individuals (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>), and 110 F<sub>2</sub> individuals (22 <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>, 64 <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>, and 24 <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>). <italic toggle="yes">a</italic> indicates a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) between CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Relationship between <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-alleles and CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity</title><p>To investigate whether CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is related to <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotypes, the 110 F<sub>2</sub> individuals were grouped into three genotypes (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>, and <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>55</sub>). The RLSICO<sub>2</sub> of each group is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>. In the three F<sub>2</sub> groups, RLSICO<sub>2</sub> scores were distributed from 1 to 5, and interquartile ranges overlapped, indicating that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is not linked to the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus in these two lines.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Reproductive tissue controlling CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity</title><p>From the F<sub>2</sub> population, two <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub> homozygotes with different RLSICO<sub>2</sub> were selected: F<sub>2</sub>-16, a CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line (RLSICO<sub>2</sub>=1±0); and F<sub>2</sub>-26, a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line (RLSICO<sub>2</sub>=4.15±0.53). These two lines were used to examine the reproductive tissue controlling CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity. Reciprocal crosses were performed between these two SI lines with or without high CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment. Because all crosses under normal conditions (without CO<sub>2</sub> treatment) were incompatible, only data from crosses performed in the high CO<sub>2</sub> condition are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. The cross between CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive F<sub>2</sub>-26 pistil and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive F<sub>2</sub>-16 pollen was CO<sub>2</sub> sensitive, showing many penetrating pollen tubes under high CO<sub>2</sub>. On the other hand, the cross between CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive F<sub>2</sub>-16 pistil and CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive F<sub>2</sub>-26 pollen was CO<sub>2</sub> insensitive, showing no penetrating pollen tubes even under high CO<sub>2</sub>. These results suggest that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is controlled by genes expressed in the female tissue (pistil).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Reciprocal crosses with CO<sub>2</sub> treatment between two <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub> homozygous individuals from the F<sub>2</sub> population with different RLSICO<sub>2</sub>. (A) CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive F<sub>2</sub> self-pollination. (B) CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive F<sub>2</sub> self-pollination. (C) A CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive F<sub>2</sub> pistil pollinated with pollen from a CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive F<sub>2</sub>. (D) A CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive F<sub>2</sub> pistil pollinated with pollen from a CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive F<sub>2</sub>. Pt, pollen tubes. Bar=1000 μm. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=3.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Marker analysis and construction of a linkage map</title><p>In order to map QTLs that determine CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity, a linkage map was constructed for this F<sub>2</sub> population. A total of 911 different genetic markers were examined in the two parental lines. To clarify the relationship between previously identified SI-related genes and CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity, <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> (an <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus marker), <italic toggle="yes">MLPK</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ARC1</italic> were also selected. Though a very low level of polymorphism (14.7%) was detected for all types of markers, 123 polymorphic markers were selected, which include 113 SSRs, five RFLPs, and five InDel markers. These 123 markers were used for linkage mapping, and generated 10 linkage groups (A01–A10) at a LOD threshold value of 6.0 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). The total length of the map was 947.5 cM, and the length of the linkage groups ranged from 63.2 cM (A10) to 168.4 cM (A03). The distance between markers varied from 0 to 29.3 cM, with an average interval of 7.7 cM. <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MLPK</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ARC1</italic> were mapped to A07, A03, and A04, respectively, which is consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Ajisaka <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Hatakeyama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>A linkage map of selected DNA markers from the F<sub>2</sub> population. Map distances are shown to the left of vertical lines of the linkage group in cM, and marker names are shown to the right.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s18"><title>QTL analysis and association of markers with high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity</title><p>Using the constructed linkage map, QTLs responsible for high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity were analysed. Three QTLs were identified on linkage groups A03 and A05 based on a LOD threshold of 3.40 (1000 permutation test, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These QTLs were tentatively named <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa SI Overcome (BrSIO) 1–3</italic>, and these results further supported the prediction that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity of SI is controlled by a polygenic system. <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> on A05 and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> on A03 are two major QTLs that explained 19.3% and 19.0% of phenotypic variation, respectively. <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO3</italic>, located near <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>, accounted for 14.5% of the variance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity QTLs</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closest marker</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL peak (cM)<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOD</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sup>2<italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additive effect<sup><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">XT05-004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRMS-042-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">BrSIO3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">KBrH110I17R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup> QTL peak position, detected by interval mapping, between two markers.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sup> Amount of phenotypic variation explained by the QTL.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup> Additive effect of the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive HA-11621 allele on RLSICO<sub>2</sub>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>QTL analysis results. The solid line indicates the LOD score and the dotted line indicates the QTL threshold (LOD=3.4) determined using a 1000 permutation test (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis represents each linkage group (cM) and the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis indicates the QTL score. Two QTLs (<italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">3</italic>) are detected in A03 and one in A05 (<italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>). Arrows show loci involved in SI stability reported by <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Hatakeyama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_f0008.jpg"/></fig><p content-type="indent">To examine the significance of these QTLs, F<sub>2</sub> progeny were classified into groups based on the genotypes of the linkage markers nearest these three newly identified loci, and the relationship of the loci to RLSICO<sub>2</sub> in individual plants was analysed using Kruskal–Wallis ANOVA by ranks (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Alleles from CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive (HA-11621) and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive (HA-11623) lines are presented as <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, respectively. Almost all classifications using the closest linkage markers showed a higher RLSICO<sub>2</sub> index in the <italic toggle="yes">SS</italic> group with significance at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, except marker BRMS-114, which showed significance at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Statistical analysis of QTL effect</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_t0002.jpg"/><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>, CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive HA-11621 allele; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive HA-11623 allele.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sup> Individuals whose genotype was unidentified are excluded.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup> Kruskal–Wallis analysis comparing phenotype between genotype groups with individuals in the same groups.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">d</italic></sup> Significance level: **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;0.01; *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p content-type="indent">Marker association was further examined with combinations of <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> since <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO3</italic> is a minor QTL closely linked to <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>, making it difficult to identify it as an independent QTL. F<sub>2</sub> progeny were classified into nine groups based on the genotypes of their closest linkage markers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). According to this classification, for example, the two above analysed <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>
<sub>46</sub> homozygous lines with different RLSICO<sub>2</sub>, F<sub>2</sub>-16 (CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive line) and F<sub>2</sub>-26 (CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line), were classified into group 8 and group 1, respectively. When groups with the same <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> genotype were compared, the <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2 SS</italic> group showed a higher RLSICO<sub>2</sub> index compared with the <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2 II</italic> group. Likewise, when the groups with the same <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> genotype were compared, the <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1 SS</italic> group showed a higher RLSICO<sub>2</sub> compared with the <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1 II</italic> group. Although the numbers of F<sub>2</sub> individuals in each group were rather low, significance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) was detected between groups 1 and 6, 2 and 6, and 2 and 8. These data suggest that <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> work additively in overcoming SI during CO<sub>2</sub> treatment in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive (HA-11621) line. No QTL was detected at genes known to affect SI stability (<italic toggle="yes">MLPK</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ARC1</italic>, or the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus), indicating that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is determined by novel genes in the experimental lines used here.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>QTL association for CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="exbotj_ert438_t0003.jpg"/><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup>
<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>, CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive HA-11621 allele; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive HA-11623 allele.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sup> Individuals whose genotype was unidentified are excluded.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup> Significance level, *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Associated gene prediction by <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> comparative mapping</title><p>Using the <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> genome sequence (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Cheng <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> could be mapped to a 569kb region flanked by InDel marker XT05-004 and SSR marker BRMS-034, and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> to a 1469kb region flanked by SSR markers BRMS-042-2 and KBrH110I17R. These two regions include 121 and 280 genes annotated in the <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> database (BRAD), respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Tables S3</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">S4</ext-link> at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online). Comparison of the <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic> genome with the Brassicaceae genome (reviewed by <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Schranz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) suggests that <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> has synteny on <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic> chromosome 2 and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> has synteny on both chromosomes 3 and 4. It is assumed that these two QTLs do not have the same genetic origin and could be two independent regions controlling high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity. Based on reciprocal cross results, the CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity trait may be controlled by genes expressed in the female organ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). A total of 121 and 280 annotated genes in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> have 103 and 243 homologues in <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic>, respectively, and 54 and 141 of these genes are expressed in <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic> pistil (microarray data of carpel at stage 12, <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://affymetrix.arabidopsis.info/narrays/search.pl?f1=1&amp;s1=ATGE_37">http://affymetrix.arabidopsis.info/narrays/search.pl?f1=1&amp;s1=ATGE_37</uri>, last accessed 14 December 2013, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Supplementary Tables S3</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">S4</ext-link>).</p><p content-type="indent">Genes involved in related biological processes are often expressed cooperatively and their co-expression information is important for understanding biological systems (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Eisen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). ATTED-II (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://atted.jp/">http://atted.jp/</uri>, last accessed 14 December 2013) is a gene co-expression database useful for identifying the potential partners working in the same biological processes (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Obayashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Co-expression analysis was performed using ATTED-II with these 195 genes and it was found that <italic toggle="yes">MAP kinase 6</italic> (At2g43790 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">ethylene overproducer 1</italic> (At3g511770 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>) showed the strongest co-expression and <italic toggle="yes">calmodulin-like 41</italic> (At3g50770 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>) has weak co-expression with <italic toggle="yes">cytochrome c oxidase 10</italic> (At2g44520in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">beta glucosidase 28</italic> (At2g44460 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>). In addition to these co-expressed genes, these two regions encode highly homologous family member proteins, for example matrixin proteins (At2g45040 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and At4g16640 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>) and senescence-associated proteins (At2g44670 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and At4g17670 in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>). All these can be candidate responsible genes, although the biological functions of these genes are mostly unknown.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Discussion</title><p>It has been &gt;40 years since <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1969)</xref> first reported that SI could be overcome by CO<sub>2</sub> and <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Nakanishi and Hinata (1973)</xref> demonstrated the applicability of this technique to commercial use. Nowadays, seed companies have adopted this method to obtain inbred parental seeds of crucifer vegetables for large-scale commercial F<sub>1</sub> hybrid seed production. However, there is still very limited understanding of the mechanism by which SI is overcome.</p><p content-type="indent">
<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2001)</xref> showed a shrunken and distorted papilla cell surface in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> cv. Hiratsuka, and suggested that these structural changes could cause SI to be overcome. The cryo-scanning electron microscopy data reported here did not show any structural changes in CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive or CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Additionally, pre-treatment of non-pollinated pistils with high CO<sub>2</sub> gas did not cause SI breakdown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Therefore, a completely different SI breakdown mechanism must be present, at least in the CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive line. In contrast, massive Ca accumulation was observed at the pollen–stigma interface specifically in CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive plants under high CO<sub>2</sub> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Brewbaker and Kwack (1963)</xref> were the first to describe the need for a high concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> for pollen germination and pollen tube growth. The high concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> could be needed for activating pectinase to loosen the papilla cell wall, allowing the pollen tube to penetrate (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Black and Charlwood, 1995</xref>), or for keeping the pollen tube cell wall rigid enough not to burst (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Hepler and Winship, 2010</xref>). Although causal relationships remain unclear, the data suggest that CO<sub>2</sub> treatment induces a certain compatible reaction leading to Ca<sup>2+</sup> accumulation at the pollen–stigma interface.</p><p content-type="indent">To date, several genetic studies have been performed to understand the mechanism of SI breakdown for breeding purposes. Niikura and Matsuura (2002) reported that in Japanese radish high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is controlled by a recessive gene that governs the construction and/or metabolism of the stigma, which reacts to CO<sub>2</sub> without any changes in gene expression. In contrast, <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Hyun <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> reported a dominant, <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotype-linked high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic>. In contrast to these previous reports, F<sub>1</sub> plants had an intermediate CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity and the F<sub>2</sub> population had a continuous frequency distribution of RLSICO<sub>2</sub> in the present study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). These results suggest that in the lines used for this study, CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity is a quantitative trait which is controlled by more than one gene.</p><p content-type="indent">Genetic linkage maps based upon frequency of recombination in segregating populations are fundamental and powerful tools for associating phenotypic trait-specific genetic regions. Linkage mapping can be used to understand the biological basis of complex traits and to dissect genetic determinants underlying the expression of agronomically important breeding traits (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Paran and Zamir, 2003</xref>). Using QTL analysis, two major QTLs for high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity were successfully identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> had similar LOD scores and explained similar amounts of phenotypic variation (19.3% and 19%), and these could be two major factors controlling high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity. Very recently, five QTLs associated with stability of SI in <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> have been identified. Two of them co-localized with <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic> (A07) and <italic toggle="yes">MLPK</italic> (A03) and the other three were on A02, A06, and A10 (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Hatakeyama <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity did not link with the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus in the present study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) and none of the other reported loci co-localized with QTLs detected here (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>), indicating that CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity of the lines in this study is determined by novel genes different from those known to affect SI stability. Genes in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic> regions have 103 and 243 homologues in <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic>, respectively, and 54 and 141 of these genes are expressed in <italic toggle="yes">A. thaliana</italic> pistil. <italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> comparative analyses identified several co-expressing genes and highly homologous genes encoded in these two regions. All these can be candidate responsible genes; however, to dentify the genes responsible for high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity in the QTL regions in <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa</italic> more accurately, it would be necessary to narrow down the regions by developing near-isogenic lines (NILs).</p><p content-type="indent">To maintain F<sub>1</sub> seed quality, inbred lines with strong but CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive SI are ideal for F<sub>1</sub> hybrid breeding, and it is very important to understand the genetic relationships between SI-related genes and CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity phenotypes. These results could be useful for the marker-assisted selection of parental lines with both stable SI and high CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s21"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic toggle="yes">JXB</italic> online.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Figure S1</ext-link>. <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotype analysis of F<sub>2</sub> plants by PCR-RFLP.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Figure S2</ext-link>. RLSICO<sub>2</sub> in CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitive and CO<sub>2</sub>-insensitive lines, and F<sub>1</sub> and F<sub>2</sub> progeny based on the number of penetrating pollen tubes after self-pollination under high CO<sub>2</sub> conditions.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>. Genetic markers and their primers used for linkage analysis.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Table S2</ext-link>. <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-haplotype segregation in the F<sub>2</sub> population.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Table S3</ext-link>. Annotated genes and <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> homologues in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO1</italic>.</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/ert438/-/DC1">Table S4</ext-link>. Annotated genes and <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> homologues in <italic toggle="yes">BrSIO2</italic>.</p><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_65_4_939__index.html" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_ert438_jexbot106187_file001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Ms Rina Nagai, Ms Hitomi Ishikawa, and Ms Yuko Yoshimura for their excellent technical assistance. This work was supported by a Grant-in-Aid for the Scientific Research on Innovative Areas (<award-id>21112003</award-id>, <award-id>23113002</award-id>) and by Grants in Aid for Scientific Research (<award-id>23570056</award-id>, <award-id>21248014</award-id>, <award-id>25252021</award-id>) from the <funding-source>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan</funding-source> (MEXT) and by the Japan Advanced Plant Science Network.</p></ack><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>InDel</term><def><p>insertion/deletion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LG</term><def><p>linkage group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LOD</term><def><p>log of odds</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QTL</term><def><p>quantitative trait locus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RFLP</term><def><p>restriction fragment length polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RLSICO<sub>2</sub></term><def><p>reaction level of SI to CO<sub>2</sub>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SI</term><def><p>self-incompatibility</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SSR</term><def><p>simple sequence repeat.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajisaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuginuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Identification and mapping of a quantitative trait locus controlling extreme late bolting in Chinese cabbage (<italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> L. ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pekinensis</italic> syn. <italic toggle="yes">campestris</italic> L.) using bulked segregant analysis: a QTL controlling extreme late bolting in Chinese cabbage</article-title>.
<source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>118</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>
<article-title>Self-incompatibility systems in angiosperms. III. Cruciferae</article-title>.
<source>Heredity</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlwood</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<source>The physiology and biochemistry of plant cell walls</source>.
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewbaker</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwack</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1963</year>
<article-title>The essential role of calcium ion in pollen germination and pollen tube growth</article-title>.
<source>American Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>859</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chantha</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platts</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoen</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Secondary evolution of a self-incompatibility locus in the Brassicaceae genus Leavenworthia</article-title>.
<source>PLoS Biology</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e1001560</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23690750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3653793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>BRAD, the genetics and genomics database for <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> plants</article-title>.
<source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21995777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2229-11-136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3213011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Cluster analysis and display of genome-wide expression patterns</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>14863</fpage>–<lpage>14868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.95.25.14863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC24541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elleman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Commonalities between pollen/stigma and host/pathogen interactions: calcium accumulation during stigmatic penetration by <italic toggle="yes">Brassica oleracea</italic> pollen tubes</article-title>.
<source>Sexual Plant Reproduction</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramchiary</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Development and linkage mapping of unigene-derived microsatellite markers in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> L</article-title>.
<source>Breeding Science</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzurco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulaman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matias</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Binding of an arm repeat protein to the kinase domain of the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus receptor kinase</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.95.1.382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC18231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9419384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horisaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshiaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Mapping of quantitative trait loci for high level of self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> L</article-title>.
<source>Genome</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1139/g10-001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winship</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Calcium at the cell wall–cytoplast interface</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20377677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2010.00923.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horisaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Developmental and environmental factors affecting level of self-incompatibility response in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> L</article-title>.
<source>Sexual Plant Reproduction</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gothandam</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Dominance relationship between two self-incompatible <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic> haplotypes in response to CO<sub>2</sub> gas</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Plant Biology</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Indriolo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tharmapalan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">ARC1</italic> E3 ligase gene is frequenctly deleted in self-compatible Brassicaceae species and has a conserved role in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> self-pollen rejection</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>4607</fpage>–<lpage>4620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23204404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.112.104943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3531855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isoga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>X-ray microanalysis of papillar cells and pollen grains in the pollination process in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> using a variable-pressure scanning electron microscope</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Electron Microscopy</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>909</fpage>–<lpage>917</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Two distinct forms of <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>-locus protein kinase localize to the plasma membrane and interact directly with <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-locus receptor kinase to transduce self-incompatibility signalling in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3961</fpage>–<lpage>3973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.106.049999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2217645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitashiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Functional test of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> self-incompatibility modifiers in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>16173</fpage>–<lpage>16178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1115283108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3207705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosambi</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1944</year>
<article-title>The estimation of map distance from recombination values</article-title>.
<source>Annals of Eugenics</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Controlling self-incompatibility by CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic>: structural alteration of papillae cell and differential gene expression by increased CO<sub>2</sub> gas</article-title>.
<source>Molecules and Cells</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11355699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moule</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Efficient large-scale development of microsatellites for marker and mapping applications in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> crop species</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>1103</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00122-003-1522-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Overcoming self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Raphanus sativus</italic> L. with high temperature</article-title>.
<source>Journal of the American Society for Horticultural Science</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>842</fpage>–<lpage>846</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monterio</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabelman</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Use of sodium chloride solution to overcome self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>HortScience</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>876</fpage>–<lpage>877</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A membrane-anchored protein kinase involved in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> self-incompatibility signaling</article-title>.
<source>Science</source>
<volume>303</volume>, <fpage>1516</fpage>–<lpage>1519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15001779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1093586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Rapid isolation of high molecular weight DNA</article-title>.
<source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>4321</fpage>–<lpage>4325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7433111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/8.19.4321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC324241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1969</year>
<article-title>Control of self-incompatibility by CO<sub>2</sub> gas in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>925</fpage>–<lpage>927</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1973</year>
<article-title>An effective time for CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment in overcoming self- incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Amino acid sequence of glycoproteins encoded by three alleles of the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> locus of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica oleracea</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>326</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of the reaction level of self-incompatibility to a 4% CO<sub>2</sub> gas treatment in the radish (<italic toggle="yes">Raphanus sativus</italic> L.)</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1193</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusaba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Registration of S alleles in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic> L. by the restriction fragment sizes of <italic toggle="yes">SLG</italic>s</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24166262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00223684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibaoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>ATTED-II: a database of co-expressed genes and <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> elements for identifying co-regulated gene groups in <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>D863</fpage>–<lpage>D869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17130150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkl783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1716726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ockendon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Effects of hexan and humidity on self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica oleracea</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24317456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00264743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Repressing the expression of self-incompatibility in crucifers by short-term high temperature treatment</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24241104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00289185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Quantitative traits in plants: beyond the QTL</article-title>.
<source>Trends in Genetics</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12801720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0168-9525(03)00117-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramchiary</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhandapani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genic microsatellite markers in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic>: development, characterization, mapping, and their utility in other cultivated and wild <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> relatives</article-title>.
<source>DNA Research</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/dnares/dsr017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3190952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haasen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldea-Brydges</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Cellular pathways regulating responses to compatible and self-incompatible pollen in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis</italic> stigmas intersect at Exo70A1, a putative component of the exocyst complex</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2655</fpage>–<lpage>2671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19789280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.109.069740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2768929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarker</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elleman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Control of pollen hydration in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> requires continued protein synthesis, and glycosylation is necessary for intraspecific incompatibility</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>4340</fpage>–<lpage>4344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.85.12.4340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC280424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16593944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schopfer</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrallah</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The male determinant of self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Science</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>1405</fpage>–<lpage>1412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.286.5445.1697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10576728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schranz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lysak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell-Olds</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The ABC’s of comparative genomics in the Brassicaceae: building blocks of crucifer genomes</article-title>.
<source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17029932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tplants.2006.09.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulaman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazarian</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnoldo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Expression of the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> receptor kinase in self-compatible <italic toggle="yes">Brassica napus</italic> cv. Wester leads to the allele-specific rejection of self-incompatible <italic toggle="yes">Brassica napus</italic> pollen</article-title>.
<source>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</source>
<volume>265</volume>, <fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11405639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s004380100446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>ARC1 is an E3 ubiquitin ligase and promotes the ubiquitination of proteins during the rejection of self-incompatible <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> pollen</article-title>.
<source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1105/tpc.009845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC152337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnoldo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>A break down of <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> self-incompatibility in ARC1 antisense transgenic plants</article-title>.
<source>Science</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>1729</fpage>–<lpage>1731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10576738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.286.5445.1729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunome</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of microsatellites in Brassica rapa L</article-title>.
<source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>1092</fpage>–<lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00122-002-0875-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunome</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Characteristics of microsatellites in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> genome and their potential. utilization for comparative genomics in Cruciferae</article-title>.
<source>Breeding Science</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Integration of Brassica A genome genetic linkage map between <italic toggle="yes">Brassica napus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. rapa.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Genome</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1139/G07-113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsukazaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunome</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Simple sequence repeat-based comparative genomics between <italic toggle="yes">Brassica rapa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: the genetic origin of clubroot resistance</article-title>.
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>173</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1534/genetics.104.038968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1461432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> receptor kinase determines self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> stigma</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>403</volume>, <fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35002628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsunemoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Sequences of <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>-glycoproteins, products of the <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic> self-incompatibility locus</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>326</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimosato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The pollen determinant of self-incompatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Brassica campestris</italic>
</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1920</fpage>–<lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.040556397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC26537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimosato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Funato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isogai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Direct ligand–receptor complex interaction controls <italic toggle="yes">Brassica</italic> self-incompatibility</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>413</volume>, <fpage>534</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11586363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35097104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatebe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1968</year>
<article-title>Studies on the physiological mechanism of self-incompatibility in Japanese radish. II. Breakdown of self-incompatibility by chemical treatments</article-title>.
<source>Journal of the Japanese Society for Horitulcultural Science</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Use of CO<sub>2</sub> and salt solution to overcome self-incompatibility of Chinese cabbage (<italic toggle="yes">B. campestris</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pekinensis</italic>
</article-title>). <source>Eucarpia Cruciferae Newsletter</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Upton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<source>Understanding statistics</source>.
<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year> JoinMap<sup>®</sup> 4, software for the calculation of genetic linkage maps in experimental populations. Wageningen, The Netherlands: Kyazma BV.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year> MapQTL<sup>®</sup> 4, software for the mapping of quantitative trait loci in experimental populations of diploid species. Wageningen, The Netherlands: Kyazma BV.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>