
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3536069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3536069.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3536069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3536069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23308089</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-26632</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Data Management</subject><subject>Regulatory Networks</subject><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nucleic acids</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA synthesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Bioengineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Systems Engineering</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Industrial Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Process Engineering</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems Engineering</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conceptual Model-Based Systems Biology: Mapping Knowledge and
Discovering Gaps in the mRNA Transcription Cycle</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Conceptual Model-Based Systems
Biology</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Somekh</surname><given-names initials="J">Judith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choder</surname><given-names initials="M">Mordechai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dori</surname><given-names initials="D">Dov</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Industrial Engineering and
Management, Technion, Israel Institute of Technology, Haifa,
Israel</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Engineering Systems Division, Massachusetts
Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States of
America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Medicine, Technion, Israel
Institute of Technology, Haifa, Israel</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names initials="T">Thomas</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>The John Curtin School of Medical Research,
Australia</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>yuditol@technion.ac.il</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JS. Performed the experiments: JS.
Analyzed the data: JS MC DD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools:
JS DD MC. Wrote the paper: JS DD MC.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">216913</issue-id><elocation-id>e51430</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2020-12-16 11:16:22.320"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Somekh et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Somekh et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0051430.pdf"/><abstract><p>We propose a Conceptual Model-based Systems Biology framework for qualitative
modeling, executing, and eliciting knowledge gaps in molecular biology systems.
The framework is an adaptation of Object-Process Methodology (OPM), a graphical
and textual executable modeling language. OPM enables concurrent representation
of the system's structure—the objects that comprise the system, and
behavior—how processes transform objects over time. Applying a top-down
approach of recursively zooming into processes, we model a case in
point—the mRNA transcription cycle. Starting with this high level cell
function, we model increasingly detailed processes along with participating
objects. Our modeling approach is capable of modeling molecular processes such
as complex formation, localization and trafficking, molecular binding, enzymatic
stimulation, and environmental intervention. At the lowest level, similar to the
Gene Ontology, all biological processes boil down to three basic molecular
functions: catalysis, binding/dissociation, and transporting. During modeling
and execution of the mRNA transcription model, we discovered knowledge gaps,
which we present and classify into various types. We also show how model
execution enhances a coherent model construction. Identification and pinpointing
knowledge gaps is an important feature of the framework, as it suggests where
research should focus and whether conjectures about uncertain mechanisms fit
into the already verified model.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded in part by a grant agreement No. 38221 for
Promoting Women in Science by the Israeli Ministry of Science to JS. The
research leading to these results has received funding from the European
Union's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement
No. 262044 – VISIONAIR and from Gordon Center for Systems Engineering at
the Technion. This work was partially supported by a grant from Israel Science
Foundation to MC. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and
analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>A myriad of detailed pieces of knowledge regarding the structure and function of the
living cell have been accumulating at an ever increasing rate while emphasis in
biological research has shifted from probing into a single molecular function to
studying complete cellular pathways, cycles and the entire cell as a system. For
example, recent knowledge links the gene expression system stages (mRNA
transcription, translation, and decay) by a single multi-functional heterodimer,
named Rpb4/7, which we previously proposed to coordinate all stages into a system
<xref rid="pone.0051430-HarelSharvit1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>.
Thus, in order to better understand the expression of protein-encoding genes, we
need to consider the entire multi-stage process, as each stage can be regarded as a
subdivision of a continuous cyclical gene expression process. This realization calls
for adopting a holistic, integrative, Conceptual Model-based Systems Biology that
would enable making mechanistic system-level sense of the countless pieces of
information that have been gathered thanks to decades of meticulous laboratory
research by many thousands of scientists. A highly expressive conceptual modeling
approach is needed not only for supporting researchers in integrating the knowledge,
but also in gradually fleshing it out to see the “big picture”—the
holistic view of a unified system.</p><p>In this paper we propose a framework for concurrently modeling structural and
behavioral aspects of molecular biology systems and address the challenges of a
coherent mechanistic model construction, its execution, and related knowledge gaps
discovery and elicitation.</p><p>Molecular biology models that represent complex systems or subsystems may become very
large, as they include many objects—proteins and other molecules and
biocomplexes, and hierarchically organized processes. Constructing a biological
mechanistic model can be compared to an attempt at assembling a huge jigsaw puzzle
from an enormous number of parts—the known facts, many of which are not in a
specific context, making the full picture incomplete or inconsistent. Conceptual
approaches supporting a consistent unification of the qualitative facts regarding
the mechanisms underlying the biological system are needed. These approaches must be
expressive enough to address the various aspects of molecular biology systems.
Moreover, the mounting facts constitute an impediment that renders purely manual
model construction very tedious, time-consuming, and virtually impractical. Thus,
automated construction of a large-scale mechanistic model from published research
papers text using natural language processing technologies seems to be a viable
option. However, the starting point for the automated model construction must be a
kernel of the system under investigation that was manually-constructed, executed,
and verified by a team of human experts that comprises system biologists and
modeling experts.</p><p>As an underlying approach for conceptual modeling, the proposed framework adopts
Object-Process Methodology (OPM), a holistic and graphical modeling language and
methodology. Using a minimal set of generic, universal concepts—stateful
objects and processes that transform them—OPM enables the representation of a
rich set of abstractions of biological structures and behaviors. These abstractions
provide for a consistent representation of knowledge about the functional, static,
and dynamic aspects of biological systems at a spectrum of interconnected levels of
abstraction, from molecules through organelles to the entire cell and its
environment. A unique important feature of OPM models is that they are automatically
translated on the fly into Object-Process Language (OPL), a set of natural English
sentences in predefined templates that reflect all the details in the graphical
model.</p><p>We take advantage of the relative simplicity of OPM and the fact that OPM models can
be executed for analyzing complex biological system, understanding them, identifying
model inconsistencies and knowledge gaps and classifying them, as the mRNA
transcription case study presented in this paper clearly demonstrates. We also
present the adaptations and modeling templates of OPM for molecular biology systems
and demonstrate their utilization on the transcription case study.</p><sec id="s1a"><title>1. Related Work</title><p>Specification and modeling of the dynamics biological systems, such as metabolic
pathways, cell transduction, and regulatory networks, is currently carried out
using a variety of methods <xref rid="pone.0051430-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Machado1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. These modeling approaches can be roughly divided into
(1) quantitative, mathematical equation-based approaches, such as Ordinary
Differential Equations (ODEs) that describe the continuous variations in the
concentration of substances and used in various environments <xref rid="pone.0051430-Takahashi1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Moraru1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> or discrete
stochastic approaches such as Gillespie's stochastic simulation algorithm
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Gillespie1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and
(2) executable-qualitative approaches. Executable-qualitative approaches are
used when data about quantities (e.g., concentrations) is missing, where
equation-based approaches cannot be used. As our focus in this work is
qualitative dynamic modeling aspects of biological systems, we briefly overview
pertinent approaches, present their advantage and disadvantage, and compare
their advantages and disadvantages to those of our proposed OPM approach.</p><p>Executable approaches for modeling biological systems use formal computational
descriptions or algorithms to describe and understand natural phenomena <xref rid="pone.0051430-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.
<bold>Boolean Networks</bold>
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Shmulevich1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> are graphs that
include nodes and arcs between them, which describe gene regulatory and
metabolic networks, focusing on cause and effect relationships among molecules
or genes. In spite of their success in understanding concepts underlying
biological systems, such as analyzing system robustness and steady states <xref rid="pone.0051430-Shmulevich1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, these network
models are limited to Boolean effects of genes. They specify neither hierarchies
nor details of the relevant molecules and processes involved in the system. OPM,
on the other hand, has inherent, built in mechanisms for modeling both process
and object hierarchies and present them at various levels of detail.</p><p>The most comprehensive works have used <bold>Petri Nets</bold> for modeling
concurrent biochemical pathways <xref rid="pone.0051430-Chaouiya1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Reddy1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kielbassa1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Peleg1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. This established
mathematical and graphical technique abstracts systems dynamic by tokens moving
in a graph composed of arcs and nodes. The execution semantics of OPM resembles
the concurrent execution semantics of the Petri-nets approach. Focusing on
processes, Petri Nets do not easily lend themselves to modeling structural
aspects such as molecules and their states, complexes, and molecular
hierarchies. The <bold>System Biology Graphical Notation</bold> (SBGN) project
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Jansson1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-LeNovre1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
aimed at standardizing a graphical representation of the biological model
includes three types of graphical diagrams: process diagrams, entity
relationship diagram, and activity flow diagram, inspired by Petri Nets. Each
diagram type has distinct semantics for representing a biological system and
provides a partial view of the overall system, making it quite difficult to
mentally combine the diagrams into one holistic representation. Conversely, in
OPM, the structure, behavior, and function of the modeled system are specified
concurrently in a single holistic diagram type at various detail levels,
preventing clutter and inconsistencies that may arise from using separated views
for the various system aspects.</p><p>
<bold>Statecharts</bold> is a formal graphical approach based on state
transitions that defines the behavior of reactive objects over time.
Statecharts-based models at the cell level and upwards were developed to
describe the various stages in the life span of various cell types <xref rid="pone.0051430-Efroni1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Harel1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Vulval cell
fate determination in <italic toggle="yes">C. Elegans</italic> was modeled using Statecharts,
expressing the mechanistic model, along with a scenario-based visual language
called <bold>Live Sequence Charts</bold> (LSC), for modeling the experimental
knowledge <xref rid="pone.0051430-Fisher2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kam1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Sadot1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In Statecharts, a molecule may be represented by a
state machine showing its possible states and event-driven transitions among
them. OPM resembles the Statechart approach by being a qualitative executable
approach, and lacks the ability to incorporate quantitative mathematical
equations, that includes continuous or stochastic data. However, being
state-oriented rather than process-oriented, as OPM is, reasoning about complex
processes, in which many types of molecules take part at various refinement
levels, is not straightforward. Molecular transient structures, such as complex
formation, which are easily modeled with OPM, are not straightforward to model
in Statecharts either. While Statechart model execution is driven by (optionally
conditioned) state changes in response to asynchronous events, the OPM mix
serial and concurrent scenario execution. In OPM, each process can have
conditions that limit its execution. To model quantitative behavior, in both
methods, multiple instances for each biological object can be added and the
system behavior can be then executed and analyzed <xref rid="pone.0051430-Efroni1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p>
<bold>Process Algebras</bold> are formal languages for specifying systems with
discrete events. For example, Regev et al. <xref rid="pone.0051430-Regev1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> proposed to represent
biochemical signaling pathways through the use of process algebra language, the
π-calculus, originally developed to model networks of communicating
processes. Using this approach, communication was mapped to molecular binding
processes, and channels were mapped to the binding domains of these
biomolecules. These languages are concurrent and compositional, but being
text-based only, they are less intuitive than graphical or bi-modal
representations, such as the bi-modal graphics-and text model representation of
OPM. In <bold>Agent-based</bold> approaches, computational entities called
agents execute their tasks autonomously and concurrently. A biological system is
modeled as a set of agents in a dynamic and often unpredictable environment that
interact through the creation or modification of signals on a shared data
structure, known as a “blackboard” <xref rid="pone.0051430-Cannata1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Applying an
Object-Oriented (OO) Unified Modeling Language (UML)-based and agent-based
approach, Webb and White <xref rid="pone.0051430-Webb1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> modeled and simulated metabolic and genetic pathways,
using Statecharts and message exchange. Due to limitations of the OO paradigm
that stem from its origins in the software domain, this model includes such
non-biological artifacts as capsules, ports, and connectors that exchange
messages, making it less than intuitive.</p><p>It is worth mentioning the <bold>Rule-based</bold> approach <xref rid="pone.0051430-Faeder1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Calzone1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> which is another method
for dealing with incomplete quantitative data. The approach has the ability to
represent rich variety of biological knowledge regarding structure, behavior and
experimental external conditions. The formalisms consists a set of facts and a
set of rules (with condition and action parts), stored in a knowledge base.
Rule-based simulation, iteratively matches the facts in the knowledge base
against the condition parts of the rules, and executes the matched action parts.
Facts can express a rich variety of knowledge about the objects of the
biological system, which can represent molecule, biological process or
environmental conditions. The objects are usually hierarchically structured and
are described by their attributes. BIOCHAM <xref rid="pone.0051430-Calzone1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> implements a rule-based
approach for model specification which is complemented with a temporal logic
language for the verification of the properties of the biological models.
Although the advantage of the rule-based approach to represent rich variety of
qualitative and quantitative knowledge, it is a text-based approach which makes
it less than intuitive for humans. OPM can also specify a rich variety of
biological knowledge, such as biological objects, their attributes, their
states, biological processes, process and object hierarchies and environmental
conditions (as we demonstrate in the sequel), but unlike rule based approaches,
which are textual, OPM is graphical.</p><p>With respect to the Semantic Web and its capabilities, the Visual Semantic Web
(ViSWeb) is a paradigm for enhancing the current Semantic Web technology <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> that is based
on OPM. ViSWeb enables modeling of systems in a single graphic and textual
model, providing for representation of knowledge over the Web in a unified way
that caters to human perceptions while also being machine processable. The
advantages of the ViSWeb approach include equivalent graphic-text knowledge
representation, visual navigability, semantic sentence interpretation,
specification of system dynamics, and complexity management. Arguing against the
claim that humans and machines need to look at different knowledge
representation formats, the principles and basics of various graphic and textual
knowledge representations are presented and examined as candidates for ViSWeb
foundation. Since OPM is shown to be most adequate for the task, ViSWeb is
developed as an OPM-based layer on top of XML/RDF/OWL to express knowledge
visually and in natural language. Both the graphic and the textual
representations are strictly equivalent. Being intuitive yet formal, they are
not only understandable to humans but are also amenable to computer processing.
The ability to use such bimodal knowledge representation is potentially a major
step forward in the evolution of the Semantic Web.</p><p>Although the methods briefly surveyed above are appropriate for computational
analysis of various aspects of the system under study, most of them abstract
only part of the information regarding the biological system such as
hierarchical structures, variable states, system events and behavioral details
of the molecular biology system. As we show next, OPM has an advantage of being
able to holistically integrate most of the biological information types and
concurrently model and execute models of complex molecular biology systems. We
note upfront that in its current form, OPM is a qualitative executable approach,
and it lacks the ability to incorporate continuous or stochastic data into its
models. We discuss this aspect in more detail in the sequel.</p></sec><sec id="s1b"><title>2. Object-Process Methodology</title><p>Object-Process Methodology <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> is a holistic graphical approach to the
representation and development of complex systems while maintaining a formal
framework. OPM was originally aimed for use by systems engineers for knowledge
management and representation of multidisciplinary man-made socio-technical
industrial and information systems <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. OPM is founded upon two
elementary building blocks. These are stateful objects - things that exist, such
as molecules, which represent the system's structure, and processes -
things that happen to objects and transform them. Processes transform the
system's objects by creating them, consuming them, or changing their
states. Two semantically equivalent modalities, one graphic and the other
textual, are used to describe each OPM model. The graphical model is
automatically translated into a textual model. The textual representation which
is built as a subset of English can ease the comprehension of the models by
non-expert viewers.</p><p>By using a single holistic hierarchical model for representing structure and
behavior, clutter and incompatibilities can be significantly reduced even in
highly complex systems, thereby enhancing their comprehensibility. OPM has
proven to be better in visual specification and comprehension quality when
represented complex reactive systems and compared to the standard in the field
of systems engineering <xref rid="pone.0051430-Peleg2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. OPM is supported by OPCAT <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yaroker1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, a software environment
that is used in this work to model the transcription case study presented later
in this paper. OPM operational semantics were recently defined by a translation
into a state transition system <xref rid="pone.0051430-Perelman1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Perelman2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> and a related OPCAT
simulation environment was developed <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yaroker1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. OPM main elements with
their semantics and biological examples are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g002">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g003">Figure 3</xref> (for full semantics see <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>OPM entities with their symbols, definitions and operation
semantics.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0051430-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>OPM procedural links: links connecting an object or state with a
process.</title><p>These links represent process pre/postcondition object set.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0051430-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>OPM structural links: links connecting an object with an
object.</title><p>Theses links represent structural hierarchies and characteristics.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g003.jpg"/></fig><sec id="s1b1"><title>2.1. OPM operational semantics</title><p>The OPCAT simulation environment supports concurrent, synchronous and
discrete time execution. The execution we used in this work is qualitative
in nature with one instance defined for each object (e.g., molecule) and
process. This enables detecting model errors by executing and analyzing the
qualitative mechanisms underlying the biological system under study. While
multiple instances can be defined in OPCAT simulation and quantitative
aspects can be inspected, these are out of the scope of this work.</p><p>Processes are executed in a synchronous manner, one after another according
to a defined timeline. The default timeline, within the context (in-zoomed
frame) of each process, is from top to bottom. Alternative scenarios or
loops, which override the default timeline, can be modeled using an
invocation link (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s002">Table S1</xref>). Concurrency is supported, and
processes whose ellipse topmost points are located at the same height in the
diagram are being executed concurrently.</p><p>Each process has a (possibly complex) precondition and a postcondition. A
process is triggered (attempted to be activated according to its place in
the timeline), and its precondition is then checked. Only if the
precondition is satisfied, the process is executed. Upon normal process
termination, the postcondition must hold. The precondition of a process is
expressed by its preprocess object set—the set of objects, which must
exist, some possibly in specific states, for the process to start. The
postcondition is defined similarly by the postprocess object set. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g002">Figure 2</xref> exemplifies the
links for modeling objects and states as process preconditions and
postconditions. Logical expressions (AND, OR, XOR) between objects in the
pre- and post-process object set can be defined (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s002">Table
S1</xref>). By default, the logical relation between the objects in the
pre-process or post-process object set is a logical AND, meaning that all
the objects in the preprocess object set must exist in their defined states
for the process precondition to be true. It is possible to change this
default definition by using the XOR and OR relation between various objects.
Process execution can also depend on random signals. To model this, we
connect the process to an environmental object (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g001">Figure 1</xref>) without or with a specific
state. This environmental object is added to the preprocess object set,
i.e., process pre-conditions. OPM semantics also include event links, for
modeling reactive systems, and time exception links which are not used in
our biological models. The complete OPM semantic is specified in <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>.</p><p>During execution initiation, system objects are initiated to be at state
“existent”. Objects created later during execution are initiated
to be “non-existent”. All objects with explicit states are
initiated to their initial state, or, if not defined, to a random state.
Environmental objects are randomly chosen to be existent or non-existent. If
an environmental object is stateful (has states), one of its states is
randomly chosen. OPM formal operational semantics can be found in <xref rid="pone.0051430-Perelman2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s1b2"><title>2.2. Handling system complexity via in-zooming and unfolding</title><p>The complexity of systems is managed in OPM models by abstraction-refinement
mechanisms, notably out- and in-zooming and folding/unfolding, which is used
to hierarchically expose or hide details of processes and objects (e.g.,
molecules), respectively. This way, a top-level view of the system is
expanded into a set of increasingly detailed diagrams that provide the
details of the processes (via in-zooming) and objects (via unfolding) shown
in the top-level view. These two mechanisms, process in-zooming and object
unfolding, are done simultaneously during model construction. While zooming
into processes, the structural or characteristic details of objects are
exposed via unfolding. Three of OPM's structural object-object
relations are used in this work: the aggregation-participation
(“part-of”) relation, the exhibition-characterization
(“attribute”) relation and the general unidirectional relation
(shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s1b3"><title>2.3. Query processing capabilities</title><p>OPM has the following query processing capabilities, embedded in OPCAT. (1)
Find: one can do a simple “find” query and get the list of all
places in which a particular string of characters appears in the OPM model.
This can be filtered by objects, processes, or states, and can be searched
as a string or as a regular expression. In response OPCAT provides a table
with all the found locations. Clicking on each line takes the user directly
to the relevant OPD and highlights the object, process, or states in red.
(2) “Show All Appearances”: right clicking on a thing (object or
process) provides a table with all the found locations. Clicking on each
line takes the user directly to the relevant OPD and highlights the object
or process in red. (3) XQuery: Since OPL can be extracted as XML, it can be
directly queried by using XQuery <xref rid="pone.0051430-Melton1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, a query and functional
programming language that is designed to query collections of XML data.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g004">Figure 4</xref> shows an example
of OPM query capability, where the object mRNA search was done using
“Show All Appearances”, providing in response the table at the
bottom right of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g004">Figure 4</xref>
with nine appearances of mRNA in various OPDs in the model. Clicking the
third line of the table brought us to the OPD titled “<bold>SD1.1.1.
Pre-initiation Complex Formation and Initiation in-zoomed</bold>”,
in which mRNA is highlighted in red. The OPD tree on the left pane shows
part of the OPD hierarchy resulting from recursively zooming into yet
lower-level processes. In this pane, SD1.1.1 is highlighted in blue to show
where we are in the OPD tree.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>An example of OPM query capability: mRNA search.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Having investigated the expressiveness of OPM in its current form to model
molecular systems, we have found that OPM lacks dedicated patterns for
modeling the full range of biological structures and behaviors, such as link
hierarchies and transient relations, forming complexes among biological
entities and various molecular functions. In this paper we explore the
characteristics of molecular biology systems from a conceptual qualitative
modeling viewpoint and classify molecular functions. We expand OPM to
accommodate these modeling constructs, and evaluate the effectiveness of the
developed modeling framework. The adaptations and templates are evaluated by
applying them to model the mRNA transcription cycle, a subsystem of the gene
expression system. Through construction and qualitative execution of the
resulting model using OPCAT tool, we show how modeling errors and knowledge
gaps are identified and we classify them into several types for the purpose
of assisting in the generation of wet laboratory experiments aimed to close
these gaps.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>1. OPM Adaptations for Molecular Biology Systems</title><p>A valuable qualitative model of a biological system should represent its static,
dynamic, and functional views <xref rid="pone.0051430-Peleg1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. As we demonstrate below, a single OPM diagram type
supports these three major system aspects, relieving us from the need to use
three or more different diagram types for these three aspects, thereby avoiding
the need to try to understand the overall view of the system by collecting and
mentally combining details from disparate diagram types. OPM has a compact set
of conceptual building blocks for representing holistically these three
aspects.</p><sec id="s2a1"><title>1.1 Modeling biological complex structures</title><p>Biological objects vary in size, starting from single molecules of growing
size through molecular complexes, all the way to the more complex
structures, including organelles, cell compartments, and the cell as a whole
system. Our focus is modeling of molecules, complexes, and interactions
among them; higher-level biological objects, which include multi-cell
organisms, societies of organisms, and entire ecological habitats, are
beyond the scope of this work. In this section we focus on modeling
molecular structures and associations between molecules. In the following
sections we present modeling templates of molecular functions and the
formation of complexes.</p><p>Biological complexes are cellular components composed of molecules (e.g.,
proteins), which are often further decomposed into several structural
domains <xref rid="pone.0051430-Alberts1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. A complex can be composed of other complexes as
well. An example of a complex is the transcription Pre-Initiation Complex,
which is composed of other complexes, including the general transcription
factors TFIIB and TFIIF. In humans, the complex TFIIF is composed of the
protein Tfg1 and other proteins <xref rid="pone.0051430-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. A
<italic toggle="yes">domain</italic> is the protein's building block, and it has
a distinct function <xref rid="pone.0051430-Alberts1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In molecular evolution, domains are recombined
in different arrangements to create proteins with different functions. A
domain can interact with more than one molecule, and it can therefore
include more than one binding site. A protein <italic toggle="yes">binding site</italic>
is defined as the minimal region that is required to bind another molecule.
A binding site is composed of some set of consecutive amino acids. One
binding site can bind more than one pair of interacting partners, but not
simultaneously. Two binding sites can be situated in different or partially
overlapping 3D regions in the same domain.</p><p>Based on these definitions of domain and binding site, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g005">Figure 5</xref> presents a generic OPM template
of the structure of a complex and an actual example. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g005">Figure 5A</xref>, the object
<bold>Complex</bold> consists of at least one (denoted
“1..m” – one to many) <bold>Proteins</bold>. Each
<bold>Protein</bold> consists of at least one <bold>Domain</bold>, each
of which, in turn, consists of at least one <bold>Binding Site</bold>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g005">Figure 5B</xref> exemplifies
application of this template to the <bold>Polymerase II</bold> complex,
which is the main transcription machinery. <bold>Rpb1</bold> is one of the
12 proteins composing <bold>Polymerase II</bold>. The C-terminal Domain
(<bold>CTD</bold>) of <bold>Rpb1</bold> in <italic toggle="yes">S.cerevisiae</italic>
is composed of 26 <bold>Repeat Sets</bold> of amino acids. <bold>Serine
2</bold>, <bold>Serine 5</bold>, and <bold>Serine 7</bold> are modeled
as <bold>Binding Sites</bold>. The type of the object (e.g., Complex,
Molecule (Protein), Domain, Binding Site) is denoted at the upper-left
corner of each object and must correspond to the template, as can indeed be
verified by comparing the template on the left to the example on the
right.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Complex generic model and example.</title><p>(A) A generic model of the structure of a Complex. The object Complex
consists of at least one (denoted by “1..m”) Protein,
which consists at least one Domain, each of which, in turn, consists
at least one Binding Site. (B) The Complex <bold>Polymerase
II</bold> with one of its proteins, <bold>Rpb1</bold> and its 26
<bold>Repeat Sets</bold> with their structure. The balloons
include explanation of the OPM semantics.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g005">Figure 5</xref> shows,
biological structures and the associations between them are complex and
often hierarchical. They should be expressed with the ability to refine
structures and links at several levels of abstraction, ultimately revealing
the most basic elements – the binding sites. To this end, our
framework provides a hierarchy of structures and a corresponding hierarchy
of links. In order to model hierarchical molecular associations clearly and
explicitly, we define <bold>Link</bold> as a specialized OPM object that
represents the association between two molecules. As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g006">Figure 6A</xref> shows, <bold>Link</bold> is
connected to two Binding Sites via the OPM unidirectional structural
link—an open head arrow. <bold>Link</bold> associations are by default
non-covalent. Covalent associations are modeled with one of the catalyzing
templates presented in the following section.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Generic link object and example.</title><p>(A) A generic simple <bold>Link</bold> example. The object
<bold>Link</bold> connects two binding sites A and B. The
<bold>Link</bold> object can be created by a binding process and
consumed by a dissociation process. (B) The <bold>TFIIF-TFIIB</bold>
Complex is composed of a <bold>TFIIF</bold> Complex, a
<bold>TFIIB</bold> Complex and a <bold>TFIIF-to-TFIIB</bold>
Complex Link Set.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The <bold>Link</bold> object provides for creating a link hierarchy.
<bold>Link</bold> is the lowest object in the link hierarchy. Above it
is the <bold>Domain Link Set</bold>. As defined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g005">Figure 5</xref>, a <bold>Domain</bold> is
composed of a set of <bold>Binding Sites</bold>. Two domains are linked via
a <bold>Domain Link Set</bold> object—a set of one or more
<bold>Links</bold>, each associating two <bold>Binding Site</bold>
objects. Analogously, one level up the link hierarchy, two proteins, each
consisting of one or more <bold>Domains</bold>, are associated via a
<bold>Protein Link Set</bold> object—a set of one or more
<bold>Domain Link Sets</bold>. At the top level, two complexes,
<bold>Complex</bold> objects, are connected by a <bold>Complex Link
Set</bold> object.</p><p>As an example for modeling biological structures consider the following
sentence, cited from <xref rid="pone.0051430-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>:</p><disp-quote><p>
<italic toggle="yes">“Tfg1, the largest subunit of TFIIF, [is] also
cross-linked with the B-finger and linker domains, demonstrating a
close association between Tfg1 and these domains of
TFIIB”</italic>.</p></disp-quote><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g006">Figure 6B</xref> presents a
model of the hierarchical association between the TFIIB and TFIIF complexes
via the B finger domain and the Tfg1 subunit. The <bold>TFIIB-TFIIF</bold>
Complex is composed of the <bold>TFIIB</bold> Complex and the
<bold>TFIIF</bold> Complex, connected by <bold>TFIIF-to-TFIIB</bold>
Complex Link Set. The <bold>TFIIF-to-TFIIB</bold> Complex Link Set is
further decomposed into its set of links, the <bold>Tfg1-to-B-finger</bold>
Protein-Domain Link Set. The <bold>Tfg1-to-B-finger</bold> Protein-Domain
Link Set represents the binding between the <bold>B-finger</bold> domain of
<bold>TFIIB</bold> and the <bold>Tfg1</bold> subunit of
<bold>TFIIF</bold>. This <bold>Tfg1-to-B-finger</bold> Protein-Domain
Link Set connects the respective parts of the <bold>Tfg1</bold> Protein and
the <bold>B-finger</bold> Domain. If the finer structure is known, the
domains can be further decomposed into their binding sites, and then the
actual links comprising the <bold>Tfg1-to-B-finger</bold> Protein-Domain
Link Set can be specified in the model. Since the type of each object is
recorded in the top-left corner of each object box, we can tell, for
example, that <bold>TFIIF–TFIIB</bold> is a Complex, so its name is
<bold>TFIIF-TFIIB</bold> Complex, and <bold>Tfg1</bold> is a Protein, so
its name is <bold>Tfg1</bold> Protein. Alternatively, declaring Protein and
Complex to be reserved words in our framework, we can call the two objects
“The Complex <bold>TFIIF–TFIIB</bold>” and “The
Protein <bold>Tfg1</bold>”.</p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title>1.2 Modeling biological molecular functions</title><p>According to the Gene Ontology, GO <xref rid="pone.0051430-Gene1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">a biological
process is accomplished via one or more ordered assemblies of molecular
functions</italic>. Adopting this definition in our framework,
<italic toggle="yes">molecular functions</italic> are a small set of basic,
non-decomposable processes that transform biomolecules. Any higher level
biological process is composed of these molecular function building blocks.
This process hierarchy spans the spectrum ranging from the simple molecular
functions all the way to the most complex biological processes, such as gene
expression. This hierarchy is clearly represented by the tree of
Object-Process Diagrams (OPDs) created top-down by recursively zooming into
processes, starting from the high-level function (e.g., mRNA lifecycle), and
ending with molecular functions as the tree leaves.</p><p>In GO, molecular functions are classified into four basic categories:
non-covalent binding, enzymatic activity, receptor activity, and transporter
activity. Inspired by this classification and building on our experience in
modeling the mRNA transcription and decay, we classify molecular functions
into the following three basic process classes.</p><p>
<bold>Catalyzing</bold> – enzyme-based stimulation of a reaction,
involving one or more molecule types. Catalyzing is further divided into
Substrate Consumption Catalyzing and Substrate Change Catalyzing.</p><p>
<bold>Binding/Dissociation</bold> – non-covalent interaction of a
molecule X selectively with a molecule Y within the same cell compartment.
Dissociation is the inverse of binding. We note that covalent interactions
are included in the catalyzing molecular function.</p><p>
<bold>Transporting</bold> – a directed movement of a molecule across
cell compartments.</p><p>As noted, higher level biological processes are composed of these basic
molecular functions. For example, shuttling of molecule M might involve
<italic toggle="yes">Binding</italic> to molecule B, followed by
<italic toggle="yes">Transporting</italic> the resulting B-M complex across a cell
compartment boundary, followed by <italic toggle="yes">Dissociation</italic> of M from
B.</p><p>The OPM graphical modeling templates, examples and execution semantics for
these three molecular functions are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g007">Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g008">Figure 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g009">Figure 9</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Binding/Dissociation molecular function, modeling templates and
example.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g007.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0051430-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Transporting molecular function, modeling template and
example.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g008.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone-0051430-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Catalyzing molecular function, modeling templates and
example.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g009.jpg"/></fig><p>In OPM, structure and behavior are combined in a single diagram type,
representing explicitly how the system's behavior effects its
structure. For example, applying the molecular binding template, example C
in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g007">Figure 7</xref>,
<italic toggle="yes">Binding and Complex Assembly</italic>, shows the process of
binding two proteins <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> and the effect on the
newly created <bold>A–B</bold> Complex. The biological objects are
<bold>A</bold> Protein and <bold>B</bold> Protein,
<bold>A–B</bold> Complex, and <bold>A-to-B</bold> Link Set.
<bold>A</bold> Protein and <bold>B</bold> Protein participate in the
<bold>A–B Complex Assembly</bold> process, along with the two
newly created objects: <bold>A–B</bold> Complex and
<bold>A-to-B</bold> Link Set. Their creation is represented by the
creation links (arrows) emanating from the <bold>A–B Complex
Assembly</bold> process to these two objects. The hierarchical structure
is represented via the “part-of” (black triangle) structural
link, connecting <bold>A–B</bold> Complex as a whole to its two parts,
<bold>A</bold> protein and <bold>B</bold> protein. The details about the
specific binding domain and binding sites can be further exposed using the
in-zooming mechanism. A more detailed explanation on complex formation
follows.</p></sec><sec id="s2a3"><title>1.3 Hierarchical associations and dissociations</title><p>The complex hierarchical details of molecular associations call for
developing and using adequate modeling tools. Our mechanism for this purpose
includes a link hierarchy that starts with general inter-complex links at
the top, all the way down to inter-binding sites links. As we climb up the
OPD set (set of OPM diagrams) tree to higher level diagrams (using the
out-zooming mechanism), low-level details about the domains and binding
sites become invisible. They are exposed only when we drill down and inspect
increasingly detailed biological processes, and eventually molecular
functions.</p><p>A complex formation process is exemplifies in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g010">Figure 10</xref> on Rpb4/7 binding to RNA
Polymerase II. Rpb4/7 is known to be a subtoichiomertic component of RNA
Polymerase II <xref rid="pone.0051430-HarelSharvit1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. The two diagrams in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g010">Figure 10</xref> show (A) the process of binding
<bold>Rpb4/7</bold> and <bold>Polymerase II</bold>, the two complexes
participating in the <bold>Rpb4/7 and Polymerase II Binding</bold>, and (B)
details of this process. The created complex and links are shown
concurrently. The details about the specific binding domain and binding
sites can be further exposed through further in-zooming. The OPM diagram
resulting from zooming into the <bold>Rpb4/7 and Polymerase II
Binding</bold> process in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g010">Figure 10A</xref> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g010">Figure 10B</xref>. The exposed subprocesses are
(1) <bold>Link Set Generating</bold>, which is further in-zoomed to expose
the exact details of binding links and domains (not shown) and (2)
<bold>Polymerase II-and-Rpb4/7 Complex Assembling</bold>, which creates
the complex and connects it to its parts during model execution. It is up to
the system modeler to decide what level of granularity is needed (or known)
for the purpose of understanding some specific point about the system and
the associated biomolecular mechanism.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Complex formation: the process of molecular binding exemplified
on Rpb4/7 to Polymerase II binding.</title><p>(A) <bold>Rpb4/7 and Polymerase II Binding</bold> process (B)
<bold>Rpb4/7 and Polymerase II Binding</bold> process zoomed
into its sub-processes, <bold>Link Set Generating</bold> and
<bold>Polymerase II–and-Rpb4/7 Complex
Assembling</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g010.jpg"/></fig><p>In many cases, a protein-protein interaction is known to occur, but the exact
domains or binding sites of this interaction is unknown. In such cases, we
model the general protein-protein interaction, as was done in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g010">Figure 10A</xref>, without
zooming further into the binding process and without exposing the binding
domains or sites. This selective refinement enables modeling a system with
unknown data, yet providing for executing it correctly.</p></sec><sec id="s2a4"><title>2. The Transcription Cycle Case Study</title><p>To evaluate the utility of OPM as a language for modeling molecular biology
systems, we have modeled the mRNA transcription cycle. We present the OPM
model of this system, its execution, the knowledge gaps detected as a result
of this modeling process, and the classification of these knowledge gaps. In
addition, by executing the model in a “halt execution” mode
(i.e., halting whenever a process precondition is not satisfied), we show
how the execution can detect model errors, which may result either from
modeling errors or from actual knowledge gaps.</p><p>The expression of protein-encoding genes is a complex process that determines
which genes are expressed as proteins at any given time, as well as the
relative levels of these proteins. The mRNA Lifecycle involves several
distinct stages: (1) RNA synthesis, or transcription and RNA processing
(after which the RNA is considered mRNA), (2) mRNA transport (in eukaryotes)
from the nucleus to the cytoplasm, (3) protein synthesis, or translation,
and (4) mRNA degradation. RNA polymerase II (pol II), a large multi-subunit
complex, is responsible for transcribing protein-encoding RNAs, namely
mRNAs, which are the focus of our case study.</p><p>Transcription by pol II, the first stage in the expression of
protein-encoding genes, produces RNA—the primary transcript. To
initiate transcription, pol II requires a series of additional proteins,
general transcription factors, and other proteins (e.g., activators). In
addition, the Mediator, a large multiprotein complex, and the chromatin
(which includes the DNA) with its main building blocks, the histones, are
responsible for modulating transcription by communicating with many
gene-specific regulators and transcription activation factors <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kornberg1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.
During the elongation phase of transcription, the nascent RNA undergoes
three types of processing events: (I) a special nucleotide, m(7)GpppN, named
“cap”, is added to the RNA's 5′ end (a process known
as capping); (II) intron sequences are removed from internal sections of the
RNA molecule (splicing) (III) A stretch of poly(A), called poly(A) tail, is
added to the 3′ end of the RNA. This process involves RNA cleavage and
further polyadenylation, and is executed prior the transcription termination
phase, which occurs downstream of this site. Each of these processes is
carried out by proteins or RNA molecules, many of which travel along with
the RNA polymerase II (Pol II). In many cases, these modifying factors bind
to C-terminal Domain (CTD) of Pol II. Transcription of a given gene is a
multiple round event, during which RNA Polymerase II undergoes phase
transitions between “initiation”, “elongation”, and
“termination”, which can repeat many times. It has been proposed
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Rani1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> that the
same Pol II can be transformed from the termination to initiation phase
without leaving the transcription unit. Thus, termination may be coupled to
initiation. The first transcription round is a rare event compared to
subsequent rounds that involve termination-coupled with re-initiation. Some
of the initiation factors remain bound to the promoter throughout the
transcription cycle, whereas others are recycled <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.
Indeed, convincing recent evidence from both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and
<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies have shown that general transcription
factors (GTFs), such as TFIID, TFIIA, and TFIIB <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Zawel1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, as well as the Mediator complex <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kornberg1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Rani1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup2" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, stay behind at the
promoter when Pol II engages in transcript elongation, allowing rapid entry
of new polymerases for re-initiation of transcription at the gene. The
Chromatin and Mediator roles, which are more significant in the first
pioneering round of transcription <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kornberg1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Rani1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>,
are beyond the scope of this paper.</p><p>Our transcription model, which yields an mRNA, includes RNA synthesis and
processing. The model focuses on the transcription reinitiating process and
its participants; the basal Pol II transcription machinery in eukaryotes,
the general transcription factors TFIID, TFIIB, TFIIE, TFIIH <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>,
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Zawel1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, Rpb4/7 <xref rid="pone.0051430-HarelSharvit1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>
and Fcp1 <xref rid="pone.0051430-Kobor1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Our main goal was to gain insight into the
reinitiating process and the role of rpb4/7 in it. It should be emphasized
that, although based on compelling results <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, the
looping model cannot yet be considered to be a well-established mechanism.
We suspect that it is relevant to some transcription units, but not to all
of them.</p></sec><sec id="s2a5"><title>2.1 Transcription OPM model</title><p>The OPM model and execution of this important cellular subsystem with
illustrations of OPM extensions and templates is presented in this section.
The transcription model is based on 32 facts and mechanisms derived from 19
research papers (presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s003">Table S2</xref>), regarding the mechanisms
underlying the transcription process in eukaryotes. Our main focus was the
transcription re-initiation process and its related factors: TFIIF
transcription factor, RNA Polymerase II, its CTD(C-Terminal Domain) changes
and its Rpb4/7 subunit, TFIIB transcription factor and Fcp1 phosphatase.
Other participating transcription factors such as- TFIIA, TFIID, TFIIH,
TFIIE where modeled as well, whenever related to the re-initiation
process.</p><p>The established model includes 50 objects and 37 processes. The 37 processes
includes, 13 higher level processes and 24 lowest level processes. Lowest
level processes are not further in-zoomed. The model's processes tree
includes 7 levels. The transcription model and the OPCAT tool can be
downloaded and executed from <xref rid="pone.0051430-ESML1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g011">Figure 11A</xref>
<bold>Transcription Cycle</bold> is zoomed into three subprocesses:
<bold>Re-initiation, Elongation</bold> and <bold>Termination</bold>. The
<bold>mRNA</bold> is created and modified during these
<bold>Transcription Cycle</bold> subprocesses. The <bold>mRNA</bold> is
created from a <bold>Nucleotide Set</bold>, which is consumed during
<bold>Termination</bold>, as depicted by the consumption link, the arrow
emanating from the <bold>Nucleotide Set</bold> object into
<bold>Termination</bold>. The <bold>mRNA</bold> is created during the
<bold>Re-initiation</bold> process in its <bold>capped</bold> state, as
denoted by the state-specified result link from the
<bold>Re-initiation</bold> process to the <bold>capped</bold> state of
<bold>mRNA</bold>. During <bold>Elongation</bold>, <bold>mRNA</bold> is
synthesized and processed, resulting in a state change from
<bold>capped</bold> to <bold>elongated</bold>. During
<bold>Termination</bold>, multiple proteins are recruited onto the
<bold>mRNA</bold>, including <bold>Export Receptor Set</bold>, which is
a set of factors that support export of <bold>mRNA</bold> with
<bold>Rpb4/7</bold> into the cytoplasm, changing its state from
<bold>elongated</bold> to <bold>mRNP</bold>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g011">Figure 11B</xref> presents the corresponding
Object-Process Language (OPL) text, which is a subset of natural English,
generated automatically by OPCAT. OPL sentences concisely specify in text
exactly what the Object-Process Diagrams (OPDs) express graphically,
catering to people who are more inclined to comprehend complexities of
systems by reading text (popularly referred to as “right-brain
people” according to the theory of “left-brain or right-brain
dominance”) rather than by diagrams (preferred by “left-brain
people”).</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption><title>The transcription process bi-modal representation.</title><p>(A) The Transcription process model. (B) The corresponding
automatically-generated Object-Process Language (OPL).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g011.jpg"/></fig><p>OPL sentences specify (1) the structure of the system and (2) the behavior of
the system, in particular how processes change object states, how they
create new objects (molecules or complexes), how they consume existing ones,
and what objects (called enablers in OPM) are required in order for a
process to take place even though they are not affected. Two examples of
structure sentences appearing in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g011">Figure 11B</xref> are: (1)
“<bold>Nucleotide Set</bold> consists of <bold>Nascent RNA Builder
Subset, Elongators Nucleotide Subset</bold>, and <bold>Cleaved
Nucleotide Subset</bold>.” (2) “<bold>Polymerase II</bold>
consists of <bold>Serine 2</bold>.”. Examples of behavior sentences
are: (1) “<bold>Termination</bold> consumes <bold>Nucleotide
Set</bold>.” – a consumption sentence, (2)
“<bold>Elongation</bold> changes <bold>mRNA</bold> from
<bold>capped</bold> to <bold>elongated</bold>.” – a
state-change sentence, specifying the state before (<bold>capped</bold>) and
after (<bold>elongated</bold>) the process <bold>Elongation</bold> took
place, and (3) “<bold>Elongation</bold> requires
<bold>Spliceosome</bold>, <bold>TREX Complex</bold>, and
<bold>phosphorylated Serine 2</bold>.” – an enabling
sentence, specifying the exact list of objects (molecules and/or complexes)
required for the <bold>Elongation</bold> process to take place.</p><p>As these examples show, not only can the English-translated OPL sentences be
understood easily by biologists who are not conceptual modeling experts;
these sentences include unambiguous, essential information for understanding
the structure, behaviour, and function of the biological system at the
various levels of hierarchy. In contrast, text in research papers is written
in free, unconstrained language. This freedom allows paper authors to write
complicated sentences that on one hand are hard to follow, and on the other
hand do not provide complete information, either because this information is
assumed to be known, or because it is not known. Most often, neither the
former nor the latter case are explicitly declared. In contrast, since OPL
is derived automatically from a formal OPM model, which is guaranteed to be
consistent, the text in each sentence expresses an unambiguous model fact
that is based on the literature and/or new findings.</p><p>While modeling facts expressed in different research papers, contradictions
may pop up. These are discovered while attempting to execute the unified
model. Indeed, we have accidently encountered at least one case of such a
contradiction between two published papers, which is beyond the scope of
this paper. The likelihood of detecting such contradiction by merely reading
free text of two different papers is very slim. This points out to another
benefit of our model-based approach. Such contradictions, which will be
reflected also in the OPL text, can be resolved by searching for supporting
evidence in related papers or executing actual lab experiments to support
one claim and refute the other. Once decided, the correct facts are
incorporated into the graphical OPM model and they will be automatically
reflected also in the text.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g012">Figure 12</xref> presents a
screenshot of the <bold>Transcription Cycle</bold> process during its
execution using OPCAT. Our conceptual model execution includes qualitative
execution of a transcription cycle of a single, representative mRNA
molecule. <bold>Elongation</bold> (colored in dark purple) is being
executed, while the <bold>Elongators Nucleotide Subset</bold> object is
being consumed, as denoted by the red dot along the consumption link, and
<bold>mRNA</bold> changes states from <bold>capped</bold> to
<bold>elongated</bold>. A transcription cycle execution record can be
downloaded from <xref rid="pone.0051430-ESML1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and for an explained partial execution see Video
S1.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g012" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g012</object-id><label>Figure 12</label><caption><title>The execution of the transcription model.</title><p>Here shown a snapshot of the <bold>Elongation</bold> process being
executed (and therefore highlighted in purple), and the
<bold>mRNA</bold> changes states from <bold>capped</bold> into
<bold>elongated</bold>. See supplemental movie SV1 for
<bold>Re-initiation</bold> process non-deterministic
execution.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g012.jpg"/></fig><p>The <bold>Re-initiation</bold> process is further zoomed (diagrams not
shown), exposing two subprocesses: <bold>Pre-initiation Complex Formation
and Initiation</bold> and <bold>Promoter Clearance</bold>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure 13</xref> presents a
diagram, in which the <bold>Pre-initiation Complex Formation and
Initiation</bold> process is further in-zoomed. Its second and third
subprocesses, <bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine 5 Phosphorylation</bold> and
<bold>TFIIB.Serine 65 Phosphorylation</bold>, are not further in-zoomed,
as depicted by their thin surrounding ellipse contour. Both are atomic
phosphorylation functions, classified as <italic toggle="yes">Catalyzing –
Substrate Changed</italic> molecular functions and modeled using the
appropriate template, as highlighted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure 13</xref> with a dashed line applied to
<bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine 5 Phosphorylation</bold>, where TFIIH is the
kinase.</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g013" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g013</object-id><label>Figure 13</label><caption><title>Pre-initiation complex formation and initiation model.</title><p>In this example we apply the Catalyzing - Substrate Changed modeling
template for modeling serine 5 phosphorylation (surrounded by dashed
square) by TFIIH Kinase. TFIIB Kinase is still conjectured and
therefore highlighted in grey.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g013.jpg"/></fig><p>
<bold>TFIIH</bold> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure
13</xref>) is defined as environmental object (surrounding line is
dashed), meaning that its existence is randomly chosen during execution. If
it is chosen to be <bold>non-e</bold> (non-existent), the <bold>Pol
II.CTD.Serine 5 Phosphorylation</bold> and <bold>TFIIB.Serine 65
Phosphorylation</bold> processes will not be executed, resulting in
abortive RNA. This flow of events exemplifies a possible non-deterministic
execution of the model. Using environmental objects, the model shows not
only a “successful” transcription process, but also includes the
possible failure scenarios, such as abortive RNAs (See Video S1). We note
that a successful transcription cycle is known to be a rare event <xref rid="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, yet
it is the only one leading to mRNA synthesis. Thus this transcription
non-deterministic model may show the abnormal termination options, which is
probably highly valuable for understanding the source of various defects and
diseases.</p></sec><sec id="s2a6"><title>2.2 The utility of conceptual model-based systems biology</title><p>Our framework assumes the existence of a “ground truth”
conceptual model: a model kernel in a specific molecular biology research
area that was constructed manually based on the best available knowledge
from the literature, validated by the best experts in this specific research
area, and adjusted to execute correctly and fit the experimental data. Our
Conceptual Model-based Systems Biology framework includes a set of
methodological guidelines that help the biologist to (1) incorporate her or
his findings into the existing model, thereby augmenting and evolving it,
making sure it is still executable and consistent, (2) identify potential
knowledge gaps within the augmented model, and (3) if a knowledge gap is
discovered, generate one or more hypotheses, incorporate it into the model,
and test the model before the design of another set of one or more lab
experiments aimed to close this gap. The model with the conjectured
hypothesis can be tested by comparing its execution to fit the experimental
findings. If the ground truth model is augmented and no knowledge gap is
discovered, the facts that have been added can potentially become part of
the new, augmented ground truth model, and this is how the model evolves
over time.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>3. Detecting Knowledge Gaps and Model Errors</title><p>During the attempts to unify the data related to the mRNA transcription and decay
processes, into one executable mechanistic OPM model, we have detected knowledge
gaps and model errors of various types. Detecting a knowledge gap during manual
OPM model construction regarding translation factors localization in P-bodies is
described in <xref rid="pone.0051430-Dori3" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, resulted in raising and experimentally proving a
conjecture about eRF3 location in the P body. We note that in this work OPCAT
execution capabilities were incomplete and were not used. Also the biological
modeling templates were not defined.</p><p>We define a <italic toggle="yes">knowledge gap</italic> as lack of knowledge regarding a
specific detail of some process and/or object in the system being modeled. We
define a <italic toggle="yes">model error</italic> as an inconsistency regarding a specific
detail of some process and/or object in the system being modeled. Knowledge gaps
and model errors prevent a given system model from being able to completely and
satisfactorily explain or execute the behavior of that system.</p><p>Model errors are detected automatically during model execution. Knowledge gaps
can arise under the following possible circumstances: (1)
<italic toggle="yes">manually</italic>, while trying to model some fact that is stated in
the literature using a modeling template of one of the three molecular functions
(see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g007">Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g008">Figure 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g009">Figure 9</xref>) or represent the
temporal execution order of two or more processes, or (2)
<italic toggle="yes">automatically</italic>, during model execution, as a result of
detecting model errors in the model of the system under test. This model errors
are raised when the model does not execute as the suggested mechanism or the
execution outcomes does not match the expected experimental outcomes.</p><p>Our qualitative model execution (with one instance defined for each model entity)
can help expose modeling errors resulting from temporal aspects, incorrect
control flows, or wrong outcomes. The execution can detect, (1) object-related
discrepancies, such as missing or redundant objects (e.g., association objects
or some molecule), or (2) state-related discrepancies, such as incorrect state
or an object being at more than one state at the same time. The detected errors
results from process-related discrepancies, such as missing, temporally
misplaced, or redundant molecular functions. After detected, the relevant
process should be adjusted to enable successful model execution. Examples of
<italic toggle="yes">missing object</italic> error and <italic toggle="yes">incorrect state</italic>
error follow.</p><p>While constructing and executing our transcription model, the control flow was
found to be incorrect, indicating one or more modeling errors or gaps in our
knowledge. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g014">Figure 14</xref> is a
screenshot of the model and this incorrect erroneous flow, causing halt of the
system during execution. For example, the <bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine 5
Phosphorylation</bold> process halted execution with the following two
errors indicated by our software:</p><fig id="pone-0051430-g014" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.g014</object-id><label>Figure 14</label><caption><title>Example of two errors found during model execution.</title><p>The transcription model execution halts during the <bold>Pol
II.CTD.Serine 5 Phosphorylation</bold> process with errors presented
in the lowest frame (see Video S2). The first error is a <italic toggle="yes">missing
object</italic> error and the second is an <italic toggle="yes">incorrect
state</italic> error.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.g014.jpg"/></fig><p>“Process <bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine 5 Phosphorylation</bold> failed to run
(time = 17458) for the following reasons:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Instrument link is not satisfied because object <bold>Pol II-TFIIH</bold>
has no instances.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Consumption link is not satisfied because object <bold>Serine 5</bold>
has no instances at state <bold>dephosphorylate</bold>”.</p></list-item></list><p>As exemplified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g014">Figure 14</xref>,
the precondition of the <bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine5 Phosphorylation</bold> process
includes three instruments: (1) the existence of the object <bold>TFIIH</bold>,
(2) existence of the object <bold>Pol II-TFIIH</bold> Link Set, i.e.,
recruitment of <bold>TFIIH</bold> to <bold>Pol II</bold>, and (3) the existence
of the object <bold>Serine 5</bold> in its <bold>dephosphorylated</bold> state.
The first error detected above is a <italic toggle="yes">missing object</italic> error since
the <bold>Pol II-TFIIH</bold> object is non-existent (i.e., has no instances).
It results from a temporal error, indicating that <bold>TFIIH</bold> was not
recruited to <bold>Pol II</bold> prior to <bold>Serine 5
Dephosphorylation</bold>, as required. The second detected error is an
<italic toggle="yes">incorrect state</italic> error since <bold>Serine 5</bold> is in the
incorrect <bold>phosphorylated</bold> state. This execution error results from a
missing molecular function. We indeed found that there is no specified molecular
function that transforms <bold>Serine 5</bold> (located at position 5 of the
C-terminal domain belonging to the Rpb1 subunit of the RNA Polymerase II) from
its <bold>dephosphorylated</bold> state to its <bold>phosphorylated</bold>
state.</p><p>As a result of detecting these errors, the model was corrected and then executed
successfully. One of the corrected diagrams is in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure 13</xref>, where the <bold>Pol II.CTD.Serine
5 Phosphorylation</bold> and <bold>TFIIB.Serine 65 Phosphorylation</bold>
processes where changed to be executed after <bold>Pre-Initiation Complex
Formation</bold> process (and TFIIH recruitment) and before <bold>Nascent
mRNA Synthesis and Capping</bold>, since <bold>TFIIB.Serine 65
Phosphorylation</bold> is a condition for transcription initiation and
capping <xref rid="pone.0051430-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p><p>The errors exemplified above are modeling errors, which are made often by the
system modeler. Many such modeling errors were detected as a result of our model
execution and fixed during the transcription model construction.</p><p>In addition to the modeling errors, which were fixed, we also detected 17 actual
knowledge gaps, which are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051430-t001">Table 1</xref>. Knowledge gap number 11, which
relates to the unknown dephosphorylation of TFIIB, was detected while cyclically
executing the transcription re-initiation. This <italic toggle="yes">incorrect state</italic>
model error was detected when the execution halted; indicating that the serine
located at position 65 of TFIIB is not in the required dephosphorylated state.
The other knowledge gaps were detected manually prior to model execution.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0051430-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051430.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Knowledge gaps found while modeling the mRNA transcription
process.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0051430-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0051430.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge Gap Type</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associated Molecular Function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowledge Gap</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When is Rpb4/7 recruited to RNA Polymerase
II?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown Object (binding molecule)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What molecule recruits Rpb4/7 to Polymerase
II?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does Rpb4/7 bind FCP1?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does Rpb4/7 bind TFIIF?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does TFIIB bind FCP1?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does FCP1 bind TFIIF?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is the temporal dependency of Rpb4/7
recruitment and TFIIH and TFIIE recruitment to PIC?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does Pol II Bind TFIIF?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown temporal order</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transporting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">When does Pol II change location from
terminator to promoter?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object (binding domain)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What domains of FCP1 does rpb4/7 bind to?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object (phosphatase)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalyzing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What molecule dephosphorylates TFIIB serine
65?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown molecular function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing Molecular Function</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How is Fcp1 inhibited?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What molecule binds Fcp1 to inhibit its
activity?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object (kinase)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalyzing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is the Ser7 kinase?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What molecule recruits Ser7 kinase?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object (phosphatase)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalyzing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is the Ser7 phosphatase?</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown object (binding molecule)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What molecule recruits Ser7 phosphatase?</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Our ability to detect most of the actual knowledge gaps manually may be due to
the fact that many of the modeled mechanisms were completely unknown, making it
hard to construct the model initially. Another reason can be that the model is
medium sized and not overly complex. However, we expect that in larger, more
complex models, concrete knowledge gaps will be more difficult to detect by
humans static inspection, yet they can be detected automatically by trying to
execute the model in the same manner exemplified above.</p><p>We note that knowledge gap can also result from an inconsistency between two or
more temporal facts stated in two or more different research papers. This might
indicate an incorrect interpretation of the experimental results in one of the
research papers between which a contradiction has been detected through the
model. We have indeed found a discrepancy between findings stated in two papers
in the decay part of our larger mRNA lifecycle model (not presented here).</p><p>After the model was constructed and evaluated to be consistent, one can replace
the execution mode from the “halt execution” mode to the “skip
process” mode. In the “halt execution” mode, instrument links
are used, representing a precondition that must hold for the model to continue
its execution. In the “skip process” mode, condition links are used,
providing for skipping a process whose precondition is not met. In the
“skip process” mode, unsatisfied conditions do not halt the model,
but rather skip the process and continue executing. This enables analysis of
system perturbations, such as mutations, and execution of non-deterministic
models (see Video S1).</p><sec id="s2b1"><title>3.1 Knowledge gaps classification</title><p>Having modeled the mRNA transcription cycle as well as the mRNA decay process
(which is not presented in this work), we fixed the modeling errors,
highlighted the actual knowledge gaps, and analyzed their characteristics.
Based on this analysis, we propose a classification of knowledge gaps that
might arise as a result of qualitative conceptual modeling of molecular
biology system mechanisms.</p><p>Our knowledge gaps classification is based on the three molecular
functions—catalyzing, binding/dissociating, and transporting—and
their modeling templates. Knowledge gaps might stem from (1) lack of
knowledge regarding a molecular function at some point in the model, (2) the
completeness of the molecular function template and the structure of the
participating objects in the template (e.g., missing knowledge on binding
sites or enzymes), or (3) the temporal execution order of a molecular
function within the scope of its higher level biological process.
Accordingly, we classify knowledge gaps into the following three types.</p><p>
<bold>Unknown Molecular Function</bold> – Lack of knowledge about
whether a molecular function F happens in a certain place under certain
circumstances. For example, it has been sown that TFIIB inhibits the
phosphatase activity of FCP1 <xref rid="pone.0051430-Friedl1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. When we tried to
incorporate this finding into the transcription model as a molecular
function, knowledge gaps emerged, preventing straightforward modeling of
this assertion. We can assume that the inhibition is due to binding of some
unknown molecule A to Fcp1. This is represented in the model using the
unknown <italic toggle="yes">Binding</italic> molecular function between Fcp1 and some
unknown molecule A. Consequently, the CTD de-phosphorylation function is
inhibited, because Fcp1 is not free to carry out its “usual”
activity due to its binding to A. The knowledge gap here is weather a
<italic toggle="yes">Binding</italic> molecular function between A and Fcp1 occurs
(see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051430-t001">Table 1</xref>, row no.
12).</p><p>
<bold>Unknown Object</bold> –Lack of knowledge about an object (such as
a molecule) that participates in a molecular function. For example, while it
is obvious that the molecular function of TFIIB.serine 65 dephosphorylation
is needed for executing a temporally coherent model, the details of this
molecular function are unknown (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051430-t001">Table 1</xref>, row no. 11). The unknown
identity of the TFIIB Kinase is highlighted in grey in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure 13</xref>. Another example is a knowledge
gap regarding the identity of A in the case of inhibiting the phosphatase
activity of FCP1, by binding <xref rid="pone.0051430-Friedl1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. We might conjecture
that it is TFIIB, as this is in line with the fact that TFIIB binds fcp1
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Kobor1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.
However, this is a mere conjecture that must be proved empirically.</p><p>
<bold>Unknown Temporal Order</bold> – Lack of knowledge about the
temporal order of the molecular function along the model timeline. It is
unknown whether a molecular function F, which is known to happen, must
happen before or after another molecular function F′, or whether F and
F′ are dependent on each other and therefore must happen in parallel,
or whether they are independent and therefore each one of them can happen
before, during, or after the other. An example of a temporal order knowledge
gap is the unknown temporal order of the RNA Polymerase II to Rpb4/7 binding
function: It is unknown whether it occurs during transcription termination,
during transcription initiation, or between these two processes (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051430-t001">Table 1</xref>, row no. 1).</p><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0051430-t001">Table 1</xref> summarizes the
17 knowledge gaps we found in the transcription model. Of those, all but
knowledge gap number 11 were found manually, while constructing the model.
Each knowledge gap is phrased as a question, and for each one, the
associated molecular function and knowledge gap type are recorded.</p><p>After a knowledge gap has been detected, be it manually or automatically, the
model needs to be augmented with a conjecture that enables its execution.
These conjectures, highlighted in grey in the model (such as TFIIB Kinase in
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051430-g013">Figure 13</xref>), are
verified by model execution and then must be verified empirically. If there
is more than one alternative conjecture, experimental results will determine
which one is correct, so the model can be updated accordingly, serving as an
evolving reliable knowledge resource.</p><p>We have also worked on a larger model, the mRNA decay model, which is not
presented in this paper. The mRNA decay model comprises 130 objects and 65
processes, of which 41 are leaf, atomic processes, and 24 are higher level.
In this mRNA decay model, which runs 9 in-zooming levels deep, we found 24
knowledge gaps, of which 13 were related to <italic toggle="yes">unknown temporal
orders</italic> and 6 were <italic toggle="yes">unknown objects</italic>. Like in the
mRNA transcription model which is the focus of this paper, only one
knowledge gap was of the type <italic toggle="yes">unknown molecular function</italic>.
Most of the knowledge gaps in both models were related to (1)
<italic toggle="yes">unknown temporal orders</italic>: 47% and 50% in
the transcription and mRNA decay models, respectively, and (2)
<italic toggle="yes">unknown objects</italic>: 47% and 25% in the
transcription and mRNA decay models, respectively.</p><p>Interestingly, since the mRNA decay is a newer, more cutting-edge research
subject, experimental results that were related to completely unknown mRNA
decay mechanisms gave rise to four wider knowledge gaps of a new kind, which
we call <italic toggle="yes">unknown mechanism</italic>. Each unknown mechanism involves
a set of several unknown molecular functions. Thus, a hierarchy of knowledge
gap types can be defined, in which <italic toggle="yes">unknown mechanism</italic> is the
widest, followed by <italic toggle="yes">unknown molecular function</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">unknown object</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">unknown temporal
order</italic>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Summary and Discussion</title><p>We have proposed a Conceptual Model-based Systems Biology framework. Our framework
enables multi-layer qualitative modeling and model execution, as well as model-based
elicitation and classification of knowledge gaps in molecular biology systems. We
also show how model execution detects model errors and enhances the construction of
a mechanistically coherent model.</p><p>The framework adapts Object-Process Methodology (OPM) to the domain of systems
biology. OPM fits the task at hand as it enables concurrent representation of the
system's structure—the objects that comprise the system, and its
behavior—how processes transform objects over time. OPM is a conceptually
rich, graphical language which has the capacity to capture the variety of biological
information by connecting stateful objects (i.e., molecules) to biological processes
that transform them: create or destroy them, or change their states at various
levels of detail.</p><p>Modeling the mRNA transcription cycle as a case in point, we started with this high
level cell function and modeled increasingly detailed processes, along with the
objects participating in these processes. This case study has demonstrated modeling
of molecular processes, such as complex formation, localization and trafficking,
molecular binding, enzymatic stimulation, and environmental intervention. While this
paper has focused on the mRNA transcription case study, using OPM for conceptual
modeling in systems biology is by no means limited to this particular subsystem.
Indeed, we have been applying OPM to model the mRNA decay process, which is the
focus of current work in progress, and the Glycolysis metabolic pathway, part of
which we present in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s001">Figure S1</xref>. Similar to the Gene Ontology (GO) definitions, at the lowest
level of our framework, all biological processes boil down to three basic molecular
functions: catalysis, binding/dissociation, and transporting. The simultaneous
representation of structure and behavior via objects and processes, along with the
modeling templates, provide for the ability to focus on particular molecules of
interests and follow their changing role over time in complex biological processes.
The ability to follow molecules as they participate in multiple processes can help
discover multi-functional molecules, such as Rpb4/7, which has a key role in each
major stage of the mRNA lifecycle <xref rid="pone.0051430-HarelSharvit1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, a finding that is
emerging as a key feature of biological systems.</p><p>During modeling and execution of the mRNA transcription model, we discovered modeling
errors and knowledge gaps. Our model execution can help expose modeling errors and
knowledge gaps resulting from incorrect control flows or wrong execution outcomes.
The execution can detect, (1) object-related discrepancies, such as missing or
redundant objects (e.g., association objects or some molecule), or (2) state-related
discrepancies, such as incorrect state or an object being at more than one state at
the same time. Many model errors were discovered during model construction and
execution, and the model was adjusted accordingly in an iterative improvement
process, until we were satisfied with its execution flow and its agreement with
published results, weeding out false positives as much as we could and leaving only
“true” knowledge gaps.</p><p>Identification and classification of knowledge gaps is a valuable feature of the
framework, as it suggests where research should focus and whether conjectures about
uncertain mechanisms fit into the already verified evolving model. From a
quantitative viewpoint, our mRNA transcription model includes 50 objects and 37
processes, 24 of which are low-level processes. In this model, we detected 17 actual
knowledge gaps. These were related to molecular functions and classified into three
types: unknown molecular function, unknown object, and unknown temporal order. About
half of the knowledge gaps (eight of 17) related to temporal aspects
(<italic toggle="yes">unknown temporal order</italic> type), another eight were unknown
biological objects participating in some molecular function (<italic toggle="yes">unknown
object</italic> type), and one related to an unknown molecular function
(<italic toggle="yes">unknown molecular function</italic> type). We also demonstrated how our
executable framework is capable of detecting temporal gaps and unknown molecular
functions in a straightforward manner. In a more complex mRNA decay subsystem, which
we also modeled, most of the knowledge gaps were also <italic toggle="yes">unknown temporal
order</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">unknown object</italic> types. In the mRNA decay
model we found a fourth, wider knowledge gap type—<italic toggle="yes">unknown
mechanism</italic>, which comprises several unknown molecular functions, giving
rise to a hierarchy of knowledge gap types.</p><p>Knowledge gaps can emerge from model execution using other conceptual formalisms. For
example, temporal inconsistencies were reported when comparing
<italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> vulval development model execution with
experimental results, using the Statecharts qualitative method <xref rid="pone.0051430-Fisher2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Moreover, some of the
questions and knowledge gaps might have been exposed by examining known facts
without constructing the model and executing it. Yet, a systematic approach enforced
by the modeling activity and the model execution may greatly enhance the detection
of inconsistencies and the elicitation of knowledge gaps. Moreover, the model may
also serve as a vehicle to resolve the detected inconsistencies and test conjectures
related to knowledge gap resolutions.</p><p>The model can provide a top-level holistic functional view, such as gene expression,
and gradually expose details of both biological processes and the involved
structures all the way down to such minute details as whether a given amino acid is
phosphorylated. OPM's in-zooming/out-zooming capability enables gradual
exposure of system details. By traversing across detail levels, this
refinement-abstraction mechanism facilitates focusing on fine details of a
particular subsystem via in-zooming, and getting an overall system view via
out-zooming. For example, using the OPM modeling tool OPCAT and its query
capabilities, we can inspect for each molecule of interest the flow of processes it
undergoes and how each process affects it. It is this ability to have a holistic
system view on one hand and to inspect low-level details on the other hand that
researchers, immersed in an ocean of details, often miss.</p><p>The benefits of using our framework to a biology researcher also include the ability
to coherently preserve, manage, and evolve knowledge about a system under study. Our
framework captures and explicitly represents both established and conjectured
qualitative mechanistic knowledge about the function, behavior, and structure of the
systems at a wide spectrum of detail levels. The model is the means to relate
disparate pieces of information into a comprehensive, system-wide conceptual
framework, in which knowledge is arranged in a consistent hierarchical way. The
sources of the knowledge pieces can be a result of one's experiments combined
with facts known from the literature. Being formal, the model can be executed in a
straightforward manner using model checking techniques <xref rid="pone.0051430-Perelman1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> from Computer Science. An
important outcome of this knowledge formalized organization is the ability to
construct a widely-expressive mechanistic coherent model and expose knowledge gaps
that can provide a basis for designing and executing experiments.</p><p>A main drawback of executable methods is their closeness to computational semantics
<xref rid="pone.0051430-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, such as
being based solely on object states or events, and lack of adequate abstractions
needed for closing the gap between these basic computation-oriented concepts and the
rich set of concepts needed for representing biological systems. As we have shown,
OPM does enable the representation of a rich set of biological structures and
behaviors. One drawback of an expressive conceptual language is the need to use a
larger set of concepts and symbols than used in other modeling methods, though in
OPM the size of this set is kept to a minimum: stateful objects and processes that
transform them as entities, and several link types to express structure and behavior
connections in a single diagram type.</p><p>Conceptual qualitative models are key for understanding the system's underlying
mechanisms, which are a result of the quantitative findings. Indeed, the model that
we have developed so far is qualitative in nature; it does not represent
continuously changing compartmental concentrations of reactants or stochastic data
that are required to formalize quantitative models. Since our model is qualitative
in nature, we map each experimental quantitative outcome to be incorporated into the
model as Boolean. For example, 70% deactivation of some process is mapped in
our model as 100% deactivation of that process. Yet, our approach is capable
of modeling kinetic coefficients of reactants by using multiple instances of the
biological objects, as exemplified in the model of the Glycolysis pathway (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p><p>The proposed framework can help conceptualize an incomplete complex molecular biology
system, drive execution, and support hypothesis generation and validation. After the
model is constructed and evaluated through execution to match the known experimental
data, it can be used to check hypotheses and to generate new ones. This can be done
by perturbing the model or by incorporating into the model new hypothesized
mechanisms and then matching its outcomes to known wet-lab experimental findings. If
the new model with the conjectured mechanism yields the expected results, the
conjecture is said to be consistent with the model and can be further tested
experimentally. Our model may detect errors in biological mechanistic conjectures
before conducting wet lab experiments. A restriction of the approach is that the
model might yield false positives, i.e., indicate that an erroneous mechanistic
conjecture is correct, because for lack of knowledge it executes correctly. Hence,
model-validated conjectures still need to be confirmed via wet-lab experiments. On
the positive side, though, many such experiments can be avoided or refined if the
model proves them wrong in the first place.</p><p>A unique advantage of OPM is its bimodal representation: the graphic model is
translated on the fly to Object-Process Language (OPL)—a subset of natural
English that enables comprehension of the model by biologists who have no knowledge
of the graphic symbols of OPM. The opposite translation of text to graphics is also
possible. In the long run, we aim to automate the conceptual modeling task by
targeted processing and analysis of natural language text from pertinent scientific
articles. To start the process, a manually-constructed and conceptual ground-truth
model of the kernel of the system under investigation must be developed and verified
by human experts and via execution. This ground truth model will be the starting
point for the automated model construction from literature text. In parallel, based
on this work, we are also developing an automatic model verification framework <xref rid="pone.0051430-Perelman1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>To create and execute the model, we used OPCAT <xref rid="pone.0051430-Yaroker1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. We started by modeling
established knowledge concerning the mRNA transcription re-initiation cycle from
pertinent research papers. The list of facts and their references is presented in
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051430.s003">Table S2</xref>.
Each basic OPM molecular function or molecular structure was defined with the
relevant modeling template using the “role” feature in OPCAT. For the
sake of executing the model, we defined one instance for each object class. We used
the instrument links for defining process precondition in the “halt
execution” mode, which was used for checking the model's consistency and
detecting model errors. In this mode the system halts at any process whose
precondition is not satisfied. Whenever the systems halted, we analyzed the detected
errors and corrected them repeatedly, until the model execution terminated
successfully. After the model was made coherent and executed as expected, the system
may be converted to the “skip process” mode by changing the instrument
links into condition links. During model construction and execution we discovered
the knowledge gaps, recorded them, and classified them. For relevant knowledge gaps
we added to the model the missing details as conjectures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0051430.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Diagram of the Glycolysis metabolic process.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0051430.s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0051430.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Main OPM elements (as used in this work), with their symbols, definitions and
execution semantics.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0051430.s002.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0051430.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Transcription model facts and relevant references.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0051430.s003.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0051430.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Video S1</label><caption><p>Record of a non-deterministic transcription re-initiation process
execution.</p><p>(7Z)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0051430.s004.avi" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0051430.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Video S2</label><caption><p>Record of the transcription cycle model execution with model errors
detected.</p><p>(7Z)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0051430.s005.avi" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0051430-HarelSharvit1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harel-Sharvit</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eldad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haimovich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barkai</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>RNA polymerase
II subunits link transcription and mRNA decay to
translation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>143</volume> (<issue>4</issue>)
<fpage>552</fpage>–<lpage>563</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21074047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2010.10.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Fisher1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henzinger</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Executable cell
biology</article-title>. <source>Nature Biotechnology</source>
<volume>25</volume> (<issue>11</issue>)
<fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt1356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17989686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Machado1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tidor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Modeling
formalisms in systems biology</article-title>. <source>AMB Express</source>
<volume>1</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22141422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/2191-0855-1-45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3285092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Takahashi1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sadamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>E-cell 2:
Multi-platform E-cell simulation system</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>19</volume> (<issue>13</issue>) <fpage>1727</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15593410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Moraru1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moraru</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaff</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slepchenko</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Virtual cell
modelling and simulation software environment</article-title>.
<source>Systems Biology, IET</source>
<volume>2</volume> (<issue>5</issue>)
<fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1049/iet-syb:20080102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2711391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19045830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Gillespie1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Exact stochastic simulation of
coupled chemical reactions</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Physical
Chemistry</source>
<volume>81</volume> (<issue>25</issue>)
<fpage>2340</fpage>–<lpage>2361</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Shmulevich1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shmulevich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lähdesmäki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Astola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The role of certain post classes in
boolean network models of genetic networks</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
<volume>100</volume> (<issue>19</issue>) <fpage>10734</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1534782100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC202352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Li1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The yeast cell-cycle network is
robustly designed</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National
Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>101</volume> (<issue>14</issue>) <fpage>4781</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15037758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0305937101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC387325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Chaouiya1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chaouiya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Petri net modelling of biological
networks</article-title>. <source>Briefings in Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>8</volume> (<issue>4</issue>) <fpage>210</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bib/bbm029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Reddy1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mavrovouniotis</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liebman</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Petri net representations in
metabolic pathways</article-title>. <source>Proc Int Conf Intell Syst Mol
Biol</source>
<volume>1</volume> (<issue>328–36</issue>)
<fpage>96038982</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Kielbassa1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kielbassa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bortfeldt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Modeling of the U1 snRNP assembly
pathway in alternative splicing in human cells using petri
nets</article-title>. <source>Computational Biology and Chemistry</source>
<volume>33</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)
<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.compbiolchem.2008.07.022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Peleg1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Modelling biological processes using
workflow and petri net models</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>18</volume> (<issue>6</issue>) <fpage>825</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.6.825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Jansson1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jirstrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Biochemical modeling with systems
biology graphical notation</article-title>. <source>Drug Discovery
Today</source>
<volume>15</volume> (<issue>9–10</issue>)
<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drudis.2010.02.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-LeNovre1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Novère</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hucka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moodie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The systems
biology graphical notation</article-title>. <source>Nature
Biotechnology</source>
<volume>27</volume> (<issue>8</issue>)
<fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.1558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Efroni1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Efroni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Toward rigorous comprehension of
biological complexity: Modeling, execution, and visualization of thymic
T-cell maturation</article-title>. <source>Genome Research</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>11</issue>) <fpage>2485</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.1215303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC403768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Harel1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Setty</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efroni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swerdlin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Concurrency in biological modeling:
Behavior, execution and visualization</article-title>. <source>Electronic
Notes in Theoretical Computer Science</source>
<volume>194</volume> (<issue>3</issue>)
<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Fisher2"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piterman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Computational insights into
caenorhabditis elegans vulval development</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States
of America</source>
<volume>102</volume> (<issue>6</issue>) <fpage>1951</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0409433102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC548551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Kam1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kam N, Harel D, Kugler H, Marelly R, Pnueli
A, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2003) Formal modeling of C. elegans development: A
scenario-based approach. Computational methods in systems biology; Springer. p.
4–20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Sadot1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sadot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Admanit</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Toward verified
biological models</article-title>. <source>Computational Biology and
Bioinformatics, IEEE/ACM Transactions on</source>
<volume>5</volume> (<issue>2</issue>)
<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1109/TCBB.2007.1076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18451431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Regev1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Regev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Representation and simulation of
biochemical processes using the pi-calculus process algebra</article-title>.
<source>In Proceedings of the Pacific Symposium of Biocomputing
(PSB2001)</source>
<volume>6</volume>:
<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1142/9789814447362_0045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11262964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Cannata1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cannata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omicini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>An agent-oriented conceptual
framework for systems biology</article-title>. <source>Transactions on
Computational Systems Biology III</source>
<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Webb1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cell modeling using agent-based
formalisms</article-title>. <source>Innovations in Applied Artificial
Intelligence</source>
<fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Faeder1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Faeder</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hlavacek</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Rule-based modeling of biochemical
networks</article-title>. <source>Complexity</source>
<volume>10</volume> (<issue>4</issue>)
<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Calzone1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Calzone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fages</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>BIOCHAM: An environment for modeling
biological systems and formalizing experimental knowledge</article-title>.
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>14</issue>)
<fpage>1805</fpage>–<lpage>1807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Dori1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>ViSWeb – The Visual Semantic
Web: Unifying Human and Machine Knowledge Representations with
Object-Process Methodology</article-title>. <source>The VLDB
Journal—The International Journal on Very Large Data Bases</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>)
<fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Dori2"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dori D (2002) Object-process methodology: A
holistic systems paradigm. Springer Verlag. 453 p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Peleg2"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The model multiplicity problem:
Experimenting with real-time specification methods</article-title>.
<source>Software Engineering, IEEE Transactions on</source>
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>8</issue>)
<fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>759</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Yaroker1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yaroker</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<article-title>An OPM Conceptual Model-Based Executable Simulation Environment:
Implementation and Evaluation</article-title>. <source>Systems
Engineering</source> July 2012. In press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Perelman1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perelman L, Somekh J, Dori D (2011) Model
Verification Framework with Application to Molecular Biology. Proceedings of the
2011 symposium on theory of modeling &amp; simulation: DEVS integrative M&amp;S
symposium; Society for Computer Simulation International; p.
140–5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Perelman2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perelman L (2011) Operational Semantics for
Object-Process Methodology. Ph.D. Thesis, November 2011, Technion,
Israel.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Melton1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Querying XML: XQuery, XPath, and
SQL/XML in context</article-title>. <source>Morgan Kaufmann Pub</source>
ISBN 1-55860-711-0.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Alberts1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M,
Roberts K, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2007) Molecular Biology of the Cell (fifth
ed.). Garland. 1392 p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Chen1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mapping the location of TFIIB within
the RNA polymerase II transcription preinitiation complex: A model for the
structure of the PIC</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>119</volume> (<issue>2</issue>)
<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2004.09.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Gene1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gene Ontology website. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/GO.function.guidelines.shtml">http://www.geneontology.org/GO.function.guidelines.shtml</ext-link>.
Accessed 2012 Nov 11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Smith1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The ontology of the gene
ontology</article-title>. <source>AMIA Annual Symposium Proceedings,
2003</source>
<volume>609</volume>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1480173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14728245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Kornberg1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Mediator and the mechanism of
transcriptional activation</article-title>. <source>Trends in Biochemical
Sciences</source>
<volume>30</volume> (<issue>5</issue>)
<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15896740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tibs.2005.03.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Yudkovsky1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yudkovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ranish</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A transcription reinitiation
intermediate that is stabilized by activator</article-title>.
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>408</volume> (<issue>6809</issue>)
<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11089979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35041603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Svejstrup1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Svejstrup</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The RNA polymerase II transcription
cycle: Cycling through chromatin</article-title>. <source>Biochimica Et
Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Gene Structure and Expression</source>
<volume>1677</volume> (<issue>1–3</issue>)
<fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15020047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbaexp.2003.10.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Rani1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ranish</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>RNA polymerase II (pol II)-TFIIF and
pol II-mediator complexes: The major stable pol II complexes and their
activity in transcription initiation and reinitiation</article-title>.
<source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source>
<volume>24</volume> (<issue>4</issue>) <fpage>1709</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.24.4.1709-1720.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC344180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Zawel1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zawel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Recycling of the general
transcription factors during RNA polymerase II
transcription</article-title>. <source>Genes &amp; Development</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>12</issue>) <fpage>1479</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7601352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.9.12.1479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Pokholok1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pokholok</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hannett</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Exchange of RNA polymerase II
initiation and elongation factors during gene expression in
vivo</article-title>. <source>Molecular Cell</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>4</issue>)
<fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11983171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1097-2765(02)00502-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Wang1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fairley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SGE</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phosphorylation of TFIIB links
transcription initiation and termination</article-title>. <source>Current
Biology</source>
<volume>20</volume> (<issue>6</issue>)
<fpage>548</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20226668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cub.2010.01.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2849011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Svejstrup2"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Svejstrup</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fellows</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gnatt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Evidence for a
mediator cycle at the initiation of transcription</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States
of America</source>
<volume>94</volume> (<issue>12</issue>)
<fpage>6075</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9177171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.94.12.6075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC21003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Kobor1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kobor</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omichinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archambault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A Motif Shared
by TFIIF and TFIIB Mediates Their Interaction with the RNA Polymerase II
Carboxy-Terminal Domain Phosphatase Fcp1p in Saccharomyces
cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>20</volume> (<issue>20</issue>)
<fpage>7438</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11003641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.20.20.7438-7449.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC86297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-ESML1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ESML (Enterprise Systems Modeling
Laboratory) website. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://esml.iem.technion.ac.il/?page_id=595">http://esml.iem.technion.ac.il/?page_id=595</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Nov
16.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Dori3"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Conceptual modeling in systems
biology fosters empirical findings: The mRNA lifecycle</article-title>.
<source>PloS One</source>
<volume>2</volume> (<issue>9</issue>) <fpage>e872</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17849002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0000872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1964809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0051430-Friedl1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tempst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The C-terminal domain phosphatase and
transcription elongation activities of FCP1 are regulated by
phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy
of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>100</volume> (<issue>5</issue>) <fpage>2328</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12591939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.2628049100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC151340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>