
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3542819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3542819.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3542819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3542819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349656</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-15984</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Social Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural Geography</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Law</subject><subj-group><subject>Regulations</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Demography</subject><subj-group><subject>Birth Rate</subject><subject>Fertility Rate</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Social Discrimination</subject><subj-group><subject>Gender Discrimination</subject><subject>Social Prejudice</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject><subject>Sexual and Gender Issues</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Divergent Trends in Abortion and Birth Control Practices in Belarus,
Russia and Ukraine</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Birth Control in Belarus, Russia and
Ukraine</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denisov</surname><given-names initials="BP">Boris P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakevich</surname><given-names initials="VI">Victoria I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasilioniene</surname><given-names initials="A">Aiva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Population Economics and
Demography, Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Demography, National Research
University Higher School of Economics, Moscow, Russia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Demographic Data, The Max Planck
Institute for Demographic Research, Rostock, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baradaran</surname><given-names initials="HR">Hamid Reza</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Iran (Islamic Republic
Of)</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>denisov@demography.ru</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Analyzed the data: VS BD. Wrote the paper: VS BD. Edited English text and
performed model building: AJ.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">215208</issue-id><elocation-id>e49986</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2020-12-16 11:16:22.320"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 Denisov et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Denisov et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0049986.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Context</title><p>The last decade witnessed growing differences in abortion dynamics in
Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine despite demographic, social, and historical
similarities of these nations. This paper investigates changes in birth
control practices in the three countries and searches for an explanation of
the diverging trends in abortion.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Official abortion and contraceptive use statistics, provided by national
statistical agencies, were analysed. Respective laws and other legal
documents were examined and compared between the three countries. To
disclose inter-country differences in prevalence of the modern methods of
contraception and its association with major demographic and social factors,
an analysis of data from national sample surveys was performed, including
binary logistic regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The growing gap in abortion rate in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine is a genuine
phenomenon, not a statistical artefact. The examination of abortion and
prevalence of contraception based on official statistics and three national
sample surveys did not reveal any unambiguous factors that could explain
differences in abortion dynamics in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine. However,
it is very likely that the cause of the inter-country discrepancies lies in
contraceptive behavior itself, in adequacies of contraceptive knowledge and
practices. Additionally, large differences in government policies, which are
very important in shaping contraceptive practices of the population, were
detected.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Since the end of the 1990s, the Russian government switched to archaic
ideology in the area of reproductive health and family planning and neglects
evidence-based arguments. Such an extreme turn in the governmental position
is not observed in Belarus or Ukraine. This is an important factor
contributing to the slowdown in the decrease of abortion rates in
Russia.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the National Research University
Higher School of Economics (grant No. 10-01-0076 2010/2011, awarded to Victoria
Sakevich). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and
analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In the former Soviet Union, the three Slavic republics, Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine,
were very much alike not only with respect to culture and economic development but
also in terms of demographic patterns. In spite of the two decades of independent
development, principal demographic characteristics of the three nations are still
very similar. In particular, all three countries experience low total fertility
rates of 1.3–1.5 and high prevalence of one-child families. Fertility in the
three countries was below the replacement level during the last forty years with an
exception for a few years in the 1980s. In times of political and economic turmoil
of the 1990s, Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine experienced a sharp fertility downturn
with a slight recovery in recent years <xref rid="pone.0049986-Shakhotko1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Zakharov1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Pirozhkov1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Goldstein1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Deliberate birth control has long been a mass practice in the region. During the
Soviet times, one of the most extensively used means of birth control was induced
abortion; this is another feature common to all the three countries. The USSR had
the world's highest level in induced abortions <xref rid="pone.0049986-Henshaw1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, and its European republics
stood out with the highest abortion levels within the USSR <xref rid="pone.0049986-Avdeev1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Popov1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Remennick1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Vishnevsky1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Mogilevkina1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Some researchers named
birth-control behavior practiced during the Soviet times as “abortion
culture” <xref rid="pone.0049986-David1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Agadjanian1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Since the beginning of the 1990s, the abortion rates are
steadily declining in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine. However, the speed of this
improvement that was nearly equal in all the three countries during the 1990s
started to diverge in the early 2000s, showing a steeper progress in Ukraine and
especially in Belarus compared to Russia. As a result, the present-day-Russia
exhibits substantially higher abortion rates compared to Belarus and Ukraine.</p><p>Research on birth control in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine is scarce and is mostly
focused on intra-country developments. Reasons for the recent divergence in abortion
rates between the three sister-countries have not been addressed and remain unclear.
The aim of this study is to investigate the phenomenon and to provide its possible
explanations.</p><p>The first hypothesis is that the observed cross-country differences can be attributed
to some changes in regulations concerning provision of abortion services and
reporting of abortion by providers that could induce changes in data collection
systems. We try to find out whether the quality and the completeness of abortion
statistics are comparable between the three countries and thus do not permit the
possibility that the differences in abortion incidence are a simple statistical
artefact. In addition, we look at and compare the country-specific approaches in
collecting official data on contraception.</p><p>The outcome of pregnancy depends on the desired number and timing of births as well
as on knowledge of and accessibility to the means of effective contraception that
would allow the realization of reproductive preferences. Abortion is a consequence
of unintended pregnancy, which results from contraceptive failure or non- use <xref rid="pone.0049986-Bongaarts1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Since
reproductive preferences and norms of family size of the three populations are
similar, and the propensity to terminate unintended pregnancy by abortion is equally
high <xref rid="pone.0049986-Goldberg1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, we
look for the explanation of the diverging abortion rates in characteristics of
contraceptive behavior.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Data and Methods</title><p>This study relies on two types of data: official statistics on abortion and
contraceptive use; and survey data that provide micro-level information about
contraceptive use and variety of its covariates.</p><sec id="s2a"><title>Official abortion statistics</title><p>Abortion statistics are available from several data sources. It appears that
figures, which ought to be the same, often are found to be somewhat different.
The data sources on abortion are as follows:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Publications of the national statistical agencies and the national
ministries of health (MoHs), in Russia during 2004–2011 it was the
Ministry of Health and Social Development.</p></list-item><list-item><p>UN data provided through the UN Demographic Yearbooks <xref rid="pone.0049986-United1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.
Annual abortion figures published by the UN correspond well to the
national data sources with a few exceptions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The WHO European Health for All Database (HFA-DB) <xref rid="pone.0049986-European1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The HFA-DB also
contains statistics on abortions, but provided figures are sometimes
lower compared to those from the above sources. Differences appear
because the WHO uses data supplied by the MoHs, which often include only
abortions performed in medical institutions subordinated to the MoHs
(see below for more details).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Online resource “Abortion statistics and other data –
Johnston's Archive”, which provides published data from
heterogeneous sources <xref rid="pone.0049986-Abortion1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p></list-item></list><p>Notable discrepancies in the data coming from different sources are especially
characteristic of Ukraine. For example, the number of abortions in Ukraine in
2000 is 345.8 thousand according to the HFA-DB, 408.9 thousand according to the
Center for Health Statistics of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine <xref rid="pone.0049986-Center1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, and 434.2
thousand according to the UN Demographic Yearbook <xref rid="pone.0049986-United1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. In such cases, we use the
data which come from the national statistical agencies as the most reliable.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Official statistics on contraception</title><p>We used the national MoHs' data on the prevalence of two types of
contraception: use of intrauterine devices (IUDs) and use of oral contraceptives
(hormonal pills). The MoHs do not collect data on using other methods of
contraception.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Nationally representative sample surveys</title><p>For the analysis of contraceptive practices and their determinants, we employ
survey data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t001">Table 1</xref>). In
the case of Russia, we used data from the second wave of the Generations and
Gender Survey, conducted in 2007 (GGS-Ru-2007). The sampling of GGS-Ru-2007
covers 11,117 respondents aged from 18 to 82 years (each respondent represents
one household) from 32 regions of Russia ensuring the survey representativeness
on a country scale. Further details about the survey may be found on the website
of the Independent Institute for Social Policy (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socpol.ru">www.socpol.ru</ext-link>). The GGS is a
part of the Pan-European Program “Generations and Gender” (see:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://live.unece.org/pau/ggp/Welcome.html">http://live.unece.org/pau/ggp/Welcome.html</ext-link>). Two waves of the
GGS – in 2004 and 2007 – were conducted in Russia by the Independent
Institute for Social Policy. At the moment, it is the only source for nationally
representative data on family planning in Russia. The GGS questionnaire included
a list of contraceptive methods, and respondents, who were younger than 50 and
had a partner at the time of the interview, were asked to indicate methods they
were currently using to prevent pregnancy. The respective question was:
“Are you or your partner/spouse using or doing any of the things listed on
the card to prevent pregnancy at this time?”.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0049986-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Selected characteristics of women having a partner at the time of the
survey, per cent.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0049986-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0049986.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus (N = 4077)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia (N = 2032)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine (N = 4042)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Age</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">under 25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30–34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Mean age</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Children ever
born</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Marital
status</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Currently married</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with a man</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Place of
residence</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rural</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">urban</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">capital city</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Education</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower than higher</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Starting in 1995, the UNICEF carries out the Multiple Indicator Cluster Surveys
(MICS) aiming to monitor the progress in achieving the millennium goals. The
third wave of the MICS, conducted in 2005, included also Belarus and Ukraine.
The MICS is a representative sampling survey at the country level. A
multi-stage, stratified cluster sampling approach was used for the selection of
the survey sample, details can be found on the MICS website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.childinfo.org/mics3_surveys.html">http://www.childinfo.org/mics3_surveys.html</ext-link>). In the case of
Belarus, it is the only known survey that provides information about fertility
control in this country. Ukraine has other surveys that are devoted to or
embrace the issues of reproductive health; the Ukrainian Reproductive Health
Survey (1999) <xref rid="pone.0049986-Kiev1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and the Ukrainian Demographic and Health Survey
(2007) <xref rid="pone.0049986-Ukrainian1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>
can be mentioned among the most important ones. In order to ensure the
comparability of Ukrainian and Belarusian data, we used the Ukrainian MICS data
in the present study.</p><p>In the MICS, questions about contraception were formulated as follows: “Are
you currently doing something or using any method to delay or avoid getting
pregnant? Which method are you using?”. These questions were given to all
women aged 15 to 49, not necessarily having a partner. Since we sought to make
the MICS data as much compatible with the GGS as possible, we did not consider
women without a partner at the time of the survey. The GGS and the MICS use
somewhat different concepts of partnership. In the GGS, partnership means a
stable intimate relationship, regardless whether the partners co-reside or live
separately. In the MICS, a partner is supposed to reside with the respondent in
the same household. For the sake of comparability, we excluded Russian cases
with separate living of partners.</p><p>The dependent variable in our analysis of contraceptive behaviour is use of
modern contraception. We apply binary logistic regression and present the
results in the form of odds ratios. The independent variables include:
women's age, the number of children ever born, place of residence,
education, and marital status. Age is split by groups: ≤25, 25–29,
30–34, 35–39, 40–45, and 45–49. Categories for the
number of children are: 0 (childless), 1, 2, and 3+. Place of residence
comprises three categories: rural, urban, and capital city. Due to limited
information on education available in the Ukrainian data, we make a distinction
only between higher and lower than higher levels of education. Marital status
has two categories: registered marriage and cohabitation. We apply a
fixed-effects model using a pooled dataset with a country-variable being used as
a covariate.</p><p>Unfortunately, none of the three surveys includes questions on abortion.</p><p>Governmental policies have the potential of suppressing abortion as a birth
control method. To find out more about governmental policies in Belarus, Russia,
and Ukraine and their role in shaping contraceptive practice in these countries,
we examine national legal documents and regulations relevant to the field of
reproductive behaviour, reproductive health, and reproductive rights, including
those promoting family planning and contraceptive use.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Trends in Abortion</title><p>According to official statistics in 1990, 4.1 million abortions were registered in
Russia, 1 million in Ukraine, and 261 thousand in Belarus. Relative indicators of
abortion (per 1000 women of reproductive age and per 100 live births) slightly
differed between the three countries, but were very high in all of them at that
time. The corresponding absolute numbers of abortions in 2010 were: 1.2 million, 177
and 33 thousand. The three countries achieved a significant improvement in
reproductive health: in twenty years numbers of abortions dropped by several times.
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t002">Table 2</xref> shows the decrease
in abortions in terms of absolute and relative indicators according to the national
statistical agencies.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0049986-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Official abortion statistics in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0049986-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0049986.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010/1990</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1">Abortions, thousand</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2766</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1676</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1386</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1292</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1186</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1019</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1">Abortions per 1000 women aged
15–49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="left" rowspan="1">Abortions per 100 live births</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note: The data include all types of abortions
(medical/pharmaceutical, vacuum/mini, and surgical).</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Data sources</italic>: Statistical Yearbook of The Republic of
Belarus: 2011/National Statistical Committee of the Republic of Belarus,
Minsk, 2011, p. 228 (in Russian), available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://belstat.gov.by/homep/ru/publications/archive/2011.php">http://belstat.gov.by/homep/ru/publications/archive/2011.php</ext-link>;
Demographic Yearbook of Russia 2010: Statistical Handbook/Federal State
Statistics Service, Moscow, 2010, p. 172 (in Russian), available:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gks.ru/wps/wcm/connect/rosstat/rosstatsite/main/publishing/catalog/statisticCollections/doc_1137674209312">http://www.gks.ru/wps/wcm/connect/rosstat/rosstatsite/main/publishing/catalog/statisticCollections/doc_1137674209312</ext-link>;
Statistical Yearbook of Ukraine: 2010/State Statistics Service of
Ukraine, 2011, p. 465 (in Ukrainian), available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ukrstat.gov.ua/">http://www.ukrstat.gov.ua/</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>However, the rate of decline varied by country (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049986.s001">Figure S1</xref>).
Over the period 1990–2010, the average annual rate of decline in the number of
abortions per 1000 women aged 15 to 49 constitutes eight per cent in Belarus, seven
per cent in Ukraine, and six per cent in Russia. Although in the 1990s the abortion
rates were decreasing at the same pace in all the three countries, in the 2000s this
parallel trend ceases. In Belarus the annual speed of reduction in abortion rates
accelerated to eleven per cent, in Russia it slowed down to five per cent, while in
Ukraine it continued at the same annual speed of six per cent. As a result, today
Russia continues to maintain one of the highest abortion rates among all countries
of the world reporting this kind of statistics <xref rid="pone.0049986-Sedgh1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. In the meantime, Belarus and
Ukraine moved from the top towards the middle of the international ranking; their
abortion levels are comparable to those of the United States, England and Wales,
Sweden, and France.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Birth Control Laws and Regulations</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Abortion legislation</title><p>In November 1920, Soviet Russia became the first country in the world, which
decriminalized and legalized abortions. In 1936, the USSR banned abortions
again, allowing them only on ill-health and medical indications. The ban was
called off in 1955, and no significant changes were introduced in the relevant
USSR legislation since then. Abortion on request was legally permitted up to 12
weeks of gestation, and after 12 weeks it could be performed only for medical
reasons. In 1987, the USSR Ministry of Health authorized an abortion during the
period up to 28 weeks of pregnancy under a range of non-medical conditions <xref rid="pone.0049986-Order1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, including
husband's death during pregnancy, woman's or her husband's
imprisonment, a large current family size (more than 5 children), deprivation of
parental rights, divorce during pregnancy, pregnancy resulting from rape, and
disability of a previously born child.</p><p>Abortion laws in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine did not experience any principal
changes in the post-Soviet period. In all of the three countries, abortion
procedure and related services are included in the basic package of
state-provided health care guarantees. This means that by law, abortion on a
woman's request must be performed in a public health care facility free of
charge.</p><p>In Belarus and Russia, each woman is legally free to choose whether to give birth
or not. Woman's right to this decision is defined in Article 27 of the
Belarusian law “On health care” enacted in 1993 <xref rid="pone.0049986-Law1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, and in Russia
it is stated in Article 36 of the Russian federal law “Fundamentals of the
health care of Russian citizens” passed also in 1993 <xref rid="pone.0049986-Federal1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Both laws assert that
abortion can be performed on woman's request up to 12 weeks of gestation or
up to 22 weeks of pregnancy in the presence of certain social reasons, and at
any stage of pregnancy if there are detrimental medical indications and a
woman's consent for abortion. In Belarus, abortion after 12 weeks of
pregnancy can take place only in a state-owned (not private) health care
institution, whereas in Russia no restrictions exist in this respect. This is
the only legislative difference between Belarus and Russia that we could
identify. In both Belarus and Russia, the Ministry of Health sanctions the list
of medical indications for induced abortion, whereas the Government determines
the list of social indications.</p><p>Post-Soviet Ukraine confirms woman's right to abortion in the law
“Fundamentals of Legislation on Health Care”, Article 50 <xref rid="pone.0049986-The1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, which went
into effect in 1992. According to this law, a woman has a right to request for
termination of her pregnancy up to 12 weeks of gestation. Abortion in the period
between 12 and 22 weeks of pregnancy is allowed under some specific
conditions.</p><p>All in all, differences in the regulations defining abortion procedure are really
minor in the three countries. Before the 12<sup>th</sup> week of gestation,
abortion is allowed on one and the only condition – a woman's
request, and after the 12<sup>th</sup> week it can be performed only in the
presence of medical reasons.</p><p>As far as social reasons are concerned, some differences exist between the
countries. It is noteworthy, however, that induced abortions performed on the
basis of social reasons represent a very small portion of reported abortions
(less than 1 per cent), and their contribution to abortion statistics is
negligible <xref rid="pone.0049986-Population1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Currently, the widest range of social grounds for
late abortion is in force in Belarus. It consists of ten items <xref rid="pone.0049986-Decree1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>: (1)
woman's or her husband's imprisonment; (2) husband's severe
disability; (3) having a child with a disability since childhood; (4)
husband's death during pregnancy; (5) divorce during pregnancy; (6)
decision of a court depriving of parental rights; (7) pregnancy resulted from
rape; (8) attained family size (more than three children); (9) woman's or
her husband's unemployment or job loss; and (10) woman's refugee
status.</p><p>Russia used to have a similar list until 2003, when it was dramatically reduced
from thirteen to four items <xref rid="pone.0049986-Decree2" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>: (1) restriction or deprivation of parental rights;
(2) woman's imprisonment; (3) husband's disability or his death during
pregnancy; (4) rape. In Ukraine, the list of social indications for abortion,
analogous to that active in Belarus until now and in Russian prior to 2003,
existed until 2006. In 2006, Ukraine entirely removed social indications from
the abortion legislation <xref rid="pone.0049986-Decree3" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Before this, in 1996, during “the difficult
period of transition”, the Russian government expanded the list of social
indications for abortion (Government Decree, May 8, 1996 № 567). The
grounds for termination of pregnancy from 12 to 22 weeks could be the following:
husband's disability, husband's death during pregnancy, woman's
or her husband's imprisonment, woman is not married, unemployment of one or
both of the spouses, absence of shelter, family income below the subsistence
minimum, court's decision on restriction or deprivation of parental rights,
dissolution of marriage during pregnancy, rape, status of refugee or forced
migrant, large family size (three children and over), a disabled child. Since
2012 the list of social indications for abortion in Russia contains only one
point (rape).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Access to modern contraception</title><p>There are no any special laws regulating use of contraception in the countries
under study and thus no legal barriers exist to using it. The only contraceptive
method, whose use is subject to some legal regulation, is sterilization. In
Russia, sterilization can be performed to a Russian citizen, who is not younger
than 35 years of age or has at least two children, upon receiving his/her
written request. For medical indications, sterilization is performed
irrespective of the person's age or number of children. According to the
Belarusian law “On health care” <xref rid="pone.0049986-Law1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, the only condition for
obtaining contraceptive sterilization is the legal age of majority (18 years).
Ukrainian citizens have no right to get sterilization for contraceptive
purposes. Surgical sterilization is permitted in Ukraine only for medical
indications, and there are fifteen indications specified for women and three for
men <xref rid="pone.0049986-Order2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>.</p><p>None of the three countries has domestic production of pills. They are all
imported, and therefore their prices are relatively high.</p><p>Free contraception actions happen episodically during manufacturers'
promotion campaigns, anti-AIDS campaigns, and similar events. According to the
Ukrainian DHS (2007) data, 6.4 per cent of female respondents had IUDs inserted
free of charge, and 1.6 per cent of them had access to free oral contraceptives
(pills) <xref rid="pone.0049986-Ukrainian1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Official Statistics on Abortions and Contraception: Data Collection
Systems</title><p>In Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine, most of abortion procedures take place in public
health facilities that are ruled by the national MoHs. These ministries are the
major abortion-service providers. The national statistical agencies
(<italic toggle="yes">Belstat</italic> in Belarus, <italic toggle="yes">Rosstat</italic> in Russia, and
<italic toggle="yes">Derzhstat</italic> in Ukraine) collect data on reported abortions from
the MoHs and combine them with information obtained from medical institutions of
other ministries as well as from private abortion providers. Abortion statistics
provided by the statistical agencies are therefore more complete than the data
possessed by the MoHs.</p><p>In Russia, according to unpublished Rosstat statistics of the 2000s, medical
institutions subordinated to the Ministry of Health and Social Development perform
about 90 per cent of officially registered abortions, and the private sector
contributes another 8–9 per cent. In Belarus and Ukraine, information on the
share of abortions performed by private medical facilities and the completeness of
respective reporting is ambiguous. The authors of the Strategic Assessment
“Abortions and Contraception in Ukraine” <xref rid="pone.0049986-Ministry1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> assume that some regions in
Ukraine do not collect complete data on abortion procedures held in private health
care facilities; at the same time they assert that private services are expensive
and continue to be unaffordable for the majority of the population. Information
about the quality of abortion reporting and registration in Belarus is
contradictory. Some experts say <xref rid="pone.0049986-UNFPA1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>: “&lt;…&gt; collection of relevant statistical
data is not yet adjusted to meet the development of paid gynaecological services,
and part of early pregnancies terminated by vacuum aspiration in private medical
centres may miss the registration”. The latter assumption is seemingly based
on the observed decline in vacuum aspiration abortions performed in public health
facilities in recent years. Other experts believe that the count of abortions
performed in the private sector is nearly complete in Belarus <xref rid="pone.0049986-Shakhotko2" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p><p>Philipov et al. <xref rid="pone.0049986-Philipov1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> assessed the reliability and the completeness of Russian
abortion statistics by comparing official statistical data on abortions with data
from several regional surveys, conducted in 1988/1989, 1996, and 2000. The study
focused on abortions performed within two years prior to the survey and found no
significant differences between the survey results and official figures. It proves
that in spite of growing private medical services, official abortion statistics in
Russia are reliable.</p><p>Reliability of the official abortion statistics in Ukraine is also supported by
surveys. Data from two nationally representative population surveys, conducted in
Ukraine in 1999 and 2007, showed quite good matching with officially reported
abortion figures. In other words, abortion estimates generated using two different
data sources – survey reporting and routine statistical registration –
show similar values.</p><p>Abortion statistics possessed by the MoH are based on information gathered in
specific accounting forms, which are annually filled out by clinics and other
medical facilities. The form asks to report not only induced abortions, but also
spontaneous (miscarriages), criminal (by definition, criminal abortion is any
intervention aiming to terminate pregnancy that takes place outside a special
facility authorized to perform an abortion), as well as unspecified abortions
(abortions outside a clinic that are not proved to be criminal while the woman did
not have her pregnancy registered in a clinic). The extended definition of abortion
is the legacy of the USSR data collection. In Russia, as reported by the MHSD,
spontaneous abortions accounted for more than 16 per cent of the total number of
abortions (using the extended definition) registered in 2010, and unspecified
abortions constituted 5 per cent. The respective figures for Ukraine were about 7
and 19 per cent in 2007 <xref rid="pone.0049986-Ministry1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. It should be mentioned that during the 1990s this
proportion in Ukraine ranged from four to eight per cent <xref rid="pone.0049986-Zhilka1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The ban of social indications
for later term abortions could have caused a higher proportion of unspecified
abortions in 2007 than in the 1990s.</p><p>Due to the continued use of the extended definition of abortion, abortion rates in
Belarus, Russia and Ukraine are misleadingly inflated and should be used with
caution for international comparisons. A proper comparative analysis requires that
the above mentioned extensions (e.g., spontaneous and unspecified) are subtracted.
The problem is that data on spontaneous and other types of abortions that take place
without medical supervision are usually not published. On the other hand, one could
argue that the inclusion of these extensions into official abortion statistics
compensates possible undercount of abortions performed in the private sector.</p><p>To sum up, our analysis shows that the data collection systems in Belarus, Russia and
Ukraine are similar. The registered levels of abortion can be considered reliable.
The fact that they share similar advantages and suffer from similar deficiencies
suggests that official abortion statistics of these countries are of comparable
quality and completeness. Consequently, we draw a conclusion that the divergence
observed in the post-Soviet abortion trends in these countries is a genuine
phenomenon.</p><p>Regarding official statistics on contraception, this information in Belarus, Russia
and Ukraine is collected via medical networks associated with the MoH only. The MoHs
compile data on patients' use of two types of contraception: intrauterine
devices (IUDs) and oral contraceptives (hormonal pills). These data can be biased
because a variety of pills and other means of contraception are available without
doctor's prescription, and there is a growing network of private institutions
providing family planning services. Prevalence of contraceptives among patients of
public medical networks may therefore differ from corresponding prevalence in the
general population. The MoH data are useful, however, as they give an insight into
how contraceptive use was changing over time in the three countries.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Contraceptive Behavior</title><sec id="s6a"><title>Contraceptive use in light of official statistics</title><p>Official statistics on contraception collected by the MoHs shows that proportions
of women practicing hormonal contraception (pills) were steadily growing in
Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine since the early 1990s (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049986.s002">Figure S2</xref>).
Almost throughout the entire period of 1990–2010, the highest level of
hormonal contraceptive use was registered in Belarus, which goes well in line
with the downward trend observed in abortion rates in this country. Between 1990
and 2010, the proportion of Belarusian women (aged 15–49) using hormonal
contraceptives increased from 5 to 20 per cent, with the most rapid increase
taking place in the early 2000s. In Ukraine, hormonal contraceptive use was
rather low before the 2000s – in the second half of the 1990s it was lower
than in Belarus and Russia. A sharp increase in use of pills occurred at the
beginning of the 2000s, and in 2009 it reached 19 per cent. Russia remains far
behind Belarus and Ukraine, despite the promising increase experienced over the
1990s. In 2010, the level of hormonal contraceptive use in Russia was 12 per
cent, which is substantially lower compared to the other two countries.</p><p>As regards the prevalence of IUDs, it was among the most commonly used modern
contraceptive methods in the late USSR. Its high popularity was a result of the
aggressive promotion campaign implemented by the Ministry of Heath of the USSR
in the 1980s. After the collapse of the USSR, a variety of contraceptives
available on the market has significantly increased, and this method became
noticeably less common. In all the three countries under study, the rise in IUD
use persisted into the early 1990s, and then went down and levelled off in the
2000s. Throughout the 1990s and the 2000s, Belarus experienced the highest
prevalence of IUDs. The trends in IUD use in Russia and Ukraine differed in the
1990s (with Russia showing higher rates of IUD prevalence), but in the 2000s
they converged.</p><p>IUD and pills are mutually exclusive. If one combines the use of hormonal
contraceptives with use of IUDs, one finds that the total contraceptive
prevalence increased from 28 to 41 per cent in Belarus and from 18 to 32 per
cent in Ukraine over the observed period of 1990–2010, whereas in Russia
it has changed only slightly (25 per cent in 2010 versus 19–22 per cent in
the early 1990s).</p></sec><sec id="s6b"><title>Contraceptive prevalence as shown by survey data</title><p>The data from the national sample surveys, which were carried out at
approximately the same time in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine, show high levels of
contraceptive use in all the three countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t003">Table 3</xref>). The highest proportion of women
having a partner and using any contraceptive method was found in Russia (77 per
cent); Belarus shows a slightly lower indicator (74 per cent), whereas Ukraine
holds the last place in this respect (69 per cent). This level of contraceptive
prevalence is similar to that typical of western countries such as France, the
Netherlands, Germany, Portugal, or USA <xref rid="pone.0049986-United2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>
</p><table-wrap id="pone-0049986-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Contraceptive prevalence among women aged 15 to 49 who have a
partner, in per cent.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0049986-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0049986.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus, 2005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia, 2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine, 2005</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any method</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.4 (72.9–75.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3 (75.6–79.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8 (67.2–70.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IUD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6 (25.1–28.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4 (19.7–23.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0 (25.5–28.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pill</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (9.7–11.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (11.1–13.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 (10.2–12.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6 (20.2–22.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5 (24.6–28.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2 (24.7–27.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sterilization</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.0–3.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.7–3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Withdrawal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3 (17.0–19.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 (10.9–13.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 (11.3–13.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Periodic abstinence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 (8.2–10.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (12.5–15.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (5.6–7.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (2.2–3.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (6.7–8.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (2.9–4.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No method</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 (24.2–27.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8 (20.1–23.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 (29.6–32.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No answer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.4–1.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4077</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2032</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4042</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Notes</italic></bold>: Respondents could indicate more
than one method; therefore the sum does not equal 100%. Since
we excluded pregnant women from our study, the results in this table
do not coincide with those published in the official national MICS
reports.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Numbers in the parentheses are 95% confidence intervals.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>After standardization by age (the standard is the average population
structure of the three samples), contraceptive prevalence
constitutes 74.3 per sent in Belarus, 77.1 per sent in Russia, and
69.0 per sent in Ukraine.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Source</italic></bold>: If not stated otherwise, the
estimates presented in this and other tables in this section are
based on the data from the Multiple Indicator Cluster Surveys (2005)
for Belarus and Ukraine and on the data from the Generations and
Gender Survey (2007) for Russia.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The Belarusian, Russian, and Ukrainian samples are rather similar in terms of the
total contraceptive prevalence as well as of the composition of contraceptive
methods. Two thirds of married or cohabiting women report to practice modern
contraception. The most popular contraceptive methods in all the three countries
are condom and intrauterine device (the first choice in Russia is condom, while
in Belarus and Ukraine it is IUD) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t003">Table 3</xref>). The third most common method in
Russia is the calendar method, whereas in Belarus and Ukraine it is withdrawal
(<italic toggle="yes">coitus interruptus</italic>); both these methods are considered
ineffective. The pill is the fourth in the ranking: it is used by 11 per cent of
women in Belarus and Ukraine and by 12.5 per cent in Russia. These results are
different from official statistics (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049986.s002">Figure S2</xref>), because official data on the use
of pills count in all women having visited a doctor in a given year, while we
restrict our sample to women in a union (marital or non-marital) only. The use
of pills is notably lower in our studied countries than in other developed
countries (e.g., in Western Europe it is 46 per cent on average <xref rid="pone.0049986-United2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>). Other
types of hormonal contraception (injections, implants) are very rarely used in
the three countries – by less than 0.5 per cent of women in union.</p><p>The world's most popular method of contraception – sterilization
– has not gained high popularity in Belarus, Russia or Ukraine. According
to the survey data, only 2.5 per cent of female respondents reported to have
undergone sterilization procedure in Belarus, 2.3 per cent – in Russia,
and 1.3 per cent – in Ukraine. Cases of male sterilization are extremely
rare. The analysis of the Russian GGS data suggests that not all female
respondents might have correctly understood the question concerning this method.
There are grounds for suspecting that the prevalence of contraceptive
sterilization might actually be even lower than shown by the survey results
<xref rid="pone.0049986-Denisov1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>.</p><p>About one fifth of any method users in the three countries reported the
simultaneous use of several contraceptive methods. Some combinations of methods
indicated by one and the same woman, such as the simultaneous use of pills and
implants or IUDs and pills, or IUDs and sterilization, make no sense. The
highest proportion of women reporting combined use of four or more methods is
found in Russia (1.3%); this proportion in Ukraine is 0.9%, and
0.5% in Belarus. The reporting of the use of multiple methods may reflect
frequent migration from one method to another that reduces method effectiveness
<xref rid="pone.0049986-Frost1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t004">Table 4</xref> shows the
distribution of women by the most effective method currently used, i.e. if the
respondent indicated more than one method, only the most effective one was
considered. In defining method effectiveness, we relied on the ranking by
Trussell <xref rid="pone.0049986-Trussell1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. It is important to note that this adjustment
slightly changes the composition of methods. Since modern and traditional
contraceptive methods are often used in a combination, it certainly increases
the proportion of more efficient modern methods and correspondingly reduces the
proportion of traditional methods. The analysis shows that the most commonly
used methods in the three countries are intrauterine devices and condoms: almost
half of women of reproductive age who have a partner use either one or the other
method. The share of IUDs in Belarus and Ukraine is 27 per cent, while in Russia
it makes 21 per cent. The respective figures for condom use are 18 per cent in
Belarus, 21 per cent in Ukraine, and 23 per cent in Russia. According to
Trussell's ranking where IUD is considered a more effective method than
condom, the composition of methods typical for Russia is less effective.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0049986-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Distribution of women aged 15 to 49 who have a partner by the most
effective contraceptive method out of those currently used, in per
cent.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0049986-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0049986.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus, 2005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia, 2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine, 2005</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any method</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.4 (72.9–75.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.3 (75.6–79.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8 (67.2–70.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IUD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6 (25.1–28.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4 (19.7–23.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0 (25.5–28.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condom</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 (16.7–19.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 (21.6–25.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (19.9–22.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pill</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4 (9.4–11.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (10.6–13.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 (9.3–11.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sterilization</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 (2.0–3.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.7–3.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.9–1.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Periodic abstinence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (4.9–6.4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (6.5–8.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (2.4–3.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Withdrawal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (8.9–10.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (4.8–6.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4 (3.7–5.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (1.1–1.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (3.9–5.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (1.1–1.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern method (including in combination with
traditional one)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9 (56.3–59.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.8 (58.8–62.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.0 (59.3–62.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traditional method only</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (15.3–17.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (14.9–18.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (6.9–8.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No method</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6 (24.2–27.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8 (20.1–23.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 (29.6–32.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No answer</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.4–1.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">Notes</italic></bold>: Method effectiveness is
evaluated using Trussell's ranking <xref rid="pone.0049986-Trussell1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>Numbers in parentheses are 95% confidence intervals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The proportion of couples using only traditional methods of contraception in
Belarusian and Russian samples constitutes 16.5 per cent; this proportion is
much higher than what is reported in Western European countries. In Ukraine, it
is twice as low, about 8 per cent only, but in the 1990s, the proportion of
users of traditional contraceptive methods was substantially higher in Ukraine
<xref rid="pone.0049986-Kiev1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Mogilevkina2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.
Moreover, Ukraine has the largest proportion of non-users among the three
countries. Unfortunately, the surveys did not include questions about reasons
for not using any contraception.</p><p>The analysis shows that the pattern of contraceptive behaviour considerably
varies depending on the age of women (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049986.s003">Figure S3</xref>).Young women are more likely to use
condom or pills; IUD is more common among women aged 30 to 44; and after the age
40, there is a significant proportion of women who tend to rely on traditional
methods (the latter is less pronounced in Ukraine though).</p><p>In addition, we tried to estimate <italic toggle="yes">the unmet need for family
planning</italic>, that is, to identify the proportion of couples who were
fertile, did not wish to have a child in the near future, and did not practice
any means of pregnancy prevention. In order to calculate this indicator for
Russia, we used the following GGS questions: “Do you intend to have
a/another child during the next three years?”, “Is it possible for
you, yourself, to have a/another baby, if you wanted it?”, and “Do
you think it would be physically possible for your current partner/spouse to
have a child of his own, if he wanted to?”. In the MICS, questions
addressing these issues were slightly differently formulated. We focused on the
questions allowing to distinguish respondents who could not get pregnant due to
health-related reasons and those who wanted to get a child in the near future.
For a better comparability with the Russian data, we selected those respondents,
who were planning to have a child in 1–2 years or “soon”. In
other words, we selected women, who were at the risk of conception and
intentionally did not use any contraception. The Ukrainian MICS additionally
contained a question: “What do you think, are you physically able to
become pregnant now?”, which helped to produce a more accurate estimate
for this country as compared with Belarus.</p><p>According to our estimation, the lowest unmet need for family planning,
experienced by 13 per cent of couples, is in Russia. In Belarus, it is
experienced by 16 per cent of couples, and in Ukraine – by 18 per cent.
After standardization by age, the corresponding proportions remain almost
unchanged. Irrespective of the observed differences, the unmet need in these
countries is rather high by the world standards.</p><p>Although the wording of the questions and therefore the way of how the index of
unmet need is estimated vary between the three countries, the unmet need in
Russia is not likely to be higher than in Belarus and Ukraine. This brings us to
a paradox – along with the highest level of abortions, Russia does not
exhibit the highest unmet need for family planning.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0049986-t005">Table 5</xref> reports the results
from binary logistic regression, where the dependent variable is use of any
modern contraceptive method. A pooled dataset combining all the three samples is
used. Model 1 presents the effect of each variable separately, adjusted for age
only. Model 2 controls for all the variables, including the age.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0049986-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049986.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals from logistic
regression linking use of modern contraceptives to selected
determinants.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0049986-t005-5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0049986.t005.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model 2</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Country</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belarus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">*</xref> (1.03–1.32)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">*</xref> (1.02–1.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">**</xref> (0.77–0.95)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.74–0.92)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Number of children ever
born</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.75–1.43)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.79–1.55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.66–1.26)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.77–1.53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">*</xref> (0.49–0.99)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.65–1.35)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Place of
residence</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">***</xref> (1.45–1.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">***</xref> (1.36–1.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capital city</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">***</xref> (1.27–1.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">**</xref> (1.12–1.58)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Education</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower than higher education</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Higher education</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">***</xref> (1.18–144)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">***</xref> (1.11–1.37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Type of union</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marriage</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (ref.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohabitation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.80–1.12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 (0.74–1.05)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt109"><label>***</label><p>p&lt;0.001,</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label>**</label><p>p&lt;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="nt112"><label/><p>Women in union who do not want to have children in the next three
years and are physically able to become pregnant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The logistic regression shows that women in Russia are more likely to use modern
contraceptives than women in Belarus or Ukraine. As expected, the odds of modern
contraception use decrease after age 40 (not shown in the table; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0049986.s003">Figure S3</xref>).
The number of children does not appear to have a significant effect. Residence
in rural area predicts lower use of modern contraception. Use of modern
contraception is significantly higher for women with higher education. A
significant association between contraceptive use and the level of education was
also found in other studies on Russia <xref rid="pone.0049986-Perlman1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-Regushevskaya1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Finally, the type
of union does not show any significant effect on the dependent variable.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>The Role of Family Planning Policies</title><p>Governmental policies play an important role in shaping contraceptive practices as
well as achieving the shift from abortion to contraception being used for family
planning purposes. Such policies promote the ideology of so-called planned
parenthood, which assumes that couples and individuals make conscious efforts to
control the number and spacing of births to make sure that all pregnancies are
intended and all children are wanted. Regarding governmental policies, Belarus,
Russia, and Ukraine considerably differ.</p><p>Ukraine pursues the most favourable and the most consistent with the above ideology
policies. The development of national-level family planning programs began in the
1990s. In 1995, the Cabinet of Ministers approved the national target program named
“Family Planning” (No. 736, September 13, 1995), outlining the action
plan for the period until 2000. Further, in 2001, a Presidential Decree (No.
203/2001, March 26, 2011) was issued, which established the national program
“Reproductive Health 2001–2005”. Finally, in 2006, the Cabinet of
Ministers set the program “Reproductive Health of the Nation” for the
period until 2015 (No. 1849, December 27, 2006). The implementation of these
programs involved establishing a network of centres and clinics providing
reproductive health and family planning services as well as setting up
youth-friendly health facilities. These programs were successful in promoting
responsible sexual behaviour and raising awareness and knowledge of modern
contraceptive methods <xref rid="pone.0049986-UNFPA1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. The Ukrainian Government subsidizes supply of modern
contraceptives to vulnerable population groups, including economically disadvantaged
women, women with serious heath problems, and young people. There are special budget
allocations for these expenditures <xref rid="pone.0049986-Ministry1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p><p>Although Belarus demonstrates the best achievements in reducing abortion incidence,
no special programs that would promote family planning were initiated there.
Reproductive health, sexual education, and other related issues were addressed in
more general documents such as the national program “Women of the Republic of
Belarus” or “The National Plan of Action for the Advancement of Women
1996–2000”. The closest to the subject of family planning is “The
National Program of Planned Pregnancy and Prevention of Miscarriage,
2008–2010”, adopted in Belarus in 2008 (Order of the Ministry of Health
of the Republic of Belarus No.42, January 23, 2008). This program aims at promoting
use of and improving access to a wider variety of contraceptives; providing free
contraception to women and adolescents from socially disadvantaged families and also
those with medical contraindications to pregnancy; as well as establishing
youth-friendly health facilities, which would include pregnancy and STD prevention
counselling.</p><p>Russia was changing its stance in relation to family planning over time. In the early
1990s, the wave of democratic reforms taking place in Russia helped to adopt the
federal target program “Family Planning”. In 1994, this program gained
the support of the President of Russia (Decree No. 1696, August 18, 1994) and was
integrated into the program called “Children of Russia”. The program
“Family Planning” was designed to fundamentally change societal
attitudes towards human reproductive rights and to create conditions for their
realization. For the implementation of this program, the Russian Ministry of Health
established a large network of centres for family planning and reproduction. Many
professionals attended special advanced courses and received extensive training in
related areas. A great deal of effort was expended to improve sexual culture of the
Russian population; expert groups developed programs of sexual education. These
activities encountered a strong resistance from some groups of the society. The
Russian State Duma (formed mainly by communists at that time) supported the campaign
against the program, and its funding was excluded from the state budget in 1998.
Programs of sexual education were never introduced in schools.</p><p>The official position of the Government of Russia on having the right to family
planning and reproductive choice as well as to safe, comfortable, and joyful sexual
life has always been and remains ambiguous. Two decades ago, the segments of society
holding traditionalist and fundamentalist views were either invisible or even
non-existent. Today, they constitute an influential social force, which stirs up
negative associations with and agitates against family planning. The belief in the
myth that birth control is synonymous to low fertility and that broader access to
family planning services inevitably leads to fertility reduction has become rather
widespread. This myth has not only become part of folk common-sense, but also has
successfully penetrated the level of decision makers. The resumption of a program,
similar to “Family planning”, is hardly possible given the current
pronatalist course proclaimed by the Government of Russia. On the contrary, many of
the centres for family planning and reproduction created in the 1990s are gradually
being closed due to lack of funding. Furthermore, by spreading fake information
about abortion and its consequences for health as well as arguing about its moral
unacceptability, the Government seems to be moving towards the decision that would
restrict access to abortion <xref rid="pone.0049986-Denisov2" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0049986-European2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. At the same time, the promotion of alternatives to
abortion, i.e. contraception, is very limited.</p><p>The Orthodox Church agitates extensively against advances in reproductive health and
rights, and this is typical of all the three countries under study. However, in
Russia, the Orthodox Church seems to exert an especially strong influence: it
successfully penetrated the public health decision-making process. The following is
a quotation from the address by the Minister of Health and Social Development to
participants of the second All-Russian Congress of Russian Orthodox doctors:
“One of the important moments, where the role of the Church is especially
significant, is the protection of family traditions and values and the prevention of
and the reduction of abortions. We need to further pursue the campaign notifying
about the harm caused to health by abortion, to inform people, particularly the
youth, about potential complications, to talk about the psychological impact of
abortion on women, and to create a proper mental attitude to motherhood” <xref rid="pone.0049986-Opening1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Moreover, the
Foundation for Socio-Cultural Initiatives, headed by the First Lady of Russia,
conducts an annual campaign called “Give me life!” aiming at protecting
unborn children; it is promoted as a week against abortion <xref rid="pone.0049986-Social1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. All these trends do not
contribute to the improvement of contraceptive use in Russia.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Discussion and Conclusions</title><p>The hypothesis that the differences in abortion observed between Russia on the one
hand and Belarus and Ukraine on the other hand is a statistical artefact was not
confirmed. Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine have liberal abortion laws and inter-country
differences in the regulations defining performance of abortion are minor. There are
no legal barriers to availability or use of modern contraceptives in all these
countries.</p><p>The data collection systems, as far as abortion statistics is concerned, are similar
in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine. They share the same or at least similar advantages
and deficiencies, and the produced data are therefore of comparable quality and
completeness. This finding allows to conclude that the divergence observed in the
post-Soviet abortion trends in these countries is a genuine phenomenon.</p><p>Official statistics on the use of pills and IUD explain to some extent why abortion
incidence in Belarus and Ukraine is lower than that in Russia. This suggests that
Belarusian and Ukrainian women who are eventually visiting medical facilities are
more actively using the two modern methods compared to their Russian counterparts.
It is possible that the medical systems in Belarus and Ukraine are more committed to
promoting and explaining the modern contraceptive methods among women which could
lead to more consistent and qualified use of these methods.</p><p>This result contradicts to our findings based on the sample surveys. After adjustment
for covariates, the Russian sample experiences higher odds of modern contraception
(although the Russian method mix is slightly less efficient). This finding is
unexpected given the higher level of abortion in Russia. It is also surprising that
low fertility and rapidly declining abortion rates in Belarus and Ukraine go
together with the inefficient structure of contraceptive methods; this fact
attracted attention of other researchers too <xref rid="pone.0049986-Levchuk1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p><p>The paradoxical combination of higher contraceptive prevalence and higher abortion
rate in Russia than in Ukraine was also noticed in the results of the 1999 surveys
<xref rid="pone.0049986-Centers1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. It is
possible that Russian surveys exacerbate contraceptive prevalence due to propensity
of Russian women to embellish their situation, sincerely confusing an intention to
use or irregular use of a method with its proper use. However, Belarusian and
Ukrainian surveys could face the same problem.</p><p>Thus, the survey data did not give an explanation of why Belarus and Ukraine
experience greater progress in reducing abortion than Russia.</p><p>In our opinion, the main source of the inter-country discrepancies lies in
contraceptive behavior itself, in adequacy of contraceptive knowledge and practices.
In other words, it is important that women who use modern contraception do it in a
proper way. It might be that higher contraceptive culture in Belarus and Ukraine in
comparison to Russia leads to inter-country differences in rates of contraceptive
failure. This explanation agrees with possible role of medical professionals that
could underlie the growing gap between Russia and the two other Slavic countries in
the use of pills and IUD.</p><p>The proportion of couples using traditional methods of contraception in these three
countries is higher than what is reported in Western European countries. It is
noteworthy that effectiveness of traditional methods can be very high: in the case
of consistent and correct use, the failure rate is only 4–5 per cent <xref rid="pone.0049986-Trussell1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The already
mentioned Reproductive Health Surveys carried out in 1999 recorded higher failure
rates in Russia than in Ukraine. Overall 12-month contraceptive failure rates were
12 per cent in Russia and 9 per cent in Ukraine, including 8 and 6 per cent
respectively for pills, 23 and 16 per cent for periodic abstinence, 17 and 12 per
cent for withdrawal <xref rid="pone.0049986-Centers1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In order to better understand the existing differences
in the quality of contraceptive use, a survey should have other than the MICS/GGS
design.</p><p>Differences in the state-implemented family planning policies in the three countries
could also contribute to the explanation of the higher abortion rate in Russia. The
Russian official (on the governmental level) stance on family planning has changed
in the recent years to a highly traditional and pronatalist one. The myth that birth
control is synonymous to low fertility and that better access to family planning
services inevitably leads to fertility reduction is very strong in Russia. Such an
extreme turn in the governmental position regarding family planning is not observed
in Belarus or Ukraine.</p><p>The way in which information about contraception is obtained plays a significant role
in efficiency of its use. The quality of information obtained from the Internet and
other types of mass media, friends and acquaintances significantly differs from
professional advice. Lack of medical services, sexuality education, and family
planning promotion can result in inefficient contraceptive use and increase in the
risk of unwanted pregnancy.</p><p>The Orthodox Church extensively campaigns against advances in reproductive health and
rights. This campaign covers all the three countries. However, in Russia the church
successfully penetrated the decision making process in public health, and its
overall influence on the Russian government is particularly strong.</p><p>The latest developments related to family planning in Russia, which involve
introduction of further legal restrictions in access to abortion, confirmed our
guesstimates about the direction of the Russian governmental policies. We do not
analyze these legal changes in this paper, but if our reasoning is correct, they
will bring about a further growth in the abortion gap between the countries and may
even terminate the ongoing decrease of abortion indicators in Russia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0049986.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Rates of decline in abortion in Belarus, Russia, and Ukraine, per 1000
women aged 15–49.
1990 = 100%.</bold>
</p><p>(PNG)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0049986.s001.png" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0049986.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Women aged 15–49 using IUD and hormonal contraception (pills), in
per cent. MoHs data.</bold>
</p><p>(PNG)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0049986.s002.png" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0049986.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Age patterns of contraceptive use of women with a partner by method, in
per cent.</bold> Source: Multiple Indicator Cluster Surveys (2005) for
Belarus and Ukraine and the Generations and Gender Survey (2007) for
Russia.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0049986.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank our colleagues – I. Kurillo, N. Levchuk, L. Shakhotko,
V. Shkolnikov, V. Steshenko, and A. Vishnevsky – for their valuable feedback
and inspiring ideas. The opinions expressed in this paper are those of the authors.
The study was implemented in the framework of the Basic Research Program at the
National Research University Higher School of Economics (HSE) in 2011.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0049986-Shakhotko1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shakhotko LP (2009) The model of
demographic development of Republic of Belarus. Minsk: Belaruskaya navuka (in
Russian).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Zakharov1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zakharov SV (2011) Is the growth of number
of births in Russia over? Demoscope Weekly (Feb 7–20): 453–454. (In
Russian). Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2011/0453/tema01.php">http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2011/0453/tema01.php</ext-link>. Accessed 2012
Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Pirozhkov1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pirozhkov SI, Safarova GL (2010) Ukraine
and Russia in a demographic dimension. Demoscope Weekly (Jan. 1–24):
405–406. (In Russian). Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2010/0405/tema04.php">http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2010/0405/tema04.php</ext-link>. Accessed 2012
Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Goldstein1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sobotka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jasilionene</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The End of “Lowest-Low”
Fertility?</article-title>
<source>Population and Development Review</source>
<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>)
<fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>699</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Henshaw1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henshaw</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Induced Abortion: A Worldwide
Perspective</article-title>. <source>Family Planning Perspectives</source>
<volume>18</volume> (<issue>6</issue>)
<fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3817120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Avdeev1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Avdeev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Troitskaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The History of Abortion Statistics in
Russia and the USSR from 1900 to 1991</article-title>. <source>Population:
An English Selection</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Popov1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Family Planning and Induced Abortion
in the USSR: Basic Health and Demographic Characteristics</article-title>.
<source>Studies in Family Planning</source>
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>6</issue>)
<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1792676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Remennick1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Remennick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology and determinants of
induced abortion in the U.S.S.R</article-title>. <source>Social Science and
Medicine</source>
<volume>33</volume> (<issue>7</issue>)
<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1948176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0277-9536(91)90389-t</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Vishnevsky1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vishnevsky AG, editor (2006) Demographic
modernization of Russia, 1900–2000. Moscow: Novoye izdatel'stvo. (In
Russian).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Mogilevkina1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mogilevkina</surname></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Induced
abortions and childbirths: trends in Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Russia,
Byelorussia and the Ukraine during 1970 to 1994</article-title>.
<source>Acta Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandlnavica</source>
<volume>75</volume>:
<fpage>908</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/00016349609055026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9003091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-David1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">David HP, Popov AA (1999) Russian
Federation and USSR Successor States. In: David HP, Skilogianis J, editors. From
Abortion to Contraception: A Resource to Public Policies and Reproductive
Behavior in Central and Eastern Europe from 1917 to the. Westport, CT: Greenwood
Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Agadjanian1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Agadjanian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Is “abortion culture”
fading in the former Soviet Union? Views about abortion and contraception in
Kazakhstan</article-title>. <source>Studies in Family Planning</source>
<volume>33</volume> (<issue>3</issue>)
<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12385085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1728-4465.2002.00237.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Bongaarts1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bongaarts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westoff</surname><given-names>ChF</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The potential role of contraception
in reducing abortion</article-title>. <source>Studies in Family
Planning</source>
<volume>31</volume> (<issue>3</issue>)
<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11020931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1728-4465.2000.00193.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Goldberg1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goldberg HI, Serbanescu F (2001)
Relationships Between Abortion and Contraception in Republics of the Former
Soviet Union, Prepared for the XXIV General Conference of the International
Union for the Scientific Study of Population, Salvador, Brazil, 18–24
August, 2001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-United1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Demographic Yearbooks.
Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/dyb/2000_round.htm">http://unstats.un.org/unsd/demographic/products/dyb/2000_round.htm</ext-link>.
Accessed 2012 Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-European1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European health for all database, WHO
Regional Office for Europe, Copenhagen, Denmark. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://data.euro.who.int/hfadb/">http://data.euro.who.int/hfadb/</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Oct
29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Abortion1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abortion statistics and other data by Wm.
Robert Johnston. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/policy/abortion/index.html">http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/policy/abortion/index.html</ext-link>.
Accessed 2012 Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Center1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Center for Medical Statistics of the
Ministry of Health of Ukraine (in Ukrainian). Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medstat.gov.ua/ukr/statreports/access.html?id=13">http://medstat.gov.ua/ukr/statreports/access.html?id=13</ext-link>.
Accessed 2012 Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Kiev1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kiev International Institute of Sociology
(KIIS), Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), and United States
Agency for International Development (USAID) (2001) 1999 Ukraine Reproductive
Health Survey. Ukraine: Kiev International Institute of
Sociology.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Ukrainian1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ukrainian Center for Social Reforms (UCSR),
State Statistical Committee (SSC) [Ukraine], Ministry of Health (MoH)
[Ukraine], and Macro International Inc. (2008) Ukraine Demographic and
Health Survey 2007. Calverton, MD: UCSR and Macro
International.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Sedgh1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sedgh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henshaw</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bankole</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Legal Abortion Worldwide in 2008:
Levels and Recent Trends</article-title>. <source>International Perspectives
on Sexual and Reproductive Health</source>
<volume>37</volume> (<issue>2</issue>)
<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21757423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1363/3708411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Order1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Order of the USSR Ministry of Health
№ 1342, 31 December 1987.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Law1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Law of the Republic of Belarus №
2435-XII, 18 June 1993.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Federal1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Federal Law № 5487-1, 22 July 1993.
From 2012 the new law “About the Fundamentals of Healthcare of the
Citizens in the Russian Federation” comes into force in Russia, but the
criteria for legal abortion are not changed substantially.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-The1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Law of Ukraine № 2801-XII, 19
November 1992.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Population1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Population of Russia 2009 (2011) Annual
demographic report. Moscow: Higher School of Economics, p.136 (in
Russian).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Decree1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Decree of the Council of Ministers of the
Republic of Belarus № 1580, 23 October 2008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Decree2"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Decree of the Government of the Russian
Federation № 485, 11 August 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Decree3"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Decree of the Council of Ministers of
Ukraine № 144, 15 February 2006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Order2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Order of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine
№121, 6 July 1994.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Ministry1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministry of Health of Ukraine, WHO (2008)
Abortions and Contraception in Ukraine. Strategic Assessment of Questions,
Policy, Programmes and Researches. Report and Recommendations,
Kiev.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-UNFPA1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFPA (2004) Belarus: Ten Years after
Cairo. National Population Report 2004. Minsk: UNFPA. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://un.by/pdf/nr2004e.pdf">http://un.by/pdf/nr2004e.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Oct
29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Shakhotko2"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shakhotko LP, personal communication with
reference to Belstat; it was confirmed by interviews with personnel of several
private clinics in Minsk.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Philipov1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Philipov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andreev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kharkova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shkolnikov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Induced Abortion in Russia: Recent
Trends and Under-Reporting in Surveys</article-title>. <source>European
Journal of Population</source>
<volume>20</volume>:
<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Zhilka1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhilka H, Irkina T, Steshenko V (2001)
Reproductive health situation in Ukraine (medical and demographic view). Kyiv:
Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Institute of Economics of the National Academy of
Science (in Ukrainian).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-United2"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations (2009) World Contraceptive
Use. New York: Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Population
Division.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Denisov1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Denisov BP, Sakevich VI (2009)
Contraceptive use in Russia (based on the sample survey). Evidence based
medicine and clinical epidemiology 1: 34–39 (In Russian).
<fpage>№1, c. 34</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Frost1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finer</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>U.S.Women's One-Year
Contraceptive Use Patterns, 2004</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on
Sexual and Reproductive Health</source>
<volume>39</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)
<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1363/3904807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Trussell1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trussell J (2004) Contraceptive efficacy.
In: Hatcher RA, Trussell J, Stewart F, Nelson A, Cates W, <etal>et al</etal>..,
editors. Contraceptive Technology: Eighteenth Revised Edition. New York: Ardent
Media.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Mogilevkina2"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mogilevkina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Odlind</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Contraceptive practices and
intentions of Ukrainian women</article-title>. <source>The European Journal
of Contraception and Reproductive Health Care</source>
<volume>8</volume>:
<fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Perlman1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Trends in Family Planning in Russia,
1994–2003</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Sexual and
Reproductive Health</source>
<volume>41</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)
<fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19291128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1363/4104009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3071936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Regushevskaya1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Regushevskaya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubikaytis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikula</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemminki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Contraceptive Use and Abortion among
Women of Reproductive Age in St. Petersburg, Russia</article-title>.
<source>Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health</source>
<volume>41</volume> (<issue>1</issue>)
<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19291129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1931-2393.2009.04115109.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-UNFPA2"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFPA, Ukrainian center of social reforms,
Institute of demography and social studies of the National Academy of Science of
Ukraine, State statistical committee of Ukraine (2009) Ukraine on the path to
15-year ICPD anniversary: implementation of ICDP plan of action 1994–2009
by Ukraine, Kyiv: Den' pechati, (in Ukrainian). Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.un.org.ua/15_2009.pdf">http://www.un.org.ua/15_2009.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Denisov2"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Denisov BP, Sakevich VI (2011) Will Russia
substitute abortion with family planning? Demsoscope Weekly (May 2–22):
465–466. (In Russian). Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2011/0465/tema06.php">http://demoscope.ru/weekly/2011/0465/tema06.php</ext-link>. Accessed 2012
Oct 29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-European2"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Parliamentary Forum on Population
and Development, Intelligence Brief, September 2011, Issue 3. Available:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epfweb.org/home/">http://www.epfweb.org/home/</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Oct
29.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Opening1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Opening welcome by the Minister of Health
and Social Development to the participants of the second All-Russian Congress of
the Russian Orthodox doctors. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.minzdravsoc.ru/health/med-service/83">http://www.minzdravsoc.ru/health/med-service/83</ext-link>. Accessed 2009
Jan 10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Social1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Social and Cultural Initiatives' Fund;
project: Give me life (in Russian) Availablet:
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fondsci.ru/project/101.html">http://www.fondsci.ru/project/101.html</ext-link>. Accessed on 2012 Oct
23.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Levchuk1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Levchuk NB, Perelli-Harris B (2009)
Declining fertility in Ukraine: What is the role of abortion and contraception?
MPIDR Working Paper, WP 2009-045, December 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0049986-Centers1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
and ORC Macro (2003) Reproductive, Maternal and Child Health in Eastern Europe
and Eurasia: A Comparative Report. Atlanta, GA: CDC.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>