
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1623</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tswj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101131163</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSWJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Scientific World Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2356-6140</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-744X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3899746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3899746.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3899746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3899746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24489488</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/123160</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Technical, Economic, and Environmental Performance of Grid-Connected Hybrid (Photovoltaic-Wind) Power System in Algeria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names initials="D">Djohra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koussa</surname><given-names initials="M">Mustapha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Said</surname><given-names initials="N">Nourredine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Centre de Développement des Énergies Renouvelables, BP62 Route de l'Observatoire Bouzareah, 16340 Alger, Algeria</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Djohra Saheb-Koussa: <email>dkoussa@cder.dz</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editors: N. F. Atta, M. Q. Fan, and M. Yari</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">218845</issue-id><elocation-id>123160</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>02</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-01-15 18:51:12.183"><day>15</day><month>01</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Djohra Saheb-Koussa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.pdf"/><abstract><p>This paper studies the technical, economic, and environmental analysis of wind and photovoltaic power systems connected to a conventional grid. The main interest in such systems is on-site consumption of the produced energy, system hybridization, pooling of resources, and contribution to the environment protection. To ensure a better management of system energy, models have been used for determining the power that the constituting subsystems can deliver under specific weather conditions. Simulation is performed using MATLAB-SIMULINK. While, the economic and environmental study is performed using HOMER software. From an economic point of view, this allows to compare the financial constraints on each part of the system for the case of Adrar site which is located to the northern part of the south of Algeria. It also permits to optimally size and select the system presenting the best features on the basis of two parameters, that is, cost and effectiveness. From an environmental point of view, this study allows highlighting the role of renewable energy in reducing gas emissions related to greenhouse effects. In addition, through a set of sensitivity analysis, it is found that the wind speed has more effects on the environmental and economic performances of grid-connected hybrid (photovoltaic-wind) power systems.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Recently, a growing number of organizations have begun to consider renewable energy and industries related to their production, distribution, and services as opportunities to take rather than regulations [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Several factors including Kyoto Protocol, alarming reports from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), and Copenhagen climate change conference (COP15) have contributed to this change in opinion, and many countries believe that the trend will continue such that it is very important for them to immediately prepare for the ‘‘green race.” The Algerian government and companies are not exceptions indeed; they have recently intensified their efforts towards promoting the economic growth via supporting green industries. Examples showing such efforts include plans for establishing numerous energy clusters in many areas like the proposed wind farm (project) with a capacity of 10 megawatts launched in Adrar and the hybrid plant in the region of Hassi R'Mel (Laghouat) built and made operational in February 2011. Similar projects, environmentally friendly and producing clean and renewable energy, are scheduled for the areas of Timimoun and Kunta Zaouiet encouraging the use of renewable energy [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Electrical energy generation from wind and PV sources is considered as being the most promising renewable energy and is, therefore, to be developed to replace coal, oil, gas, and even nuclear based production. However, any process of transforming energy from one form into another usable form is complex and naturally includes a certain number of economic and environmental features of different kinds (operation of large-scale renewable energy requires space where the resource is available that requires a “good” management planning and the electrical networks will also be adapted and managed so as to promote decentralized production). The obtained technoeconomic and environmental results allow reaching an objective judgment regarding the studied system.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Presentation of the Different Systems of Distributed Generation from Renewable Energy </title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Standalone Systems</italic>. For standalone installations, the energy produced employing photovoltaic solar panels or wind generators is either immediately consumed (pumping, ventilation, lighting, refrigerator, etc.) or stored in batteries for later use. The produced current is either directly fed to the consuming equipment or converted using an inverter to supply devices that require AC power [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Multisource Hybrid Systems</italic>. These systems supply electricity that is often used at remote sites and are built coupling different sources of production of electrical energy such as wind, solar, and others. They also allow a more reliable supply of electricity. Nearly two billion people are not connected to the utility grid (44% of the world population). Thus, the development of hybrid systems for renewable energy conversion will undoubtedly help to solve many social problems, especially in poor countries, and open up vast commercial markets [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Distributed Systems Connected to the Grid</italic>. These are usually medium and large systems which are grid connected [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and which, in general, produce electrical energy amounts depending on sunshine and wind conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Characteristics of the PV-Wind Systems Considered</title><p>The architecture presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> is the one upon which this paper is based. With this type of PV-wind system for the generation of electrical energy the objective is to inject into the grid the energy thus generated.</p><p>For the design, the power production of the different sources becomes freely controllable without affecting the state values of the grid. Decoupling the state values means that the variations of the renewable resources like the velocity of the wind and the intensity of the solar radiation will not influence the state values of the electrical grid as the harmonics generation, flickers, frequency fluctuation, under voltage, and over voltage. These values are only controlled by the inverter for the photovoltaic generator and by the microprocessor-controlled OptiTip pitch regulation, ensuring continuous and optimal adjustment of the angles of the blades in relation to the prevailing wind, for the wind generator. On the other hand, changes in the loads, which influence the state values of the grid, will not affect the generation side.</p><p>A control/management strategy is developed for this architecture to operate it in the highest efficient way. The efficiency here means the most utilization of the renewable energy sources in order to minimize the cost of the produced energy while preserving the reliability of the system.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Methodology</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>4.1. Theoretical Aspect of the Modeling</title><sec id="sec4.1.1"><title>4.1.1. Modeling of the PV System</title><p>For each hour h in a year, the power delivered by a PV generator <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> (W) is described by the IV characteristic which varies with the hourly solar radiation <italic toggle="yes">G</italic>
<sub>h</sub> and the hourly dry temperature <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub>h</sub>. This is given, in algebraic form, by
<disp-formula id="EEq1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pv-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ph-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Singer model [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] has been used and MATLAB-SIMULINK program was developed for this purpose.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">MPPT Algorithm</italic>. In MPPT (maximum power point tracking) operation, the PV array produces maximum power under variable conditions of solar radiation and ambient temperature. The MPPT algorithm which is used in this work is the incremental conductance algorithm (IC). Conductance algorithm is based on the differentiation of PV power and on condition of zero slope of PV curve. The MPPT can be tracked by comparing the incremental conductance <italic toggle="yes">dI</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">dV</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> to the instantaneous conductance /<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>. Therefore the sign of the quantity <italic toggle="yes">dI</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">dV</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> indicates the correct direction of perturbation leading to the MPPT. When MPPT has been reached, the operation of the PV is held at this point and perturbation is stopped. If a change in <italic toggle="yes">dI</italic> is presented, the algorithm increments or decrements the <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> to track the new MPPT the increment (or decrement) size determines how fast the MPPT is tracked.</p><p>When the optimum operation point of PV curve is to the left of the MPPT, we have <italic toggle="yes">dI</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">dV</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>≺0 thus a reduction in PV's voltage is essential to achieve MPPT.</p><p>Similarly, when the optimum point is to the left of the MPPT, we have <italic toggle="yes">dI</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">dV</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub>≻0; thus an increase in PV's voltage is essential to achieve MPPT. Traditionally these changes in PV's voltage may be done by coupling a DC/DC converter to PV and controlling properly its duty cycle. In the present study the used DC/DC converter in MPPT is the boost due to easy way of duty cycle control [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Inverter</italic>. In this paper the connection of PV system to the grid takes place in one stage using a voltage source inverter. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> we can see that between the PV generator and the inverter only one capacitor exists. Based on the IC algorithm, when the output voltage of PV generator is changed, the MPPT changes simultaneously. For the implementation of IC algorithm directly to the inverter, the switching elements of the inverter must be appropriately pulsed so that every moment the voltage capacitor of the DC bus is equal to the reference voltage which is given by MPPT algorithm (VDC-ref). Therefore, the algorithm brings in the capacitor voltage and the PV's current as inputs and the desirable PV's voltage (which is capacitors new reference voltage) as output [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Control and Synchronization with the Grid</italic>. In all the power conversion chains, it should be noticed that the inverter output voltages must be synchronized with the distribution grid [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. For that purpose, we introduced and turned a phase locked loop (PLL) which delivers the angle <italic toggle="yes">θ</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">ωt</italic> mandatory for the Park transformation (translation into the synchronous frame). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3"> Figure 3</xref> shows the block diagram of this PLL algorithm. While supplying to the load or the grid a current corresponding to the real power reference, a swing is created between voltages and currents in order to deliver a reactive power according to the command.</p><p>A proportional integral controller is used to control the active and reactive power flowing.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.1.2"><title>4.1.2. Modeling of the Wind System</title><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Wind Speed Variation with Height [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</italic>. To calculate the output of the wind turbine in each of the 8760 hours in a year, the hourly values of measured wind speed in the Adrar site at the hub height of the machine is calculated by using
<disp-formula id="EEq2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>hub-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>hub</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>data</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>
<sub>hub</sub> is the hub height of the wind turbine (m), <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>
<sub>data</sub> is the anemometer height (m), <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is the surface roughness length (m) [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and the <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>
<sub>hub-h</sub> is the wind speed at the anemometer height during the hour h (m/s).</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Dynamic Model</italic>. The types of wind turbine generators may vary from wind generator to wind generator due to different generator types (asynchronous, synchronous), especially the circuitry connecting the wind generator to the three-phase grid which can have two different forms (direct or indirect grid connection).</p><p>In the studied case, the generator has been connected directly to the three-phase alternating current grid. The resulting configuration is simple and, according to the literature [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], is widely used in practice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Wind Turbine Dynamics Model</italic>. The mechanical power extracted from the wind [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] is given by the following relation:
<disp-formula id="EEq3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
with
<disp-formula id="eq4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> is the area swept by the wind in m²; <italic toggle="yes">ρ</italic> is the air density equal at standard conditions 1.294 kg m<sup>−3</sup>; <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> is the wind speed in m/s; <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub> is the radius in m.</p><p>The power coefficient <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub> depends on the tip speed ratio (<italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>) and the blade angle (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic>). In the case of turbines without pitch control, the blade angle is constant and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub> values only depend on those of <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic>, the tip speed ratio being expressed as follows:
<disp-formula id="EEq4"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Also, the mechanical torque produced by the wind is expressed in the following relation:
<disp-formula id="EEq5"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
The VESTAS 47-660 wind generator experimental power output data given by the manufacturer as well as the <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub> curve [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] have been approximated by using a simple MATLAB polynomial interpolation, available as polyfit polynomial function and the obtained correlations are expressed as follows:
<disp-formula id="EEq6"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4240</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">472</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">7</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">219</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">56</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">88</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">8.9</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0.58</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0.024</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">9</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">6.64</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.1072</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.2698</mml:mn><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.4931</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.00084</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0781</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4.27</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:maligngroup/><mml:malignmark/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.37</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.44</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.83</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Then, the operation of the wind turbine system is simulated using the wind turbine equations which evaluate the mechanical torque (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>) and requires the turbine angular speed (<italic toggle="yes">Ω</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>) and the wind speed (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>) as data.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Drive Drain Dynamics Model</italic>. To evaluate the generator speed (<italic toggle="yes">Ω</italic>
<sub>am</sub>), the generator torque (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub>am</sub>) and the turbine torque (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>′) are required as data. The dynamic behaviour of the mechanical system is determined by using the classical rotational dynamics equations. The inertia is considered as concentrated in one lumped mass including the contribution of blades, generator shafts, and gear box. The dynamic motion equation of the mechanical system has the following expression:
<disp-formula id="EEq8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>am</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>am</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>′</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>am</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>The turbine torque and generator speed (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>′ and <italic toggle="yes">Ω</italic>
<sub>am</sub>) and the mechanical torque and turbine speed (<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub> and <italic toggle="yes">Ω</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>) supplied to the wind turbine block simulation have been linked by means of the gear box whose ratio is <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">k</italic> = 50.5) for the VESTAS 660-47 wind generator.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Asynchronous Machine Dynamics Model.</italic> The asynchronous machine equations permit to calculate the electrical power generation of the system and return the generator torque <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>
<sub>am</sub>, the active and reactive power. The generator speed <italic toggle="yes">Ω</italic>
<sub>as</sub> and voltage <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">d</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub> are the required input parameters, obtained by using the Park transform block PT of the three-phase system into the two-phase system [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">(a) Electric and Magnetic Equations.</italic> The voltage equations representing an induction machine [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] in an arbitrary reference frame can be written, in terms of the phase currents, as given by [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>In the present model, the stator and rotor voltages along the <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> axes are given by [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>Using these last ones, a model for wound rotor generators can be developed. This latter has short circuited windings and, as a consequence, rotor voltages evaluate to zero (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">dr</italic></sub> = 0 and <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">qr</italic></sub> = 0) in this case. Therefore, the representative wound rotor generator equations are
<disp-formula id="EEq9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="EEq10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">(b) Evaluation of the Electromagnetic Torque</italic>. The electromagnetic torque has been calculated by employing (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq11">11</xref>), proposed by [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>Consider
<disp-formula id="EEq11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>am</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">(c) Evaluation of Real and Reactive Power.</italic> The active (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>) and reactive (<italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>) power have been calculated by using the following equations:
<disp-formula id="EEq12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="EEq13"><label>(13)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="EEq13EAAAABAADCA" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Using these equations, a model for wound rotor generators can be developed. This type of generator has short circuited windings; thus the corresponding rotor voltages go to zero (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">dr</italic></sub> = 0, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">qr</italic></sub> = 0). Taking into account these conditions, (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq13">13</xref>) give <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></sub> = 0 and <italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">r</italic></sub> = 0.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>5. Simulation</title><p>The energy system components are photovoltaic modules, wind turbine, grid, and power converter. This study develops a suitable assembly of the key parameters such as photovoltaic array power, wind turbine power curve, battery storage, and converter capacity to match the predefined load. For economic analysis, the cost including the initial capital, replacement cost, and operating and maintenance cost are considered as simulating conditions.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Photovoltaic Arrays.</italic> The initial cost of photovoltaic arrays may vary from $4.00 to $5.00 per watt. Considering a more optimistic system, the costs of installation, replacement, and maintenance of a 1 kW solar energy system are taken as $5000 and $4000. Sizes of the photovoltaic arrays are varied between 0, 100, 200, 300, 400, 500, 600, and 700 kW.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Wind Turbine</italic>. Energy generation form wind turbine depends on wind speed variations. The wind turbine rated power should be greater than average electrical load. Therefore, according to the load data discussed above, the average load is around a 7.7 MW. Therefore, a VESTAS 47–660 turbine manufactured by VESTAS wind power is used. Its rated power is 660 kW AC.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Grid</italic>. Grid exists as the main power component in this hybrid renewable energy system. Moreover, grid has the functions as a storage system, so a grid power system does not need a battery.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Power Converter</italic>. A converter is required for systems in which DC components serve an AD load or vice versa. For a 1 kW system the installation and replacement costs are taken as $800 and $750, respectively. Lifetime of a unit is considered to be 25 years with an efficiency of 90%.</p><p>For the considered system, it is necessary to simulate, during all the hours in a complete year, all the possible designs. Variables are considered hourly, and, therefore, there will be 8760 in a year. At the end of the simulation, we will know the quantity of electrical energy from a PV generator injected to the grid in the year and the electrical energy from wind turbines that is also injected [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>As a sample site, the Adrar site has been chosen and the following data are used as input:<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>the hourly global and diffuse radiation measured on a horizontal plane and the ambient temperature. From the data collected on a horizontal plane, the components of the solar irradiance have been projected onto the surface of a PV panel. Moreover, the inclination of the used solar panel corresponds to the yearly optimum slope as indicated in [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>];</p></list-item><list-item><p>the measured wind speeds and the electromechanical characteristics of a wind turbine, of the VESTAS 47–660 type. This is a three-blade model with a diameter of 46 m, a speed multiplier ratio of 50.5 and a hub height of 100 m [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, the power produced by this wind turbine has been calculated using the power curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>), provided by the manufacturer.</p></list-item></list>
</p><sec id="sec5.1"><title>5.1. Power Produced by the Photovoltaic Generator</title><p>For calculating the output characteristics of the photovoltaic system, a program has been developed which requires the global incident radiation and the air temperature as main input data. So, the research unit in renewable energy U.R.E.R. of Adrar provided hourly measured values over a full year of global and diffuse irradiation on a horizontal plane together with those related to the ambient temperature. From the global radiations on the horizontal plane collected data and based on the equations given in [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], the developed program calculates the overall incident irradiations on the surface of the PV panel. These latter and the ambient temperatures are used to calculate the power and current delivered by the PV generator.</p><p>The obtained results are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>5.2. Power Produced by the Wind Generator</title><p>Generally, to calculate the power generated by a wind turbine, we use the data drawn from the main characteristic <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>) related to the turbine and supplied by the manufacturer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). In this study, using the equations given in [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the hourly values of the wind turbine are read from a file in which the wind speed for each hour of the year is given.</p><p>By using the power curve of the wind turbine, the output power is calculated. With the speed at the hub of the wind turbine, and using its power curve, the power that the wind turbine provides in an hour h, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
<sub>w-h</sub> (W) is obtained. If there are <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">w</italic></sub> wind turbine connected in parallel, this amount is multiplied by <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
<sub><italic toggle="yes">w</italic></sub> [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The obtained results are as follows:<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7(a)</xref> shows the evolution of hourly wind speeds;</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7(b)</xref> shows the plots of the active power developed at the asynchronous machine terminals;</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7(c)</xref> shows the plots of the reactive power developed at the asynchronous machine terminals;</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7(d)</xref> shows the current delivered by the wind generator.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>5.3. Management of the System [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref> presents the MATLAB-SIMULINK program diagram of the hybrid system. In this system the power delivered by each of the system devices (PV or wind) should be managed in such a way that the surplus of power produced by any of them is conducted to the grid without giving rise to any phenomena leading to a disturbance of any of these devices. These last ones disturbed by generating harmonics that may distort the grid waveform, flickers, high frequency wave, frequency fluctuation, under voltage, and over voltage.</p><p>Thus, for each hour of the year h, the amount of electrical energy available at the transformer connected to the grid is evaluated by [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]
<disp-formula id="EEq14"><label>(14)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>AC-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pv-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>INV</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow/></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TR</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">η</italic>
<sub>INV</sub> is the inverter efficiency rate, modeled as a variable depending on the power delivered by the inverter, <italic toggle="yes">η</italic>
<sub>TR</sub> is the efficiency rate of the transformer connected to the electrical grid, including the losses of power in the transmission lines, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>w-h</sub> is the power (W) generated by the wind generator within an hour time, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>pv-h</sub> is the power (W) generated by the PV generator within an hour time.</p><p>However, the amount of power that can be injected each hour into the grid, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>EE-h</sub> (W), cannot be higher than the allowed evacuation capacity at the point of connection to the grid, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>MAX-GRID</sub> (W) [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="EEq15"><label>(15)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>EE-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mo>⁡</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MAX-GRID</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>AC-h</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Where <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>MAX-GRID</sub> (W) is the maximum power evacuation value allowed, which the Algerian law fixes for 20 to 30% of the line thermal limit at the point of connection.</p><p>The amount of energy to be injected into the grid obtained from the PV generator (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>EE-PV-h</sub>) and the wind generator <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>EE-w-h</sub> will be calculated as indicated by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>.</p><p>The results obtained in the case of the previously described scenario are represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref> which shows that the hourly produced power injected into the grid is lower than <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sub>MAX-GRID</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>5.4. Total Annual Production</title><p>The contribution of each part of the hybrid system (PV-wind-grid) to satisfy a specific load of the 34,815 MWh/yr is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11">Figure 11</xref>. It is to be noted that the PV generator produces only 365 MWh/year and covers only 1% of the load. The wind generator, in turn, produces 7,225 MWh/year which constitute nearly 21% of load requirements against a covered load rate of 78% (27,225 MWh/year) provided by the conventional electricity grid [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. These results are explained by the fact that HOMER software promotes the wind system because of it's efficiency which is very higher than that of PV system.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.5"><title>5.5. Hours of Operation</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12">Figure 12</xref> represents the duration of the operation (in hours) of each of the renewable energy equipment of the hybrid PV-wind-Grid system. It is found that the wind generator works over the longest time interval with a 48% rate of the total period, followed by the PV generator and inverter with a rate of 26% for each.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.6"><title>5.6. Economic Aspects</title><p>The HOMER optimization model [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] uses relatively simple strategies based on the ones studied by Barley et al. [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and it is able to obtain an optimal design of a hybrid system by selecting the most appropriate strategy.</p><p>Thus, from an economic point of view, it is found that the system composed of a 200 kW rated PV system and three 660 kW rated wind turbines can cover 22% of the electrical energy demand and has a net present cost (NPC) of $177 million and a cost of energy per kilowatt hour (COE) of $0.399/kWh. A comparative economic analysis between the conventional and the optimized system (PV-wind system) employing HOMER software package [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] has been performed and the results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>. From these results, it is noticed that the hybrid system (PV-wind-grid) is more economical than the conventional system if the price per produced kWh of the latter is set to $0.4/kWh. However, the net present cost is calculated for a project lifetime period of 25 years and on the basis of an interest rate of 6%. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13">13</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14">14</xref> show the details of the corresponding costs to each of the systems and the related annual costs [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec5.7"><title>5.7. Environmental Aspects</title><p>The results regarding the effects of each system configuration, that is, the conventional grid and the hybrid system (PV-wind-grid), on the environment obtained by again using HOMER software in the case of the Adrar site are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref> [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In this table the quantities of the main gases that are harmful to the environment including CO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, and NO<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub> are presented. From these results, it is found that the PV-wind-grid hybrid system produces a reduction in the carbon dioxide gas, sulfur dioxide, and nitrogen oxide rates by, respectively, 20%, 22%, and 22% as compared to the quantities produced by the conventional system [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec5.8"><title>5.8. Sensitivity Results</title><p>In this study, sensitivity analysis was done to study the effects of variation in the solar irradiation and wind speed. The simulation software simulates the long-term implementation of the hybrid system based on their respective search size for the predefined sensitivity values of the components. The emissions, renewable fraction, NPC, and COE are simulated based on the three sensitivity variables: wind speed (m/s), solar irradiation (kW/m<sup>2</sup>/day), and grid electricity price ($/kWh). A long-term simulation for every possible system combination and configuration was done for a one year period (from January 1st 2005 to December 31st 2005). In the present case, solar irradiation is set as sensitivity variables: <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> = 3.5, 4.5, 5, 5.5, 5.72, 7.8, 8 kW/m<sup>2</sup>/day, while wind speed are <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 6.9, 7, 7.5, 7.8, 8, 8.8 m/s. Moreover, the grid electricity price is also defined as a sensitivity variable (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4 $/kWh). A total of 192 sensitivity cases were tried for each system configuration. The simulation time was 23 minutes and 46 seconds on a personal computer with Intel CORE Intel Core Duo Processor of 2.53 GHz and a RAM of 2 GB. The sensitivity results in terms of solar irradiation, wind speed, and grid electricity price analyze the feasibility of each system. Here the feasibility of hybrid renewable energy system is analyzed based on emission reduction and cost saving. This type of sensitivity analysis of the systems provides information that a particular system would be optimal at certain sensitivity variables [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The PV-wind system is feasible when the grid electricity price is more than $0.4 kW/h. Under this condition, the RF can be between 0.21 and 0.22. A PV-wind system is feasible when global solar irradiation is more than 5.72 kWh/m<sup>2</sup> per day and the grid electricity price is more expensive than $0.4 kWh. Based on the optimization results, wind energy production shows a bigger proportion of energy generation than solar. While the solar power occupies less than 1% of the total energy generation, wind power occupies approximately a quarter.</p><p>Therefore, the wind energy resource has more impact on the implementation. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18">18</xref> reflect the cost, renewable fraction, and emission variation dependent on the sensitivity variable wind speed. The NPC and COE of the hybrid power system reduce when the wind speed increases from 6.9 m/s to 8.8 m/s, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15">Figure 15</xref>.</p><p>Simultaneously, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16">Figure 16</xref>, renewable fraction rises sharply from 0 to 16% (when wind speed increases from 6.9 to 7 m/s) and then steadily increases to 24% at a slower rate. In addition, as shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17">17</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig18">18</xref>, the main emissions of carbon dioxide, sulfur dioxide, and nitrogen oxide persistently decrease 22%.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>6. Problems Encountered in Decentralized Systems [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] </title><p>The major difficulty associated with decentralized energy sources is that they generally do not participate in ancillary services (voltage control, frequency, ability to operate in standalone mode, etc.). This is especially true for renewable energy sources whose power flow is unpredictable and very volatile. The integration of decentralized energy generation into power networks raises the following problems:<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>random and unpredictable energy production (wind, solar);</p></list-item><list-item><p>lack of power-frequency control;</p></list-item><list-item><p>no voltage adjustment performed;</p></list-item><list-item><p>sensitivity to voltage dips;</p></list-item><list-item><p>significant sensitivity to changes in primary source (wind, solar) energy levels.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>The failure to take part in system services makes this type of sources behave as passive generators, from the electrical energy generation point of view. The penetration of distributed energy generation must be limited from 20 to 30% of the consumed power in order to guarantee acceptable system stability [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>7. Conclusion </title><p>This study is related to the technical, economic, and environmental impact of grid-connected decentralized systems to which an appropriate management of energy is applied and by means of which are developed models of the different parts. The solar and wind energy resource data are collected from the weather station of Adrar which is a typical arid region. The most significant results are as follows.</p><p>The power that any subsystem can deliver depends on the weather conditions of the considered site.</p><p>The PV based system only covers 1% of the total load consumption. On the other hand, the wind generator contribution amounts to about 21% of the energy production while the remaining 78% are supplied by the conventional electricity grid.</p><p>From an economic point of view, it is found that for the Adrar site, which is characterized by a high wind potential, the hybrid system is competitive compared with the conventional system with a cost of the energy COE produced by the network equal to $0.4/kWh since the estimated COE related to the hybrid system is equal to $0,399/kWh, based on an average wind speed greater than or equal to 6 m/s.</p><p>From an environmental standpoint, the rates of greenhouse gases (CO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, and NO<sub><italic toggle="yes">x</italic></sub>) emissions are reduced from 20 to 22% in the case of a hybrid system, compared with the conventional system.</p><p>The sensitivity analysis indicates that PV-wind hybrid system is feasible under the meteorological conditions in Adrar region. With the increasing wind speed, the NPC, COE, and emissions of the hybrid renewable energy system reduce, and renewable fraction grows up.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>None of the authors of this paper has a financial or personal relationship with other people or organisations that could inappropriately influence or bias the content of the paper.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic evaluation of renewable energy systems under varying scenarios and its implications to Korea’s renewable energy plan</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Applied Energy</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>88</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2254</fpage><lpage>2260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79951511952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source><italic toggle="yes">World Energy Outlook</italic></source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Paris, France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IEA</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canada’s energy perspectives and policies for sustainable development</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Applied Energy</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>86</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-58049171292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weigt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Germany’s wind energy: the potential for fossil capacity replacement and cost saving</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Applied Energy</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>86</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>1863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-64649100428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashmi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospects of biodiesel production from microalgae in India</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2361</fpage><lpage>2372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-68949166307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on sustainable energy: recent developments and future prospects of dimethyl ether (DME)</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of the 10th International Symposium on Process Systems Engineering (PSE '09)</conf-name><conf-date>2009</conf-date><conf-loc>Bahia, Brazil</conf-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Adrar: lancement des travaux du projet de la ferme éolienne</article-title><comment>2011, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.algerie360.com/algerie/adrar-lancement-des-travaux-du-projet-de-la-ferme-eolienne/">http://www.algerie360.com/algerie/adrar-lancement-des-travaux-du-projet-de-la-ferme-eolienne/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducluzaux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>L'énergie électrique d'origine éolienne</article-title><conf-name>Conférence sur l’Énergie</conf-name><conf-date>2004</conf-date><conf-loc>Grenoble, France</conf-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguefeu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waymel</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PWM inverters in decentralized generation systems: characterization of the dynamic behavior under utility fault conditions</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Distributed Energy Resources</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panayiotou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalogirou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tassou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and simulation of a PV and a PV-Wind standalone energy system to power a household application</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable Energy</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79961126767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaahid</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of research on autonomous wind farms and solar parks and their feasibility for commercial loads in hot regions</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3877</fpage><lpage>3887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79961108436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhadidy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaahid</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parametric study of hybrid (wind + solar + diesel) power generating systems</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable Energy</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0034039876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaahid</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhadidy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Technical and economic assessment of grid-independent hybrid photovoltaic-diesel-battery power systems for commercial loads in desert environments</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1794</fpage><lpage>1810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34250174170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belhamel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic and technical study of a hybrid system (wind-photovoltaic-diesel) for rural electrification in Algeria</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Applied Energy</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>86</volume><issue>7-8</issue><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-61849108757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockington</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldock</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feasibility analysis of stand-alone renewable energy supply options for a large hotel</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable Energy</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>1490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-40949137874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celik</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Present status of photovoltaic energy in Turkey and life cycle techno-economic analysis of a grid-connected photovoltaic-house</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-31144465258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>MAH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of renewable energy resources potential for electricity generation in Bangladesh</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2401</fpage><lpage>2413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-78651468598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belhamel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nouredine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling and simulation of the fixed-speed WECS (wind energy conversion system): application to the Algerian Sahara area</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Energy</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>4116</fpage><lpage>4125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77956171617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Amin</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Feasibility study of hybrid retrofits to an isolated off-grid diesel power plant</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33748435908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozenshtein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of PV array output using a small number of measured parameters</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Solar Energy</italic></source><year>1984</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0021122411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution à l'étude théorique du comportement d'un système hybride (eolien- photovoltaïque- diesel) de production d'électricité sans interruption</article-title><comment>Mémoire de magister Blida, Septembre 2005</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsengenes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adamidis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the behavior of a three phase grid-connected photovoltaic system to control active and reactive power</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Electric Power Systems Research</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>81</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77958047405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A phase tracking system for three phase utility interface inverters</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">IEEE Transactions on Power Electronics</italic></source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0033686420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufo-López</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal-Agustín</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendoza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design and economical analysis of hybrid PV-wind systems connected to the grid for the intermittent production of hydrogen</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Energy Policy</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3082</fpage><lpage>3095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-65749088851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossanyi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Wind Energy Handbook</italic></source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>West Sussex, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Union for Coordination of Transmission of Electricity</collab><article-title>Wind Power in the UCTE interconnected System</article-title><comment>November 2004, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.entsoe.eu/fileadmin/user_upload/_library/publications/ce/otherreports/Wind_Power_20041125.pdf">https://www.entsoe.eu/fileadmin/user_upload/_library/publications/ce/otherreports/Wind_Power_20041125.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spooner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct coupled permanent magnet generators for wind turbine applications</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">IEE Proceedings Electric Power Applications</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>143</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laverdure</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raison</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elements of modelling of wind power systems with energy management: two structures in comparison</article-title><volume>2</volume><conf-name>Proceedings of the 28th IEEE Annual Conference of the Industrial Electronics Society</conf-name><conf-date>November 2002</conf-date><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036949777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krichen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fuzzy logic supervisor for active and reactive power control of a fixed speed wind energy conversion system</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Electric Power Systems Research</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>78</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-38649115648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>The Cres Wind Farm</collab><article-title>3.01 MW Demonstration wind farm in Greece. Various wind energy technologies in complex Terrain topography</article-title><comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creswindfarm.gr/site1/Articles/V47_US.pdf">http://www.creswindfarm.gr/site1/Articles/V47_US.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Wind Power in Power Systems</italic></source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Royal Institute of Technology, John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poitiers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Asynchronous generator study and control for the wind energy use [Ph.D. thesis]</italic></source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Nantes, France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Nantes</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kacira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simsek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demirkol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determining optimum tilt angles and orientations of photovoltaic panels in Sanliurfa, Turkey</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Renewable Energy</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-1542643767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belhamel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benferhat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution à l’étude théorique du comportement d’un système hybride (eolien- photovoltaïque- diesel) de production d’électricité sans interruption</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Afrique Science</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source><italic toggle="yes">HOMER—Getting Started Guide for HOMER Version 2.1</italic></source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>National Renewable Energy Laboratory, U.S. Department of Energy Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barley</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winn</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimal control of remote hybrid power systems—part I: simplified model</article-title><conf-name>Proceedings of National Avian-Wind Power Planning Meeting</conf-name><conf-date>1995</conf-date><conf-loc>Washington, DC, USA</conf-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saheb-Koussa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etude technique, économique et environnementale des systèmes décentralisés connectés au réseau électrique</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bulletin des Energies Renouvelables</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtecuisse</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Supervision d’une centrale multi sources à base d’éoliennes et de stockage d’énergie connectée au réseau électrique [Thèse de doctorat]</italic></source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Ecole Nationale des Arts et Métiers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Decentralized installation connected to the grid.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of a connected PV-grid [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Transport delay-based PLL algorithm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Wind system block diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Typical wind turbine power curve.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Representation of climatic characteristics, power, and current produced by the photovoltaic module BP SX 150 S installed on the Adrar site.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.006.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Simulation results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.007.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Management of the system.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.008.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Flowchart for calculating the amount of power to be inject into the grid.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.009.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Power injected into the grid.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.010.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Structure of the production system (PV-wind-grid).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.011.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig12" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Distribution of operation hours of each of the renewable energy equipment of the hybrid PV-wind-Grid system.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.012.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig13" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>Net present cost.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.013.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig14" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>Annual net cost.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.014.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig15" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>The relationship between cost and wind speed.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.015.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig16" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>The relationship between RF and wind speed.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.016.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig17" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p>The relationship between CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and wind speed.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.017.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig18" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p>The relationship between sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions and wind speed.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="TSWJ2013-123160.018.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cost comparison between a standard system (grid) and a hybrid system (PV-wind-grid).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional system grid</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hybrid system PV-wind-grid</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPC ($/yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177,714,200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177,090,600</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COE ($/kWh)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Emissions comparison between a standard system (grid) and a hybrid system (PV-wind-grid).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollutant Kg/yr</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conventional system grid</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hybrid system PV-wind-grid</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO<sub>2</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,965,160</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,199,524</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,229</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74,568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>X</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46,572</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36,467</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>