
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">331</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosgen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101239074</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3009686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3009686.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3009686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3009686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLGE-RA-3618R2</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Developmental Biology/Molecular Development</subject><subject>Developmental Biology/Pattern Formation</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Animal Genetics</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Initiator Elements Function to Determine the Activity State of BX-C Enhancers</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Initiator Swap in the BX-C</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iampietro</surname><given-names initials="C">Carole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gummalla</surname><given-names initials="M">Maheshwar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutero</surname><given-names initials="A">Annick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names initials="F">François</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names initials="RK">Robert K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>National Centre of Competence in Research (NCCR) Frontiers in Genetics and Department of Zoology and Animal Biology, University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names initials="N">Norbert</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Harvard Medical School, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Robert.Maeda@unige.ch</email> (RKM); <email>Francois.Karch@unige.ch</email> (FK)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CI FK RKM. Performed the experiments: CI MG AM. Analyzed the data: CI MG AM FK RKM. Wrote the paper: FK RKM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">192237</issue-id><elocation-id>e1001260</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>01</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2019-01-14 12:56:06.547"><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2019</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Iampietro et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.pdf"/><abstract><p>A &gt;300 kb <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory region is required for the proper expression of the three bithorax complex (BX-C) homeotic genes. Based on genetic and transgenic analysis, a model has been proposed in which the numerous BX-C <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements are spatially restricted through the activation or repression of parasegment-specific chromatin domains. Particular early embryonic enhancers, called initiators, have been proposed to control this complex process. Here, in order to better understand the process of domain activation, we have undertaken a systematic <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> dissection of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6 cis</italic>-regulatory domain using a new method, called InSIRT. Using this method, we create and genetically characterize mutations affecting iab-6 function, including mutations specifically modifying the <italic toggle="yes">iab</italic>-6 initiator. Through our mutagenesis of the <italic toggle="yes">iab</italic>-6 initiator, we provide strong evidence that initiators function not to directly control homeotic gene expression but rather as domain control centers to determine the activity state of the enhancers and silencers within a <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domain.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>Understanding how genes become activated is one of the primary areas of research in modern biology. In order to decipher the DNA components required for this process, scientists have traditionally turned to transgenic reporter assays, where DNA elements are removed from their native environment and placed next to a simplified reporter gene to monitor transcriptional activation. Although this approach is powerful, it can result in artifacts stemming from the channelization of regulatory element activities into predetermined classes. In this manuscript, we investigate the biological role of elements from the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> bithorax complex, called initiators. In transgenic assays, these elements have been categorized as enhancers. However, genetic analysis suggests that, <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic>, these elements perform a far more complex function. Here, using a new method to repeatedly target a genetic locus for mutagenesis, we show that initiators function as control elements that coordinate the activity of nearby enhancers and silencers. Overall, our study highlights how gene expression can be controlled through a hierarchical arrangement of <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> bithorax complex (BX-C) is one of two homeotic gene clusters in the fly and is responsible for determining the segmental identity of the posterior thoracic segment and each of the fly abdominal segments <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Lewis1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-SanchezHerrero1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. It does this by using a &gt;300 kb <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory region to control the parasegement-specific expression of the three BX-C homeotic genes: <italic toggle="yes">Ubx, abd-A and Abd-B</italic> (for review, see <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Maeda1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>).</p><p>Through the early genetic analysis of the BX-C, it was shown that its <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory sequences can be divided into nine parasegment-specific chromosomal domains (<italic toggle="yes">abx/bx, bxd/pbx, and iab-2</italic> through <italic toggle="yes">iab-8</italic>), where each domain controls the activation of one of the three BX-C homeotic genes in a pattern appropriate for that parasegment <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Peifer1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bender1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Since their identification, these domains have been dissected using transgenic reporter assays to identify individual regulatory elements capable of modifying reporter gene expression. Among the elements identified were early embryonic enhancers (initiators), cell-type-specific enhancers, silencers and insulators <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Simon1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Interestingly, although homeotic gene expression is restricted along the antero-postero (A–P) axis, many of the elements identified by transgenic analysis do not control reporter gene expression in an A–P restricted manner. These findings, when combined with the early genetic data suggest a model in which the <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements of the BX-C are controlled through the activation or repression of parasegment-specific chromatin domains <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Peifer1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Maeda2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Maeda3" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>According to this model, the BX-C functions through multiple layers of control. First, there are the enhancers that directly activate homeotic gene expression in a pattern appropriate for a specific parasegment. Based on the genetic data, these enhancers are known to be grouped in a way where all the enhancers required to produce a PS-specific pattern of homeotic gene expression are clustered into domains within the BX-C sequence. However, although these enhancers produce a pattern of homeotic gene expression appropriate for a specific parasegment, in transgenic assays, they are not restricted along the A–P axis, and are only restricted to specific cell-types <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Simon1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Pirrotta1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>The second layer of control comes from Polycomb-response element silencers (PREs). These silencers are thought to turn off the clusters of enhancers in parasegments where they are not needed, via modification of the local chromatin structure around the enhancers (for reviews <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Muller2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>). Once again, however, like the cell-type-specific enhancers, by themselves, PREs do not seem to sense positional information and can silence genes regardless of A–P position <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Chiang1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.</p><p>Domain boundary elements form a third layer of BX-C control. Each of the PS-specific enhancer clusters seems to be flanked by boundary elements, required to keep each cluster separate and autonomous from other clusters. <italic toggle="yes">In situ</italic>, loss of a domain boundary causes the fusion of PS-specific domains, resulting in mutant phenotypes, where the affected segments displays phenotypes characteristic of the other <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Barges1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gyurkovics1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> (for review see <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Maeda4" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>). In transgenic assays, these elements have been shown to behave as insulators, blocking both positive and negative effects of <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements on reporter gene activity <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Hagstrom1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Zhou2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Barges1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gruzdeva1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. However, the presence of boundary elements cannot explain the A–P restriction of the BX-C regulatory elements, for, as with the enhancers and silencers, when taken out of the BX-C, boundary elements do not seem to have an A–P restricted activity.</p><p>So then, how do non-restricted regulatory elements control homeotic gene expression in an A–P position-dependent manner? If we are to assume that the reporter gene assays represent a reasonable estimate of the activity of the various regulatory elements in a domain, then there must be some other element in each domain that coordinates the activity of these elements across the A–P axis. Special early embryonic enhancers, called initiators, are the prime candidates to perform this function <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Simon1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Zhou2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Barges1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>
<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Shimell1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. As mentioned above, the activity of most of the elements isolated from the BX-C is not restricted along the A-P axis. In this respect, however, initiator elements are exceptional. In transgenic assays, these elements behave as early embryonic enhancers that activate reporter gene expression in a pattern along the A-P axis, consistent with the activity of the domain from which it was isolated. For example, the initiator identified from the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> domain, which controls <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression in PS10/A5, activates reporter gene expression in PS10/A5 and more posterior segments in a pair-rule fashion <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Because similar elements were found in many PS-specific domains and these elements were the only elements discovered in the BX-C capable of reading the early parasegmental address set up by the maternal, gap and pair-rule gene products, it was hypothesized that initiators would act as the primary switches to determine if a domain was active or silenced. Unfortunately, although initiators are thought to play such a key role in BX-C gene regulation, their actual role has never been directly tested <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> due to the lack of appropriate mutations and the difficulties in performing homologous recombination in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila.</italic>
</p><p>Thus, in order to explore the function of initiators and other regulatory elements <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, we developed a method to streamline the homologous recombination process for rapid, precise, and systematic mutagenesis. Using this method, called InSIRT (<underline>In</underline>
<underline>S</underline>itu <underline>I</underline>ntegration for <underline>R</underline>epeated <underline>T</underline>argeting), we have created twenty new mutations in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> region of the BX-C, including mutations that directly test the role of the initiator in BX-C gene regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001260-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Synopsis of the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> locus of the BX-C and diagram of the mutations created for this study.</title><p>A. Synopsis of the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> locus of the BX-C. Diagram of the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> gene and its 3′<italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>regulatory region. The horizontal line represents the DNA sequence of the BX-C (see scale on top left). The <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression pattern in the central nervous system of a 10 hours embryo is shown above the DNA line. In parasegment 10 (PS10) <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> is present in a few nuclei at a relatively low level. This PS10-specific expression pattern is controlled by the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> regulatory domain located 55 kb downstream from the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> promoter. In PS11, PS12 and PS13, <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> is present in progressively more nuclei and at higher levels. These patterns are controlled by the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">iab-7</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-8</italic> regulatory domains, respectively. Each regulatory domain functions autonomously from its neighbors due to the presence of the boundaries that flank them (red ovals). B. Diagram of the mutations created for this study. The top line shows the DNA coordinates of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic>, according to the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> Genome Project. Below this line, and to approximate scale, are the locations of the various elements isolated from the BX-C including the IAB5 initiator<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, DNase hypersentive site 1 (HS1/<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> including the CTCF binding sites) and 2 (HS2/PRE) <xref rid="pgen.1001260-PerezLluch1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Holohan1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, the 2.8 kb <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator fragment <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, the minimal initiator fragment and the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-7</italic> boundary <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Hagstrom1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gyurkovics1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Below this line are the DNAs reintegrated to make the mutations. The various <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> alleles are indicated as solid bars, with gaps indicating the areas deleted. These bars are color coded such that blue bars indicate mutants that show no cuticle or CNS phenotypes at 25°C, red bars indicate mutants with <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic>-type phenotypes, turquoise bars indicate mutants with <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6</italic> phenotypes, and green bars indicate mutants with <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> phenotypes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pgen-1001260-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Mutations and phenotypes.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pgen-1001260-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region Deleted</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligos</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3R:12705250–12724572</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5<sup>Δ1</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12705410–12706585</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12705410–12708661</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4–5/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R: 12705410–12713431</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4–5/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12706583–12708661</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4–5/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D2+P6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>4+IAB5</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12717635–12718561†</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D6+P3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>1</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12716494–12719281</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5+P2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12717635–12719281</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D6+P2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>3</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12716494–12718561</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5+P3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12717635–12718561</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D6+P3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>5</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12717635–12724398</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D6+P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>6</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12712171–12724398</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4+P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>7</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12708714–12724398</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3+P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12712171–12716492</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4+P4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ5</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12721546–12724398</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D8+P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ6</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12719282–12724398</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7+P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ7</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12708714–12713431</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3+P5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>2</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12705410–12716492</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>3</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12705410–12718561</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>4</sup></italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">3R:12705410–12719281</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4/A5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1+P2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Column one lists the name of each mutation created for this work. Column two indicates the regions deleted in each line based on the coordinates of the Drosophila genome project (Release 5). Columns three and four summarize the transformations observed in the cuticle and embryonic CNS of A5/PS10 (labeled A5) and A6/PS11 (labeled A6). (†) indicates that in the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>4+IAB5</sup></italic> mutation, the sequence indicated was deleted, but was replaced by the sequence of the IAB5 initiator. (*) has been used to indicate that the cuticle trichome pattern occasionally shows signs of weak transformation towards A6. Based on other observations, we believe this could be a <italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>over expression effect <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Chiang1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Lewis2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref> due to the loss of PRE sequences. (**) Mutations <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ5</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ6</sup></italic> display a slight loss of A6 cuticle at 18°C. Finally column five indicates the oligos listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001260-t002">Table 2</xref> that were used to generate the corresponding deficiencies.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pgen-1001260-t002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Oligos used to generate the deletions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pgen-1001260-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dist</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGCCACTCACGCAGGACCCAGTTCCATCGAGGGATATTTATAGGGAGATG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CAGAAATGTAAAATAAACCTTTAATATTTTCTAACCATTCCAGAAATCTG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TACGAGCGAGCATCTTGCCAAAATGAGAAAACTTTTGCCAACACCAAACG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GACTAAACTCGAAGCACTTGAGCCGGCATATCTTTTTAATTTGGACGAGG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CCGACGACCGAGTGGTGGAATACGCGGAATCTGGTTAACAATCTTGTTTG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AAGTGCCCACTGTGCGCATGTGCGGGATTTCGCGTTGCCACGACCCATGG<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CGAGGGTCACAAAAAGAGGGGGCGGGGTGCTGGTTCCATGTGTCCCAGCC<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GGCAGCACGAATAGTTTAGTTTATTTTAGCCATAGCTCAAGAACGACAGC<bold>GAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prox</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGGCGTCATGTACCAGAATTTTCTTTGGCGGTGGAAAAGCGAGCAATTTC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GTCACTCGTTTTTCCAGTAATAAGGAGTATAAAATATATTAACTTACTGC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">AACAAGATTGTTAACCAGATTCCGCGTATTCCACCACTCGGTCGTCGGCC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">GCACGAAAGACCCACAACTGGACCCCGTGGAATATGAATGCATCTCGAGC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TTGGCAACAAAGTTGGATGCATTGTGGGTGGCAAAATATCAAACAATGGC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">CTTGGGCGAAGGGTTCGGCACTGGCTTCATTAAGTGCCAGAAGGTGCTGC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<named-content content-type="gene">TGCTGGGGATATAAAAGAAAAGTTTGGCAGGCCAAAATATTGGCCAACAC<bold>CTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG</bold>
</named-content>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P7</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Bold sequences correspond to the FRT-kanamycin-FRT sequences used to prime the amplification of the FRT-kanamycin-FRT cassette. Regular characters correspond to the homology regions used to generate the deletions by recombineering. P1–P7 correspond to the oligos used to generate the proximal breakpoint of the deletions (relative to the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> promoter), while D1–D8 correspond to the oligos used to generate the distal breakpoint.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results/Discussion</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Creation of an <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> integration site in the BX-C</title><p>To study the <italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>regulatory elements regulating BX-C homeotic gene expression within their natural chromosomal environment, we sought to design a method that could be used to rapidly and repeatedly target the BX-C for site-specific mutagenesis. Because this method is related to the SIRT method <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, we named it InSIRT for <underline>In S</underline>itu <underline>I</underline>ntegration for <underline>R</underline>epeated <underline>T</underline>argeting. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g002">Figure 2</xref> provides a rough schematic of this method as used here in the BX-C. In short, homologous recombination is used to replace a genomic region of interest with an entry site (<italic toggle="yes">attP</italic>) recognized by the φC31-bacteriophage integrase <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gong1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bischof1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Once a region of the genome is replaced by an <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> site, a DNA fragment corresponding to the deleted region can be systematically mutagenized <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and reinserted into its normal chromosomal location by φC31 integration. As φC31 integration is a relatively fast process (by genetic standards), InSIRT allows site-specific mutagenesis of actual genes to be accomplished within the timeframe required to create a simple transgenic fly. For our experiments, we replaced a 19.3 kb region of the BX-C, roughly corresponding to the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6 cis</italic>-regulatory domain, with a 255bp φC31 integrase <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g002">Figure 2</xref>; note that the previously identified IAB5 initiator fragment <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-7</italic> boundary element <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gyurkovics1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> are left intact by the deletion, while the area presumed to be the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary is removed <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>InSIRT.</title><p>A. Step one: Homologous Recombination. The original “ends-out” donor vector (pW25) was modified to contain an <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> insertion site and a removable <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic> reporter gene. Using the yellow reporter, homologous recombination events could be identified by screening for flies with yellow expression in the A5 and A6 segments (a consequence of having <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic> inserted in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> domain). The yellow reporter could then be removed to leave only the <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> site and a single <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> recombination site (white triangle) in place of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic>. B. Step two: Reintegration. Plasmids containing a 288 bp <italic toggle="yes">attB</italic> site, a single <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> site, a yellow reporter and a version of the 19.3 kb fragment were injected into <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> embryos expressing a maternally supplied φC31 integrase <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bischof1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Integration events were isolated based on yellow gene expression, then crossed to the Cre recombinase to remove the yellow gene and all vector backbone sequence.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Removal of <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domains in the BX-C typically results in the homeotic transformations of posterior segments towards anterior segments. The segments transformed depend on the <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domains removed and are transformed towards the last more-anterior segment whose <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domain is intact. For example, deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6 cis</italic>-regulatory domain should result in the transformation of segment A6 (whose development in specified by <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic>) into A5 (whose development is controlled by <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>). As we were attempting to delete only <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> in our deletion, we thus expected flies homozygous for our 19.3 kb deletion to display a typical iab-6 mutant phenotype. However, this was not the case. Flies homozygous for our 19.3 kb deletion have both their A5 and A6 segments transformed towards A4, indicating that both <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> activity are affected by our deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3</xref>). This can be clearly seen on the adult cuticle. Most of the segments of the adult fly abdomen can be identified independent of their position, by distinct cuticular features. For example, the wild type male sixth segment (A6) is distinguished from other segments by having a darkly pigmented tergite, covered in a distinctive pattern of tiny hairs, called trichomes, and is devoid of sternite bristles. Meanwhile, the fifth segment (A5) displays a similar darkly pigmented tergite that is uniformly covered with trichomes, and has a sternite with numerous bristles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Flies homozygous for our deletion display an A4-like pigmentation pattern on both the male fifth and sixth abdominal tergites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). Also, the A6 sternite, normally devoid of bristles, displays numerous bristle like the A4 or A5 sternite. Based on these phenotypes, we named our deletion <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>.</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> phenotype and rescue.</title><p>A. A wild-type adult male cuticle with A4-A6 labeled. Segment A5 differs from A6 based on the sternite shape and the bristles present on the A5 sternite. For reference, the A6 tergite is indicated by a red arrowhead and the A6 sternite is indicated by a red arrow. B. A wild-type embryonic nerve cord (anterior towards the top) stained with an antibody to <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> (brown). Notice the step gradient of <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression increasing in each parasegment towards the posterior. C. An adult male cuticle of a fly homozygous for the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> chromosome with A5 and A6 transformed towards A4 (notice the A4-like pigmentation on the tergites and the bristled sternites). D. The embryonic nerve cord of homozygous <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> embryos shows only a transformation of A6 into A5, as seen by the repetition of PS10/A5-like Abd-B levels in PS11/A6, indicating that the inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> is incomplete and not seen in the embryo. E. An adult male cuticle from a fly homozygous for the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>rescue</sup></italic> chromosome, where the entire 19.3 kb area deleted in <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> is reintegrated into <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>, looks completely wild type. F. The complete rescue is confirmed by the wild-type pattern of <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> in the embryonic ventral nerve cord.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>Although the adult cuticular phenotypes indicate that <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> function is affected in <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>, this inactivation is incomplete and only some PS10/A5 phenotypes are affected. For example, in the embryonic CNS, the PS10/A5 <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression pattern is normal, indicating that in embryos, <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> is still active (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3B</xref> with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). Also, while <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> null mutants are sterile, <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> mutants are fertile. Based on these results, we believe that <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> removes an adult cuticle enhancer from <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>, while leaving the rest of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> cis-regulatory domain intact. <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function, as would be expected of the deletion we created, seems to be universally affected, as both the adult cuticle, and the embryonic CNS staining are affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3C, 3D</xref>).</p><p>As a control for the InSIRT method, we first decided to reintegrate the 19.3 kb fragment removed in <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>. As expected, the reintegrated line, <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6 <sup>rescue</sup></italic>, reverts all phenotypes associated with <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> and demonstrates the feasibility of our approach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3E, 3F</xref>).</p><p>To begin our dissection of the <italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>regulatory elements in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> domain, we created a series of overlapping deletions spanning the 19.3 kb <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001260-t001">Table 1</xref>) and examined their resulting phenotypes on the adult cuticle and embryonic CNS. We will first discuss deletions affecting the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>The <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator is necessary, but not sufficient to control <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression in PS11/A6</title><p>Previously, we identified a 2.8 kb element from <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> that displayed the characteristics of an initiator in a transgenic reporter assay. Accordingly, this 2.8 kb fragment was shown to be able to drive the early expression of a <italic toggle="yes">lacZ</italic> reporter in a spatially restricted, pair-rule pattern, from PS11/A6 <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Unfortunately, as with other initiators, its precise function in the BX-C was never investigated genetically. We thus created a mutation that removes this 2.8 kb initiator fragment from the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> domain. The resulting mutant is named, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). According to the domain model, initiators should act as switches to turn on all of the enhancers in a domain. Thus, removal of the initiator from <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> should result in a complete loss of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function. This is, in fact, what we see. In flies homozygous for this deletion, A6 seems to be completely transformed into A5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). This can be clearly seen on the adult cuticle where the 6<sup>th</sup> sternite takes on the shape and bristle pattern characteristic of A5. The transformation can also be seen in the embryonic CNS, where the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression pattern in PS11/A6 is replaced by the pattern normally found in PS10/A5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4C</xref>).</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Phenotypes from initiator mutants.</title><p>Genotypes are as follows: A.–C. <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>1</sup></italic>, D.–F. <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic> and G.–I. <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic>. A., D. and G. show adult male cuticles. B., E. and H. show pseudo-darkfield views of the fifth and sixth tergites to visualize the trichome patterns. C., F. and I. show the Abd-B staining pattern in the embryonic nerve cord. In wild-type flies, A5/PS10 differs from A6/PS11 based on the sternite shape, the bristles present on the A5 sternite, the trichome pattern on the fifth and sixth tergites, and the Abd-B staining pattern in the CNS (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g003">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic> show transformations of A6 to A5 for all phenotypes monitored. Meanwhile <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic> shows only a partial transformation of A6 to A5 as seen by the sternite shape and trichome pattern on A6, which remain A6-like.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>In as much as the 2.8kb fragment had not been further dissected in the reporter gene assay, we decided to further narrow down the initiator by integrating smaller deletions from within the 2.8 kb fragment. In order to select these deletions, we first applied a bioinformatic approach (fly_Ahab: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gaspard.bio.nyu.edu/fly_ahab.html">http://gaspard.bio.nyu.edu/fly_ahab.html</ext-link>) to identify regions in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> domain that correspond to binding sites for known <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> transcription factors. Using this approach, we identified a potential <italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>regulatory module in an ∼900 bp region of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator. This module contains the predicted binding sites for the Kruppel, Caudal and Hunchback proteins, and is supported by recent genome-wide ChIP analysis (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu">http://genome.ucsc.edu</ext-link>). As previous work had indicated that initiators sense A-P position through the binding of the maternal, gap and pair-rule gene products <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Qian1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Zhou2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Shimell1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-White1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Casares1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, we decided to test if this ∼900 bp region is required for <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function in the BX-C. To do this, we created three overlapping deletions, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>3</sup></italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>, that each deletes this 900 bp region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). As flies homozygous for any of these three mutations display the same phenotype, we will concentrate on the smallest of these deletions, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>, which deletes only a 927 bp sequence corresponding to the identified <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory module. Flies homozygous for <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic> show a complete loss of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function, like that seen in <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> flies. The extent of the transformation is corroborated by the tergite trichome pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4E</xref>) and the embryonic <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression pattern in the CNS, where the PS11/A6-specific pattern is replaced by the pattern normally found in PS10/A5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4F</xref>). Based on these results, we conclude that this 927 bp fragment is absolutely necessary for <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> activation of <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> in PS11/A6. The fact that a deletion of the initiator is capable of completely removing <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> activity in the epidermis and the CNS, is consistent with the idea that the initiator functions as a switch to turn on all of the regulatory elements in a cis-regulatory domain. However, these results would also be consistent with the initiator being the sole positive regulatory element in A6/PS11. To rule out this possibility, we created another mutation that removes much of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> cis-regulatory region but leaves intact the 2.8 kb initiator fragment. This mutation, called <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref>), also shows a strong loss of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4G</xref>). Thus, although the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator is critical for <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function, it is not sufficient for <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> activity.</p><p>One important point to note regarding <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic> is that the loss-of-function (LOF) phenotype is slightly weaker than in <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>. The difference between these two mutants can be seen when examining the trichome pattern on the transformed A6. While the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic> mutation displays a transformed A6 with an A5-like trichome pattern (uniformly covered, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4E</xref>), the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic> trichome pattern still resembles that of a wild-type A6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g004">Figure 4H</xref>). This suggests that although <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>8</sup></italic> removes most of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> sequence, there is still some functionality left in the domain. This is an important finding because it supports a prediction of the domain model, which suggests that removal of cell-type specific enhancers would affect individual (or grouped) characteristic, while removal of initiator elements would affect all characteristics. To test this idea more directly, we next performed an initiator swapping experiment.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Initiators act as domain control centers for <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domains</title><p>The domain model suggests that initiators act as switches to turn on (or off) the various regulatory elements present in a domain. In the simplest state, this would mean that initiators would not participate directly in driving homeotic gene expression, but would simply coordinate the activity of cell/tissue-type specific enhancers along the A-P axis. If this were true, then we hypothesized that we should be able to transform a segment into another, simply by turning on the cell/tissue-type specific enhancers of domain in an area where they are normally off. Using our InSIRT method, we could do this by exchanging initiators from different domains.</p><p>For these experiments, we chose to remove the 927 bp <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator and replace it with the molecularly identified initiator from <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> initiator is defined as a 1 kb DNA fragment (called IAB5) that, when cloned in front of the <italic toggle="yes">Ubx-lacZ</italic> reporter gene, activates strong β-galactosidase in a pair-rule fashion from PS10 <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Therefore, if the domain model is correct, by replacing the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator with that of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>, we should be able to activate the enhancers required for PS11/A6 development in PS10/A5. As the difference in the expression pattern of <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> between PS10 and PS11 can be summarized as PS11 having a higher level of <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression than PS10 (and in more cells), we would expect ectopic activation of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> to be epistatic to the activity of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>. In other words, we expected to see a posterior transformation of A5 into A6.</p><p>As predicted by the domain model, the swapping of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator with that of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> results in a dominant A5 to A6 transformation that is stronger in homozygous flies. This type of posterior-directed abdominal transformation in the BX-C is typically called a <italic toggle="yes">Frontabdominal</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Fab</italic>) transformation. For this reason, we have named this new mutation, <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>IAB5</sup></italic>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g005">Figure 5C</xref> shows an abdominal cuticle of a <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>IAB5</sup></italic> homozygous male. In this fly, we observe an A6-like lack of A5 sternite bristles, an A6-like trichome pattern on the A5 tergite and a PS11/A6-like <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> pattern of expression in PS10/A5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g005">Figure 5F</xref>). The fact that A5 appears to be a copy of A6 suggests that everything required for the patterning of A6 is still present in the modified <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> domain, but that these elements have simply been activated one segment too-anterior. These findings strongly support the model in which initiators function, not as enhancers to directly control homeotic gene expression, but rather as domain control centers to turn on the other <italic toggle="yes">cis-</italic>regulatory elements in a domain.</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Phenotypes from initiator mutants.</title><p>Genotypes are as follows: A. and D. <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>. B. and E. wild type. C. and F. <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>IAB5</sup></italic>. A.–C. Show the ventral sternite cuticles made from adult males, homozygous for the genotype indicated above. Notice that A5 differs from A6 based on the sternite shape and the bristles present on the A5 sternite. The opposite homeotic transformations are highlighted by the direction of the arrows on the left and the right of the cuticles. D.–F. Show ventral nerve chords made from homozygous embryos of the genotypes indicated above. Parasegment borders are marked to the left.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Interestingly, in the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>IAB5</sup></italic> mutation, A6 seems to be unaffected by the IAB5 swap. As mentioned above, the IAB5 fragment drives reporter gene expression in a pair-rule manner from PS10/A5 (i.e. not in PS11) <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Busturia1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. In fact, reporter transgenes carrying the entire <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> domain are still only capable of driving reporter gene expression in a pair-rule fashion <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. If this assay reflects IAB5 activity <italic toggle="yes">in vivo,</italic> then what turns on <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> in PS11/A6? Currently, we do not have a completely satisfying answer to this question. However, previous genetic studies tell us that the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5 cis</italic>-regulatory domain is indeed capable of working in PS11/A6. In <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> mutants, for example, A6 is transformed into A5 <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Crosby1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Thus, it seems clear that our interpretation of IAB5 activity from the transgenic reporter assay, oversimplifies IAB5 function. This is perhaps not too surprising, as the reporter gene assays were designed to simply test if a DNA fragment is capable acting as an enhancer. From our experiments, however, it seems that initiators may have a more complex function that is not reflected in the transgene assay.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Mutations affecting <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary function</title><p>During our dissection of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> domain, we also created a number of deletions affecting <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary function. Boundaries function to keep domains autonomous. Based on what was observed in other boundary deletions, we know that boundaries prevent both ectopic activation of posterior domains by elements present in anterior domains (initiators), as well as, prevent anterior domains from being silenced by posterior silencing elements (PREs) <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Barges1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. The removal of a boundary element, therefore, results in a mixed transformation, where clones of cells in anterior segments become transformed towards cells of more-posterior segments, and clones of cells from posterior segments become transformed towards cells of more-anterior segments. Using our series of deletions, we have narrowed down the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary to an ∼650 bp region of the BX-C.</p><p>Previous work from our lab <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> genetically mapped the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary to an ∼4.5 kb region of the BX-C between the distal (relative to the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> transcription unit) breakpoints of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>IH</sup></italic> (3R:12712604) and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6,7<sup>1</sup></italic> (3R:12708067) mutations. By using deletions nested on the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic>-distal side of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> mutation, we were able to quickly narrow down the location of the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary further. The first deletion we will speak about, <italic toggle="yes">iab-5<sup>Δ1</sup></italic>, removes an ∼1.2 kb region from the distal side of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> but displays no visible phenotype. This indicates that neither the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> cuticle enhancer (see above), nor the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary element is removed by this deletion. On the other hand, two bigger deletions, removing ∼3.2 kb and ∼8 kb respectively (<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>), show mixed anteriorizing (LOF) and posteriorizing (GOF) transformations of A5 and A6 towards A4 or A6. An example of this (<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>) can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g006">Figure 6A</xref> where we see a loss of bristles on the A5 sternite (indicative of a posterior-directed transformation of A5 to A6), and a loss of pigmentation on the A5 tergite (indicative of an anterior-directed transformation of A5 to A4). Meanwhile, in the A6 segment of each mutant, we see a gain of bristles on the sternite and a loss of pigmentation on the tergite, both indicative of an anterior-directed transformation (probably towards A4). Although very similar, we must note that the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic> mutation displays a slightly stronger GOF phenotype than <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> (data not shown). Consistent with this finding, a PRE has recently been mapped to the region differentiating the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic> mutations <xref rid="pgen.1001260-PerezLluch1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Thus, if <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic> functions like other boundary mutations, the enhanced <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> GOF phenotype is probably caused by deleting this silencing element and shifting the balance between GOF and LOF phenotypes.</p><fig id="pgen-1001260-g006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001260.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary mutations.</title><p>The genotypes of the adult male cuticles of A. <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic>, and B. <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup>.</italic> C. (wild type) and D. (<italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup></italic>) are embryonic nerve cords stained for Abd-B protein. Notice the increased level of Abd-B in PS10 in mutants (D.) relative to wild-type (C.).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pgen.1001260.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The smallest mutation we created that displays an <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> phenotype is <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup></italic> which deletes an ∼2 kb span of DNA between the proximal breakpoints of <italic toggle="yes">iab-5<sup>Δ1</sup></italic> (3R:12706585) and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> (3R:12708661). As expected <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup></italic> displays a phenotype similar to <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g006">Figure 6B</xref>) with mixed gain- and loss-of-function phenotypes. Meanwhile, a deletion spanning the PRE region that differs between <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>2</sup></italic> shows no phenotype (<italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ7</sup></italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref>), suggesting that the critical elements required for <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> function are all contained in <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6<sup>3</sup></italic>. Thus, when combining our new data with those of the past, we can now narrow down the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary to an ∼650 bp region, spanning from the proximal breakpoint of <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6,7<sup>1</sup></italic> (3R:12708067) to the distal breakpoint of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ7</sup></italic> (3R:12708714). Consistent with this mapping, it has recently been shown that this region contains binding sites for the insulator protein dCTCF <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Holohan1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, and that a fragment containing these dCTCF binding sites blocks enhancer-promoter interactions in an insulator reporter assay <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Additional mutations in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> region</title><p>Other deletions created for this study are presented here, solely for the purpose of completeness. These additional deletions are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1</xref> and their phenotypes are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001260-t001">Table 1</xref>. Although we will not discuss these mutants in detail, we would like to point out two key issues surrounding these mutations. First, all deletions removing the initiator fragment show a loss of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function comparable to that seen in <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>4</sup></italic>. This finding is in agreement with the domain model and our data, which suggests that the initiator is absolutely required for activating <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> function in the cuticle and CNS. Second, we have also isolated a number of mutations that show no noticeable <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> phenotype. These mutations, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ7</sup></italic>, <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ5</sup></italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ6</sup></italic>, remove a total of ∼9.8 kb of <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> sequence without dramatically changing the morphology of the adult cuticle or modifying the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression pattern in the embryonic CNS (data not shown). Does this mean that these sequences are without function? Absolutely not. In fact, we know that the region deleted in <italic toggle="yes">iab-6<sup>Δ7</sup></italic> probably contains a PRE, whose deletion produces a phenotype when combined with the deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-6</italic> boundary. Also, as we have scanned only a small fraction of the possible developmental pathways in which <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> is involved, we believe that it is very likely that these other regions contain cell-type specific enhancers controlling <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> expression in other tissues than the CNS and the cuticle. Obviously, now that we have the ability to manipulate regions of the BX-C at a base-pair level, we now require equally precise methods to monitor potential phenotypic changes.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>The initiator and a hierarchical structure to gene regulation</title><p>For more than twenty years, much of the work on the BX-C has proceeded on the assumption that the BX-C cis-regulatory regions control homeotic gene expression through a multilayered, hierarchical process, summarized in the domain model. Key to this model was the idea that there existed specialized switch elements to control the activity state of the entire domain. Based on transgenic assays, these switch elements were thought to be special early embryonic enhancers, often called initiators. Although through the years, we, and others, have generated many results consistent with this model, we were never able to directly test initiator function <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic>, due to experimental difficulties. Thus, a key prediction of the domain model went untested for decades. Here, we have finally provided the data confirming the key role of the initiator in domain activation.</p><p>Besides being important for studies on BX-C gene regulation, our findings highlight the possibility of having elements whose sole function may be to control the activity state of other elements. Although we still do not understand how this is accomplished mechanistically, we believe that it is probably through modifying the local chromatin environment around the enhancers. In fact, taking into account the enhancer activity of initiators in transgenic constructs, we are left with an intriguing and testable model for initiator action. As mentioned above, initiators were first isolated as early embryonic enhancers that turned on reporter gene expression in an A-P restricted manner. It has been known for years that the <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory sequences of the BX-C are transcribed in a parasegment-specific manner where transcripts from each <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domain are expressed along the A-P axis in correspondence to where a domain is expected to be active <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-SanchezHerrero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In other experiments it has been shown that forced transcription across PREs in the BX-C can prevent Pc-dependent silencing, and hence, activate a domain <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bender2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>–<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Schmitt1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Thus, by combining these findings, it is possible to imagine a causal relationship between the initiator and transcription, and the transcription of a domain and domain activation. Accordingly, we propose that initiators might act as enhancers, responding to gap and pair-rule gene products to activate transcription from promoters within the <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory domains. In doing so, they would indirectly activate homeotic gene expression by preventing the <italic toggle="yes">Pc</italic> silencing of homeotic gene enhancers. Using the tools developed here, we are now in the process of testing this model.</p><p>Another question that we can now address using InSIRT is whether or not initiators are required later in development. Thus far, we have been discussing initiators as only functioning early in development. It is still possible, however, that initiators are constantly required for domain activation or that they play a later role in the regulation of homeotic gene expression. Although the initiator being constantly required to keep a domain active cannot be ruled out, based on our current understanding of initiator function, we do not believe this to be the case. Perhaps the strongest evidence supporting this belief comes from transgenic assays. In transgenic assays, initiator fragments seem to respond to the maternal, gap and pair-rule gene products. Upon disappearance of the early expression pattern of these proteins, initiator activity in transgenes often disappears, or produces a pattern of expression not restricted along the A-P axis (if not paired with a PRE/maintenance element). Based on this, we believe that their role in coordinating the activity of a domain is probably limited to early development. However, this does not mean that all initiators would have no activity outside of initiation phase, only that their function in domain initiation would be limited to early embryogenesis. As mentioned above, the pattern of reporter gene expression driven by some initiator fragments degenerates into a cell-type specific enhancer-like pattern later in development. Therefore, it may be possible that DNA fragments with initiator function may also contain cell-type specific enhancers.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>InSIRT as a method to study gene expression</title><p>The transgenic reporter assay has played an important role in shaping our understanding of eukaryotic gene expression <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Small1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Its advantages stem from its speed and the cleanliness of the approach in isolating <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory elements away from competing or obfuscating signals. To gain these advantages, reporter assays must make a number of critical assumptions. First, they must assume that an activity performed by an element in the reporter assay, is the activity performed by the element <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Second, they must assume that critical transcriptional activities can be tested using the molecular construct devised. And third, they must assume that it is through the addition of these <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-regulatory activities that controlled gene expression is achieved. However, these assumptions are not always correct. Although in the study of the BX-C, transgenes have been extremely useful in estimating the activity of elements, our work on the initiator and our previous work on boundary elements <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Cleard1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref> highlight how sometimes the activity seen in transgenes assays only represents a portion of an element's activity <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><p>InSIRT is a complementary approach. Relative to the transgenic approach, InSIRT has one main advantage: it tests for changes on biologically relevant targets without necessarily simplifying or assuming an activity. This is key when trying to understand unusual regulatory elements, like initiators. Furthermore, this advantage can be achieved with only a small penalty in time, as, once the homologous recombination has been performed, InSIRT mutagenesis takes only as much time as establishing a single transgenic line. Because transgenic approaches often require the analysis of multiple lines to control for genomic position effects, this penalty is further reduced. Thus, we believe that InSIRT offers scientists a powerful new tool that can be used in combination with classical transgenic methods to better study gene regulation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Fly methods and phenotypes</title><p>All crosses, and cuticle preparations were performed using standard <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> methods. <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> antibody staining was performed as in <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> monoclonal antibody was purchased from the “Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank” at the University of Iowa. Injection experiments were performed using cleaned DNA preparations (Qiagen) and injected into the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> flies stocks containing an X chromosome expressing the φC31 integrase enzyme under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">vasa</italic> promoter <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Bischof1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.frontiers-in-genetics.org/flyc31/">http://www.frontiers-in-genetics.org/flyc31/</ext-link>).</p><p>Phenotypes depicted are representative of the genotypes shown. As some of the boundary phenotypes seem to be clonal in nature, there is an occasional variance in the exact number of bristles and the exact pattern of trichomes. We have, therefore, attempted to choose an average representative cuticle for display. Otherwise, the phenotypes can be considered 100% penetrant.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Homologous recombination</title><p>Creation of a donor vector for homologous recombination: An <italic toggle="yes">AscI-NotI</italic> fragment containing the <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic> reporter gene flanked by the two <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> sites, and a 255 bp <italic toggle="yes">attP</italic> integration site was cloned into pW25 digested with <italic toggle="yes">AscI-NotI</italic> to create the pY25 plasmid. Homology regions of ∼4 kb were created by PCR using the following primer pairs: IAB7-<italic toggle="yes">AvrII</italic>: <named-content content-type="gene">CCTAGGCGGCGAACAGTAGGGAAG</named-content> and Fab7-<italic toggle="yes">AscI</italic>: <named-content content-type="gene">CAGC-AAAAATCGTAAAAAAG</named-content>, and IAB5-<italic toggle="yes">NotI</italic>: <named-content content-type="gene">GCGGCCGCGGTCAGTAAACGG-GTCCC</named-content> and IAB5-SpHI: <named-content content-type="gene">GCATGCACTGGCGACATTTCTC</named-content>. These homology regions were then cloned into the pY25 vector in the <italic toggle="yes">AvrII</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">AscI</italic> sites or the <italic toggle="yes">NotI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SphI</italic> sites respectively. The resulting P-element vector, Py-del <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic>, was injected into <italic toggle="yes">yw</italic> flies and transformants were isolated as <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic>
<sup>+</sup> flies. Homologous recombination was performed using two independent transformants and the ends-out homologous recombination method of Gong and Golic <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Gong1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>.</p><p>Potential homologous recombinants were isolated based on their yellow pigmentation limited to the segments posterior and including A5 (as a result of being in <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic>). Genomic southern blots, however showed that all identified events were aborted recombination events in the BX-C. As aborted events happened on each side of the targeted region, we were able to generate the final “planned” deletion by recombining two chromosomes each having recombined properly at one homology region. This recombination was mediated by the Cre recombinase at the <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> sites left behind after removal of the <italic toggle="yes">yellow</italic> reporter gene. The final chromosome, <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic>, was verified by genomic southern blot and sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Generation of integration vectors</title><p>A base vector containing the 19.3 kb area deleted in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> deletion, a 288 bp <italic toggle="yes">attB</italic> sequence, a yellow reporter, and one <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> site (called KsY-iab6H) was generated using gap-repair recombineering (<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref> see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-1001260-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). For this, ∼500 bp PCR products were generated to both the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> regions (each starting at the breakpoints of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> deletion) using the following primers:</p><p>Iab-5 N: <named-content content-type="gene">ATAAGAATGCGGCCGCGGTGCGTTTCCATTT-TCCCTAGG</named-content>
</p><p>Iab-5 new (+PmeI): <named-content content-type="gene">CTCACCATAGAGCACCACGTTTAAACGTCGT-CCGGAAATGGCAACCAG</named-content>
</p><p>Iab-6: <named-content content-type="gene">CTTTGCCAGCTTTTGCCACTCGTCC</named-content>
</p><p>Iab-6P(+PmeI): <named-content content-type="gene">GGTTGCCATTTCCGGACGACGTTTAAACGGTG-AAGGCGCG-AAACTGTGA</named-content>.</p><p>These two products were linked using overlap PCR. This 1 kb fragment was then cloned into a vector containing a 288 bp <italic toggle="yes">attB</italic> sequence, a yellow reporter, and one <italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> site (in that order), resulting in the plasmid, Ks-Y <italic toggle="yes">attB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic>.</p><p>The Ks-Y <italic toggle="yes">attB</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">loxP</italic> plasmid was digested with <italic toggle="yes">PmeI</italic> and used in recombineering experiments to capture the 19.3 kb region deleted in the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5,6<sup>CI</sup></italic> deletion. All recombineering procedures were performed as in (<xref rid="pgen.1001260-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Basically, the digested plasmid was transformed by electroporation into heat-shock induced competent cells of the EL350 recombineering bacterial strain that was previously transformed with the <italic toggle="yes">Abd-B</italic> region-containing BAC, BACR24L1 (BACR24L18, GenBank: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AC095018">AC095018</ext-link>). The resulting plasmid is called KsY-iab6H.</p><p>The KsY-iab6H was then modified using recombineering. For the initiator deletions, we generated PCR fragments containing a Kanamycin selector gene surrounded by two FRT sites, using primers containing 5′ leaders with 50 bp of homology to the region flanking the sequences to be deleted. The FRT-kanamycin-FRT DNA template for PCR came from pGEM1-K7-FRT-Kan-FRT (kindly provided by François Spitz). For the modification of KsY-iab6H by recombineering, PCR targeting fragments (containing an FRT-Kan-FRT cassette) were generated using the primers listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-1001260-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p><p>For the recombineering of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6/iab-5</italic> initiator swap, the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> initiator was amplified by PCR using the following primers:</p><p>s-sub-iab5 <named-content content-type="gene">5′ATGGCGCGCCGGAGGCGGCAAATGCACAAAG3′</named-content>
</p><p>as-sub-iab5 <named-content content-type="gene">5′ATGGCGCGCCTACTACGCCGATTCTGCTGG3′</named-content>
</p><p>Two fragments (of 1.7 kb and 1.3 kb, respectively), each homologous to one side of the <italic toggle="yes">iab-6</italic> initiator were amplified by PCR using the following primers:</p><p>sub1-AscI: <named-content content-type="gene">5′ATGGCGCGCCCAGATTTCTGGAATGGTTAGAAAAT-ATTAAAGG3′</named-content>
</p><p>sub2-NotI: <named-content content-type="gene">5′ACTCGCGGCCGCTCGGAAACATCAAAGCATCAGCA-AC3′</named-content>,</p><p>sub3-AscI: <named-content content-type="gene">5′ATGGCGCGCCGCAGTAAGTTAATATATTTTATAC-TCC3′</named-content>
</p><p>sub4-NotI: <named-content content-type="gene">5′ACTCGCGGCCGCAGAGAAATATATTCTTTGGCAG-CGAGC3′</named-content>.</p><p>The IAB5 initiator was cloned between these regions of homology using the AscI restriction site to create the vector, Target iab5(+). An FRT-Kan-FRT cassette was amplified by PCR using the following primers:</p><p>5′ SnaBI: <named-content content-type="gene">5′ACATGGAAAACAACAGTTTCAATCAGGTCATGTAC-CTAATAAATGTATACGAATACAAGCTTGGGCTGCAGG3′</named-content>
</p><p>3′ SnaBI <named-content content-type="gene">5′AGCTTACATTTTGATAGCTTAAGTGGATGTTTCAAGGA-ATTTATATATACCTCGCCCGGGGATCCTCTAGAG3′</named-content>
</p><p>This cassette was then cloned into a unique SnaBI site within the 1.7 kb homology domain (245 bp from the IAB5 initiator) of Target iab5(+), to make Target iab5(+) Kan FRT. A NotI fragment containing the two homology regions, the IAB5 initiator and the Kan-FRT cassette was then used to recombineer the <italic toggle="yes">iab-5</italic> swap integration vector. The recombineering was otherwise performed as above.</p><p>Upon recombineering on the KsI-iab6H plasmid, the plasmids carrying the designed deletion were selected on Kan plates. The Kanamycin cassette was then removed using a bacterial strain expressing the flipase enzyme under an inducible arabinose promoter (EL 250; <xref rid="pgen.1001260-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank François Spitz for guiding us during our first attempts at recombineering. We also thank Jean-Michel Gibert for discussions and critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This work was supported by grants to FK from the Sate of Geneva, the Swiss National Foundation for Research, the NCCR "Frontiers in Genetics," and the Claraz Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen.1001260-Lewis1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>A gene complex controlling segmentation in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">103000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/276565a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-SanchezHerrero1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Herrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morata</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Genetic organization of Drosophila bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>313</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3917555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/313108a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Maeda1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The ABC of the BX-C: the bithorax complex explained.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16556913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.02323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Peifer1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>The bithorax complex: control of segmental identity.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1.9.891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30184830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-SanchezHerrero2"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Herrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Control of the expression of the bithorax complex genes abdominal-A and abdominal-B by cis-regulatory regions in Drosophila embryos.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1680047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.111.2.437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Celniker1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celniker</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keelan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>The molecular genetics of the bithorax complex of Drosophila: cis- regulation in the Abdominal-B domain.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>4277</fpage><lpage>4286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2265608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1990.tb07876.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC552210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Karch1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiffenbach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>The abdominal region of the bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3935319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(85)90014-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Bender1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Molecular genetics of the bithorax complex in Drosophila melanogaster.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>221</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17737996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.221.4605.23</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Simon1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Regulatory elements of the bithorax complex that control expression along the anterior-posterior axis.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>3945</fpage><lpage>3956 Issn: 0261-4189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1979031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1990.tb07615.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC552165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Qian1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capovilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>The bx region enhancer, a distant cis-control element of the Drosophila Ubx gene and its regulation by hunchback and other segmentation genes.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1902784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1991.tb07662.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC452803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Muller1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Sharp anterior boundary of homeotic gene expression conferred by the fushi tarazu protein.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>3653</fpage><lpage>3661 Issn: 0261-4189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1356761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1992.tb05450.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC556825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Busturia1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busturia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Silencers in abdominal-B, a homeotic Drosophila gene.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>1425 Issn: 0261-4189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8096812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1993.tb05785.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC413353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Zhou1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barolo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>The Fab-7 element of the bithorax complex attenuates enhancer-promoter interactions in the Drosophila embryo.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>3195</fpage><lpage>3201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.10.24.3195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Hagstrom1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Fab-7</italic> functions as a chromatin domain boundary to ensure proper segment specification by the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>3202</fpage><lpage>3215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8985188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.10.24.3202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Hagstrom2"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>A <italic toggle="yes">Polycomb</italic> and GAGA dependent silencer adjoins the <italic toggle="yes">Fab-7</italic> boundary in the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> bithorax comple.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>1365</fpage><lpage>1380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9258680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/genetics/146.4.1365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1208081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Fritsch1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kassis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>The DNA-binding Polycomb group protein Pleiohomeotic mediates silencing of a Drosophila homeotic gene.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>3905</fpage><lpage>3913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.126.17.3905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Zhou2"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Characterization of the transvection mediating region of the abdominal- B locus in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>3057</fpage><lpage>3065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10375498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.126.14.3057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Barges1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barges</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mihaly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Fab-8</italic> boundary defines the distal limit of the bithorax complex <italic toggle="yes">iab-7</italic> domain and insulates <italic toggle="yes">iab-7</italic> from initiation elements and a PRE in the adjacent <italic toggle="yes">iab-8</italic> domain.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>127</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.127.4.779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Horard1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Structure of a polycomb response element and in vitro binding of polycomb group complexes containing GAGA factor.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>3187</fpage><lpage>3197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10757803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mcb.20.9.3187-3197.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC85613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Shimell1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Functional analysis of repressor binding sites in the iab-2 regulatory region of the abdominal-A homeotic gene.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>218</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/dbio.1999.9576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Gruzdeva1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruzdeva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyrchanova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parshikov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kullyev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The Mcp Element from the bithorax Complex Contains an Insulator That Is Capable of Pairwise Interactions and Can Facilitate Enhancer-Promoter Communication.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>3682</fpage><lpage>3689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MCB.25.9.3682-3689.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1084309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Mihaly1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mihaly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barges</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sipos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Dissecting the regulatory landscape of the Abd-B gene of the bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>2983</fpage><lpage>2993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.02451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Maeda2"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The bithorax complex of Drosophila an exceptional Hox cluster.</article-title><source>Curr Top Dev Biol</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19651300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0070-2153(09)88001-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Maeda3"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Cis-regulation in the Drosophila bithorax Complex.</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><volume>689</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20795320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-4419-6673-5_2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Pirrotta1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Distinct parasegmental and imaginal enhancers and the establishment of the expression pattern of the Ubx gene.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>141</volume><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8601485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/genetics/141.4.1439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1206878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Muller2"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kassis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Polycomb response elements and targeting of Polycomb group proteins in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gde.2006.08.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Ringrose1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ringrose</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Polycomb/Trithorax response elements and epigenetic memory of cell identity.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.02723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Schwartz1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Polycomb silencing mechanisms and the management of genomic programmes.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17173055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrg1981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Chiang1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Discrete Polycomb-binding sites in each parasegmental domain of the bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1689 Issn: 0950-1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7600985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.121.6.1681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Gyurkovics1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyurkovics</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gausz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kummer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>A new homeotic mutation in the Drosophila bithorax complex removes a boundary separating two domains of regulation.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>2579</fpage><lpage>2585 Issn  0261-4189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1973385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1990.tb07439.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC552290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Mihaly2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mihaly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gausz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyurkovics</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>In situ dissection of the Fab-7 region of the bithorax complex into a chromatin domain boundary and a Polycomb-response element.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>1809</fpage><lpage>1820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9165128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.124.9.1809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Maeda4"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Making connections: boundaries and insulators in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17904351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gde.2007.08.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Gao1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A powerful method combining homologous recombination and site-specific recombination for targeted mutagenesis in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>13999</fpage><lpage>14004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0805843105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2529331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Gong1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golic</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Ends-out, or replacement, gene targeting in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>2556</fpage><lpage>2561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12589026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0535280100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC151379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Groth1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calos</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Phage integrases: biology and applications.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>335</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14687564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jmb.2003.09.082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Bischof1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bischof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hediger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>An optimized transgenesis system for Drosophila using germ-line-specific φC31 integrases.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>3312</fpage><lpage>3317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0611511104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1805588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-White1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>A gap gene, hunchback, regulates the spatial expression of Ultrabithorax.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2876779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0092-8674(86)90453-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Irish1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Arias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Spatial regulation of the Antennapedia and Ultrabithorax homeotic genes during Drosophila early development.</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1527</fpage><lpage>1537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2569971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1989.tb03537.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC400984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Zhang1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bienz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Target sequences for hunchback in a control region conferring Ultrabithorax expression boundaries.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1179 Issn: 0950-1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1687458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.113.4.1171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Shimell2"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Enhancer point mutation results in a homeotic transformation in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>264</volume><fpage>968</fpage><lpage>971 Issn: 0036-8075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7909957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.7909957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Casares1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez Herrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Regulation of the infraabdominal regions of the bithorax complex of Drosophila by gap genes.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1866 Issn: 0950-1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7600999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.121.6.1855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Crosby1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosby</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundquist</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tautvydas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>The 3′ regulatory region of the Abdominal-B gene: genetic analysis supports a model of reiterated and interchangeable regulatory elements.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>824 Issn: 0016-6731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8349112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/genetics/134.3.809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1205518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-PerezLluch1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Lluch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuartero</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azorin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinas</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Characterization of new regulatory elements within the Drosophila bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>6926</fpage><lpage>6933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkn818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2588531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Holohan1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holohan</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adryan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartkuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>CTCF genomic binding sites in Drosophila and the organisation of the bithorax complex.</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e112</fpage><comment>doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.0030112">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030112</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1904468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Smith1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loukinov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Genome wide ChIP-chip analyses reveal important roles for CTCF in Drosophila genome organization.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>328</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19210964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ydbio.2008.12.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6620017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Bae1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drewell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Characterization of the intergenic RNA profile at abdominal-A and Abdominal-B in the Drosophila bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>16847</fpage><lpage>16852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.222671299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC139232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Cumberledge1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cumberledge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaratzian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakonju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Characterization of two RNAs transcribed from the cis-regulatory region of the abd-A domain within the Drosophila bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>3259</fpage><lpage>3263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1692133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.87.9.3259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC53879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Lipshitz1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipshitz</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peattie</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogness</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Novel transcripts from the Ultrabithorax domain of the bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3119423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1.3.307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-SanchezHerrero3"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Herrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Spatially ordered transcription of regulatory DNA in the bithorax complex of Drosophila.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2632227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.107.2.321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Bender2"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Transcription activates repressed domains in the Drosophila bithorax complex.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>129</volume><fpage>4923</fpage><lpage>4930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.129.21.4923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Hogga1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Transcription through the iab-7 cis-regulatory domain of the bithorax complex interferes with maintenance of Polycomb-mediated silencing.</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>129</volume><fpage>4915</fpage><lpage>4922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12397100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.129.21.4915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Schmitt1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prestel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Intergenic transcription through a polycomb group response element counteracts silencing.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15741315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.326205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1065723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Small1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warrior</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of a pair-rule stripe in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2026328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.5.5.827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Cleard1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moshkin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Probing long-distance regulatory interactions in the Drosophila melanogaster bithorax complex using Dam identification.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng1833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Lee1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez de Velasco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tessarollo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swing</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>A highly efficient Escherichia coli-based chromosome engineering system adapted for recombinogenic targeting and subcloning of BAC DNA.</article-title><source>Genomics</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11352566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/geno.2000.6451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Liu1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A highly efficient recombineering-based method for generating conditional knockout mutations.</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.749203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC430283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pgen.1001260-Lewis2"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Regulation of the genes of the bithorax complex in Drosophila.</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3868476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/sqb.1985.050.01.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>