
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3534039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3534039.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3534039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3534039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23300937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-21953</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Research Design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Mental Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavior</subject><subject>Social Psychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nursing Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Nursing Education</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ophthalmology</subject><subj-group><subject>Corneal Disorders</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral and Social Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and Behavioral Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Social Psychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Attitudes Underlying Corneal Donation in a Group of Trainee Allied Health Professionals</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Underlying Influences to Corneal Donation</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlade</surname><given-names initials="D">Donal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McClenahan</surname><given-names initials="C">Carol</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierscionek</surname><given-names initials="B">Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>School of Biomedical Science, University of Ulster, Coleraine, Northern Ireland</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>School of Psychology, University of Ulster, Coleraine, Northern Ireland</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Science, Engineering and Computing, Kingston University London, Kingston upon Thames, Surrey, England</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names initials="MS">Mercedes Susan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Colorado, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>b.pierscionek@kingston.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DM CM BP. Performed the experiments: DM. Analyzed the data: DM CM BP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DM CM BP. Wrote the paper: DM CM BP.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">216913</issue-id><elocation-id>e53538</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-03-29 21:51:41.797"><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2012 McGlade et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>McGlade et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0053538.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The focus of this study was to investigate factors that may influence personal willingness to register consent to donate corneal tissue upon death using the theory of planned behaviour in a relatively ethnically homogenous group of trainee allied health professionals. The attainment of this knowledge will be of paramount importance in relation to potential interventions that are designed to change donation-related behaviour.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A questionnaire-based study was undertaken with 92 pre-registration nurses (mean age 24.0 years (standard deviation ±5.6 years); female:male  = 89:3) enrolled at a University in Northern Ireland. Intention to register consent to donate corneal tissue upon death was assessed using both direct and belief-based measures found in the theory of planned behaviour. Descriptive statistics were used to assess demographic information, with correlation and regression analyses being used to identify factors influencing intentions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The majority of participants were religious (94.6%, n = 87) and mostly Protestant (58.7%, n = 54) or Catholic (35.9%, n = 33). Generally speaking, the theory of planned behaviour accounted for 84% of the variance in intention to register consent. In relation to the constructs found in the theory of planned behaviour, attitude was found to be the strongest predictor of intention to register consent, with subjective norm being the second strongest predictor. Perceived behavioural control did not significantly predict intention to register consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The theory of planned behaviour has allowed an understanding of the factors that influence the personal intentions of a group of future allied health professionals from the same ethnic group to register consent to donate their corneal tissue.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite the advancements made in transplantation medicine, one of the major factors that limits and hinders transplantation in the United Kingdom is the shortage of available donor tissues <xref rid="pone.0053538-Marks1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Although corneal transplantation can help improve and restore sight to those with poor visual function, it has been shown that 10% of people on the national Organ Donor Register are unwilling to donate their corneae <xref rid="pone.0053538-NHSBT1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Unfortunately this level of unwillingness has demonstrated a rise of 3% from the previous year <xref rid="pone.0053538-NHSBT2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. A recent analysis of data in the United Kingdom has shown that significant regional differences exist, especially in relation to the donation of corneal tissue <xref rid="pone.0053538-McGlade1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. More importantly, it has been found that Northern Ireland possesses the lowest rate of corneal donation across the United Kingdom for the majority of years examined <xref rid="pone.0053538-McGlade1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. While it has been suggested that unwillingness to donate may be based on the individual's attitude, social structures, cultural practices and religious beliefs <xref rid="pone.0053538-McGlade1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> conclusive evidence has yet to be found.</p><p>Several attempts have been made to determine the relationship between attitude and behaviour and how this may influence the decision making process of organ donation <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, a significant gap in knowledge exists with regards to the opinions and attitudes of nurses, who are the allied health professionals most frequently involved in donor tissue collection <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ertin1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. It is notable that whilst nurses play a leading role in the donation and transplantation system <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ertin1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, the emergence of evidence suggests that this group of health professionals commonly exhibit concerns about their lack of knowledge of organ donation <xref rid="pone.0053538-Akgn1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Zambudio1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Due to the existence of these gaps in knowledge <xref rid="pone.0053538-Akgn1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Zambudio1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and the low levels of provisions afforded to health professionals to undertake appropriate training <xref rid="pone.0053538-Anker1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Garde1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>; health professionals' opinions and practices will therefore more likely be based on a personal locus of control. This perspective may create conflict for the health professional and affect their ability to engage in pro-social behaviours <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ammerman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Pipe1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>.</p><p>This paper presents the factors that influence personal willingness to register consent to donate corneal tissue upon death among a group of trainee allied health professionals based in Northern Ireland. The study focussed on pre-registered nurses at the same stage of training, mostly within a similar age range and in a part of the UK where ethnic homogeneity is high. Participants had not undergone any teaching on organ donation and transplantation and none had worked in this area. The level of variance in knowledge is therefore low. The study used a well-established theoretical framework <xref rid="pone.0053538-Armitage1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> known as the theory of planned behaviour. The theory of planned behaviour takes into consideration salient beliefs about the likely consequences of the behavior (behavioural beliefs), beliefs about the expectations of others (normative beliefs) and beliefs about those factors that may encourage or prevent performance of the behavior (control beliefs) <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ajzen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Behavioural beliefs produce either a favourable or unfavourable attitude towards the behaviour, normative beliefs result in perceived social pressure or subjective norm to perform or refrain from the behaviour; with control beliefs resulting in a perceived behavioural control with regards to the level of ease or difficulty in performing the behaviour <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ajzen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. The theory of planned behaviour proposes that an intention to perform a behaviour will be directly influenced by the individual's attitude, subjective norm and perceived behavioural control <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ajzen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. The theory of planned behaviour has been applied to a wide range of health and health-related behaviours, including alcohol consumption <xref rid="pone.0053538-Huchting1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, food consumption <xref rid="pone.0053538-Blanchard1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, smoking <xref rid="pone.0053538-BenNatan1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and blood donation <xref rid="pone.0053538-Giles1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Participants and procedures</title><p>The study was designed as a questionnaire-based analysis that received permission from the University of Ulster Research Ethics Committee. A total of 92 students were recruited using convenience sampling from the School of Nursing at the University of Ulster, Northern Ireland. All participants were pre-registered nursing students undertaking a full-time degree course leading to the award of BSc. (Hons). The study was conducted during January 2012. Participation in the study was voluntary and without any form of compensation.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>The questionnaire</title><p>To ensure consistency was maintained throughout, a vignette was provided at the beginning of the questionnaire that informed participants about the nature of the study and the behaviour under investigation. The questionnaire consisted of two defined sections: demographics and theory of planned behaviour-based items. Demographical items consisted of gender, age and religion; the theory of planned behaviour section was developed into direct and belief-based items as recommended in a previous study <xref rid="pone.0053538-Fishbein1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Participants completed items assessing their intention, attitude, subjective norms and perceived control that were based on findings from the literature <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Giles1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Armitage2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde4" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. An elicitation study, conducted in accordance to recommendations <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ajzen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, was used to construct the belief-based items. The questionnaires were self-explanatory and required participants to respond using a seven-point forced-choice Likert-type scale.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Measures contained within the questionnaire</title><sec id="s2c1"><title>Attitude</title><p>Six items in total were included to assess direct attitude (e.g. For me to register my consent to donate my eyes is good/bad) and had a high level of internal consistency (Cronbach's α  = 0.96). The score for direct attitude ranged from 1 to 7.</p><p>Seven behavioural belief-based items have been used (e.g. Registering my consent to donate my eyes would make me feel good/bad); with each belief statement converted into seven corresponding outcome evaluations (e.g. Feeling better about myself is good/bad). Using recommended procedures <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, a unipolar response scale (1 to 7) was used for behavioural beliefs, with a bipolar response scale (−3 to +3) for outcome evaluations. The indirect measures of attitude have been obtained by multiplying the participant's perception about performing the behaviour (behavioural belief) with their corresponding evaluation of the consequences of performing the behaviour (outcome evaluation) <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The score for each indirect attitude item ranged from ±21. A composite score had then been obtained by summing all weighted behavioural beliefs <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and ranged from ±147. <italic toggle="yes">(See caveat below regarding scoring of belief-based measures using the multiplicative composite approach.).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="s2c2"><title>Subjective norm</title><p>Three items in total were included to assess direct subjective norms (e.g. Most people who are important to me think I should/should not register my consent to donate my eyes) and had a high level of internal consistency (Cronbach's α = 0.85). The score for direct subjective norm ranged from 1 to 7.</p><p>Seven normative belief-based items have been used (e.g. I think that my family would be likely/unlikely to want me to register my consent to donate my eyes); with each belief statement converted into seven corresponding motivational statements (e.g. I am likely/unlikely to do what my family thinks I should do). Using recommended procedures <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, a bipolar response scale (−3 to +3) was used for normative beliefs, with a unipolar response scale (1 to 7) for motivational outcomes. The indirect measures of subjective norm have been obtained by multiplying the participant's perception of the expectations of other referent individuals about performing the behaviour (normative belief) with their corresponding motivation to comply (motivational outcome) <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The score for each indirect subjective norm item ranged from ±21. A composite score had then been obtained by summing all weighted normative beliefs <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and ranged from ±147. <italic toggle="yes">(See caveat below regarding scoring of belief-based measures using the multiplicative composite approach.).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="s2c3"><title>Perceived behavioural control</title><p>Eight items in total were included to assess direct perceived behavioural control (e.g. I see myself as capable/incapable of registering consent to donate my eyes) and had an acceptable level of internal consistency (Cronbach's α  = 0.69). The score for direct perceived behavioural control ranged from 1 to 7.</p><p>Fifteen control belief-based items have been used (e.g. Having more information on how to register would make registering consent more likely/less likely); with each belief statement converted into 15 corresponding measures of control (e.g. Having more information on how to register would make registering consent much easier/much more difficult). Using recommended procedures <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, a unipolar response scale (1 to 7) was used for control beliefs, with a bipolar response scale (−3 to +3) for control outcomes. The indirect measures of perceived behavioural control have been obtained by multiplying the participant's perceived presence of factors that may influence or impede upon their ability (control belief) with their corresponding measure of control (control outcome) <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. The score for each indirect perceived behavioural control item ranged from ±21. A composite score had then been obtained by summing all weighted control beliefs <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and ranged from ±315. <italic toggle="yes">(See caveat below regarding scoring of belief-based measures using the multiplicative composite approach.).</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="s2c4"><title>Behavioural intention</title><p>Three items in total were included to assess behavioural intention (e.g. I agree/disagree that I intend to register my consent to donate my eyes) and had an excellent level of internal consistency (Cronbach's α  = 0.97). The score for behavioural intention ranged from 1 to 7.</p></sec><sec id="s2c5"><title>The scoring of belief-based measures using the multiplicative composite approach</title><p>Despite the theory of planned behaviour being one of the most well-established and widely applied models of the socio-cognitive determinants in health and health-related behaviours <xref rid="pone.0053538-Armitage1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, inconsistencies regarding the scoring methods employed for belief-based measures continue to exist <xref rid="pone.0053538-Evans1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Whilst it has been argued that belief-based measures should make use of a weighting process involving both a unipolar and bipolar scale <xref rid="pone.0053538-Francis2" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, it has also been suggested that this may lead to statistically uninterpretable findings <xref rid="pone.0053538-Evans1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Participants were predominantly female (96.7%, n = 89), reflecting the gender base of the profession <xref rid="pone.0053538-NursingandMidwifery1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Age ranged from 18 to 46 years, with a mean of 24.0 years and a standard deviation of 5.6 years. The majority of participants (84.8%, n = 78) were under 30 years of age, with 13.1% (n = 12) aged between 30 and 39 years old and 2.2% (n = 2) aged 40 years or older. The majority had some form of religious affiliation (94.6%, n = 87), most frequently reported as either Protestant (58.7%, n = 54) or Catholic (35.9%, n = 33).</p><sec id="s3a"><title>Predicting intentions</title><p>To identify the factors influencing pre-registration nurses' intentions to personally register their consent, correlation and regression analyses were conducted. Means, standard deviations and correlations of intention among the theory of planned behavior constructs and beliefs have been shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t001">Table 1</xref>. All direct constructs and indirect measures of belief demonstrated a moderate to high level of correlation. For direct items, attitude exhibited the greatest degree of correlation with intention to register consent, followed by subjective norm and finally perceived behavioural control. For the belief-based measures, normative beliefs exhibited the greatest degree of correlation with intention, followed by behavioural beliefs and control beliefs.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053538-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Means, standard deviations and correlations of intention with the theory of planned behaviour direct constructs (attitude, subjective norm and perceived behavioural control) and the respective underlying behavioural, normative and control beliefs.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0053538-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0053538.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1) Intention</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2) Attitude</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3) Subjective norm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4) Perceived behavioural control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5) Behavioural beliefs<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">1</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6) Normative beliefs<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">1</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7) Control beliefs<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">1</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">standard deviation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.75</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>p&lt;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>1</label><p>Using a composite score.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In order to further explore the relative importance of the main independent variables in the prediction of intention, a hierarchical multiple regression analysis was conducted (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t002">Table 2</xref>). As religion was the only demographical item that correlated with intention, it was entered as an independent variable on Step 1 (F<sub>1,85</sub>  = 6.57, p = 0.012) and accounted for 7% (6% adjusted) of the variance in intention to register consent. The theory of planned behaviour constructs were added in Step 2 (F<sub>4,82</sub>  = 105.68, p&lt;0.001) and accounted for 84% (83% adjusted) of the variance in intention to register consent (F change<sub>3,82</sub>  = 128.84, p&lt;0.001). The standardised regression coefficients demonstrated that attitude was the strongest predictor of intention to register consent (β = 0.78, p&lt;0.001) followed by subjective norm (β = 0.12, p = 0.045). However, the construct of perceived behavioural control failed to significantly predict intention to register consent (β = 0.08, p = 0.126).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053538-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Hierarchical multiple regression of intention to register consent on religion (Step 1) and the theory of planned behaviour direct constructs (Step 2).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0053538-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0053538.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted R<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">β</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Step 1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.268<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Step 2</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attitude</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.84**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective norm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">*</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived behavioural control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.05; ** p&lt;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Relationship between intention and the indirect measures of belief</title><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t003">Table 3</xref> highlights the relationship between intention to register consent and the beliefs that underpin the pre-registration nurse's attitude. It indicates that all seven beliefs found in the questionnaire correlate significantly with intention to register consent. Of those beliefs, helping to improve feelings of self-worth exhibited the greatest degree of correlation with intention, with family decision making showing the lowest degree of correlation with intention.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053538-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Means and standard deviations of behavioural beliefs and Pearson's correlations (r) of behavioural beliefs with intention.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0053538-t003-3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0053538.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beliefs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Make me feel better about myself</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allow other people to think I am a better person</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Will set a good example for others to follow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Will help to minimise family conflict</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Help to improve another person's life</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Give hope to someone in need</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ensure that my family are in a better position to carry out my wishes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.88</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.05; ** p&lt;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t004">Table 4</xref> highlights the relationship between intention to register consent and the beliefs that underpin subjective norms. The results indicate that all seven beliefs correlate significantly with intention to register consent. Of those beliefs, pre-registration nurses expressed that their friends would most expect them to register consent, closely followed by family members. The lowest degree of correlation with intention to register consent was found with the expectations of charitable organisations that support people who need a corneal transplant.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053538-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Means and standard deviations of normative beliefs and Pearson's correlations (r) of normative beliefs with intention.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0053538-t004-4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0053538.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normative belief</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">My friends would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">My family would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health care professionals would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The family of people who need a corneal transplant would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">People who need a corneal transplant would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religious groups would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charitable organisations that support people who need a corneal transplant would want me to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t005">Table 5</xref> highlights the relationship between intention to register consent and the beliefs that underpin the pre-registration nurse's perceived behavioural control. The results indicate that of the 15 beliefs found in the questionnaire, three beliefs did not correlate significantly with intention to register consent. These included: body appearance; issues of mortality; and the existence of superstitions. For the beliefs that did correlate significantly, it is apparent that certain factors appear to encourage pre-registration nurses to personally register their consent. These include: improving access to information on how to register; increasing awareness of what eye donation involves; facilitating the process of registration at more convenient places; and raising awareness about the benefits of donation. Barriers to registering consent included: fears concerning other people looking through their eyes; issues of identity and impersonation; a general objection to ‘not having eyes’; and concerns that eye donation would result in a delay in burial.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053538-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053538.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Means and standard deviations of control beliefs and Pearson's correlations (r) of control beliefs with intention.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0053538-t005-5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0053538.t005.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beliefs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Having more information on how to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being more aware of what eye donation involves</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being able to register at more convenient places</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being more knowledgeable about the benefits of donation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Having more opportunity to discuss donation with my family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The thought of someone else looking through my eyes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The thought of someone else assuming my identity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowing that my decision to register would cause less distress to my family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowing that my family would approve of my decision to register</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knowing whether religious groups support organ donation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The thought of not having my eyes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A possible delay in my burial</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26**</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The appearance of my body after death without my eyes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Having to think about death</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The thought of registration bringing me bad luck</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.65</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><label>*</label><p>p&lt;0.05; ** p&lt;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>During its existence the theory of planned behaviour has been applied to a wide range of health and health-related behaviours, including that of organ donation <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. The results from these studies demonstrate that the theory of planned behaviour has been successful in explaining between 51% and 74% of the variance in intention to register as an organ donor <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. The findings obtained from this investigation provide further support for the predictive ability of the theory of planned behaviour as it has been capable of accounting for 84% (83% adjusted) of the variance in intention to register consent for corneal donation in this sample of pre-registered nurses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t002">Table 2</xref>). What is striking is that the findings obtained are somewhat higher than the variance explained in previous studies <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. This higher level of variance is most likely to be the result of using a target population that has more altruistic tendencies (based on choice of profession) than that of the general population <xref rid="pone.0053538-Heyes1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>.</p><p>In relation to the constructs found in the theory of planned behaviour, attitude was found to be the strongest predictor of intention to register consent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t002">Table 2</xref>). This is consistent with results from previous research that confirmed attitude as being the most significant predictor of intention to register consent for those considering organ donation in general <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, three groups found the construct of attitude to be the weakest predictor of intention <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Subjective norm was found to be the second strongest predictor of intention to register consent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t002">Table 2</xref>) and is consistent with results from previous research <xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Other studies have found the predictive ability of subjective norm to be either lower <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> or higher <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> than that found in this investigation. In contrast to the predictive power of attitude and subjective norm, perceived behavioural control failed to significantly predict intention to register consent to corneal donation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053538-t002">Table 2</xref>). This lack of predictive ability is consistent with results from previous research that found registering consent to be within volitional control <xref rid="pone.0053538-Park1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, it is important to note that most other studies did find perceived behavioural control to have a significant role to play in helping predict intentions to register consent <xref rid="pone.0053538-Godin1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Hyde3" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053538-Bae2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.</p><p>The results also indicate that the majority of beliefs that underpin the constructs found in the theory of planned behaviour correlate significantly with intention to register consent. For instance, a positive association between registering consent and the benefits of improved self-worth and self-image has been confirmed in this investigation. This is not a surprising result considering that it has been shown that participation in a voluntary and altruistic act can positively impact upon the perception of an individual regarding his/her own character <xref rid="pone.0053538-Schwatz1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Skowronski1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. With regards to the beliefs that underpin subjective norm, the findings highlight those people who are considered influential in helping to make a well-informed decision. It is also apparent from the results that certain factors may encourage registration of consent. Therefore it would be important for awareness campaigns to be implemented and directed exclusively towards health professionals. This would be in a bid to ensure appropriate levels of knowledge are maintained on issues surrounding the benefits of donation while informing audiences about the process of eye donation in a manner that will be conducive to donation. This is an important aspect that needs to be considered, as it has been shown that the removal of certain barriers will positively impact upon the implementation of organ donation-related behaviours <xref rid="pone.0053538-Siegel1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>.</p><p>The results generated by this sample demonstrate merit in the need for further research to be conducted within this important area particularly as it has been recognised that many previous interventions have been ineffective at eliciting behaviour change <xref rid="pone.0053538-Michie1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> due to a lack of theoretical underpinning <xref rid="pone.0053538-Michie2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>.</p><p>Further work needs to consider larger samples of groups such as nurses who are involved in organ donation and registration of potential donors. Future investigations comparing results from nurses originating and residing in different regions of the UK and in different countries are warranted. Longitudinal studies on the same cohort of individuals looking at questionnaires taken at pre-registration, early in post-registration and at regular intervals during their established careers would offer important insights into whether attitudes, perceptions, salient beliefs and behaviours alter with experience. In addition to nurses, attitudes, beliefs and perceptions of medical doctors and other health-care practitioners who deal with organ donation, as well as those of broader based cohorts from the general population, and indeed from a range of populations in different countries, need to be probed. This may indicate why wide variations in organ donation rates are found when making inter-nation comparisons <xref rid="pone.0053538-McGlade1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>This study utilised a convenience sample and it is recognised that the use of convenience sampling to recruit participants limits the ability to make generalisations about the total population from which the sample was chosen. However, the sample of future nurses was selected because a) it is nurses who predominantly deal with issues of organ donation and the recruitment of donors and b) a student population is most likely to provide responses that are as yet unaffected by experiences in professional practice and therefore will reflect the underlying beliefs of the individual. The sample was also biased towards females, which is indicative of the gender balance of the nursing profession <xref rid="pone.0053538-NursingandMidwifery1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Nevertheless, data generated by this convenience sample does provide valuable information about behaviour that may underlie corneal donation in a group of trainee allied health professionals.</p><p>Whilst the current study has adopted the method endorsed by Ajzen <xref rid="pone.0053538-Ajzen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, the method for assessing expectancy-value and the inconsistencies that may arise with regard to scoring of belief-based measures has been challenged <xref rid="pone.0053538-Evans1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> and labelled the ‘expectancy-value muddle’. In essence, the measurement of beliefs with different forms of item scaling (uni- or bipolar) coupled with multiplicative composite of beliefs and evaluations of outcome renders the computation statistically lacking in interpretation <xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Four alternative measures to resolve this have been suggested but all have either practical or conceptual limitations <xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Recently, Newton et al have proposed a solution using dimensional salience <xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. This requires participants to choose a small number of salient beliefs from a list and, assuming that personally salient beliefs have a greater likelihood of eventuating than non-salient beliefs <xref rid="pone.0053538-Cronen1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, these beliefs could be used to denote the expectancy component. The assumption was tested and found to be satisfied, indicating that the summation of a participant's value ratings of his/her salient beliefs could replace the multiplicative composite <xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p><p>The methodology required for application of dimensional salience was not used in this study; belief-based items were obtained through an elicitation study. Whilst this study offers conceptual insights into the attitudes of a relatively homogenous cohort of trainee nurses; further investigations, designed in accordance with the dimensional salience approach <xref rid="pone.0053538-Newton1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> will provide additional statistical information that can offer better predictive capacity of attitude and intention.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The present survey findings demonstrate that the theory of planned behaviour continues to provide a benchmark against which to investigate the socio-cognitive determinants of behaviour. More specifically, the theory of planned behaviour has allowed an understanding of the factors that influence the intention of pre-registered nurses based in Northern Ireland to register consent to donate their corneal tissue. It has been shown that attitude is the strongest predictor of intention to register consent, with subjective norm being ranked second and perceived behavioural control lacking any predictive ability. This adds to the body of knowledge about potential interventions that may alter donation-related behaviour.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the students that participated in the elicitation and main studies.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0053538-Marks1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orlowski</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Organ donation and utilization, 1995–2004: entering the collaborative era</article-title>. <source>Am J Transplant</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1101</fpage>–<lpage>1110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16613590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2006.01269.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-NHSBT1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">NHSBT (2011) Transplant activity in the UK 2010–2011. Bristol: NHSBT.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-NHSBT2"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">NHSBT (2009) Transplant activity in the UK 2008–2009. Bristol: NHSBT.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-McGlade1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">McGlade D, Rae G, McClenahan C, Pierscionek B (2011) Regional and temporal variations in organ donation (secondary analyses of databases). BMJ Open doi:10.1136.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3211055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Bresnahan1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bresnahan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shearman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nebashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A theory of planned behaviour study of college students' intention to register as organ donors in Japan, Korea, and the United States</article-title>. <source>Health Commun</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17567252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10410230701307436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Godin1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bélanger-Gravel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagné</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blondeau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Factors predictive of signed consent for posthumous organ donation</article-title>. <source>Prog Transplant</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18615976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/152692480801800208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Hyde1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>To be a donor or not to be? Applying an extended theory of planned behavior to predict posthumous organ donation intentions</article-title>. <source>J Appl Soc Psychol</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Hyde2"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Communication prompts donation: exploring the beliefs underlying registration and discussion of the organ donation decision</article-title>. <source>Br J Health Psychol</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18783643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1348/135910708X339542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Hyde3"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Disclosing donation decisions: the role of organ donor prototypes in an extended theory of planned behaviour</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Res</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1080</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/her/cyp028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Park1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Distinctiveness and influence of subjective norms, personal descriptive and injunctive norms, and societal descriptive and injunctive norms on behavioral intent: a case of two behaviors critical to organ donation</article-title>. <source>Hum Commun Res</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Ertin1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ertin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmanci</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmutoglu</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basagaoglu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nurse-focussed ethical solutions to problems in organ transplantation</article-title>. <source>Nurs Ethics</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21097969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0969733010378933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Akgn1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akgün</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bilgin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokalak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haberal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Organ donation: a cross-sectional survey of the knowledge and personal views of Turkish health care professionals</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1273</fpage>–<lpage>1275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0041-1345(03)00437-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Bener1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shoubaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Maslamani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Do we need to maximise the knowledge and attitudes level of physicians and nurses towards organ donation and transplant?</article-title>
<source>Exp Clin Transplant</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19338484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Flodn1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Flodén</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A phenomenographic study of ICU-nurses' perceptions of and attitudes to organ donation and care of potential donors</article-title>. <source>Intensive Crit Care Nurs</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19608419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.iccn.2009.06.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Ozdag1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ozdag</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The nurses knowledge, awareness and acceptance of tissue-organ donation</article-title>. <source>EDTNA</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1755-6686.2001.tb00179.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Smith1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Smith M, McGee H (2004) Organ donation services in Ireland: current situation and future prospects. Dublin: Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Wight1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wight</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deblander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Donor action: a systematic approach to organ donation</article-title>. <source>Transplant Proc</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2253</fpage>–<lpage>2254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9723460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0041-1345(98)00609-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Zambudio1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zambudio</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Alarcón</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parrilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramírez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Attitude of nursing staff toward organ donation in a Spanish hospital with a solid-organ transplant program</article-title>. <source>Prog Transplan</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/152692480901900415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20050463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Anker1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anker</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feeley</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruejler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Teaching organ and tissue donation in medical and nursing education: a needs assessment</article-title>. <source>Prog Transplant</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20050457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/152692480901900409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Garde1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garde</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Organ donation: knowledge and attitudes of nursing and college students</article-title>. <source>J Transpl Coord</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Ammerman1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ammerman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeVellis</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keyserling</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strogatz</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Physician-based diet counselling for cholesterol reduction: current practices, determinants, and strategies for improvement</article-title>. <source>Prev Med</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8475015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/pmed.1993.1007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Bleich1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bleich</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gudzune</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impact of physician BMI on obesity care and beliefs</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/oby.2011.402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3645927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Spencer1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elon</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hertzberg</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serdula</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Predictors of nutrition counselling behaviors and attitudes in US medical students</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>655</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16960182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajcn/84.3.655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Abramson1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaufele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frates</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Personal exercise habits and counseling practices of primary care physicians: a national survey</article-title>. <source>Clin J Sport Med</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10695849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00042752-200001000-00008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Kawahara1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minowa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Study of the smoking behavior of medical doctors in Fukui, Japan and their antismoking measures</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10860299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2188/jea.10.157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Kawakami1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Relation between smoking status of physicians and their enthusiasm to offer smoking cessation advice</article-title>. <source>Intern Med</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2169/internalmedicine.36.162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Nardini1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nardini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoletti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rastelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The influence of personal tobacco smoking on the clinical practice of Italian chest physicians</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir</source>
<volume>J12</volume>: <fpage>1450</fpage>–<lpage>1453</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1183/09031936.98.12061450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9877508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Pipe1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pipe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Physician smoking status, attitudes toward smoking, and cessation advice to patients: an international survey</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ Couns</source>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18774670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pec.2008.07.042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Armitage1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Efficacy of the theory of planned behaviour: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Br J of Soc Psychol</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11795063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1348/014466601164939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Ajzen1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ajzen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The theory of planned behaviour</article-title>. <source>Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Huchting1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huchting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LaBrie</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>An application of the theory of planned bahavior to sorority alcohol consumption</article-title>. <source>Addict Behav</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>538</fpage>–<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.addbeh.2007.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2387076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Blanchard1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kupperman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sparling</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nehl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Do ethnicity and gender matter when using the theory of planned behaviour to understand fruit and vegetable consumption?</article-title>
<source>Appetite</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.appet.2008.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8080276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-BenNatan1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Natan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golubev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shamrai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Smoking during pregnancy: analysis of influencing factors using the theory of planned behaviour</article-title>. <source>Int Nurs Rev</source>
<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20796071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1466-7657.2010.00807.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Giles1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McClenahan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mallet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>An application of the theory of planned behaviour to blood donation: the importance of self-efficacy</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Res</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/her/cyg063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Fishbein1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Fishbein M, Ajzen I (2010) Constructing a reasoned action questionnaire. In: Predicting and changing behavior: the reasoned action approach. New York: Psychology Press. 449–454.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Armitage2"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Social cognitive determinants of blood donation</article-title>. <source>J Appl Soc Psychol</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1431</fpage>–<lpage>1457</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Bae1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Entertainment-education and recruitment of corneal donors: the role of emotion and issue involvement</article-title>. <source>J Health Commun</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18307134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10810730701806953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Hyde4"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Are organ donation communication decisions reasoned or reactive? A test of the utility of an augmented theory of planned behaviour with the protoype/willingness model</article-title>. <source>Br J Helath Psychol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1348/135910709X468232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19769797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Francis1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Francis JJ, Eccles MP, Johnston M, Walker A, Grimshaw J, et al.. (2004) Constructing questionnaires based on the theory of planned behaviour: a manual for health service researchers. Newcastle: Centre for Health Services Research.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Evans1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The problem of analyzing multiplicative composites: interactions revisited</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-French1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hankins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The expectancy-value muddle in the theory of planned behaviour – and some proposed solutions</article-title>. <source>Br J Health Psychol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12643815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1348/135910703762879192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Newton1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Resolving the theory of planned behaviour's 'expectancy-value muddle' using dimensional salience</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21879806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/08870446.2011.611244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Francis2"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Francis JJ, Johnston M, Eccles MP, Grimshaw J, Kaner EFS (2004) Measurement issues in the theory of planned behaviour: a supplement to the manual for constructing questionnaires based on the theory of planned behaviour. Newcastle: Centre for Health Services Research.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-NursingandMidwifery1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Nursing and Midwifery Council (2008) Statistical analysis of the register 1 April 2007 to 31<sup>st</sup> March 2008. London: Nursing and Midwifery Council.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Bae2"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The influence of viewing an entertainment-education program on cornea donation intention: a test of the theory of planned behavior</article-title>. <source>Health Commun</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18443996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10410230701808038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Heyes1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heyes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The economics of vocation or “why is a badly paid nurse a good nurse”?</article-title>
<source>J Health Econ</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>569</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2004.09.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Schwatz1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwatz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>The social psychology of the gift</article-title>. <source>AJS</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6072579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/224432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Skowronski1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Skowronski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>On the psychology of organ donation: attitudinal and situational factors related to the willingness to be an organ donor</article-title>. <source>Basic Appl Soc Psych</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Siegel1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Siegel JT, Alvaro EU, Hohman ZP (2010) A drawing recognition of factors for increasing donor registration. The IIFF model. In Siegel JT, Alvaro EM, editors. Understanding organ donation. Chichester, West Sussex: Wiley-Blackwell. 313–330.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Michie1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Interventions to change health behaviours: evidence-based or evidence-inspired?</article-title>
<source>Psychol Health</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Michie2"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardeman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>From theory to intervention: mapping theoretically derived behavioural determinants to behaviour change techniques</article-title>. <source>J Appl Psychol</source>
<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053538-Cronen1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cronen</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conville</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Fishbein's conception of belief strength: A theoretical, methodological and experimental critique</article-title>. <source>Speech Monographs</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>