
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3248464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC3248464.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">3248464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">3248464</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22242140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-23588</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Epigenomics</subject><subject>Functional Genomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromosome Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Chromatin</subject><subject>Chromosome Structure and Function</subject><subject>Meiosis</subject><subject>Mitosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Yeast and Fungal Models</subject><subj-group><subject>Saccharomyces Cerevisiae</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nucleic acids</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA recombination</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of Biological Features Associated with Meiotic Recombination Hot and Cold Spots in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Recombination Hot and Cold Spots in Yeast</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names initials="L">Loren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="NK">Nak-Kyeong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariño-Ramírez</surname><given-names initials="L">Leonardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landsman</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Computational Biology Branch, National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Library of Medicine, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Boston University, Bioinformatics Program, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, Virginia, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>PanAmerican Bioinformatics Institute, Santa Marta, Magdalena, Colombia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names initials="IK">I. King</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Georgia Institute of Technology, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>marino@ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LH DL LM-R. Performed the experiments: LH N-KK. Analyzed the data: LH N-KK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LH N-KK. Wrote the paper: LH DL LM-R.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">203141</issue-id><elocation-id>e29711</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>01</month><year>2012</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-03-29 01:47:08.690"><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Hansen et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0029711.pdf"/><abstract><p>Meiotic recombination is not distributed uniformly throughout the genome. There are regions of high and low recombination rates called hot and cold spots, respectively. The recombination rate parallels the frequency of DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs) that initiate meiotic recombination. The aim is to identify biological features associated with DSB frequency. We constructed vectors representing various chromatin and sequence-based features for 1179 DSB hot spots and 1028 DSB cold spots. Using a feature selection approach, we have identified five features that distinguish hot from cold spots in <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> with high accuracy, namely the histone marks H3K4me3, H3K14ac, H3K36me3, and H3K79me3; and GC content. Previous studies have associated H3K4me3, H3K36me3, and GC content with areas of mitotic recombination. H3K14ac and H3K79me3 are novel predictions and thus represent good candidates for further experimental study. We also show nucleosome occupancy maps produced using next generation sequencing exhibit a bias at DSB hot spots and this bias is strong enough to obscure biologically relevant information. A computational approach using feature selection can productively be used to identify promising biological associations. H3K14ac and H3K79me3 are novel predictions of chromatin marks associated with meiotic DSBs. Next generation sequencing can exhibit a bias that is strong enough to lead to incorrect conclusions. Care must be taken when interpreting high throughput sequencing data where systematic biases have been documented.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Meiosis is the biological process by which the genome is divided in half to generate daughter cells that can participate in sexual reproduction. In eukaryotes, this process is accompanied by meiotic recombination, which involves pairing of homologous chromosomes and exchanging of genetic material. Meiosis serves to increase genetic diversity in progeny (for review see <xref rid="pone.0029711-Lichten1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0029711-MartinezPerez1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>). Recombination does not occur with a uniform frequency across the genome. Instead, there are regions with high and low recombination rates called hot and cold spots, respectively. Recombination is initiated by double-strand breaks (DSBs) which are catalyzed by Spo11 <xref rid="pone.0029711-Keeney1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. In this biological event, broken DNA ends are processed to produce single-strand ends that can invade the homologous chromosome <xref rid="pone.0029711-Petes1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Mapping DSB hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Buhler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Blitzblau1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and factors correlated with hot/cold spot formation is an active area of research. Several biological features have been found to correlate with higher levels of Spo11-catalyzed DSBs. Genome-wide mapping and analysis of Spo11-catalyzed DSB sites in the yeast <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> showed that regions with a high break frequency had a high G+C content <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. A recent study using this same dataset revealed that several types of microsatellites were associated with recombination hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Bagshaw1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Additionally, studies using machine learning-based techniques and sequence-based features have differentiated DSB hot and cold spots somewhat successfully <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, suggesting that differences in sequence composition between these regions exist.</p><p>In addition to sequence-based factors, chromatin structure is associated with regions of high and low recombination. Many hot spots exhibit an open chromatin structure constitutively in both meiotic and mitotic cells <xref rid="pone.0029711-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Ohta1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Some of these hot spots also show an increase in micrococcal nuclease (MNase) sensitivity in meiotic cells shortly before DSB formation <xref rid="pone.0029711-Murakami1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, indicating active chromatin remodeling to a more open configuration upon the onset of meiosis. Some posttranslational histone marks are also associated with increased DSB frequency, with H3K4me4 and bulk histone acetylation (in <italic toggle="yes">Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>) showing a positive correlation <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamada1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> and H3K36 methylation exhibiting a negative correlation. Here we used a multivariate feature selection approach to determine the sequence and chromatin features that best distinguish hot and cold spots in <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic>. The histone modifications and nucleosome occupancy data used in our analysis were derived from vegetatively growing mitotic cells, which is a different cell state than meiotic cells. Genome-wide epigenetic studies using both mitotic and meiotic states were used to increase the amount of useable data; there is good reason to believe that epigenetic marks found at hot or cold spots in mitotic cells will also be present at those same sites in meiotic cells (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Discussion</xref>).</p><p>Feature selection is a dimensionality reduction technique designed to identify the subset of features that is most informative in producing robust predictive models. Feature selection has been used successfully in microarray gene expression studies <xref rid="pone.0029711-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Sha1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and biomarker identification <xref rid="pone.0029711-Xiong1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Shin1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. When attempting to build a classifier based on vectors of features, many features are irrelevant. For example, a common task in microarray studies is to identify which genes are relevant in distinguishing between two or more experimental conditions. In this case, the expression level of thousands of genes (i.e., features) is measured, but only a small subset is relevant in discriminating between the experimental conditions. Many pattern recognition techniques were not designed to deal with circumstances in which the number of relevant features is outnumbered by irrelevant ones <xref rid="pone.0029711-Saeys1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In these instances, feature selection can be used to reduce over fitting, improve predictive performance by identifying a subset of relevant features, and provide insight into the underlying biological processes that generated the data. Machine learning-based approaches have already been applied to the problem of discriminating between hot and cold spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, these studies analyzed low resolution data and feature selection was not performed. Here we report the results of applying feature selection to identify factors associated with recombination hot and cold spots. A feature vector as used in this study is a string of numerical features; each feature in the string represents a measurement of a biological quantity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Definition of hot and cold regions</title><p>Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Buhler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> mapped the frequency of meiotic DSBs in S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic> with high resolution tiling arrays. Using this data, we obtained 1179 and 1028 regions identified as hot and cold spots, respectively, for a total of 2207 regions. Each region was 600 base pairs (bp) in length. Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> produced a set of peaks representing hot spots with 5-fold and 2-fold enrichment over background. In our analysis, hot spots were defined by centering a 600-bp window at the midpoint of peaks that were enriched 5-fold over background. Cold spots were obtained by finding at least three adjacent probes with a log2 hybridization ratio of less than 0.75, and then centering a 600-bp window at the midpoint of the centermost probe. For each region, we produced a vector of length 350 to represent features such as the chromatin-associated factors “Nucleosome occupancy”, “H3K14ac”, “H3K36me3”, “H3K4me1”, “H3K4me2”, “H3K4me3”, “H3K79me3”, and “H3K9ac”.</p><p>Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> identified hot spots by mapping the binding of Spo11 using high throughput sequencing. We centered 600-bp windows at the middle of hot spots as defined by Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Cold spots were defined by a set of non-overlapping 600 bp windows with no reads aligned that did not overlap to any extent simple repeats as downloaded from the UCSC genome browser.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Generation of chromatin structure-based features</title><p>Pokholok <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> used tiling arrays to map histone modifications in S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>. We obtained this data from the public database ArrayExpress Archive (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/</ext-link>) and normalized using MA2C normalization <xref rid="pone.0029711-Song1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. There are a number of publically available datasets containing additional chromatin marks mapped genome wide that potentially could have been included in this study. Unfortunately they are low resolution; one microarray element per ORF or intergenic region or they do not control for differences in nucleosome occupancy. For each region, we obtained the degree of enrichment by averaging the normalized hybridization values of the probes within that region. For example, the feature “H3K14ac” represents the average degree of acetylation of lysine 14 in histone H3 for the given region. A similar approach was used for each histone modification. To calculate the degree of nucleosome occupancy we used a dataset produced by Kaplan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. For most positions in the genome, Kaplan and co-authors calculated a nucleosome occupancy score. The average nucleosome occupancy was normalized to zero. A value greater than zero represents nucleosome enrichment relative to the genome-wide average, while a value less than zero signifies nucleosome depletion. For each hot or cold region, nucleosome occupancy was calculated by averaging the nucleosome occupancy scores for that region.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Generation of sequence-based features</title><p>In this study, 342 out of 350 features were sequence-based in which each sequence feature represented the normalized frequency of the region for one of the 1–4 possible k-mers. For example, feature 9 for region × would be the number of times the 2-mer “AT” was found in the region divided by the number of k-mers of size 2 found in the region. Hence the feature represents the enrichment of AT relative to all 2-mers found in the region. Similarly, feature 300 for region × would be the number of times “AAGT” was found in the region divided by the number of k-mers of size 4 found in the region. We also included two sequence features “AT content” and “GC content”, reflecting the overall AT and GC content for that region, respectively. It would seem the sequence features could further be reduced by removing the reverse complement of the given k-mer (CG is the same as GC). Whether or not the reverse complement is redundant is based on whether or not strand specific processes are acting at Hot spots. There are examples of strand specific trans-acting factors operating at hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-White1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Hence reverse complements were retained in the final set of features.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Feature selection</title><p>Feature selection can be described as finding the subset of features from the set of all possible combinations of features that can best distinguish classes of interest. Because the search space of all possible combinations of features grows exponentially with the number of features, it is rarely feasible to perform an exhaustive search. Instead, various heuristic search methods can be used to identify meaningful feature subsets that can be used to build classifiers with high accuracy. Here we used a genetic algorithm (GA)- based approach <xref rid="pone.0029711-David1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> similar to those published previously <xref rid="pone.0029711-Hansen1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. We used the R package Galgo <xref rid="pone.0029711-Trevino1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> to implement the algorithm.</p><p>The dataset of 2207 features was divided randomly into two groups, a training dataset containing 1471 regions and a testing dataset containing 736 regions. Each dataset contained roughly equal numbers of hot and cold regions. The training dataset was further divided into three pairs of sub-training and validation datasets. Each pair of the sub-training datasets contained 981 regions, while those of the validation dataset contained 490 regions. The GA was then applied to these datasets in search of a subset of features with optimal accuracy based on the average accuracy across all sets of sub-training and validation data. More specifically, the GA searched for a feature subset that optimized a score defined as A<sub>total</sub> = (A<sub>1</sub>+A<sub>2</sub>+A<sub>3</sub>)/3, in which A<sub>i</sub> is defined as the accuracy of the given subset of features using a random forest classifier built utilizing the sub-training dataset <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> and tested on the validation dataset <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> = {1, 2, 3}. In general, accuracy was defined as the total number of regions classified correctly divided by the total number of regions in the validation dataset. The search space of 350 features was prohibitively large, and running the GA twice on the same training and validation datasets would most likely have yielded two different solutions representing local optima. Thus, a sampling of the fitness landscape was used in which the GA was run 10,000 times on different random divisions of the training dataset into the sub-training and sub-validation datasets. The final solution was obtained by combining the results of these independent runs. Features were ranked according to their frequency of occurrence within the subset of optimal features selected by the GA. Features that were present across many runs were presumed to be more important than those that were selected less often (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g001">Figure 1</xref>). For example, if feature one was present in 9,000 of the 10,000 optimal subsets returned by the GA, while feature two was present in only 5,000, then feature one would be considered more important and thus ranked higher than feature two. The final subset of features was obtained using a forward selection approach. Features were added individually based on ranking until no significant improvement in accuracy was observed. The corresponding accuracy was calculated using the testing dataset.</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Overview of the feature selection procedure.</title><p>The initial set of 2207 regions was divided into a training set of 1471 regions and a testing dataset containing 736 regions. The training dataset was further divided into sub-training and validation datasets. (a) The (Genetic Algorithm) GA was run 10,000 times on different sub-training and validation datasets, producing a subset of optimal features for each run (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). We divided the number of times each feature occurred in an optimal feature subset by the total number of times the GA was run (i.e., 10,000) to calculate the frequency of observation (FOO). Features that occurred most often in many different optimal subsets across different splits of the training dataset were ranked higher than features that were selected less often. (b) To obtain the final subset, features were added individually based on their FOO score from highest to lowest. Then, the corresponding accuracy using the testing dataset was calculated. Features were added until no substantial improvement in accuracy was observed, indicated in the figure panel (b) by the solid black line. Panels (c) and (d) are identical to (a) and (b) except random regions were used (i.e., 1179 and 1028 regions randomly selected and labeled as “hot” and “cold”, respectively).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Alignment methodology</title><p>Alignments were performed using BLASTN with default parameters <xref rid="pone.0029711-Altschul1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. When allowing multimapping of reads we followed the procedure as defined in <xref rid="pone.0029711-Albert1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>; briefly any alignment yielding an identify less than 90% was discarded and, for alignments between 90% and 95%, only the maximum score was retained. All alignments with greater than 95% identity were kept. Identity was defined as alignment length divided by read length.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>MNase control subtraction methodology</title><p>Normalizing for differences in sequencing coverage was accomplished by dividing read counts at each base pair by the total number of unique mappable reads for each dataset, similar to the procedure used in <xref rid="pone.0029711-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The following formula was used to subtract out the normalized counts of the MNase control. Given two sequencing datasets D<sub>1</sub> and a control D<sub>2</sub> with normalized counts of read coverage at each base pair represented by c<sub>1</sub> = {c<sub>1,1</sub>, c<sub>1,2</sub> ,….c<sub>1,m</sub>} and c<sub>2</sub> = {c<sub>2,1</sub>, c<sub>2,2</sub> ,….c<sub>2,m</sub>}, the subtracted read density was defined at each base pair as<disp-formula><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="image" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.e001.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="image" xlink:href="pone.0029711.e002.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a constant set to 2 to avoid division by zero errors and to dampen noise.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A dataset consisting of 2207 regions (1179 hot spots, 1028 cold spots) was first randomly divided such that two-thirds were analyzed by feature selection (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>) and one-third was set aside as a testing dataset. The testing dataset was used to test how accurately the features identified can distinguish between hot and cold spots. Setting aside a testing dataset ensures a fair test with the features being tested on data not used to obtain the features. Hot spots as used in this manuscript refer to regions of increased meiotic DSBs and cold spots to regions of decreased meiotic DSBs. Features were first ranked in order of importance based on the training dataset. The final subset of features was obtained using a forward selection approach. Features were added individually based on ranking until no significant improvement in accuracy was observed. The corresponding accuracy was calculated using the testing dataset. Thus, accuracy using only highly ranked features was estimated based on data not used to rank the features. A subset of five features (i.e., H3K4me3, H3K14ac, H3K36me3, H3K79me3, and GC content) was identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g001">Figure 1</xref>) with a classification accuracy of 80.4%, sensitivity of 80.5%, and specificity of 80.3%. Many of the identified features were found to be associated with recombination, according to published literature.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>Chromatin Structure</title><p>All of the histone modifications used in this study were mapped in vegetatively growing mitotic cells. While the DSB frequency dataset used to map meiotic hot and cold spots was obtained from meiotic cells we address this issue in more detail in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">discussion</xref> section. The feature selected as having the highest predictive importance was the degree of H3K4me3 methylation. Published literature strongly associates this mark with recombination hot spots. In <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic>, the methyltransferase Set1 is responsible for H3K4 methylation. Set1 mutants exhibit dramatically reduced DSB frequency at well-characterized hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Sollier1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Additionally, H2B ubiquitination promotes Set1 activity <xref rid="pone.0029711-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, thereby increasing H3K4 methylation. Preventing this mark leads to decreased DSB frequency <xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamashita1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Importantly, Borde <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> demonstrated that deleting Set1 reduced or eliminated DSBs at 84% of the hottest sites in S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae.</italic> In addition, recent work has associated PRDM9, a sequence-specific DNA binding methyltransferase, with hot spot activity in mammalian meiosis <xref rid="pone.0029711-Myers1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Parvanov1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Baudat1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Our results are consistent with these studies, indicating that H3K4me3 associates positively with areas of high recombination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Selected histone marks are correlated with meiotic DSB frequency.</title><p>(A) Presence of histone marks at hot or cold spots. The first row displays histograms of the log ratios for all probes on the microarray. The higher the log ratio, the more enriched is the given mark. The second row is the enrichment of the histone marks at hot spots. Log ratios were binned in 600-bp windows centered at hot spots and the averages for each bin plotted. The third row is the enrichment of the histone marks at cold spots. Log ratios were binned in 600-bp windows centered at cold spots and the averages for each bin plotted. (B) Histone mark enrichment is correlated with DSB frequency. Probes on both microarrays measuring DSB enrichment and histone modification were paired based on whether they mapped to the same genomic location. Pairs of probes were then grouped in 100 bins according to their DSB enrichment (x-axis). The corresponding log ratios measuring histone modification for the given mark were then averaged for the probes in each bin (y-axis). Bins representing extreme DSB enrichment values had a very low number of probes ∼1–10 hence the histone modification averages for these bins was highly variable. Therefore any bin containing less than 50 probes was discarded.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>H3K14ac is a histone mark associated with active transcription. Like H3K4me3, H3K14ac is localized primarily to the 5′ end and promoter region of open reading frames and is correlated with the rate of transcription <xref rid="pone.0029711-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Rando1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Research has linked histone acetylation with meiotic DSB frequencies. For instance, Sir2 deacetylates histones H3 and H4 <xref rid="pone.0029711-Blander1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Mutants deficient in Sir2 exhibit widespread changes in meiotic DSB frequencies with 12% of yeast genes showing altered DSB frequency <xref rid="pone.0029711-Mieczkowski1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Moreover, the histone deacetylase Rpd3 represses meiotic recombination at the well-studied hot spot <italic toggle="yes">HIS</italic>4 in S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Merker1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Finally, deletion of the histone acetyltransferase <italic toggle="yes">GCN</italic>5, which preferentially acetylates H3 histones, leads to decreased recombination at the <italic toggle="yes">ade6-M26</italic> hot spot in S. <italic toggle="yes">pombe</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamada1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Our analysis indicates that H3K14ac is associated with DSB hot regions, with high levels of this mark corresponding to hot spots and low levels to cold spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Plots of average modification level around transcription start sites (TSS).</title><p>The x-axis represents- position relative to the TSS set at zero. Positive numbers represent positions downstream of the TSS, while negative numbers are upstream. The y-axis indicates the average histone modification enrichment log ratios. Black dots represent points statistically significantly different (p-value&lt;0.01 wilcox rank sum test) than the corresponding point in the other curve. Forpanels (a, b, d and e) the blue line represents TSS at least 3000 bps away from the center of a hot spot, log ratios were binned in 200-bp windows and the average for each bin plotted. The black line represents genes with the center of a hot spot located within 500 bp upstream of the TSS,log ratios were binned in 200-bp windows and the average for each bin plotted. For panels (c and f) the black line represents the average histone modification in genes which entirely contain a cold spot (for definition of cold spot see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). The blue line represents the average histone modification in genes which do not overlap to any extent a cold spot. Plots were produced by binning histone modification log ratios in bins proportional to gene size (each bin was 1/10 the size of the given gene) the average for each bin is plotted.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g003.jpg"/></fig><p>H3K36me3 is a post-translational modification catalyzed by the methyltransferase Set2, and is found primarily in the coding region of genes being actively transcribed <xref rid="pone.0029711-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. By recruiting the repressor Rpd3, H3K36me3 suppresses spurious transcription initiation <xref rid="pone.0029711-Carrozza1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. H3K36me3 may also play a role in differentiating exons from introns <xref rid="pone.0029711-KolasinskaZwierz1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Our results indicate that the presence of H3K36me3 may play a largely inhibitory role in DSB frequency as this mark is enriched in cold spots relative to hot spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">3</xref>). In addition, studies have shown that Set2 the methyltransferase responsible for H3K36me3 represses meiotic recombination at the HIS4 hot spot in yeast <xref rid="pone.0029711-Merker1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.</p><p>Like H3K36me3, H3K79me3 is found primarily within coding regions. Unlike H3K36me3, however, the degree of H3K79me3 presence is not strongly associated with transcription <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. The exact function of this mark is unknown, although some evidence suggests that H3K79me3 may play a role in histone H3 exchange <xref rid="pone.0029711-GatViks1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Our results indicate H3K79me3 may play a minor repressive role in DSB frequency since cold spots appear to be enriched for H3K79me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">3</xref>). Most of the histone modification features show a strong partitioning with hot spots being either enriched or depleted for the chromatin mark and vice versa for cold spots. H3K79me3 is an exception cold spots are enriched for this mark but hot spots are not depleted instead showing about the genome average of H3K79me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g002">Figure 2</xref> panel a). This trend could be explained by H3K79me3 having a lesser effect on DSB frequency or by an indirect effect.</p><p>Computational analysis is rarely capable of demonstrating a causal relationship. Feature selection can identify which biological features out of a large number of candidate features are associated with regions of high/low meiotic DSBs. The method cannot identify the reason behind the association. Once an association is discovered it is important to identify potential confounding variables and test whether they may be solely responsible for the correlation of biological features. Such an analysis cannot prove a causal relationship but it is helpful in elucidating uninteresting correlations.</p><p>An important confounding variable that arises when working with recombination hot spots is their tendency to localize to promoter regions while cold spots localize to coding regions. Many of the histone marks we studied also have a tendency to localize either to the 5′ end of genes or to coding regions. Therefore, it is possible that the results of our analysis reflect this co-localization effect. To explore this, we compared promoter regions of genes with a hot spot within 500 bp upstream of the transcription start site (TSS) (N = 218) to those genes whose TSS is at least 3000 bp away from a hot spot (N = 2491) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> panels a and d). Divergent promoters were removed from this analysis. Gene coordinates were obtained from the UCSC genome browser.</p><p>Both H3K14ac and H3K4me3 exhibit a “peak” of modification in promoters of genes that contain hot spots. This “peak” is absent in promoters that lack hot spots. H3K14ac and H3K4me3 are positively correlated with transcription. It is possible that the enrichment of H3K14ac and H3K4me3 observed upstream of genes close to hot spots is due to increased transcriptional rates. To test this we obtained gene expression data <xref rid="pone.0029711-Holstege1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> and compared transcription rates. The set of genes with a hot spot upstream of the TSS, on average do have a higher transcriptional rate compared with genes whose TSS is at least 3000 bp away from a hot spot (2.2 mRNA/h compared to 1.7 mRNA/h, p-value = 0.003, Wilcox rank sum test), an association that has previously been reported <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>To test whether this difference in transcription could explain the extra enrichment of H3K14ac and H3K4me3 upstream of the TSS we plotted these marks for genes with an upstream hot spot whose transcriptional rate was less than 1 mRNA/h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> panels b and e) (N = 43). The peaks of upstream enrichment are retained even for inactive genes. This analysis indicates that H3K14ac and H3K4me3 enrichment in areas of high recombination is likely not due solely to the tendency of hot spots to localize to promoter regions or to differences in transcriptional activity. Similarly, we compared coding regions that entirely contain a cold spot to those that do not overlap to any extent with cold spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref>, panels c and f). Genes that contain cold spots show an increased enrichment for both H3K36me3 and H3K79me3. Both H3K36me3 and H3K79me3 within gene bodies are positively correlated with transcriptional activity <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pokholok1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, H3K36me3 is strongly correlated and H3K79me3 is weakly correlated. Perhaps the increased enrichment of H3K36me3 and H3K79me3 in genes containing cold spots compared to genes without cold spots is due to the fact that cold spots are preferentially located in active genes. We compared transcriptional rates for genes with (N = 498) and without cold spots (N = 4516). Genes with cold spots have lower transcription rates than genes without cold spots (median transcriptional rate 1.3 mRNA/h compared to 2.3 mRNA/h, p-value&lt;1e-16 Wilcox rank sum test). Even though genes containing cold spots have on average lower transcriptional rates than genes without cold spots they exhibit a higher degree of H3K36me3 and H3K79me3 methylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> panels c and f).</p><p>Holstege <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> measured gene expression in mitotic cells. The purpose behind the preceding analysis is to check whether the observed patterns of histone modifications at hot or cold spots are due to differences in gene activity and not to the presence or absence of a hot or cold spot. Given that the histone modifications were measured in mitotic cells, the appropriate dataset for the above analysis is gene expression also measured in mitotic cells. While this manuscript was in preparation, a high resolution map of DSB hot spots was published <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. This map was produced by sequencing and mapping oligos bound by Spo11 where the hot spots were mapped at much higher resolution than the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> dataset. We obtained the set of hot spots mapped by Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> in order to check if the association of meiotic DSB frequency with the histone marks H3K14ac, H3K4me3, H3K36me3 and H3K79me3 observed using the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> dataset were also observed using an independently produced higher resolution hot spot map. The Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots, like the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots, strongly localized to promoter regions <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Hence, a positive correlation with H3K14ac and H3K4me3 and a negative correlation with H3K36me3 and H3K79me3 would be expected.</p><p>We duplicated the analysis described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> using the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots, and found similar results to what was seen using the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots. Additionally, we show that the H3K14ac and H3K4me3 peaks observed upstream of genes with a hot spot are in general proportional to the strength of the hot spot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s001">Figure S1</xref>). The comparison of gene expression rates between hot spot associated genes and non-hot spot associated genes and cold spot associated genes with non-cold spot associated genes was performed using gene expression obtained in vegetatively growing mitotic cells. To check if the same patterns are observed with meiotic cells we repeated the above comparisons with gene expression measured at different time points after cells were placed in sporulation media (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s002">Figure S2</xref>) gene expression data was taken from <xref rid="pone.0029711-Primig1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. The expression dataset used measured gene expression for four yeast strains SK1, non-sporulating SK1 control, W303 and a non-sporulating W303 control. For the non-sporulating controls which do not enter meiosis the above described patterns held true for all time points. That is hot spot associated genes are transcriptionally more active than non-hot spot associated genes and cold spot associated genes are transcriptionally less active than non-cold spot associated genes.</p><p>Interestingly, this pattern did not hold true in the case of hot spot genes compared to non-hot spot genes in meiotic cells. Upon the entrance to meiosis the difference in gene expression between hot and non-hot genes gradually falls to zero (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s002">Figure S2</xref> panel's b and d). This could be explained by the observation that hot spot associated genes have a tendency to be repressed in meiosis <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Cold spot associated genes are transcriptionally less active than non-cold spot genes in both mitotic and meiotic cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s002">Figure S2</xref> panel's e, f, g and h).</p><p>As discussed above there is ample evidence from multiple studies that H3K4me3 is involved in hot spot selection. Given that histone marks are in general correlated with one another <xref rid="pone.0029711-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, is it possible the association of H3K14ac, H3K79me3, and H3K36me3 with DSB frequency is simply a consequence of these marks being correlated with H3K4me3? In the case of H3K36me3 there is previous research linking this mark with hot spot activity at a well-studied hot spot in yeast <xref rid="pone.0029711-Merker1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. As discussed above multiple studies have linked histone acetylation with hot spot activity.</p><p>H3K4me3 in general is correlated with other histone marks but it is particularly strongly correlated with H3K14ac (r = 0.85, p-value&lt;2.2 e-16) compared to its correlation with H3K4me2 which is the next strongest correlation (r = 0.62, p-value&lt;2.2 e-16). Even when comparing a large number of histone marks H3K4me3 is inordinately strongly correlated with H3K14ac <xref rid="pone.0029711-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Taken together with the previous work linking histone actylation with recombination, the usually strong correlation of H3K4me3 with H3K14ac combined with our results suggests these marks may act together at meiotic DSB hot spots. While there is a statistically significant correlation between H3K4me3 and H3K79me3 (r = 0.09, p-value&lt;2.2 e-16) this correlation is too small and in the wrong direction to explain the association of H3K79me3 with meiotic DSB frequency.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>AT/CG Content</title><p>One of the features selected by the feature selection algorithm was a sequence based feature AT content. AT content and GC content measure the same quantity and both were included in the input feature set as a “sanity check” or control. If our computational method is working correctly, then these features should rank similarly. Indeed, this is what was observed AT content ranks 2<sup>nd</sup> out of 350 features GC content ranks 7<sup>th</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g001">Figure 1</xref>) . Our analysis is in agreement with published results <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> indicating that GC content in hot spots is higher than the overall average in S. <italic toggle="yes">cerevisiae</italic>. More specifically, the mean GC content within a 600-bp window centered on hot spots was 39.6%, while the GC content of the entire genome was 38.1%. Not surprisingly, the mean AT content in cold spots (63.8%) is greater than that across the entire genome (61.9%).</p><p>To further explore the relationship between GC content and recombination cold spots we examined the set of cold spots found entirely within coding sequences. Coding sequences in yeast have a GC content of 39.6%, which is GC rich relative to the genome as a whole. The mean GC content of cold spots found entirely within coding sequences was 37.0% compared to the genome average of 38.1% and compared to 36.0% percent GC content calculated for the entire set of cold regions. Cold spots found within otherwise GC-rich regions (i.e., coding sequences) still showed reduced GC content contrary to the overall trend of coding regions as a whole. Studies have shown that hot spots are generally absent from protein coding sequences despite their high GC content <xref rid="pone.0029711-Baudat2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Liu2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Our results suggest that cold spots may be associated with regions of low GC and high AT content within coding sequences.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Nucleosome Occupancy</title><p>Of the four biological features included in our analysis with previous evidence from the literature associating them with meiotic DSBs (H3K4me3, H4K36me3, GC content and nucleosome occupancy) three were selected by our method (H3K4me3, H3K36me3, GC content). Our method did not identify nucleosome occupancy as an important feature distinguishing hot from cold spots. This is surprising since multiple studies <xref rid="pone.0029711-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Ohta1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Mizuno1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> have suggested that recombination hot spots are typically found in regions of increased sensitivity to nucleases, presumably reflecting a local open chromatin structure. The dataset we used to test nucleosome occupancy was produced by Kaplan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> and based on high throughput sequencing technology.</p><p>One possible explanation for our results is that chromatin remodeling may be occurring after cells have entered meiosis. Kaplan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> measured nucleosome occupancy using data derived from vegetatively growing mitotic cells. There are examples of hot spots showing a closed chromatin structure during mitosis but an open one in meiosis <xref rid="pone.0029711-Hirota1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. However, a recent study that measured nucleosome occupancy using formaldehyde-assisted isolation of regulatory elements (FAIRE) showed that meiotic DSB hot spots genome-wide overlapped with nucleosome-free regions in mitotic cells greater than would be expected by random chance <xref rid="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref> which greatly weakens the above hypothesis. To investigate this further, we obtained a set of nine different nucleosome occupancy maps from three microarray-based and six high throughput sequencing-based studies and examined nucleosome occupancy around hot spots in each dataset. All six sequencing-based datasets are plotted together in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s003">Figure S3</xref>. All of the sequencing based datasets fragmented DNA using nuclease digestion. Two of the microarray based nucleosome positioning maps used sonication. One of them, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4 (c)</xref>) similar to the sequencing based datasets used micrococcal nuclease digestion <xref rid="pone.0029711-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. The Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> dataset also mapped nucleosome positions at a high resolution ∼4 bp similar to the 1 bp resolution of the sequencing based studies. Our analysis yielded a discrepancy in the results comparing microarray- and sequencing-based nucleosome occupancy maps. The microarray-based results all show a well-defined valley representing nucleosome depletion centered at hot spots. Based on these results and previously referenced studies, we conclude that the microarray results best approximate what occurs <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. On average, nucleosomes are depleted at hot spots for mitotically dividing cells. Contrary to these results, the sequencing-based datasets yielded a small peak of nucleosome occupancy at hot spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Some datasets exhibited a variable amount of bias (compare peak to baseline differences <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels d and e to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panel f).</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Nucleosome occupancy at hot spots.</title><p>Multiple nucleosome occupancy maps produced using three different technologies (i.e., FAIRE, Chip-Chip, Chip-Seq) were obtained. Hot spots were aligned Z-score standardized nucleosome occupancy as is shown in 100 bp bins (y-axis). The center of the aligned hot spots is zero on the x-axis. (a–c) Nuclesome occupancy maps based on microarray technology. The sign was reversed in panel a to be consistent with how nuclesome depeletion is represented in the other microarry-based techniques. (d–f) Nuclesome occupancy maps based on high throughput sequencing. The green line plots the mean GC content around hot spots as calcuated by averaging the GC content in 100-bp bins. The y-axis scale on the right is for the GC content plot. The first word in each plot title is the last author on the paper in which the given dataset was described. (references for datasets: a <xref rid="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref> , b <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, c <xref rid="pone.0029711-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, d <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, e <xref rid="pone.0029711-Field1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, and f <xref rid="pone.0029711-Eaton1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>). Nucleosome occupancy scores were used as calculated by the authors.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g004.jpg"/></fig><p>We obtained and plotted read density at and around hot spots using two publicly available control datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Control dataset “a” was produced by micrococcal nuclease (MNase) digestion of purified DNA followed by size selection for nucleosome-sized fragments and subsequent sequencing using the Solexa platform <xref rid="pone.0029711-Locke1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Control dataset “b” was the product of sonicated purified DNA followed by size selection for nucleosome-sized fragments and sequenced using the Solexa platform <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Both control datasets showed a peak of read density at hot spots very similar to the peak of nucleosome occupancy observed in the six sequencing-based nucleosome occupancy maps implying nucleosome occupancy at hot spots, as measured by high throughput sequencing, is likely dominated by experimental artifacts. Because the read density peak was observed in both controls, this bias was most likely not introduced by a MNase sequence preference.</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Read density for sequencing controls at hot spots.</title><p>(a) Purified DNA digested with micrococcal nuclease (MNase) and sequenced using the Solexa platform. (b) Purified DNA following sonication and sequencing using the Solexa platform. The black line indicates the z-score standardized mapped read density, while the green line depicts GC content as calculated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref>. Data was smoothed using loess smoothing.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>The nucleosome occupancy maps produced using high throughput sequencing show a split peak with a small valley of occupancy centered at hot spots. The low point of this valley is still higher than or equal to the baseline nucleosome occupancy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels d, e and f). This split peak is likely due to the competing influences of depleted nucleosome density at hot spots with the peak of control read density also centered at hot spots. Thus the trend observed with the sequencing datasets at hot spots is the result of experimental bias as seen in the control datasets combined with nucleosome depletion as seen in the microarray results.</p><p>A recent study <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> mapped hot spots and nucleosome occupancy in yeast at high resolution using high throughput sequencing, showing nucleosome depletion at hot spots. Using this dataset we plotted read density at and around hot spots for the MNase and the sonication controls. Similar to the results seen for the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots, there is a spurious peak of read density at the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s004">Figure S4</xref>). This is likely due to GC content bias, Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots correlate with a higher GC content similar to the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. However, when we plotted nucleosome occupancy at the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots using the same six sequencing based nucleosome occupancy maps we plotted at the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots we observed a valley of nucleosome occupancy centered at hot spots contrary to the peak seen with the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots (compare <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s003">Figure S3</xref> with <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s005">Figure S5</xref>). There is wide variability in the level of bias within the sequencing based nucleosome occupancy datasets examined. This can be seen comparing the distance of the peak height to the baseline in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels d, e and f and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s003">Figure S3</xref>. The effects of this variability in bias can also be seen when plotting nucleosome occupancy at the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s005">Figure S5</xref>). Those datasets with the strongest bias exhibit a strong split peak with depletion centered in the middle of a peak (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s005">Figure S5</xref> panel a). Those datasets with a weaker bias show a much smaller split peak (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s005">Figure S5</xref> panels c and f).</p><p>The Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots are mapped with much higher resolution than the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hotspots. A higher fraction of the mapped Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots will be located close to or at the real hot spot, which is likely to be nucleosome depleted; therefore the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots will have a higher signal to noise ratio than the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots. The lower signal to noise ratio of the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots is sufficient using microarray based nucleosome occupancy maps, such that the correct biological conclusion can be obtained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels a, b and c). Using biased nucleosome occupancy maps the lower signal to noise ratio of the Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots is not sufficient and an incorrect biological conclusions is drawn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels d, e and f). These same nucleosome occupancy maps, when used with hot spots mapped with much higher resolution and a corresponding greater signal to noise ratio like the Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> hot spots can qualitatively produce the correct biological picture (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p><p>To further examine this issue using a single sequencing based nucleosome occupancy map, we plotted nucleosome occupancy at three different hot spot datasets: Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Buhler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, Borde <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> and Pan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Depending on which hot spot maps were used, nucleosomes were either depleted at hot spots or nucleosome occupancy at hot spots was more difficult to distinguish from baseline (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s006">Figure S6</xref> panels d, e and f). Also plotted is a single nucleosome occupancy as mapped by ChIP-chip <xref rid="pone.0029711-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> for the three different sets of hot spots. Contrary to the sequencing based nucleosome occupancy maps, the ChIP-chip based map showed clear nucleosome depletion regardless of which hot spot datasets were used (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s006">Figure S6</xref> panels a, b and c). Using high-resolution hot spot datasets coupled with sequencing based nucleosome occupancy maps supports an accurate qualitative interpretation. However, it is quantitatively difficult to determine nucleosome occupancy due to the bias imposed by the sequencing technologies.</p><p>It is tempting to conclude that the bias observed at hot spots is due to a GC content bias in next generation sequencing. Our results, in agreement with others <xref rid="pone.0029711-Gerton1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> demonstrate that hot spots have a tendency to be GC-rich. Several studies have reported evidence of significant GC content bias in next generation sequencing <xref rid="pone.0029711-Dohm1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Hillier1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Fan1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Cheung1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. In support of this hypothesis, plots of nucleosome occupancy near the center of hot spots closely mirror those of GC content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref>, panels d, e and f, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p><p>To further explore this question, read libraries for all six sequencing-based nucleosome occupancy maps plus two control datasets were aligned against the yeast genome, and the GC content of reads that aligned with at least 95% identity (alignment length divided by read length) was calculated. This set was further divided according to whether the reads mapped to intergenic or coding regions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029711-t001">Table 1</xref>). An obvious GC bias was discovered in mappable reads (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029711-t001">Table 1</xref>, column 4). Studies have shown intergenic regions are nucleosome poor compared to coding regions <xref rid="pone.0029711-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Since nucleosomes are concentrated to some extent in GC rich coding regions and coding regions are GC-rich a genome-wide examination of sequence bound by nucleosomes would be expected to find a high GC content relative to the genome average. However, it is unlikely that this effect can completely explain the GC bias shown by the six sequencing-based datasets. The GC content in coding regions of the yeast genome is 39.6% whereas that shown by reads mapped to coding regions is ∼42.0%. At 41.3%, the GC content of reads mapped to intergenic regions is much higher than the GC content of intergenic regions (34.8%).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0029711-t001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Average GC content for reads mapped to the yeast genome.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0029711-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dataset</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intergenic GC content</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coding GC content</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total GC content</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast Genome</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.84%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.62%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.15%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Segal 454</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.35%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.40%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Segal Solexa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.69%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.97%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pugh 454</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.49%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.60%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.81%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rando Solexa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.66%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.26%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.52%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Friedman Solexa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.99%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.46%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacAlpine Solexa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.71%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.96%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.54%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNase Control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.84%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.37%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.51%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sonicated Control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.58%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.66%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.19%</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Comparison of the GC bias between the two control datasets was particularly interesting. The MNase control showed a strong GC bias in mappable reads of 47.6%, which was nearly 10.0% higher than the overall yeast GC content. The sonication control displayed a much lower GC content bias (39.2%) for mappable reads. All of the sequencing-based nucleosome occupancy maps were produced using MNase digestion. Given the clear GC bias calculated for the MNase control, it is possible that much of the GC bias shown by these maps is a product of MNase cleavage bias. Furthermore, our analysis indicates that the bias seen at hot spots occurs regardless of sequencing platform. Nucleosome occupancy maps produced using both Solexa and 454 sequencing exhibited a bias at recombination hot spots. Given the differing nature of these sequencing platforms, the bias may be introduced during sample preparation and not by the sequencing technologies themselves.</p><p>Not surprisingly, read mapping methodology can also influence downstream analysis. Five of the six sequencing-based datasets and all of the control datasets used only unique aligned reads. However, Mavrich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Mavrich1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref> used a more lenient mapping approach whereby any alignment yielding an identity less than 90% was discarded and, for alignments between 90% and 95%, only the maximum score was retained <xref rid="pone.0029711-Albert1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. All alignments with greater than 95% identity were kept. The key difference is that their method retained reads that mapped with high confidence to multiple areas along the genome. Using this mapping strategy, a broad shallow valley of read density was observed at hot spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g006">Figure 6</xref>, panel a). When only unique aligned reads from the same dataset were used, a peak of read density similar to that seen with other sequencing-based datasets was seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g006">Figure 6</xref>, panel b). When the control datasets were examined using the Mavrich <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> mapping approach, a similar shallow depletion of read density was observed for the sonication control (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s007">Figure S7</xref>, panel a). The MNase control showed a similar shallow depletion, with the exception of a small peak of read density centered at hot spots. This peak closely mirrors the increase in GC content also centered on hot spots and is likely due to the increased GC bias seen in the MNase control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0029711-t001">Table 1</xref>). Hence, depending on the mapping approach, opposing biases can be introduced.</p><fig id="pone-0029711-g006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029711.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effect of including multimapping reads.</title><p>(a) Plot of nucleosome occupancy at hot spots using data produced by the Mavrich <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. mapping approach. (b) Plot of nucleosome occupancy of the same dataset at hot spots using uniquely aligned reads only. Green line represents GC content as calculated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Fig. 4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0029711.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>Using uniquely aligned reads will bias mapped read density towards unique sequence; including multimapping reads will bias read density towards repetitive sequences. The broad shallow depletion in read density observed at hot spots when allowing multi mapping of reads may reflect the fact that hot spots have a tendency to be located in unique sequences.</p><p>Next, we plotted the read density for the six sequencing-based nucleosome occupancy maps following subtraction of the MNase control (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). When the MNase control was subtracted from the nucleosome occupancy maps, the read density at hot spots is qualitatively in agreement with the microarray-based results, displaying a valley of nucleosome occupancy at hot spots (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s008">Figure S8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>It is difficult using <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analysis alone to demonstrate the existence of a causal relationship between two biological features. What it can do is to identify promising relationships to explore further <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. Here we have shown that feature selection using machine learning techniques can usefully be applied to a complex biological process. While this manuscript was in preparation a high resolution map of DSB hot spots was published <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Sequencing and mapping oligos bound by Spo11 produced this map. Spo11 hot spots compared with hot spots identified by ssDNA hybridization studies such as Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> show a strong degree of concordance with Spo11 hot spots accounting for nearly all hot spots mapped by ssDNA techniques <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>.</p><sec id="s4a"><title>Resolution of Hot Spots</title><p>The set of DSB hot and cold spots used in this study were derived by mapping single stranded DNA produced by nucleolytic processing of DSBs <xref rid="pone.0029711-Buhler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. These ssDNA fragments may be quite large, 1 to 2 kb. Hence the locations of hot spots as reported by Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> are mapped with some imprecision. This will certainly affect any study that attempts to use this data to elucidate genomic features associated with DSB hot/cold spots.</p><p>It is not necessary in this computational analysis for the sites defined as hot spots to exactly overlap the “true” hot spots. It is only necessary that an appropriately sized window centered at the sites defined as hot spots overlap to some degree with the genomic features that are associated with true hot spots. A recent paper studying the association of H3K4me3 with meiotic DSB found enrichment of this mark in a broad region ∼1–2 kb around DSBs <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. This indicates that regions of high DSB frequency mapped by Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> are likely sufficiently precise to identify at least some chromatin features associated with regions of high meiotic DSBs. Our results strengthen this conclusion of the five features we associated with meiotic DSBs. Three of them H3K4me3, H3K36me3 and GC content have previously been associated with meiotic DSBs. Additionally we obtained a set of recently produced hot spots mapped at high resolution <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> and tested whether the same patterns identified using the low resolution Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> dataset are present using higher resolution data. The same patterns were present using either dataset compare (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> with <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s001">Figure S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Mitotic Histone Marks</title><p>All of the histone marks associated with recombination in this study were obtained in vegetatively growing mitotic cells. The DSB set we used was mapped in meiotic cells. How can we be sure the histone marks do not change dramatically between these two cell states? There are two major reasons suggesting patterns in histone modifications found at hot spots in mitotic cells may hold true for meiotic cells. First, it has previously been shown that a number of chromatin features present at hot spots in meiotic cells are also present at hot spots in mitotic cells <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. For example, H3K4me3 does not change dramatically in mitotic compared to meiotic cells <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The set of hot spots mapped in meiotic cells by Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> have been shown to be on average nucleosome depleted in mitotic cells <xref rid="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref> indicating that at least two chromatin features associated with recombination hot spots in meiotic cells are also present to some degree at those same sites in mitotic cells. Additionally, a recent study examined the changes in chromatin states from mitotic to meiotic cells for a number of nucleosome associated biological features including H3K9ac, H3K4, H3K36 and H3K79 tri-methylation. The conclusion reached was that histone modification states were remarkably stable changing little between mitotic and meiotic cells <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. These authors also examined the distribution of H3K36me3, H3K4me3 and H3K79me3 at hot and cold spots in meiotic cells. Their results mirror our own obtained in mitotic cells. In addition, Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> showed that in general the distribution of these marks change little between mitotic to meiotic cell states suggesting that the chromatin features associated with hot or cold spots are present in both mitotic and meiotic cells.</p><p>Second, we show that, in general, histone modifications peak heights for H3K14ac and H3K4me3 found in promoter regions of genes with hot spots are proportional to the strength of the corresponding hot spots and not dependent on transcriptional rates. The fact that this pattern is present in mitotic cells is strongly suggestive it will be present in meiotic cells. Our results showing an association between DSB frequencies measured in meiotic cells and enrichment for histone modifications measured in mitotic cells suggests that nucleosome occupancy and H3K4me3 may not be the only chromatin features that mark sites of meiotic DSBs in mitotic cells before the entrance to meiosis. Although, this is a question that cannot be answered by <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analysis because it requires further experimentation measuring the distribution of these marks for both meiotic and mitotic cells.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Role of Histone Modifications</title><p>The role of histone modifications in specifying sites of Spo11-catalyzed DSBs is unclear. Specific marks could serve to directly recruit proteins involved in recombination. Alternatively, histone modifications, such as acetylation, may act indirectly by modifying the local chromatin structure. Histone acetyltransferases and ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling factors have been shown to regulate recombination at the <italic toggle="yes">ade6-M26</italic> hotspot in S. <italic toggle="yes">pombe</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamada1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Hirota2" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. Deletion of the histone acetyltransferase <italic toggle="yes">GCN</italic>5 gene causes a significant delay in chromatin remodeling, leading to a partial reduction in recombination frequency. Double deletion of SNF22, a component of a chromatin remodeling complex, and GCN5 leads to a complete loss of meiotic recombination. RSC4p, a component of the chromatin remodeling complex RSC, contains tandem bromodomains that recognize H3K14ac, suggesting that this mark may recruit chromatin remodeling factors directly <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kasten1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>. In addition, acetylation leads to a more open and less condensed chromatin structure, allowing easier access for recombination proteins or chromatin remodeling complexes.</p><p>Dot1p the methyltransferase responsible for lysine 79 methylation has been linked with DNA repair <xref rid="pone.0029711-vanLeeuwen1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Deletion of Dot1p confers increased sensitivity to radiation in yeast <xref rid="pone.0029711-Game1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. Additionally the correct function of the DNA checkpoint response requires H3 methylation by Dot1p <xref rid="pone.0029711-Giannattasio1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref> . The presence of Dot1p is necessary for efficient repair of DSB by sister chromatid repair <xref rid="pone.0029711-Conde1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. This suggests H3K79me3 may be associated with regions of low meiotic DSBs frequency because it is a marker for DNA repair.</p><p>Another possibility is that specific histone modifications may affect DSB frequencies indirectly by inhibiting or enhancing other histone modifications that play a more direct role. For instance, preventing H2B ubiquitination leads to decreased meiotic DSBs<xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamashita1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. By promoting H3K4me3, H2B ubiquitination may be enhancing DSB formation <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kniewel1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>. Another possible example of similar “cross-talk” between histone modifications is H3K36me3-mediated repression of DSB formation at the well-studied <italic toggle="yes">HIS4</italic> recombination hot spot in budding yeast <xref rid="pone.0029711-Merker1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. H3K36me3 recruits the Rpd3 histone deacetylase <xref rid="pone.0029711-Carrozza1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, suggesting that this mark may have an indirect negative effect on DSB frequency by preventing or reducing histone acetylation since there appears to be a positive correlation between histone acetylation and DSB frequency at some hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Yamada1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Nucleosome mapping</title><p>Locke et al. <xref rid="pone.0029711-Locke1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref> were able to predict nucleosome positions using nuclesome free control data they suggest this could be because MNase sequence preference or sonication fragmentation coincides with nucleosome excluding sequence. If this were the case any “peaks” of read density in the MNase or sonication control datasets at hot spots may well reflect true nucleosome occupancy. In support of this hypothesis a recent study in mice found evidence of increased nucleosome binding at hot spots <xref rid="pone.0029711-Smagulova1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>.</p><p>We do not think this is the case for the genomic loci in question for a number of reasons. One the same set of genomic loci used in our study i.e.(Buhler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> Hot spots) were recently shown to be on average nucleosome depleted using FAIRE <xref rid="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. This directly contradicts the sequencing based results at these same loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> panels d, e and f). Two microarray based nucleosome occupancy maps are in agreement with one another but disagree with the results of the uncorrected sequencing based studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Finally a number of individual hot spots have been examined (see above) and in general they are nucleosome depleted.</p><p>The extent to which nucleosome binding is based on sequence preferences is currently an active area of research <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. One approach to answering this question is comparing nucleosome maps produced <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Our results, along with others <xref rid="pone.0029711-Fan2" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Chung1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, indicate that a systematic bias can dominate at certain genomic loci, thereby obscuring the true biological representation. It is unknown to what extent this influences the genome wide similarity observed between <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> produced nucleosome occupancy maps.</p><p>Using control experiments to remove the systematic bias is an obvious approach in dealing with experimental artifacts. Unfortunately, producing suitable controls is not necessarily straightforward <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan2" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. Previously, controls have rarely been used in nucleosome mapping with high throughput sequencing methods. When experimental bias is not controlled for, the opposite of the most likely correct biological picture is observed at yeast meiotic hot spots mapped at low resolution. However, when we subtract a MNase control experiment from the nucleosome occupancy maps, the correct biological interpretation can be derived indicating the suitability of this control for the loci under investigation in this study. Furthermore, our results underscore the importance of addressing experimental bias in nucleosome mapping high throughput sequencing experiments. Our analysis is not intended to be a comprehensive examination of all possible biological features potentially associated with meiotic DSB frequency Future work could expand the set of genome wide features being examined at sites of high/low meiotic DSB frequencies. Here we have shown feature selection can productively be used to identify promising biological associations. Our approach successfully identified previously known correlations while making several novel predictions.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Plots of average modification level around transcription start sites (TSS) using Pan </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots.</bold> Figure is produced as described for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g003">Figure 3</xref> with one difference. For panels a, b, d and e genes with a hotspot in their promoter regions were further divided based on the strength of the hot spot. The blue line is the given histone modification plotted upstream of genes whose hot spot is below the first quartile. The red line is genes whose hot spot strength falls between the first and second quartile. The purple line is genes whose hot spots falls betweeen the second and third quartile. The green line is genes whose hot spots strength is greater than the third quartile.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Gene expression comparison in meiotic cells.</bold> Panels a-d is comparing gene expression between genes associated with hot spots to genes not associated with hot spots. Height of bars represents the difference in median gene expression for genes associated with hot spots to genes not associated with hot spots (i.e. Median hot gene expression – Median not hot gene expression). Time points represent time after yeast culture is placed in sporulating media. Panels (a) an (c) represent gene expression measured at the given time points for sporulation deficient SK1 and W303 strains these strains do not enter meiosis. Panels (b) and (d) represent gene expression for sporulation-proficient SK1 and W303 strains. An asterisk represents the difference in medians is significant with p-value&lt;0.05, p-value calculated using the Wilcox rank sum test. Panels c-h is as described above except height of bars represents the difference in median gene expression for genes associated with cold spots to genes not associated with cold spots (i.e. Median cold gene expression – Median not cold gene expression). Gene expression is represented by hybridization fluorescence intensities.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s002.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Nuclesome occupancy at Buhler </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots for all sequencing-based datasets.</bold> For all datasets, reads were mapped to the yeast genome. Only uniquely aligned reads were retained and the count mapped to each base pair was calculated. The z-score standardized count of reads is plotted using the same procedure as described for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> with the green line representing GC content. (references for datasets: a <xref rid="pone.0029711-Field1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, b <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, c <xref rid="pone.0029711-Eaton1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref> , d <xref rid="pone.0029711-Weiner1" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, e <xref rid="pone.0029711-Mavrich1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref> and f <xref rid="pone.0029711-Tsankov1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s003.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Read density for sequencing controls at Pugh </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots.</bold> (a) Purified DNA digested with micrococcal nuclease (MNase) and sequenced using the Solexa platform. (b) Purified DNA following sonication and sequencing using the Solexa platform. The black line indicates the z-score standardized mapped read density. Data was smoothed using loess smoothing.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s004.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Nucleosome occupancy at Pugh </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots for all sequencing-based datasets.</bold> For all datasets, reads were mapped to the yeast genome. Only uniquely aligned reads were retained and the count mapped to each base pair was calculated. The z-score standardized count of reads is plotted at centered Pugh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> hot spots. Plot is produced similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029711.s003">Figure S3</xref>. (References for datasets: a <xref rid="pone.0029711-Field1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, b <xref rid="pone.0029711-Kaplan1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, c <xref rid="pone.0029711-Eaton1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref> , d <xref rid="pone.0029711-Weiner1" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, e <xref rid="pone.0029711-Mavrich1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref> and f <xref rid="pone.0029711-Tsankov1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s005.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p>
<bold>Nucleosome occupancy at recombination hot spots obtained at various resolutions.</bold> Z-score standardized nucleosome occupancy is shown in 100 bp bins (y-axis). The center of the aligned hot spots is zero on the x-axis. Panels a, b and c represent nucleosome occupancy data measured by ChIP-chip produced by Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> at three different hot spot datasets from left to right <xref rid="pone.0029711-Buhler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, and <xref rid="pone.0029711-Pan1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Panels d, e and f represent nucleosome occupancy in the same three datasets but now using a nucleosome occupancy map produced by ChIP-seq <xref rid="pone.0029711-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. This sequencing based nucleosome occupancy map has previously been used in analyzing nucleosome occupancy at hot spots as defined by Borde <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0029711-Borde1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s006.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p>
<bold>Sonication and MNase control plotted at Buhler </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots allowing multimapping reads.</bold> Reads for sonicated (a) and MNase-digested controls (b) were mapped allowing multimapping of reads. Read density centered at hot spots is plotted. Data was smoothed using loess smoothing.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s007.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0029711.s008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p>
<bold>Nuclesome occupancy at Buhler </bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic></bold>
<bold> hot spots for all sequencing-based datasets following subtraction of the MNase control.</bold> Nucleosome occupancy was plotted at hot spots for all sequencing-based nucleosome mapping datasets following subtraction of the MNase control as described in the text. Data plotted similarly to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029711-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0029711.s008.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Michael Lichten for advice and for critically reading this manuscript. We are also grateful to Jean and Danielle Thierry-Mieg for multiple discussions on the results and interpretation of this work and for their constructive suggestions. We would also like to thank Istvan Albert who provided data and advice. This study utilized the high-performance computational capabilities of the Biowulf Linux cluster at the National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Md. (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biowulf.nih.gov">http://biowulf.nih.gov</ext-link>).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This research was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the National Institutes of Health, National Library of Medicine and National Center for Biotechnology Information. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0029711-Lichten1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Meiotic recombination hotspots.</article-title><source>Annual Review of Genetics</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.ge.29.120195.002231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8825482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-MartinezPerez1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Perez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colaiacovo</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Distribution of meiotic recombination events: talking to your neighbors.</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics &amp; Development</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19328674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gde.2009.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2729281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Keeney1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giroux</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleckner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Meiosis-specific DNA double-strand breaks are catalyzed by Spo11, a member of a widely conserved protein family.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9039264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81876-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Petes1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petes</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Meiotic recombination hot spots and cold spots.</article-title><source>Nature Reviews: Genetics</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35072078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Buhler1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buhler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Mapping meiotic single-strand DNA reveals a new landscape of DNA double-strand breaks in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>e324</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18076285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pbio.0050324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2121111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Blitzblau1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blitzblau</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochwagen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Mapping of meiotic single-stranded DNA reveals double-stranded-break hotspots near centromeres and telomeres.</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>2003</fpage><lpage>2012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18060788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cub.2007.10.066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Gerton1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerton</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Inaugural article: global mapping of meiotic recombination hotspots and coldspots in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>11383</fpage><lpage>11390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.97.21.11383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC17209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Bagshaw1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagshaw</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gemmell</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>High frequency of microsatellites in S. cerevisiae meiotic recombination hotspots.</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18226240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-9-49</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2267716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Zhou1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Support vector machine for classification of meiotic recombination hotspots and coldspots in Saccharomyces cerevisiae based on codon composition.</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>223</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16640774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2105-7-223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1463011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Jiang1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>RF-DYMHC: detecting the yeast meiotic recombination hotspots and coldspots by random forest model using gapped dinucleotide composition features.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>W47</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17478517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkm217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1933199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Wu1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Meiosis-induced double-strand break sites determined by yeast chromatin structure.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>263</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8290959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.8290959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Ohta1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Changes in chromatin structure at recombination initiation sites during yeast meiosis.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>5754</fpage><lpage>5763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7988571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1994.tb06913.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC395541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Murakami1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Correlation between premeiotic DNA replication and chromatin transition at yeast recombination initiation sites.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>4085</fpage><lpage>4090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12853625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkg441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC165956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Borde1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonfils</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Histone H3 lysine 4 trimethylation marks meiotic recombination initiation sites.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19078966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/emboj.2008.257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2634730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Yamada1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahls</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Roles of histone acetylation and chromatin remodeling factor in a meiotic recombination hotspot.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14988732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC394230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Ooi1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Genetic algorithms applied to multi-class prediction for the analysis of gene expression data.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12499291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/19.1.37</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Sha1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dragoni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Bayesian variable selection in multinomial probit models to identify molecular signatures of disease stage.</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.0006-341X.2004.00233.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Xiong1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Biomarker identification by feature wrappers.</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>1878</fpage><lpage>1887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11691853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.190001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC311150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Shin1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markey</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Guilt-by-association feature selection: identifying biomarkers from proteomic profiles.</article-title><source>Journal of Biomedical Informatics</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17544868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jbi.2007.04.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Saeys1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeys</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larranaga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A review of feature selection techniques in bioinformatics.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>2507</fpage><lpage>2517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Pan1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kniewel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blitzblau</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>A hierarchical combination of factors shapes the genome-wide topography of yeast meiotic recombination initiation.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2011.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3063416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Song1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Model-based analysis of two-color arrays (MA2C).</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>R178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17727723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/gb-2007-8-8-r178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2375008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Kaplan1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fondufe-Mittendorf</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gossett</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tillo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The DNA-encoded nucleosome organization of a eukaryotic genome.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>458</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19092803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2658732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-White1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petes</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Transcription factors are required for the meiotic recombination hotspot at the HIS4 locus in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>6621</fpage><lpage>6625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.90.14.6621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC46984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8341678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-David1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Genetic Algorithms in Search, Optimization and Machine Learning: Addison-Wesley Longman Publishing Co., Inc.</article-title><size units="page">372</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Hansen1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hestir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrelly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Controlling feature selection in random forests of decision trees using a genetic algorithm: classification of class I MHC peptides.</article-title><source>Combinatorial chemistry &amp; high throughput screening</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19519331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/138620709788488984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Li1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Gene assessment and sample classification for gene expression data using a genetic algorithm/k-nearest neighbor method.</article-title><source>Combinatorial chemistry &amp; high throughput screening</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11894805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1386207013330733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Li2"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Gene selection for sample classification based on gene expression data: study of sensitivity to choice of parameters of the GA/KNN method.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.12.1131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Trevino1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trevino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falciani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>GALGO: an R package for multivariate variable selection using genetic algorithms.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16510496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Altschul1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool.</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Albert1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavrich</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomsho</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanton</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Translational and rotational settings of H2A.Z nucleosomes across the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>446</volume><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature05632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Xu1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>An HMM approach to genome-wide identification of differential histone modification sites from ChIP-seq data.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2344</fpage><lpage>2349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18667444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Sollier1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sollier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soustelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suhre</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Set1 is required for meiotic S-phase onset, double-strand break formation and middle gene expression.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1957</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15071505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC404324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Sun1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Ubiquitination of histone H2B regulates H3 methylation and gene silencing in yeast.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>418</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature00883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Yamashita1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Rad6-Bre1-mediated histone H2B ubiquitylation modulates the formation of double-strand breaks during meiosis.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>11380</fpage><lpage>11385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0400078101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC509210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Myers1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tumian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bontrop</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Drive against hotspot motifs in primates implicates the PRDM9 gene in meiotic recombination.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>327</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1182363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3828505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Parvanov1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parvanov</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petkov</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paigen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Prdm9 controls activation of mammalian recombination hotspots.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>327</volume><fpage>835</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1181495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2821451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Baudat1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fledel-Alon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ober</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>PRDM9 is a major determinant of meiotic recombination hotspots in humans and mice.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>327</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20044539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1183439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4295902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Liu1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buratowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Single-nucleosome mapping of histone modifications in S. cerevisiae.</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e328</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1195719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Pokholok1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pokholok</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harbison</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannett</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Genome-wide map of nucleosome acetylation and methylation in yeast.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>122</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2005.06.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Rando1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Global patterns of histone modifications.</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Genetics &amp; Development</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17317148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gde.2007.02.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Blander1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guarente</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The Sir2 family of protein deacetylases.</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biochemistry</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.biochem.73.011303.073651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15189148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Mieczkowski1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mieczkowski</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petes</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Loss of a histone deacetylase dramatically alters the genomic distribution of Spo11p-catalyzed DNA breaks in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>3955</fpage><lpage>3960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0700412104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1805699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Merker1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenwell</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouck</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>The histone methylase Set2p and the histone deacetylase Rpd3p repress meiotic recombination at the HIS4 meiotic recombination hotspot in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>1298</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dnarep.2008.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2518087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Carrozza1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrozza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Florens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suganuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Histone H3 methylation by Set2 directs deacetylation of coding regions by Rpd3S to suppress spurious intragenic transcription.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>123</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16286007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2005.10.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-KolasinskaZwierz1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolasinska-Zwierz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Down</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Differential chromatin marking of introns and expressed exons by H3K36me3.</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19182803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng.322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2648722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-GatViks1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gat-Viks</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vingron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Evidence for gene-specific rather than transcription rate-dependent histone H3 exchange in yeast coding regions.</article-title><source>PLoS Computational Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1000282</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19197343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2625437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Holstege1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holstege</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Dissecting the regulatory circuitry of a eukaryotic genome.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81641-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Primig1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Primig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tevzadze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The core meiotic transcriptome in budding yeasts.</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/82539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Baudat2"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Clustering of meiotic double-strand breaks on yeast chromosome III.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>5213</fpage><lpage>5218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.94.10.5213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC24658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Liu2"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>The location and structure of double-strand DNA breaks induced during yeast meiosis: evidence for a covalently linked DNA-protein intermediate.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>4599</fpage><lpage>4608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7556103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1995.tb00139.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC394552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Mizuno1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>The meiotic recombination hot spot created by the single-base substitution ade6-M26 results in remodeling of chromatin structure in fission yeast.</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9106659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.11.7.876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Hirota1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Multiple modes of chromatin configuration at natural meiotic recombination hot spots in fission yeast.</article-title><source>Eukaryotic Cell</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>2072</fpage><lpage>2080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/EC.00246-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2168419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Berchowitz1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berchowitz</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copenhaver</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>A positive but complex association between meiotic double-strand break hotspots and open chromatin in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>2245</fpage><lpage>2257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.096297.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2792181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Lee1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tillo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A high-resolution atlas of nucleosome occupancy in yeast.</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>1235</fpage><lpage>1244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng2117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Locke1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolkunov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moqtaderi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>High-throughput sequencing reveals a simple model of nucleosome energetics.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>20998</fpage><lpage>21003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1003838107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3000311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Zhang1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moqtaderi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Euskirchen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Intrinsic histone-DNA interactions are not the major determinant of nucleosome positions in vivo.</article-title><source>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nsmb.1636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2823114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19620965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Dohm1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lottaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borodina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Himmelbauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Substantial biases in ultra-short read data sets from high-throughput DNA sequencing.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>e105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18660515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkn425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2532726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Hillier1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dooling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fewell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing and variant discovery in C. elegans.</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18204455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nmeth.1179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Fan1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quake</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Sensitivity of noninvasive prenatal detection of fetal aneuploidy from maternal plasma using shotgun sequencing is limited only by counting statistics.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>e10439</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20454671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0010439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2862719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Cheung1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Down</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Systematic bias in high-throughput sequencing data and its correction by BEADS.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkr425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3159482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21646344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Bernstein1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlstein</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Global nucleosome occupancy in yeast.</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>R62</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/gb-2004-5-9-r62</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC522869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Mavrich1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavrich</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioshikhes</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venters</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomsho</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A barrier nucleosome model for statistical positioning of nucleosomes throughout the yeast genome.</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18550805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.078261.108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2493396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Zhang2"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Stable and dynamic nucleosome states during a meiotic developmental process.</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21515815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.117465.110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3106320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Hirota2"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Distinct chromatin modulators regulate the formation of accessible and repressive chromatin at the fission yeast recombination hotspot ade6-M26.</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18199689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1091/mbc.E07-04-0377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2262960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Kasten1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szerlong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tempst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Tandem bromodomains in the chromatin remodeler RSC recognize acetylated histone H3 Lys14.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15014446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC381415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-vanLeeuwen1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gafken</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottschling</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Dot1p modulates silencing in yeast by methylation of the nucleosome core.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0092-8674(02)00759-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Game1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Game</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baccari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>X-ray survival characteristics and genetic analysis for nine Saccharomyces deletion mutants that show altered radiation sensitivity.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>169</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1534/genetics.104.028613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1448898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Giannattasio1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannattasio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazzaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plevani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzi-Falconi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The DNA damage checkpoint response requires histone H2B ubiquitination by Rad6-Bre1 and H3 methylation by Dot1.</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>9879</fpage><lpage>9886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M414453200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Conde1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Refolio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordon-Preciado</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortes-Ledesma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aragon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>The Dot1 histone methyltransferase and the Rad9 checkpoint adaptor contribute to cohesin-dependent double-strand break repair by sister chromatid recombination in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>182</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1534/genetics.109.101899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2691753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Kniewel1"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kniewel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Histone methylation sets the stage for meiotic DNA breaks.</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19158660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/emboj.2008.277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2634739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Smagulova1"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smagulova</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregoretti</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camerini-Otero</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Genome-wide analysis reveals novel molecular features of mouse recombination hotspots.</article-title><source>Nature</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature09869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3117304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Fan2"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moqtaderi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Nucleosome depletion at yeast terminators is not intrinsic and can occur by a transcriptional mechanism linked to 3′-end formation.</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>17945</fpage><lpage>17950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1012674107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2964211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Chung1"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krobitsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>The effect of micrococcal nuclease digestion on nucleosome positioning data.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>e15754</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21206756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0015754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3012088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Kaplan2"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieb</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Contribution of histone sequence preferences to nucleosome organization: proposed definitions and methodology.</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>140</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/gb-2010-11-11-140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3156944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Field1"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fondufe-Mittendorf</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Distinct modes of regulation by chromatin encoded through nucleosome positioning signals.</article-title><source>PLoS Computational Biology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>e1000216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18989395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2570626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Eaton1"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacAlpine</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Conserved nucleosome positioning defines replication origins.</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1913210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2854390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Weiner1"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>High-resolution nucleosome mapping reveals transcription-dependent promoter packaging.</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19846608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gr.098509.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2798834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0029711-Tsankov1"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsankov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Socha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>The role of nucleosome positioning in the evolution of gene regulation.</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1000414</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20625544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2897762</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>