
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4705103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4705103.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4705103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4705103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26720590</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-30047</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Associations of TERC Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms with Human Leukocyte Telomere Length and the Risk of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Associations of TERC SNPs with Telomeres and Obesity</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Khaldi</surname><given-names initials="R">Rasha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mojiminiyi</surname><given-names initials="O">Olusegun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlMulla</surname><given-names initials="F">Fahd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdella</surname><given-names initials="N">Nabila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pathology, Faculty of Medicine, Kuwait University, Kuwait, Kuwait</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Deartment of Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Kuwait University, Kuwait, Kuwait</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saretzki</surname><given-names initials="G">Gabriele</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Newcastle, UNITED KINGDOM</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RA OM NA. Performed the experiments: RA. Analyzed the data: RA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: OM. Wrote the paper: RA OM NA FA. Clinical evaluations of Type 2 Diabetic patients: NA.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>segunade@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">261489</issue-id><elocation-id>e0145721</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>01</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-06 21:25:22.123"><day>06</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Al Khaldi et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Al Khaldi et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0145721.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0145721.pdf"/><abstract><p>Previous Studies have mapped putative loci that may probably regulate leukocyte telomere length (LTL). The strongest associations with LTL were reported for SNP rs12696304 and rs16847897 near the non-coding Ribose Nucleic Acid (RNA) molecule component (<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>) of telomerase enzyme on 3q26. It is unclear whether these identified loci coding functional components of telomerase, exert a similar effect on LTL in other populations or influence risk factors of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM). The present study was performed to: study the influence of <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> polymorphisms on LTL, human telomerase reverse transcriptase (hTERT), indices of obesity and explore the potential associations with T2DM. 225 T2DM patients and 245 age and sex matched controls were studied. Allelic Discrimination (AD) genotyping was utilized to determine <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs [rs12696304 and rs16847897]. hTERT, adiponectin, Insulin, Homeostasis Model Assessment (HOMA-IR), and LTL were measured. Body Mass Index (BMI) and waist circumference (WC) were recorded. [CC] genotype of rs16847897 was significantly associated with shorter LTL [OR = 1.6, p = 0.004], lower hTERT levels [OR = 0.4, p = 0.006], higher BMI [OR = 2.2, p = 0.006], larger WC [OR = 23.4, p = 0.007] and hypo-adiponectemia [OR = 0.6, p = 0.006]. [GG] genotype of rs12696304 was also significantly associated with shorter LTL [OR = 1.5, p = 0.004], lower hTERT [OR = 0.7, p = 0.006] but with larger WC[OR = 5.3, p = 0.004]. [CC] genotype of rs16847897 and [GG] genotype of rs12696304 together increased the risk of T2DM significantly [OR = 1.7, p = 0.004]. We provide insights connecting a structure that is critically involved in maintaining genomic stability with obesity and T2DM. Given the central role of telomere length in determining telomere function our findings may expand our understanding of the pathological mechanisms underlying age associated conditions such as T2DM.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by College of Graduate Studies [Research Sector Grant – YM06/11]. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Telomeres are tandem TTAGGG repeats that cap the ends of our chromosomes preventing chromosomal fusions and genomic instability [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Telomeres are bound by a specialized protein complex known as Shelterin and replenished by telomerase [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Telomerase is composed of the main catalytic subunit with reverse transcriptase activity [TERT] subunit and an ubiquitously expressed non-coding Ribose Nucleic Acid (RNA) molecule complementary to the hexametric telomeric repetitions (<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>) subunit [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Telomeres and telomerase have recently been linked to several age associated diseases namely obesity and Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM). At present, telomere shortening is widely accepted as a biomarker for age and stress related conditions [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Over the past decade, quantitative trait locus studies have mapped putative loci that may be involved in regulating Leukocyte Telomere Length (LTL) to human chromosomes 3q26.1, 10q26.13, and 12q12.22 [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Indeed, a number of recent genome-wide association studies (GWAS) identified common single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> associated with LTL in European, American, and Chinese populations [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The strongest associations with LTL were reported for SNPs rs12696304 and rs16847897 near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> on 3q26 [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, it is unclear whether the locus identified in Europeans, American, and Chinese exerts a similar effect on LTL in the Arab population and specifically in the Kuwaiti population. None of the earlier studies attempted to explore the effect of such SNPs on serum human telomerase reverse transcriptase (hTERT) levels. Hence, this study aims at exploring the associations, between the two major SNPs near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> [rs16847897 and rs12696304], LTL, and hTERT levels in the Kuwaiti population. Since the link between shorter LTL and obesity is well documented we propose that SNPs near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> could also affect the degree of obesity, as well as obesity related adipocytokines such as adiponectin (AdipoQ). This study also aims at exploring the influence of the two commonly reported SNPs near TERC (rs16847897 and rs12696304) on anthropometric measures, AdipoQ, and its high molecular weight isoform (HMW-AdipoQ). We aim to also investigate the potential associations of these SNPs with the incidence of T2DM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>2.1 Patients and controls</title><p>As part of the protocol approved by local ethics committee in accordance with the ethical standards in Helsinki declaration, we obtained fasting 12- to -14-h blood samples from 225 T2DM patients (115 females, 110 males) who were recruited from Mubarak Al-Kabeer Hospital. Diagnosis of T2DM was based on World Health Organization (WHO) criteria [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 245 (111 females and 134 males) age- and sex- matched healthy subjects were enrolled from the Kuwait Blood Bank Center. The study protocol as approved by the ethics committees of the Ministry of Health and the Faculty of Medicine was explained thoroughly by a consultant physician (Nabila Abdella) to the subjects who were then asked to sign informed voluntary consent form in order to participate in the study. Only subjects who gave consent to participate in the study were included in this study. Patients were given free access to the study protocol and were free to ask questions related to the use of their blood samples for the study. Subjects who needed time to consider their potential participation were given sufficient time to do so and were only recruited after obtaining their consent. As per local laws, all data were kept confidential and protected. All participants had the right to withdraw from the study unconditionally at any time without giving any reasons. The care they received while in the hospital, and afterwards were not affected in any way if the participants had chosen not to participate or withdraw from the study at a later time. Informed voluntary verbal consent to participate in the study were obtained. The ethics committees of the Ministry of Health and the Faculty of Medicine, Kuwait University approved and accepted the use of verbal informed voluntary consent obtained from study subjects. Subjects were identified as Kuwaitis by their civil identification cards.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>2.2 Anthropometric measures</title><p>Body weight (Kg) was measured in light clothing without shoes and height (cm) was measured as the distance from the top of the head to the bottom of the feet using a fixed stadiometer. Subsequently, body mass index (BMI) [Kg/m<sup>2</sup>] as an index of general obesity, was calculated according to the following formula: BMI = Weight (Kg) / Height (m<sup>2</sup>). Waist circumference (WC) (cm) at the level of the umbilicus was also taken. Blood pressure was measured in the right arm of a seated participant by using a standard gauge mercury column sphygmomanometer after resting for at least 5 minutes. Hypertension was defined as systolic blood pressure ≥ 140 mm Hg, diastolic blood pressure ≥90 mm Hg and/or current history of antihypertensive medication [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. All the previous measurements were taken by one investigator (Rasha M Al-Khaldi) only, to exclude any inter-observer variability.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>2.3 Biochemical analysis</title><p>The collected blood samples were immediately chilled on ice and centrifuged at 3000 RPM for 10 minutes in a cold centrifuge. The harvested plasma, serum, and blood cells were stored frozen at -20°C for subsequent analysis in appropriate 300 μL labeled aliquots to avoid frequent freezing and thawing. Serum levels of hTERT were determined using (Genway Biotech Inc., San Diego, USA). The plasma AdipoQ concentrations were measured by Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay Kit [ELISA] (Linco Research, Missouri, USA). HMW-AdipoQ was measured in plasma using AdipoQ Mulitmeric Sandwich ELISA (ALPCO<sup>™</sup> Diagnostics, New Hamshire, USA). Performance characteristics of each ELISA Kit used in this study are summarized in “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>”. Serum levels of insulin were measured using (Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics, Deerfield, USA). Degree of insulin resistance (IR) was assessed using the homeostatic model assessment (HOMA-IR) Calculator software version 2.2.2 for Windows [Diabetes Trials Unit, University of Oxford, at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dtu.ox.ac.uk/index.htm?maindoc=/publications/">http://www.dtu.ox.ac.uk/index.htm?maindoc=/publications/</ext-link> [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Fasting plasma glucose (FPG), total cholesterol (TC), triglycerides (TG), and high density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-Chol), were measured using UniCel<sup>®</sup> DxC Synchron 800 analyzer (Beckman Corporation, Brea, CA, USA). Low density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-Chol) was calculated using Friedewald formula. Glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) was measured on TOSOH G8 High Performance Liquid Chromatography Analyzer (TOSOH Bioscience, California, USA) with dedicated reagents.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>2.4 DNA extraction</title><p>Maxwell<sup>®</sup> 16 Blood DNA Purification Kit (Promega was used to extract deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) from whole blood samples. DNA quantity and quality were checked using Nano-drop spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc, Massachusetts, USA). The expected range of high quality DNA preparations based on the A260/A280 nm wavelength ratio should be ≥ 1.7. Ratios of samples which deviated from this range, indicated protein, or RNA contamination, and, re-purification of DNA was performed until satisfactory.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>2.5 Telomere length measurement</title><p>Singleplex quantitative polymerase chain reaction [qPCR] was used to measure LTL. The method involved determining the telomere to single copy gene [T/S] ratio in comparison to reference DNA to yield relative T/S ratios proportional to average telomere length [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Reactions for telomere and single-copy control gene [S] [36B4, acidic ribosomal phosphoprotein PO, located on chromosome 12] were run in duplicates in 25 μl on 7500 Fast Real Time PCR (Applied Biosystems, California, USA) (Detailed protocol, “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>”). All samples were analyzed in a blinded fashion without knowledge of the clinical data.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>2.6 Genotyping of SNPs near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>
</title><p>Genotyping of the candidate <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs (rs16847897 and rs12696304) was carried out by allelic discrimination [AD] using pre-designed TaqMan<sup>®</sup> SNP genotyping assays (Applied Bio-systems, California, USA). The protocol of Applied Biosystems was followed carefully. The results of automated allele calling were verified by examining the amplification plots and the Ct values of each sample.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>2.7 Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were tested for normality using the Kolmogorov Smirnov test. Non-parametric variables were normalized by log transformation to use parametric tests, otherwise non-parametric tests were used. Descriptive statistics, namely mean±SD, 95% confidence interval (CI) or median and inter-quartile range were used as appropriate. Comparison between mean values in the 2 groups (Patients and Controls) was evaluated using students <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. For each SNP, Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium was assessed using the following facility: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oege.org/software">www.oege.org/software</ext-link>. The differences in LTL, hTERT, anthropometric and biochemical findings between <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes of the two SNPs were evaluated by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). The association between <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes and variables of interest was assessed using multivariate logistic regression analysis. The association between <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes and T2DM risk was determined by calculating the odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) using binary logistic regression. Logistic regression analyses were adjusted for any confounders, such as age and sex. linear regression were used to determine the association between gentotypes of the two SNPs, telomere length, telomerase and obesity related factors. For that purpose, Beta coefficients (β) with 95% confidence interval (CI) were presented. Haplotypes and their frequencies as well as the presence of Linkage disequilibrium were inferred using <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.iconcologia.net/snpstats/start.htm">http://bioinfo.iconcologia.net/snpstats/start.htm</ext-link>. All the statistical analyses were performed with International Business Machines Corporation Statistical Package for Social Sciences (IBM SPSS Statistics, New York, USA), version 21. The criterion for statistical significance was p&lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec010"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec011"><title>3.1 Demographic, anthropometric and biochemical characteristics of the study population</title><p>A total of 225 T2DM patients and 245 controls were included in this study. <xref rid="pone.0145721.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the demographic and anthropometric characteristics of the study population according to their status (controls versus T2DM). T2DM patients had significantly higher BMI and WC than control subjects. Not surprisingly, T2DM patients had significantly higher HbA1c, FPG and TG but lower HDL-Chol compared to control subjects. T2DM patients had significantly shorter LTL and lower levels of hTERT as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Frequencies of metabolic syndrome in the study population according to the three major definitions of metabolic syndrome are shown in “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>”.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0145721.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic, anthropometric and biochemical characteristics of the study population.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0145721.t001g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparently Healthy Control Subjects [n = 245]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2DM Patients [n = 225]</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age [Years]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.9±9.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.7±9.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI [Kg/m<sup>2</sup>]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0±7.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4±6.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC [cm]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.8±15.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.2±12.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sys BP [mm/Hg]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124±16.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136.0±21.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dia BP [mm/Hg]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0±10.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0±11.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c [%]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9±1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3±1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPG [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2±0.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8±3.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0±1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2±1.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6±1.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-Chol [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0±0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-Chol [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTL [T/S ratio]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2±0.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5±0.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hTERT [ng/mL]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9±8.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3±4.74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>BMI = Body Mass Index, WC = Waist Circumference, BP = Blood Pressure, Sys = Systolic, Dia = Diastolic, HbA1c = Glycated Hemoglobin A1c, FPG = Fasting Plasma Glucose, TC = Total Cholesterol, TG = Triglycerides, HDL-Chol = High Density Liporpotein Cholesterol, LDL-C = Low Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol, LTL = Leukocyte Telomere Length, hTERT = Human Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>3.2 Prevalence rates of <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes</title><p>SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 were genotyped in all the 470 samples. Neither of the two SNPs showed a statistical deviation from Hardy—Weinberg equilibrium [<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value = 0.22 and 0.32] respectively. The [<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>] allele of rs16847897 and [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>] allele of rs12696304 frequencies were 35.6% and 35.9% respectively in this study as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>”.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>3.3 Anthropometric and biochemical characteristics according to <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes</title><p>Homozygous carriers of minor allele <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] of rs16847897 had significantly larger WC compared to [<italic toggle="yes">GC</italic>] or [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotypes as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. On the other hand, [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 tended to have slightly larger WC compared to [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] or [<italic toggle="yes">GC</italic>] genotypes. Carriers of minor allele <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> of rs16847897 had significantly higher FPG, HbA1c% and TG levels compared to [<italic toggle="yes">GC</italic>] or [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotypes. Homozygous carriers of [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>] allele of rs12696304 showed similar trends.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0145721.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Anthropometric and biochemical characteristics according to <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 genotypes in the study population.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0145721.t002g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">rs16847897</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">rs12696304</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean±SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI [Kg/m2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4±9.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2±8.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5±6.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2±0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9±0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9±0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist Circumference [cm]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.1±17.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.5±17.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0±14.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.7±15.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.6±15.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.1±14.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA1c%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3±2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4±2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5±2.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1±2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2±2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FPG[mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4±3.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±3.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1±3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9±3.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7±3.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8±3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8±1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG[mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7±1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7±1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL-Chol [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL-Chol [mmol/L]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTL [T/S ratio]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±3.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04±6.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2±0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±3.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8±0.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hTERT [ng/mL]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7±5.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8±7.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1±7.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0±1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7±1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6±2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AdipoQ [ng/mL]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3±2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5±2.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7±2.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1±2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMW-AdipoQ [ng/mL]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1±0.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin [μU/mL]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4±2.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5±7.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2±2.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1±2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5±2.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-IR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1±2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8±2.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5±2.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4±2.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>BMI = Body Mass Index, WC = Waist Circumference, HbA1c = Glycated Hemoglobin A1c, FPG = Fasting Plasma Glucose, TC = Total Cholesterol, TG = Triglycerides, HDL-Chol = High Density Liporpotein Cholesterol, LDL-Chol = Low Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol, LTL = Leukocyte Telomere Length, hTERT = Human Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase, AdipoQ = Adiponectin, HMW-AdipoQ = High Molecular Weight Adiponectin, HOMA-IR = Homeostasis Model Assessment Insulin Resistance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>3.4 Variations in LTL, hTERT levels and other obesity related parameters with TERC genotypes</title><p>[<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype of rs16847897 had significantly the shortest LTL and the lowest hTERT levels among the 3 genotypes of rs16847897. [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs16847897 had significantly higher AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ levels compared to [<italic toggle="yes">GC</italic>] or [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotypes. Though no significant differences in insulin levels were observed between the 3 genotypes, homozygous carriers of minor allele <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> of rs16847897 had significantly higher HOMA-IR compared to [<italic toggle="yes">GC</italic>] or [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>]. Homozygous carriers of the minor allele <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] of SNP rs12696304 had significantly the shortest LTL and the lowest hTERT levels compared to the other two identified genotypes. On the other hand, [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype had significantly higher total AdipoQ. Moreover, [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype had significantly the highest IR presented by HOMA-IR as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> compared to other genotypes.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>3.5 <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes and Logistic regression analysis</title><p>Using binary logistic regression analysis, it was found that homozygous carriers of the C allele of rs16847897 were at risk of the 1.6 folds of having shorter LTL compared to those carrying G alleles [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>]. Additionally, [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype was significantly associated with lower levels of hTERT as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. We also found that [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype was significantly associated with higher BMI, WC and lower levels of total AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ levels. [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 was significantly associated with increased risk of shorter LTL and lower levels of hTERT as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Furthermore, [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of SNP rs12696304 was significantly associated with higher BMI, WC, lower total AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ levels. In the parallel negative association between [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 and AdipoQ, we found that [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 was significantly associated with higher HOMA-IR as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Beta Coefficients [95CI] for associations of TERC SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 with LTL, hTERT, anthropometric indices and metabolic factors of obesity as shown in “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5 Table</xref>”.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0145721.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>ORs [95CI] for associations of <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 with LTL, hTERT, anthropometric indices and metabolic factors of obesity.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0145721.t003g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTL</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hTERT</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AdipoQ</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMW-AdipoQ</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-IR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="9" align="center" rowspan="1">
<bold>rs16847897</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC+CC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.3–1.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.6–0.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6[0.9–2.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[4.1–13.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[0.7–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0[0.9–1.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[1.8–2.1]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC+GG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.5–1.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.4-.06]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.5–3.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[15.6–35.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.2–1.4]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[2.1–2.7]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="center" rowspan="1">
<bold>rs12696304</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC+GG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.3–1.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref> [0.6–0.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0[0.9–1.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5[0.3–1.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.6–0.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[1.1–1.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[1.2–1.4]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GC+CC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.4–1.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.3–0.5]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.1–1.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[3.5–8.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5<xref rid="t003fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.3–1.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[1.1–1.3]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>* <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p>** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn003"><p>*** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn004"><p>**** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.0001,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn005"><p>No * = No Significance.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn006"><p>LTL = Leukocyte Telomere Length, hTERT = Human Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase, BMI = Body Mass Index, WC = Waist Circumference, AdipoQ = Adiponectin, HMW-AdipoQ = High Molecular Weight Adiponectin, HOMA-IR = Homeostasis Model Assessment Insulin Resistance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>3.6 Haplotype-analysis</title><p>The two <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs were in high, although not in perfect, linkage disequilibrium (LD) in the study population [D’ = 0.839, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.687]. [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype had significantly higher BMI and WC compared to [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] haplotypes “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6 Table</xref>”. LTL and hTERT levels varied significantly among the 3 identified haplotypes (S7 Table). Indeed, LTL was the shortest and hTERT levels were the lowest in [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotypes as shown in Figs <xref rid="pone.0145721.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0145721.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. We found that [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype was significantly associated with higher risk of shorter LTL and lower telomerase levels (<xref rid="pone.0145721.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). On the other hand, [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] haplotype was significantly associated with higher hTERT levels but not with LTL. Additionally, [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] haplotype was found to be associated with lower risk of shorter LTL and higher levels of hTERT in contrast to [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype was significantly associated with larger WC. In accordance with the high WC, [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype was significantly associated with higher HOMA-IR. [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] haplotypes showed the opposite trends to haplotype [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>]. In fact [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] haplotype was significantly associated with higher total AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ levels (<xref rid="pone.0145721.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). This probably explains the negative association reported in those haplotypes with HOMA-IR and insulin levels.</p><fig id="pone.0145721.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Box plots show the distribution of Leukocyte Telomere Length [LTL].</title><p>The horizontal line within the box corresponds to the median value. Vertical bars represent the values between 2.5<sup>th</sup> to 97.5<sup>th</sup> percentiles excluding outliers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone.0145721.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Box plots show the distribution of serum levels of human telomerase reverse transcriptase [hTERT].</title><p>The horizontal line within the box corresponds to the median value. Vertical bars represent the values between 2.5<sup>th</sup> to 97.5<sup>th</sup> percentiles excluding outliers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0145721.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>ORs [95%CI] for associations of haplotypes with LTL, hTERT, anthropometric indices and metabolic factors of obesity.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0145721.t004g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.t004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTL</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hTERT</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WC</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AdipoQ</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMW-AdipoQ</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOMA-IR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCGC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.4–1.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[0.2–0.80]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[0.8–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[3.8–13.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[1.1–1.2]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.5–0.7]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.2–1.3]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>[2.2–3.0]</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87[0.7–1.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.9–2.8]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.4–0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8[0.7–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[2.3–22.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.7<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[42.7–50.0]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.3–0.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.49–0.59]</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGG</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.49–0.59]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.7–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[1.2–3.1]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[5.3–8.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.7–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.7–0.9]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[2.1–3.6]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4<xref rid="t004fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>[0.3–0.6]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p>* <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="t004fn002"><p>** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="t004fn003"><p>*** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.001,</p></fn><fn id="t004fn004"><p>**** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&lt;0.0001,</p></fn><fn id="t004fn005"><p>No * = No Significance.</p></fn><fn id="t004fn006"><p>BMI = Body Mass Index, WC = Waist Circumference, LTL = Leukocyte Telomere Length, hTERT = Human Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase, AdipoQ = Adiponectin, HMW-AdipoQ = High Molecular Weight Adiponectin, HOMA-IR = Homeostasis Model Assessment Insulin Resistance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>3.7 Association of SNPs and haplotypes with T2DM risk</title><p>We found that [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype rs16847897 and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 were significantly associated with higher risk of T2DM [OR = 1.6[1.5–1.9], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005]. On the other hand, we found that [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype was associated significantly with higher risk of T2DM [OR = 1.5[1.3–1.9], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007]. On the contrary, [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] haplotypes were associated with lower risk of T2DM [OR = 0.2[0.1–0.6], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03, OR = 0.3[0.1–0.6], <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02] respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec018"><title>Discussion</title><p>Homozygous carries of risk alleles [<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>] of rs16847897 and [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>] of rs12696304 were found to have shorter LTL compared with other genotypes in our study. Our results are in agreement with what has been found in European, American and Chinese Han populations [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The frequencies of shorter LTL risk alleles [<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>] were similar to those reported in Europeans and Americans, but contrasted to those found in the Chinese Han population [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Indeed, the risk alleles of rs16847897 [<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>] and rs12696304 [<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>] were major alleles in the Chinese Han population. These discrepancies can be explained by ethnic/racial differences. Genetic drift that occurs in all populations may also explain the differences in allele frequencies reported in different populations. These findings are important in understanding the effect of evolution on population genetics and designing replication studies to identify risk alleles of short LTL in different ethnic groups. In the future, collaborative efforts of researchers with different ethnicities will identify genetic variants that are relatively common across populations and unravel the interactions among these susceptibility variants and also with environmental exposures that modulate LTL. Rather than considering each marker individually, specific combinations of allelic variants in a series of tightly linked markers on the same chromosome, i.e. haplotypes, were tested. To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first to examine the association of haplotypes, LTL, hTERT levels, anthropometric indices, and metabolic factors of obesity. In this study, we showed a strong LD between rs16847897 and rs12696304 [D’ = 0.84, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.69] in contrast to the weak LD found in the Chinese Han population [D’ = 0.62, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.26] “<xref rid="pone.0145721.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>”. The strong LD found in our study simply refers to a strong correlation of tightly linked variants and hence lead to cost savings for future association studies in the field of telomere biology. Risk alleles of both SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 were not only associated with higher risk of shorter LTL but additionally, were significantly associated with lower levels of hTERT, an active subunit of telomerase and a major regulator of LTL. In fact, the negative association between risk alleles of SNPs rs16847897, rs12696304 and hTERT levels strongly suggests that those genetic factors may play a role in regulating levels of telomerase. In this regard, the negative association found in our study between [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype and lower hTERT levels is not surprising since this haplotype is composed of the major risk alleles associated with lower hTERT levels. Therefore, we strongly suggest that the reported SNPs may actually affect telomerase levels rather than affecting LTL directly. Our assumption is supported by the telomere hypothesis, which states that in cells without telomerase activity, loss of telomere DNA will eventually trigger a cellular response, via DNA damage response, that leads to growth arrest or apoptosis. The essential role of telomerase in maintaining LTL is also supported by the observation that ectopically introduced telomerase activity can extend telomeres and indefinitely prolong cellular lifespan. More direct support for the role of hTERT in maintaining cell survival was afforded by the introduction of hTERT into primary human cells that already contained the telomerase RNA, which resulted in restoring the proliferating capacity of such cells through elongating telomeres [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Though the exact mechanisms by which those SNPs (rs16847897 and rs12696304) are linked to hTERT levels are still vague, they may alter transcription, post-transcriptional or translational activity or induce changes in the tertiary structure of the gene product human telomerase [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In that essence, the effect of such SNPs can be mediated through one of the other genes in 3q26 locus that were found to actually play a role in controlling expression either by activating or repressing the transcription of various genes such as encoding myoneurin (<italic toggle="yes">MYNN</italic>) including telomerase. Region 3q26 was also found to harbor genes encoding for cell surface proteins such as three members of the Leucin-rich repeat containing (<italic toggle="yes">LRCC</italic>) super-family (<italic toggle="yes">LRRC34</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">LRRC31</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LRRIQ4</italic>) that are essential to mediate protein to protein interactions essential for mediating the downstream effects of telomerase on LTL [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The negative association among risk alleles of SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304, LTL and hTERT levels may also be attributed to the fact that homozygous carriers of C allele and G allele respectively had higher indices of obesity namely, BMI and WC. Our finding is further supported by a recent study that has shown a negative association between anthropometric measures of obesity and LTL [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Evidence for the presence of linkage of 3q26 with BMI was reported in many different populations. Several genes were found to be located in this region such as: Trans-membrane 4 super-family member 1 (<italic toggle="yes">TM4SF1</italic>), and Ring-finger protein 13 [<italic toggle="yes">RNF13</italic>] which can be in LD with the studied SNPs. The effects of near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> gene polymorphisms on obesity related metabolic factors have also been studied. Homozygous carriers of risk alleles of both SNPs that were associated with shorter LTL and lower hTERT levels mentioned earlier had the lowest AdipoQ, [also mapped to loci 3q26] levels. The presence of hypo-adiponectemia in [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] genotype of rs16847897 and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] genotype of rs12696304 may be explained by the high WC in individuals carrying those genotypes. Our assumptions are in agreement with a previous study in the Kuwaiti population, Mojiminiyi et al., 2007, reported a negative correlation between anthropometric indices of obesity and AdipoQ [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Another possible explanation of the negative association among risk alleles of SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304, AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ is the high index of HOMA-IR, in subjects carrying those genotypes. Studies on Pima Indians have shown that high adiponectin levels are protective against the impairment of glucose metabolism reducing the risk of developing T2DM [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0145721.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Mojiminiyi and colleagues (2007) reported also that adiponectin levels in T2DM patients were closely related to IR and the components of the metabolic syndrome [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Unfortunately, most if not all of the published reports examined the potential involvement of telomere-associated pathway gene variation with various types of cancer and to the best of our knowledge none of the risk of T2DM. This lack of information on the relevance of telomere pathway genes with T2DM not only makes a cross- reference comparison with the present findings difficult, but signifies the need of further investigations into the importance of telomere-pathway genes in age related disorders such as T2DM. Nevertheless, the effects of the studied SNPs on different biochemical analytes discussed previously may account partially for the association of certain genotypes of rs16847897 and rs12696304 with the risk of T2DM in this study. In this regard, [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] of rs16847897 and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] of rs12696304 genotypes were significantly associated with IR, which lies at the core of the pathogenesis of T2DM. Hence, not surprisingly, in this study, the odds ratio of [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] of rs16847897 confirmed that both of these genotypes have an elevated risk of T2DM. Moreover, the negative association of the risk alleles <italic toggle="yes">C</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">G</italic> of both SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 with AdipoQ, an anti diabetic adipocytokine can also explain the higher risk of individuals carrying two copies of risk alleles for T2DM. Not surprisingly, the association between [<italic toggle="yes">CG</italic>] haplotype and the higher risk of T2DM may be attributed also to the negative association of this haplotype with AdipoQ levels. Subjects carrying [<italic toggle="yes">CC</italic>] and [<italic toggle="yes">GG</italic>] haplotypes in our study had a lower risk of T2DM probably due to the positive association of earlier mentioned haplotypes and higher levels of protective total AdipoQ and HMW-AdipoQ. The effects of SNPs may also be based on direct genetic effects, or gene-environment interactions. In fact epistasis [gene-gene] interaction has been shown to play an important role in human genetics [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In support of this, region 3q26 was found to harbor candidate genes that were associated significantly with the pathogenesis of T2DM such glucose transporter 2 (<italic toggle="yes">GLUT2</italic>), Apolipoprotein D (<italic toggle="yes">APOD</italic>), and Adiponectin [<xref rid="pone.0145721.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, before any conclusions can be made regarding the effects of genetic polymorphisms on T2DM, a clear statistical picture of the normal genotypes’ frequencies should be established for each ethnic and regional population group under study. Studies exploring the possible differences in the functional implications of different genotypes and haplotypes on the gene product are also needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec019"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have provided insights into the genetic determination of a structure that is critically involved in maintaining genomic stability. Given the importance of telomeres in cellular function and the central role of telomerase in determining telomere function, our findings may have broad relevance for both physiological and pathological age associated mechanisms. To date our study is the first in Kuwait and probably in the world that investigated the association of common <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs, LTL, hTERT levels, anthropometric measures, and AdipoQ. Our data show the complex interplay between TERC SNPs, short telomeres, telomerase and obesity related factors as shown in <xref rid="pone.0145721.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>. Presumably SNPs in telomere pathway genes may alter their function or regulation, in a manner that accelerates the telomere loss phenotype in certain complex disorders such as T2DM. Our results also strongly suggest that non-coding regions such as <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genes can harbor genetic variants of clinical relevance. The identified haplotypes in this research probably captured much of the correlation between the two studied SNPs holding the key to better understanding of the role of genetic variants in the pathogenesis of complex diseases such as T2DM.</p><fig id="pone.0145721.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145721.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Complex interplay between TERC SNPs, short telomeres, telomerase and obesity related factors.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0145721.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec020"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>SNP annotation map showing the locations of both studied SNPs (rs16847897 and rs12696304).</title><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Performance characteristics of ELISA kits used to measure analytes of interest in this study.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s002.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Frequency of metabolic syndrome in the study population.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s003.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>The distribution of <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes within the study population.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s004.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s005" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S4 Table</label><caption><title>Frequency of metabolic syndrome in the study population according to <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> genotypes.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s005.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s006" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S5 Table</label><caption><title>Beta Coefficients [95CI] for associations of <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> SNPs rs16847897 and rs12696304 with LTL, hTERT, anthropometric indices and metabolic factors of obesity.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s006.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s007" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S6 Table</label><caption><title>Anthropometric and biochemical characteristics according to haplotypes.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s007.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0145721.s008" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Text</label><caption><title>Detailed protocols for Leukocyte Telomere Length (LTL) measurement and genotyping SNPs near <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> using Allelic Discrimination.</title><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0145721.s008.doc" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research is supported by the College of Graduate Studies [Research Sector Grant—YM06/11]. We gratefully acknowledge the contribution of the General Facility KU Project [SRUL02/13].</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AD</term><def><p>Allelic Discrimination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AdipoQ</term><def><p>Adiponectin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p>One-way analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>APOD</term><def><p>Apolipoprotein D</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>β</term><def><p>Beta Coeffecients</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>Body Mass Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CI</term><def><p>Confidence Interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ct</term><def><p>Cycle Threshold</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CV</term><def><p>Coefficient of Variation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DNA</term><def><p>Deoxyribonucleic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ELISA</term><def><p>Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FPG</term><def><p>Fasting Plasma Glucose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GLUT2</term><def><p>Glucose Transporter 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GWAS</term><def><p>Genome Wide Association Studies</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HbA1c</term><def><p>Glycated Hemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HDL-Chol</term><def><p>High Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HMW-AdipoQ</term><def><p>High Molecular Weight Adiponectin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HOMA-IR</term><def><p>Homeostasis Model Assessment—Insulin Resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hTERT</term><def><p>Human Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IR</term><def><p>Insulin Resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LD</term><def><p>Linkage Disequilibrium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LDL-Chol</term><def><p>Low Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LTL</term><def><p>Leukocyte Telomere Length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MPW</term><def><p>Millipore Water</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MYNN</term><def><p>Encoding Myoneurin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>Odds Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p>Quantataive Real Time Polymerase Chain Reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNA</term><def><p>Ribose nucleic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNF13</term><def><p>Ring Finger Protein 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>S</term><def><p>Single Copy Gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNPs</term><def><p>Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPSS</term><def><p>Statistical Package for Social Sciences</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T</term><def><p>Telomere</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T2DM</term><def><p>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TC</term><def><p>Total Cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TERC</term><def><p>Non-coding Ribose nucleic acid (RNA) molecule component</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TERT</term><def><p>Telomerase Reverse Transcriptase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TG</term><def><p>Triglycerides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TM4SF1</term><def><p>Transmembrane 4 Super Family Member 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WC</term><def><p>Waist Circumference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0145721.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Artandi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomeres, telomerase, and human disease</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>355</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1195</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. Epub 2006/09/23. 355/12/1195 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp068187</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanyam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adaikalakoteswari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monickaraj</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomere shortening &amp; metabolic/vascular diseases</article-title>. <source>The Indian journal of medical research</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17496367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sumida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamakawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomerase and oral cancer</article-title>. <source>Oral oncology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11337264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1368-8375(00)00132-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meeker</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomeres and telomerase in prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia and prostate cancer biology</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. Epub 2006/03/08. S1078-1439(05)00262-0 [pii] <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.urolonc.2005.11.002</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16520276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sauerwald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cristofari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lingner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Structure of active dimeric human telomerase</article-title>. <source>Nature structural &amp; molecular biology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2530</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23474713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3785136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armanios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomeres and age-related disease: how telomere biology informs clinical paradigms</article-title>. <source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>996</fpage>–<lpage>1002</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI66370</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23454763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3673231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Codd</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Harst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braund</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Common variants near TERC are associated with mean telomere length</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.532</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20139977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3773906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Trudeau</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genetic Variations in Telomere Maintenance, with Implications on Tissue Renewal Capacity and Chronic Disease Pathologies</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharmacogenomics Person Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. Epub 2011/01/25. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21258621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1875692111008010007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3024291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Common variants near TERC are associated with leukocyte telomere length in the Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source>European journal of human genetics: EJHG</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2011.4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3110055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vasa-Nicotera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brouilette</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clemitson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mapping of a major locus that determines telomere length in humans</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/426734</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1196417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<article-title>The World Health Report 1997—conquering suffering, enriching humanity</article-title>. <source>World health forum</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9478137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chobanian</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakris</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Izzo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Seventh report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1206</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.0000107251.49515.c2</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14656957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Correct homeostasis model assessment (HOMA) evaluation uses the computer program</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Care</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2191</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9839117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diacare.21.12.2191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cawthon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Telomere length measurement by a novel monochrome multiplex quantitative PCR method</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e21</fpage> Epub 2009/01/09. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn1027</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2647324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Human telomerase and its regulation</article-title>. <source>Microbiology and molecular biology reviews: MMBR</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>, table of contents. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12208997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/MMBR.66.3.407-425.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC120798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nuclear localization of profilin III-ArpM1 complex in mouse spermiogenesis</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>582</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2998</fpage>–<lpage>3004</lpage>. Epub 2008/08/12. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2008.07.058</pub-id> S0014-5793(08)00665-0 [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18692047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alliel</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seddiqi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goudou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cifuentes-Diaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Myoneurin, a novel member of the BTB/POZ-zinc finger family highly expressed in human muscle</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>273</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>. Epub 2000/06/30. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.2862</pub-id> S0006-291X(00)92862-6 [pii]. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cifuentes-Diaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bitoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goudou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seddiqi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Neuromuscular expression of the BTB/POZ and zinc finger protein myoneurin</article-title>. <source>Muscle Nerve</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. Epub 2003/12/25. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mus.10526</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14694499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Associations of leukocyte telomere length with body anthropometric indices and weight change in Chinese women</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2582</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.20321</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3676725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mojiminiyi</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdella</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al Arouj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Nakhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adiponectin, insulin resistance and clinical expression of the metabolic syndrome in patients with Type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.ijo.0803355</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16755284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adiponectin and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.ATV.0000099786.99623.EF</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14551151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ryo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shibazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adiponectin as a biomarker of the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Circulation journal: official journal of the Japanese Circulation Society</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>975</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1253/circj.68.975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epistasis—the essential role of gene interactions in the structure and evolution of genetic systems</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Genetics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2452</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18852697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2689140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0145721.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chiodini</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of 4 coronary heart disease genome-wide linkage studies confirms a susceptibility locus on chromosome 3q</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1863</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. Epub 2003/08/30. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.ATV.0000093281.10213.DB</pub-id>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12947017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>