
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4281248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4281248.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4281248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4281248</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25551769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19416</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Community Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Trophic Interactions</subject><subj-group><subject>Herbivory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ecosystems</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecosystem Functioning</subject><subject>Tropical Ecosystems</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant-Animal Interactions</subject><subj-group><subject>Plant-Herbivore Interactions</subject><subject>Plant-Insect Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biodiversity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unexpected High Diversity of Galling Insects in the Amazonian Upper Canopy: The Savanna Out There</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Galling Insect Diversity in Tropical Canopies</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Julião</surname><given-names initials="GR">Genimar R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venticinque</surname><given-names initials="EM">Eduardo M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names initials="GW">G. Wilson</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names initials="PW">Peter W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Coordenação de Ecologia, Instituto Nacional de Pesquisa da Amazonia (INPA), Manaus, Amazonas, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Fiocruz Rondônia, Laboratório de Entomologia, Porto Velho, Rondônia, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Departamento de Ecologia, CB/Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte, Campus Universitário, Lagoa Nova, Natal, RN, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Ecologia Evolutiva e Biodiversidade/DBG, C P 486, ICB/Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG), Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Northern Arizona University, Flagstaff, Arizona, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazzari</surname><given-names initials="CR">Claudio R.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Tours, France</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>gw.fernandes@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GRJ EMV GWF PWP. Performed the experiments: GRJ. Analyzed the data: EMV GRJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GRJ EMV GWF PWP. Wrote the paper: GRJ EMV GWF PWP.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">245922</issue-id><elocation-id>e114986</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2020-12-15 14:16:17.167"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Julião et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Julião et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0114986.pdf"/><abstract><p>A relatively large number of studies reassert the strong relationship between galling insect diversity and extreme hydric and thermal status in some habitats, and an overall pattern of a greater number of galling species in the understory of scleromorphic vegetation. We compared galling insect diversity in the forest canopy and its relationship with tree richness among upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> floodplains in Amazonia, Brazil. The soils of these forest types have highly different hydric and nutritional status. Overall, we examined the upper layer of 1,091 tree crowns. Galling species richness and abundance were higher in <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests compared to <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests. GLM-ANCOVA models revealed that the number of tree species sampled in each forest type was determinant in the gall-forming insect diversity. The ratio between galling insect richness and number of tree species sampled (GIR/TSS ratio) was higher in the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest and in seasonally flooded <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>, while the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> presented the lowest GIR/TSS ratio. In this study, we recorded unprecedented values of galling species diversity and abundance <italic toggle="yes">per</italic> sampling point. The GIR/TSS ratio from <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> was approximately 2.5 times higher than the highest value of this ratio ever reported in the literature. Based on this fact, we ascertained that <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> floodplain forests (with lower GIA and GIR), together with the speciose <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> galling community emerge as the gall diversity apex landscape among all biogeographic regions already investigated. Contrary to expectation, our results also support the “harsh environment hypothesis”, and unveil the Amazonian upper canopy as similar to Mediterranean vegetation habitats, hygrothermically stressed environments with leaf temperature at lethal limits and high levels of leaf sclerophylly.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Funds were provided by the Mamirauá Sustainable Development Institute, Mamirauá Civil Society, and Biological Dynamics of Forest Fragment Project (INPA/Smithsonian Institution). G.R. Julião was a PhD grant holder supported by CNPq (Process Number: 141415/2003-7); GWF acknowledges the support provided by CNPq (30 3352/2010-8, 403781/2012-4, 457519/2012-6) and Fapemig (APQ-04105-10); and EMV acknowledges the support provided by CNPq no309458/2013-7. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="20"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that, for approved reasons, some access restrictions apply to the data underlying the findings. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s001">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s002">Table S2</xref>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that, for approved reasons, some access restrictions apply to the data underlying the findings. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s001">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s002">Table S2</xref>).</p></notes></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In spite of the increasing knowledge on the spatial distribution patterns of many species worldwide, the evolutionary processes and ecological mechanisms shaping them remain poorly known, due to geographic and physiological limitations. At least in some rare cases advances have been made over the last decades, such as in the interactions between galling insects and their host plants. The studies on galling insects have been successfully used as tools to assess the main factors affecting the distribution patterns and diversity of insects (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Sullivan1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>).</p><p>Peak diversity of galling insects has been widely recorded at latitudes between 24°–45° N/S, or equivalent altitude. So far, sampling sites in Arizona (USA), Australia, Israel, South Africa, and Minas Gerais (Brazil) presented the greatest richness of galling insects <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes3" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Furthermore, increases in the richness of these insects with decreasing site altitude were reported in Arizona (USA), Indonesia, and Minas Gerais (Brazil) <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes3" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Lara1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. A relatively large number of studies reassert the strong relationship between galling insect diversity and hydric, thermal, and nutritional stresses in some habitats, resulting in an overall pattern of a greater number of galling species <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Lara2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. This endophytic insect fauna would benefit from the protection against desiccation, sunlight radiation, and natural enemies (free-living herbivores, predators, fungi, other pathogens) in these habitats, and by nutritive tissues provided by gall structure <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes3" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Hence, this pattern (higher galling diversity in stressed environments) was consistently demonstrated in the understory of Neotropical scleromorphic vegetation (response to low nutrient levels <xref rid="pone.0114986-Hill1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>), xeromorphic vegetation (response to low water levels <xref rid="pone.0114986-Hill1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>) in the northern hemisphere, and non-scleromorphic vegetation in the mesic latitudes. However, few studies have been developed in the Neotropical vegetation with non- scleromorphic physiognomy (<xref rid="pone.0114986-Veldtman1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, but see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Yukawa1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Julio1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>).</p><p>Studies evaluating galling insect diversity have usually sampled shrubs and lower stature trees; as a consequence these studies encompass the canopy and understory of xeric/scleromorphic vegetation while taller trees in rainforests have been investigated less frequently <xref rid="pone.0114986-Julio1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Except in a few studies, galling insect richness and abundance associated with the canopy of mesic/non-scleromorphic vegetation remained underestimated for some time. A pioneer study from 1998 found that the understory of moist forests was richer in galling species, compared to tree canopy of a secondary forest near Porto Velho (RO, Brazil), and in Panama <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. With the increased availability and use of sampling techniques such as canopy cranes, access limitations were overcome, and a higher richness of galling insects in the canopy was found in the tropical forests of Panama, when compared to its understory <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro3" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Paniagua1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. These results indicate that the harsh conditions, including host leaf sclerophylly, observed in the Mediterranean types of vegetation and in the canopy of tropical rain forests may also favor galling. Leaf sclerophylly occurs in several vegetation types, along a broad climatic and geographic range; it includes hard, thick and tough leaves, and can be expressed by the ratio between crude fiber to crude protein content. This trait has been proposed as an adaptation to water and nutrient limitation, as well as protection against herbivore damage <xref rid="pone.0114986-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>The assortment of vegetation found in the Amazon region is enormous as well as variation within habitats (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0114986-Prance1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Pires1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>). Water level changes dramatically in flooded forests <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, while different nutrient concentration and soil physical properties engender the development of endless strategies and adaptations by the flora, which is reflected in the associated community <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk2" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Pereira1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Várzea</italic> forests, for instance, are forests seasonally flooded by water that carries nutrient-rich sediments; consequently they have fertile soils and a diverse flora and fauna. The oligotrophic <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests are sluiced with acid and nutrient poor water, resulting in soils with nutrient scarcity, and lower numbers of plant and animal species than <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk3" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, depending on the taxa and on the geographical area. In both flooded forests, while some tree species lose their leaves during the flooding peak <xref rid="pone.0114986-Schngart1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, and flush new leaves when water levels diminish, other species retain their green leaves throughout the flooding season <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Another vegetation type, the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest, is characterized by lack of flooding and high species diversity with plants growing in dry and poor soils in upland terrain of the Amazonian basin <xref rid="pone.0114986-Pires1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Oliveira1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Diversity in <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest is maintained through several plant adaptations to ensure economic and efficient nutrient cycling. Main adjustments by this upland flora include a dense and superficial mesh of fine roots, thereby increasing the nutrient absorption area, and association with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi <xref rid="pone.0114986-Powers1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.</p><p>A gradient in soil fertility exists naturally in the Amazonian rain forest: the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> soils represent the most fertile ones followed by the upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> floodplain <xref rid="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. According to the hypothesis of nutritional stress <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, it is expected that plants located in these different landscapes would be exposed to a large array or levels of physiological stress, which would result in differential richness and abundance of galling insects. In this study, we hypothesize that upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests would present greater diversity of galling insects than <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forests. Considering that <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> has an extraordinarily diverse flora, with average richness of ca. 280 tree species (≥10 cm dbh) per hectare <xref rid="pone.0114986-Oliveira1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, we also expect that this landscape would present the highest galling insect richness as an outcome of the wide availability of ecological niches and resources <xref rid="pone.0114986-Lara1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Southwood1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes7" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Therefore, richness of galling insects would decrease from upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>&gt; <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>&gt; <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forests.</p><p>Thus, the goals of this study were to: (i) compare the richness, abundance and composition of galling insects between three types of Amazonian forests, located in soils with different hydric and nutritional status, and (ii) evaluate the relationship between galling insect and tree richness in such discrete landscapes. Furthermore, we contextualize our results in the scenario observed in the literature and attempt to detect and discuss possible mechanisms involved in the association of galling insect richness with harsh and stressed habitats.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Collection and transport of plant and galling insect specimens involved in this research were authorized by the Brazilian Institute of Environment and Renewable Natural Resources (IBAMA-AM, Permit numbers 23/2004; 04-DITEC/2006; 054NUFAS/2004; 31/2006-NUFAS).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Study Area</title><p>The study was conducted in the reserves of the Biological Dynamics of Forest Fragments Project (BDFFP, 2°30′S; 60°W), located about 70 km north of Manaus, in Mamirauá Sustainable Development Reserve (MSDR, 2°51′S, 64°55′W), and Amanã Sustainable Development Reserve (ASDR, 2°26″S; 64°47′W) near the municipality of Tefé, Amazonia, Brazil. Samplings were done between May 2004 and December 2005. BDFFP reserves consist of <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests exclusively, which are never flooded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). MSDR is situated in the interfluvial land between the Japurá and Solimões Rivers; a large extension of this reserve is subjected to flooding, being characterized as a floodplain. Placed in the middle of Solimões River, ASDR comprises <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> habitats, but due to the influence of the Rio Negro basin, some habitats are characterized as <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>. Along with the Jaú National Park, MSDR and ASDR form the largest biological corridor of preserved tropical rainforest in the world. Overall, 56 sampling points were established in the BDFFP reserves (28 sites), in MSDR (8 sites) and in ASDR (20 sites); all reserves are located within Amazonas State, Brazil. These three forest types also differ in vegetation structure and composition. The upper canopy of <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> reaches 30–37 m, some emergent trees grow to 45–50 m, and the forest is dominated by Sapotaceae, Lecythidaceae, and Burseraceae tree species <xref rid="pone.0114986-Oliveira1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Euphorbiaceae is the most important botanical family in the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests <xref rid="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Várzea</italic> forest contains a wide range of canopy heights, depending on the forest zonation: trees can be 15–35 m or 35–45 m tall, and a few emergents which reach 58 m <xref rid="pone.0114986-Wittmann1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Wittmann2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. In future publications, we will describe host and non-host tree species, genera and families of MSDR, ASDR, and BDFFP reserves.</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study area at the BDFFP, MSDR, and ASDR reserves, Central Amazonia, Brazil.</title><p>Map sources: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pdbff.inpa.gov.br/area3p.htm">http://www.pdbff.inpa.gov.br/area3p.htm</ext-link> (Biological Dynamics of Forest Fragments Project - BDFFP); <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mamiraua.org.br/downloads/mapas">http://www.mamiraua.org.br/downloads/mapas</ext-link> [Mamirauá (MSDR) and Amanã (ASDR) Sustainable Development Reserves].</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Galling Insect and Host Plant Sampling</title><p>Each sample point consisted of eight plots of 5×20 m, which were 20 m apart from each other (total area of 800 m<sup>2</sup>). The set of plots was established in the forest understory with a measuring tape and then visually projected on the canopy. The sample area was delimited, and the individual tree crowns were distinguished in the upper canopy (characterized by no shading from other trees and positioned at the air-canopy interface). Then, a haphazard sampling was performed in each individual tree crown, by clipping 10 terminal units of the plant <xref rid="pone.0114986-Julio1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Bell1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> using the peconha climbing technique (known as the “foot-belt” <xref rid="pone.0114986-Malcolm1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>) and a telescoping aluminum pole (10 m). In our case, terminal unit length ranged from 30–50 cm, and it encompassed branches, stems, leaves, flowers, and fruits (the last two structures, if they were present). In the field, insect gall morphotypes were recorded as well as their abundances for each tree individual. Gall morphotypes were characterized by external morphology, shape, color, trichomes, single or grouped occurrence, and the host plant organ attacked (see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>). Due to high specificity in the relationship between galling insects and their host plants, each gall morphotype was considered a species of galling insect (see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Carneiro1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> for a review). After this, galling insect richness (GIR) and galling insect abundance (GIA) were estimated from the number of galling species and number of individual galls for each morphotype, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Galling insect richness (GIR) and galling insect abundance (GIA) were considered response variables (separately) and forest type and number of tree species sampled (TSS: unattacked and attacked trees) as predictors, as well the interaction between them. We built GLM (generalized linear models) assuming Poisson error distribution, and compared them with Chi squared tests, in order to deal with overdispersion observed in the data <xref rid="pone.0114986-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. To verify possible effects on GIR and GIA, we used two approaches recommended by Crawley <xref rid="pone.0114986-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>: (i) ANCOVA-GLM model simplification (full model) and (ii) ANOVA-GLM model contrast, to check the effects of the forest type levels in the explanatory power of a model. In the first one, a full model included forest type categories (<italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>), TSS, and the interaction term. The models were manually updated by excluding a combination of explanatory variables. After this, initial and final models were compared by Chi squared tests. Model contrast (second approach) was employed when pairs of factor levels (categorical variable) presented similar parameter values (in our case, mean). Forest type levels (<italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> categories) were concatenated, and model parameters were compared with <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-test. The variation in the gall morphospecies composition (presence/absence) among forest types was evaluated with Jaccard dissimilarity index, running vegan package (version 2.0–10). All analyses were done in the R software program <xref rid="pone.0114986-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Amazonian GI Diversity x Literature Patterns</title><p>Two variables were used to compare results obtained in this study and patterns of distribution and diversity of galling insects recorded in the literature: (i) galling insect richness (GIR) per sample point, and (ii) the ratio GIR/TSS in which the first variable is divided by the number of tree species sampled (host plants and non-hosts; TSS). In this study, the ratio GIR/TSS values of each landscape were computed as averages per sample point (<italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest: n = 14; <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forest: n = 14; <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forest: n = 14).</p><p>GIR values obtained in this study were also plotted onto <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g002">Fig. 2</xref> (page 586) of the study published by Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, where GIR's from various biogeographic regions on an extensive latitudinal gradient were combined. This study emphasized vegetation traits (scleromorphic and non- scleromorphic) and habitat types (xeric, away from water bodies, or mesic, near water bodies). GIR comparisons were visually made. Some studies in this review had adopted the architectural census sampling, which included the intensive investigation of gall insects on 45 trees, 100 shrubs, and 1000 herbs. However, 45 trees and 100 shrubs were only collected in a few studies (see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>), while most studies employed the 60-minute census, shown to be equivalent to the architectural census <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Relationship between galling insect richness (GIR) and number of tree species sampled (TSS) in the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> (red curve and symbols), <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> (green curve and symbols), and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> (black curve and symbols) forests at Amazon.</title><p>GIR variation explained by TSS differed among levels of forest type.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The sampling method employed here (800 m<sup>2</sup> sampling area) does not encompass a record of shrubs and herbaceous plants; nevertheless, number of trees sampled at each site can be used in the data comparisons. Almost all of <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">igapó,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> sites were represented by fewer than 45 individual trees (the number proposed as sufficient to reach an asymptote in species richness <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>), with the exception of one sampling site in the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forest (Sampled trees  = 48 individuals; GIR = 53 morphospecies). In addition, Fernandes and Price <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> observed that 90% of galling species were collected, on average, after sampling 26 individual trees. In this study, a range of ten to 25 tree individuals were found in 38 sites, while 27, 31, 34, and 48 trees were sampled in the other four remaining sites.</p><p>GIR/TSS ratios estimated for <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forests were compared to the two highest and two lowest ratio values compiled by Espírito-Santo and Fernandes (<xref rid="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, but see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Wright1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche3" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>). In addition, values were compared to the GIR/TSS values found for tropical forests of Panama <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. However, sampling methods used in these studies varied widely and galling diversity can be affected by plant community composition <xref rid="pone.0114986-Veldtman1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and plant richness <xref rid="pone.0114986-Lara1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes7" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. We tentatively minimize the GIR over- and under-estimation for a given location/site using the GIR/TSS ratio once sampling effects can be controlled by the number of tree species sampled (host plants and non-hosts).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Overall, we examined 1,091 tree individuals, which were identified as 491 species belonging to 49 botanical families. Out of this total, 89.6% of the trees (978 individuals) were attacked by galling insects, comprising 445 host tree species and 46 non-host tree species. In addition, 141,244 galls induced by 1,150 morphospecies of galling insects were recorded. However, only part of the dataset was included in our statistical analysis in order to balance sampling efforts at different forest types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s001">S1 Table</xref>). Higher abundance and richness of galling insects were found in the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest, followed by <italic toggle="yes">várz</italic>ea and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> habitats (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0114986-t001">Table 1</xref>). However, <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forest presented more galling species <italic toggle="yes">per</italic> tree species sampled (GIR/TSS) than <italic toggle="yes">várz</italic>ea forest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0114986-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0114986-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Number of individuals and species of host plants; galling insect richness (GIR), abundance (GIA), and dissimilarity among the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests in Amazon, Brazil.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0114986-t001-1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Host Plant</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Galling Insect</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Jaccard Dissimilarity to</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest Type</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individuals</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Terra Firme</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Várzea</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Terra Firme</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,055</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Várzea</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,244</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9874</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Igapó</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,994</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9608</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9098</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>*N: number of sampling sites in each landscape.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0114986-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Ratios between galling insect richness and number of tree species sampled (GIR/TSS) in the understory (U) and canopy (C) of different vegetation types in several biogeographic regions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone-0114986-t002-2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetation type</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locality/Country</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIR/TSS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling Area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Savanna <xref rid="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NATT/Australia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U+C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fynbos<xref rid="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Wright1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cape Floristic Province/South Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Various <xref rid="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Yang1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Various/Taiwan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Montane-Desert gradient <xref rid="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche3" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Big Bend National Park/USA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry Tropical Forest <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parque Natural Metropolitano/Panama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry Tropical Forest <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parque Natural Metropolitano/Panama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Rainforest <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuerte Sherman/Panama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Rainforest <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuerte Sherman/Panama</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Rainforest/Terra firme<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDFFP/Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Rainforest/Várzea <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDSR, ADSR/Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tropical Rainforest/Igapó <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADSR/Brazil</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,200</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>*Our Study.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3a"><title>Galling Insect Richness x Tree Species x Forest Type</title><p>Our initial (maximal) model was highly significant (d.f. = 36,41; P&lt;0.001) and explained 83% of variability observed in the galling insect richness (GIR). The predictor variables were forest type (categorical: <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>), TSS (the number of tree species sampled), and interaction between them. A significant variation was also observed in GIR when we removed the interaction and compared with null model (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.77; d.f. = 38,41; P&lt;0.001). However, there was a statistical difference between the two models (d.f. = 38,36; P&lt;0.01), indicating the importance of the interaction as an explanatory term (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), and hence, it was retained in the analysis. In concern to the individual effects of forest types (<italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>) on the values of gall richness, level concatenation (flooded forests: <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>) produced a significant model (d.f. = 38,41; P&lt;0.001, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.74), but also significantly different from our initial model. Again, there was no justification to maintain a final model based on this simplification approach. Although our initial model presented few significant parameters, higher <italic toggle="yes">z</italic> values were observed on the number of tree species sampled (TSS) in igapó and igapó forest type, and the interaction between <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> category and its TSS.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Galling Insect Abundance x Tree Species x Forest Type</title><p>A significant amount of variability in GIA was not explained by the ANCOVA-GLM (d.f. = 36,41; P&lt;0.001; R<sup>2</sup> = 0.52), but all parameters (and their interactions) were highly significant in the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Simplification approaches were, however, employed in order to access explanatory power of the final models. Both the removal of TSS*forest type interaction and level concatenation in forest type resulted in lower values of R<sup>2</sup> (both models: 49%; d.f. = 38,41; P&lt;0.001).</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Relationship between galling insect abundance (GIA) and number of tree species sampled (TSS) in the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> (red curve and symbols), <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> (green curve and symbols), and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> (black curve and symbols) forests at Amazon.</title><p>All parameters were significant in our initial model, in spite of its insufficient predictive power.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Gall Morphospecies Composition</title><p>Overall, 886 morphospecies of gall-forming insects were discovered in the fourteen-site sample at each Amazonian forest type. Only a minor proportion of galling insects (∼8%, n = 70) was shared among <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Forty-four morphospecies were common to the flooded forests, <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and i<italic toggle="yes">gapó</italic>. Gall morphospecies composition differed between pairs of forest types and higher values of Jaccard dissimilarities were observed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0114986-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>A Venn diagram representing the number of galling morphospecies exclusive and common to the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> (blue), <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> (green), and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> (orange) forests, Central Amazonia, Brazil.</title><p>Presence/absence data revealed great dissimilarity among Amazonian forest types, even considering the flooded forests.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Global Patterns in Galling Insect Diversity</title><p>The original studies of Fernandes and Price <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> established the first trends of habitat-related patterns in galling insect distribution. Using a different sampling protocol, the highest number of galling insects recorded by Fernandes and Price <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes4" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> reached 46 morphospecies. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g005">Fig. 5</xref> illustrates the present Amazonian galling richness (42 sites) in comparison with the values for other vegetation of Brazil and the world, compiled by Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and Price <xref rid="pone.0114986-Price2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Absolute GIR fluctuated greatly among sites and forest types in central Amazon rainforests. GIR ranged from 60 galling insect morphospecies, found in a sample point of upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> (BDFFP continuous forest) to 13 morphospecies, collected in a <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> ASDR site, with the same 800 m<sup>2</sup> sampling area. Visual comparison highlighted that GIR highest value - 60 morphospecies - was observed in an Amazonian site, where 22 tree individuals were examined.</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>GIR in Central Amazon sites and values from other vegetations types from Brazil and world.</title><p>The figure was re-drawn from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, page 586, work of Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. GIR (galling insect richness) is equivalent to the number of galling species <italic toggle="yes">per</italic> sample point.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g005.jpg"/></fig><p>GIR/TSS ratios were compared among <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forests and contrasted with the values reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0114986-t002">Table 2</xref>). The lowest value of this ratio in the Amazonian forest was found in the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forest. However, tropical rainforest ratios were, at least, 2.5× higher than the results reported in the literature <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. This also indicates the highest galling insect diversity ever recorded for any biogeographic realm so far.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The sampling of galls at the upper canopy of three Amazonian rain forest types indicated that both galling insect richness and abundance were higher in upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests located on poor and strongly leached soils and lower in the floodplain forests. Given that <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests had been characterized as nutrient-poor habitats by some authors <xref rid="pone.0114986-Sioli1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Victoria1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, we would expect a high galling diversity in such environments (see <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes4" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>). In contrast, lower absolute values of GIR and GIA were found in the <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests; the reasons for this await further investigations based on plant physiology, chemical and mechanical defenses against herbivores, and relationships between flood tolerance and herbivory.</p><p>Disregard with the explanatory power of models (amount of variability in response variable explained by the predictor variables), GIR and GIA were highly influenced by the number of trees species sampled (host and non-host plants) in each forest type (interaction term). Our data support the hypothesis that the estimated parameters to richness and abundance of galling insects are intimately dependent on host plant diversity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0114986.s002">S2 Table</xref>), and vegetation community where they are located, as observed in the <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forest. In addition, we unveiled some environmental filters shaping galling species patterns in the Amazonian forest ecosystems - vertical gradient in leaf traits, flooding, species composition, soil/water nutrients, and super host occurrence.</p><p>Impoverished floras have been consistently recorded in the <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests in comparison to <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> and upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests (e.g., <xref rid="pone.0114986-Prance1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk3" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>). The arthropod fauna (oribatid mites and spiders) seems to be more speciose in <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> than <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Franklin1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Hfer1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. We also found that <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forest had a greater number of galling species per plant species than <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic>, in spite of their floristic similarity. GIR/TSS ratios revealed that <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> plants accumulated a larger number of galling species, similar to upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> trees. Such similarity between <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> could be explained by the low nutritional status of their soils, given that these landscapes are very distinct in regard to hydrological features. Haugaasen and Peres <xref rid="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> verified that <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> soils of the lower Purús River were richer in nutrients, while <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> had no significant differences regarding their nutritional status (Ca, Mg, Al, Zn and Mn, excepting phosphorus in the <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic>). Therefore, apart from the influence of number of plant species in a given location or type of vegetation, this study supports the nutritional stress hypothesis <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Blanche2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, which predicts a greater GIR in environments whose plants are subject to nutrient limitation.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Igapó</italic> flooded forests have additional characteristics that make them prone to a high diversity of galling insects. Similarities based on taxonomic and biogeographic traits were found between <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> flora and oligotrophic habitats in the Amazon savannas, “caatingas”, and white sand savanna, which are located on poor soils <xref rid="pone.0114986-Prance2" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Kubitzki1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Moreover, some areas of <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> vegetation experience desert-like conditions in the dry season and its plants exhibit xeromorphic adaptations such as sclerophyllous leaves <xref rid="pone.0114986-Prance1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> floodplain vegetation is more related to the vegetation growing on fertile habitats from upland <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest <xref rid="pone.0114986-Worbes1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Nutrient-poor soils and large water table fluctuations have been argued to be the main explanation of enhancement of leaf construction costs, and a thickness and sclerophylly index in microhabitats of mixed forests of Venezuela <xref rid="pone.0114986-Sobrado1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. In lowland tropical forest of Panamá, significant higher leaf sclerophylly was found on the higher strata of rainforest, and insect gall richness was positively affected by sclerophylly <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro3" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. The alterations in leaf traits (area, mass/area, thickness, anatomy) have been also related to an ontogenetic transition between sapling/emergent tree life stages, besides the harsh conditions at the upper canopy <xref rid="pone.0114986-Sanches1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>.</p><p>A canopy measurement study from four towers situated in <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forests from Central Amazon, Brazil, evaluated the effects of leaf temperature variation on respiration and photosynthesis. It revealed that some canopy leaves reach temperatures very close to their lethal limit <xref rid="pone.0114986-Tribuzy1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. The author also found that the temperature of sunlit leaves exceeded air temperature by 6°C, on average, in both rainy and dry seasons, and reached values 10°C above air temperature. Surprisingly, values for canopy leaf temperatures surpass 45°C, indicating that upper canopy leaves experience a habitat under strong thermal stress <xref rid="pone.0114986-Tribuzy1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Doughty1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Morphological and physiological alterations in the upper canopy leaves help them tolerate such stress; lower values of specific leaf area indicate such leaves have larger amounts of leaf mass per area unit <xref rid="pone.0114986-Tribuzy2" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Of 21 tree individuals identified at the species level by Tribuzy <xref rid="pone.0114986-Tribuzy1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, fourteen individuals (66.7%) belonged to tree species also sampled in our study. These plant species hosted 40 galling insect morphospecies and accounted for 7.4% of total gall abundance (10,467 galls). Considering a vertical profile of leaf traits, leaves which grow in full sunlight were hard, with lower specific leaf area (SLA), and a higher sclerophylly index than shaded leaves in the Brazilian Central Amazon <xref rid="pone.0114986-Marenco1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Camargo1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>; the specific leaf area has also been used to characterize the sclerophyllous leaves in several vegetation types <xref rid="pone.0114986-Groom1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Lima1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>.</p><p>However, evidence suggests that flooding may represent a strong regional selective pressure on these floodplain forest systems. Leaves of Amazonian floodplain trees present several traits which help with the scanty water supplies to the crowns, during the flooding period. On average, 5–33% higher values of specific leaf mass (another indirect measure of sclerophylly) were found during the flooding period than in the non-flooded months <xref rid="pone.0114986-Junk4" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Waldhoff1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. For instance, a flood-adapted species, <italic toggle="yes">Calophyllum brasiliense</italic> (Clusiaceae) hosts five leaf and stem galling species (<italic toggle="yes">Lopesia caulinaris</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">L.conspicua</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">L. elliptica</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">L. linearis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Contarinia gemmae</italic>) <xref rid="pone.0114986-Madeira1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. On this species, Ribeiro <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro4" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref> reported a high frequency of galling attack on flooded individuals compared to non-flooded ones. The abundance of galls and the number of successfully emerged adults per leaf was also higher on plants subjected to flooding <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro4" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. We conclude that selection for sclerophyllous foliage could be an adaptive mechanism (sunlight, flooding) which has favored the galling insect fauna.</p><p>Galling insect abundance was also higher in the <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> landscape where we also recorded larger numbers of insect galls per host plant. Tree hosts from <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> supported similar but lower values of galling insect abundance. However, which factors modulate the number of galls per insect species in the Amazonian forests deserve more attention in future studies, since interactions with other organisms could affect directly or indirectly the abundance of gall-forming insects <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fagundes1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>.</p><p>High values of GIR/TSS ratios obtained in this study could be explained by the small number of plant species not attacked by galling insects (in our study, only tall trees), and the large number of “superhost” species; i.e, plant species attacked by a large number of galling species <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-MendonaJr1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes8" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. In the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forest we observed the highest number of tree species not attacked by galling insects (45 tree species). <italic toggle="yes">Terra firme</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests presented much smaller numbers of non-host trees, 26 and 19 tree species, respectively. In our study, <italic toggle="yes">Protium altsonii</italic> Sandw., <italic toggle="yes">P. tenuifolium</italic> (Engl.) Engl. (Burseraceae), and <italic toggle="yes">Licania micrantha</italic> Miq. (Chrysobalanaceae) were the host tree species which presented higher number of gall morphospecies (ten morphotypes per tree species); the first two were collected only in <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> sites while the third one was sampled in <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests.</p><p>Knowledge on plant diversity, as well as floristic composition of a site, have been assigned as main relevant factors in the analysis of distribution patterns of galling insect communities <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes7" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Wright2" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Veldtman and McGeoch <xref rid="pone.0114986-Veldtman1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> found that the floristic composition was a major factor in local GIR through the presence of “superhosts”. This pattern was also observed for free-living insect herbivores associated with the forest canopy of Laurisilva, Azores <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro5" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. Out of 129 herbivorous insect species found, 65 species were sampled on <italic toggle="yes">Juniperus brevifolia</italic>, and 53 species on the <italic toggle="yes">Erica azorica</italic>. In this study, Fabaceae accumulated 222 galling morphospecies (mainly on the genus <italic toggle="yes">Inga</italic>; nineteen <italic toggle="yes">Inga</italic> species supported 69 galling morphotypes), followed by the families Sapotaceae and Lecythidaceae, with 159 and 106 galling insect morphospecies, respectively. Carvalho-Fernandes <xref rid="pone.0114986-CarvalhoFernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref> also found 95 galling morphospecies associated with 15 <italic toggle="yes">Protium</italic> species (Burseraceae) in a <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic> forest, near Manaus (Amazonas, Brazil). Further analysis will provide inferences about the role of each host plant species in galling diversity patterns observed in the canopy of <italic toggle="yes">terra firme</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">várzea,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">igapó</italic> forests.</p><p>To elaborate and refine the explanatory hypotheses related to galling insect distribution patterns and galling insect diversity, it is necessary to investigate other systems, and preferably, vegetation types which contrast with the scenarios where the main hypotheses have been formulated and corroborated. By doing so, we reported larger gall richness than those recorded to date. GIR/TSS ratio in the <italic toggle="yes">várzea</italic> forest was approximately 2.5 times larger than the largest value of this ratio ever recorded in the literature (canopy of tropical forest, Panama, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Medianero3" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>). The clear difference between ratio values indicates that even the GIR poorest site in Amazonian vegetation is among the habitats with the greatest diversity of galling species of all biogeographic regions already investigated.</p><p>Despite that galling insect diversity peaks having been reported exclusively for scleromorphic vegetation, our results strongly support the hypothesis of Fernandes and Price <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0114986-Fernandes4" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, Price <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0114986-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and Ribeiro <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, and unveil the Amazonian upper canopy as a hygrothermically stressed habitat, which possess high levels of sclerophylly, compared to the understory habitat <xref rid="pone.0114986-Marenco1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0114986-Camargo1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, a non- scleromorphic humid forests of central Amazonia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Ribeiro and Basset <xref rid="pone.0114986-Ribeiro3" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> showed the importance of leaf sclerophylly to galler oviposition preferences in the upper canopy, resulting in an enemy-free space (death by fungi and free-feeding herbivores). Besides, the effects of hydraulic stress in large tropical trees and the number of active meristems (higher in canopy than understory) on the galling insect richness remains to be tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114986-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). In spite of being in a humid domain, the canopy of the Amazonian Equatorial forest might most resemble a savanna or Mediterranean type environment with high temperatures and UV radiation where galling herbivores flourish.</p><fig id="pone-0114986-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114986.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Mechanisms shaping the distribution patterns of galling insects in the Amazonian forests.</title><p>Down arrow icon means lower value/level; up arrow icon, higher ones in the comparison between canopy and understory.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0114986.g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0114986.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><p>
<bold>Sampling points in the Amazonian forest types, the richness and abundance of galling insects, host plants, and geographical location.</bold>
</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0114986.s001.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0114986.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><p>
<bold>Host plant list of the Amazonian gall-forming insects.</bold>
</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0114986.s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank M. Barbosa and H. Vasconcelos for helpful comments on the initial versions of this manuscript. J. Guedes, J. Ramos, E. Pereira, P. Assunção, and J. Inuma provided valuable technical assistance in several phases of this project. M.S. Rodrigues was helpful in the statistical analysis. This is publication number 658 in the BDFFP Technical Series.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Biogeographical gradients in galling species richness: test of hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28312192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00379948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The adaptive significance of insect gall distribution: survivorship of species in xeric and mesic habitats</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28312265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00317803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Price1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>ACF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brawn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Global patterns in local number of insect galling species</article-title>. <source>J Biogeogr</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-EspritoSanto1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Espírito-Santo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>How many species of gall-inducing insects are there on Earth, and where are they?</article-title>
<source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Tooker1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tooker</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohr</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Gall insects can evade and alter indirect plant defenses</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>
<volume>178</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>671</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18331430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02392.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Medianero1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Medianero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibáñez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieves-Aldrey</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Importance of beta diversity in local gall-inducing arthropods communities</article-title>. <source>Neotrop Entomol</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/s1519-566x2010000300009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Sullivan1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brudvig</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Can dispersal mode predict corridor effects on plant parasites?</article-title>
<source>Ecology</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1559</fpage>–<lpage>1564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21905422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1890/10-1116.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes3"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fernandes GW, Gonçalves-Alvim SJ, Carneiro MAA (2005) Habitat-driven effects on the diversity of gall-inducing insects in the Brazilian cerrado. In: Raman A, Schaefer CW, Withers TM, editors.Biology, ecology, and evolution of gall-inducing arthropods.Enfield, USA: Science Publishers. pp. 693–708.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes4"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fernandes GW, Price PW (1991) Comparisons of tropical and temperate galling species richness: the role of environmental harshness and plant nutrient status. In: Price PW, Lewinsohn TM, Fernandes GW, Benson WW, editors.Plant-animal interactions: evolutionary ecology in tropical and temperate regions.New York: John Wiley. pp. 91–116.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes5"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>ACF</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Diversity of Indonesian gall-forming herbivores along altitudinal gradients</article-title>. <source>Biodivers Letters</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Lara1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>ACF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonçalves-Alvim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Tests of hypotheses on patterns of gall distribution along an altitudinal gradient</article-title>. <source>Trop Zool</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Lara2"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>ACF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The highest diversity of galling insects: Serra do Cipó, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Biodivers Letters</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes6"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Insect galls from Jequitinhonha Valley, Minas Gerais, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Naturalia</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Blanche1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Diversity of insect-induced galls along a temperature-rainfall gradient in the tropical savannah region of the northern territory, Australia</article-title>. <source>Aust Ecol</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-CuevasReyes1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cuevas-Reyes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quesada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siebe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Spatial patterns of herbivory by gall-forming insects: a test of the soil fertility hypothesis in a Mexican tropical dry forest</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Ribeiro1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <article-title>MB, Tagliati MC, Chavana-Bryant C (2011) Vegetation traits and herbivory distribution in an Australian subtropical forest</article-title>. <source>Mem Queensl Mus - Nature</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Hill1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Fossil evidence for the onset of xeromorphy and scleromorphy in Australian Proteaceae</article-title>. <source>Aust Syst Bot</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Veldtman1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Veldtman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gall-forming insect species richness along a non-scleromorphic vegetation rainfall gradient in South Africa: The importance of plant community composition</article-title>. <source>Aust Ecol</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Yukawa1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uechi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Species richness of galling arthropods in Manaus, Amazon and surroundings of the Iguassu Falls</article-title>. <source>Esakia</source>
<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Julio1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Julião</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Venticinque</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Richness and abundance of gall-forming insects in the Mamirauá Várzea, a flooded Amazonian forest</article-title>. <source>Uakari</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Ribeiro2"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ribeiro SP (2003) Insect herbivores in the canopies of savannas and rainforests. In: Basset Y, Novotny V, Miller SE, Kitching RL, editors.Arthropods of Tropical Forests: spatio-temporal dynamics and resource use in the canopy.Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press. pp. 348–359.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Ribeiro3"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basset</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Gall-forming and free-feeding herbivory along vertical gradients in a lowland tropical rainforest: the importance of leaf sclerophylly</article-title>. <source>Ecography</source>
<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>672</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Medianero2"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Medianero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Riqueza de insectos cecidógenos en el dosel y sotobosque de dos zonas ecológicas en Panamá</article-title>. <source>Scientia (Panamá)</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Paniagua1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paniagua</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medianero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structure and vertical stratification of plant galler-parasitoid food webs in two tropical forests</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Turner1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Sclerophylly: primarily protective?</article-title>
<source>Funct Ecol</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Prance1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prance</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Notes on the vegetation of Amazonia III. The terminology of Amazonian forest types subject to inundation</article-title>. <source>Brittonia</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Pires1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pires JM (1985) The vegetation types of the Brazilian Amazon. In: Prance GT, Lovejoy TE, editors.Key environments: Amazonia.Oxford, UK: Pergamon Press. pp. 83–94.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Junk1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Junk WJ (1983) As águas da região Amazônica. In: Salati E, Junk WJ, Shubart HOR, Oliveira A, editors.Amazônia: desenvolvimento, integração e ecologia.Brazil: Editora Brasiliense/CNPq. pp.45–100.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Junk2"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Junk WJ (1989) Flood tolerance and tree distribution in central Amazonian floodplains. In: Nielsen LB, Nielsen IC, Balslev H, editors.Tropical forests: botanical dynamics, speciation and diversity.London: Academic Press. pp. 47–64.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Haugaasen1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haugaasen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Floristic, edaphic and structural characteristics of flooded and unflooded forests in the lower Rio Purús region of central Amazonia, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Acta Amaz</source>
<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Pereira1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>MJR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmeirim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Vertical stratification of bat assemblages in flooded and unflooded Amazonian forests</article-title>. <source>Curr Zool</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Junk3"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Junk WJ (1984) Ecology of the várzea, floodplain of Amazonian white water rivers. In: Sioli H, editor.The Amazon: Limnology and landscape ecology of a mighty tropical river and its basin.The Netherlands, Dordrecht: W. Junk Publishers. pp. 215–243.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Schngart1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schöngart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piedade</surname><given-names>MTF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junk</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worbes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Wood growth patterns of Macrolobium acaciifolium (Benth.) Benth. (Fabaceae) in Amazonian black-water and white-water floodploain forests</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00442-005-0147-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Oliveira1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A central Amazonian terra firme forest. I. High tree species richness on poor soils</article-title>. <source>Biodivers conserv</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1219</fpage>–<lpage>1244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Powers1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Treseder</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lerdau</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Fine roots, arbuscular mycorrhizal hyphae and soil nutrients in four neotropical rain forests: patterns across large geographic distances</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>
<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>921</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2004.01279.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Blanche2"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westoby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Gall-forming insect diversity is linked to soil fertility via host plant taxon</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>2334</fpage>–<lpage>2337</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Southwood1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Southwood</surname><given-names>TRE</given-names></name> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>The abundance of Hawaiian trees and the number of their associated insect species</article-title>. <source>Proc Hawaiian Entomol Soc</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes7"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Plant historical and biogeographical effects on insular gall-forming species richness</article-title>. <source>Global Ecol Biogeogr Lett</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Wittmann1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anhuf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junk</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Tree species distribution and community structure of Central Amazonian várzea forests by remote sensing techniques</article-title>. <source>J Trop Ecol</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Wittmann2"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junk</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piedade</surname><given-names>MTF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The várzea forests in Amazonia: flooding and the highly dynamic geomorphology interact with natural forest succession</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecol Manag</source>
<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Bell1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dines</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Branch construction and bud defense status at canopy surface of a West African rainforest</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc</source>
<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>499</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Malcolm1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Comparative abundances of Neotropical small mammals by trap height</article-title>. <source>J Mammal</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Carneiro1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>CSA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>CED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almada</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>MBM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Are gall midge species (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae) host plant specialists?</article-title>
<source>Rev Bras Entomol</source>
<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Crawley1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Crawley MJ (2007) The R Book. West Sussex, England, John Wiley &amp; Sons. 942p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Price2"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Price PW (1991) Patterns in communities along latitudinal gradients. In: Price PW, Lewinsohn TM, Fernandes GW, Benson WW, editors.Plant-animal interactions: Evolutionary ecology in tropical and temperate regions.New York: John Wiley. pp. 51–70.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Wright1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samways</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Insect species richness tracking plant species richness in a diverse flora: gall-insects in the Cape Floristic Region, South Africa</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28308436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s004420050537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Yang1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang MM, Tung GS (1998) The diversity of insect-induced galls on vascular plants in Taiwan: a preliminary report. In Csóka G, Mattson WJ, Stone GN, Price PW, editors. The Biology of Gall-Inducing Arthropods. General Technical Report NC-199, U. S. Department of Agriculture, Washington, USA. pp. 44–53.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Blanche3"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blanche</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Species richness of gall-inducing insects and host plants along an altitudinal gradient in Big Bend National Park, Texas</article-title>. <source>Am Midl Nat</source>
<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Medianero3"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Medianero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Diversidad de insectos minadores de hojas y formadores de agallas en el dosel y sotobosque del bosque tropical</article-title>. <source>Acta Zool Mex</source>
<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Sioli1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sioli H (1991) Amazônia: fundamentos da ecologia da maior região de florestas tropicais. Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: Editora Vozes. 72 p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Victoria1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Victoria RL, Martinelli LA, Cunha HB, Richey JE (2000) The Amazon basin and its natural cycles. In: Salati E, Absy ML, Victoria RL, editors.Amazônia: um ecossistema em transformação.Manaus: INPA, Brasília: CNPq. pp.163–214.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Franklin1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Franklin EN, Adis J, Woas S (1997) The Oribatid Mites. In: Junk WJ, editor.The Central-Amazonian Floodplain: Ecology of a Pulsing System. Ecological Studies.Vol. 126. Berlin, Heidelberg, New York: Springer Verlag. pp. 331–349.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Hfer1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Höfer H (1997) The spider communities. In: Junk WJ, editor.The Central-Amazonian Floodplain: Ecology of a Pulsing System. Ecological Studies.Vol. 126. Berlin, Heidelberg, New York: Springer Verlag. pp.373–383.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Prance2"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Prance GT (1989) American tropical forests. American tropical forests. In: Lieth H, Werger MJA, editors.Tropical rain forest ecosystems - biogeographical and ecological studies.Amsterdam: Elsevier Science Publishers. p. 99–132.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Kubitzki1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kubitzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The ecogeographical differentiation of Amazonian inundation forests</article-title>. <source>Plant Syst Evol</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Worbes1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Worbes M (1997) The Forest Ecosystem of the Floodplain. In: Junk WJ, editor.The Central-Amazonian Floodplain: Ecology of a Pulsing System. Ecological Studies.Vol. 126.Berlin, Heidelberg, New York: Springer Verlag. pp. 223–266.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Sobrado1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sobrado</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Leaf characteristics, wood anatomy and hydraulic properties in tree species from contrasting habitats within upper Rio Negro forests in the Amazon region</article-title>. <source>J Trop Ecol</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Sanches1"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanches</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalvi</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva Júnior</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Differential leaf traits of a neotropical tree Cariniana legalis (Mart.) Kuntze (Lecythidaceae): comparing saplings and emergent trees</article-title>. <source>Trees</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Tribuzy1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tribuzy ES (2005) Variações da temperatura foliar do dossel e o seu efeito na taxa assimilatória de CO<sub>2</sub> na Amazônia Central. Unpublished PhD thesis, Universidade de São Paulo, Brazil.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Doughty1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doughty</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goulden</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Are tropical forests near a high temperature threshold?</article-title>
<source>J Geophys Res</source>
<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>G00B07</fpage> doi:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2007JG000632">10.1029/2007JG000632</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Tribuzy2"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tribuzy ES, Teixeira LM, Chambers JQ, Reis TS, Trumbore S, et al. (2003) Physiological responses of tree species growing under different site conditions in the Central Amazon. In: Seventh LBA-ECO Science Team Business Meeting, Fortaleza, Brazil. LBA/INPA/NASA. p. 94</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Marenco1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marenco</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>JFC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Leaf gas exchange and carbohydrates in tropical trees differing in successional status in two light environments in central Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/treephys/21.18.1311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Gonalves1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>JFC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marenco</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraz</surname><given-names>JBS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos Junior</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nutritional status and specific leaf area of mahogany and tonka bean under two light environments</article-title>. <source>Acta Amaz</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>.23</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Camargo1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marenco</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Growth, leaf and stomatal traits of crabwood (Carapa guianensis Aubl.) in central Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Revista Árvore</source>
<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>07</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Groom1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Groom PK, Lamont BB (1999) Which common indices of sclerophylly best reflect differences in leaf structure? Ecoscience 6, 471–474.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Lima1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Boeger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelozzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soffiatti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Sclerophylly in mangrove tree species from South Brazil</article-title>. <source>Rev Mex Biodiv</source>
<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>1166</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Junk4"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Junk WJ, Piedade MTF, Parolin P, Wittmann F, Schöngart J (2010) Ecophysiology, biodiversity and sustainable management of central Amazonian floodplain forests: A synthesis. In: Junk WJ, Piedade MTF, Wittmann F, Schöngart J, Parolin P, editors.Amazonian Floodplain Forests: Ecophysiology, Biodiversity and Sustainable Management.Dordrecht, Heidelberg, London, New York: Springer. pp. 511–540.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Waldhoff1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Waldhoff D, Parolin P (2010) Morphology and anatomy of leaves. In: Junk WJ, Piedade MTF, Wittmann F, Schöngart J, Parolin P, editors.Amazonian Floodplain Forests: Ecophysiology, Biodiversity and Sustainable Management.Dordrecht, Heidelberg, London, New York: Springer. pp.179–202.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Madeira1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Gall makers (Cecidomyiidae, Diptera) on <italic toggle="yes">Calophyllum brasiliense</italic> Camb. (Clusiaceae): descriptions and biology</article-title>. <source>Arch Mus Nac (Rio de J)</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Ribeiro4"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Does flooding favour galling insects?</article-title>
<source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fagundes1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Direct and indirect interactions involving ants, insect herbivores and parasitoids on the host plant Baccharis dracunculifolia (Asteraceae)</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-MendonaJr1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mendonça Jr</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Plant diversity and galling arthropod diversity searching for taxonomic patterns in an animal-plant interaction in the neotropics</article-title>. <source>Bol Soc Argent Bot</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Fernandes8"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almada</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Gall-Inducing Insect Species Richness as Indicators of Forest Age and Health</article-title>. <source>Environ Entomol</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1134</fpage>–<lpage>1140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22127163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1603/EN09199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Wright2"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samways</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Gall-insect species richness in the African Fynbos and Karoo vegetation: The importance of plant species richness</article-title>. <source>Biodiv Lett</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-Ribeiro5"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>PAV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaspar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>ARM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Canopy insect herbivores in the Azorean Laurisilva forests: key host plant species in a highly generalist insect community</article-title>. <source>Ecography</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0114986-CarvalhoFernandes1"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carvalho-Fernandes SP (2010) Insetos galhadores associados à família Burseraceae da Reserva Florestal Ducke, Manaus-AM. Unpublished MSc thesis, Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia, Brazil.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>