
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">582</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0372763</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4439557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4439557.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4439557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4439557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25552595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db14-0745</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">0745</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Islet Studies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Novel Stable Isotope Analyses Demonstrate Significant Rates of Glucose Cycling in Mouse Pancreatic Islets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8846-267X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname><given-names initials="ML">Martha L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pound</surname><given-names initials="LD">Lynley D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trenary</surname><given-names initials="I">Irina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names initials="RM">Richard M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names initials="JD">Jamey D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, Vanderbilt School of Engineering, Nashville, TN</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Molecular Physiology and Biophysics, Vanderbilt University Medical School, Nashville, TN</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Jamey D. Young, <email>j.d.young@vanderbilt.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>64</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">253226</issue-id><fpage>2129</fpage><lpage>2137</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2016-06-08 21:05:43.047"><day>08</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 by the American Diabetes Association. Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="db140745.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="db140745.pdf"/><abstract><p>A polymorphism located in the <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic> gene, which encodes an islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit, is the most important common determinant of variations in fasting blood glucose (FBG) levels in humans. Studies of <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> knockout (KO) mice suggest that G6pc2 represents a negative regulator of basal glucose-stimulated insulin secretion (GSIS) that acts by hydrolyzing glucose-6-phosphate (G6P), thereby reducing glycolytic flux. However, this conclusion conflicts with the very low estimates for the rate of glucose cycling in pancreatic islets, as assessed using radioisotopes. We have reassessed the rate of glucose cycling in pancreatic islets using a novel stable isotope method. The data show much higher levels of glucose cycling than previously reported. In 5 mmol/L glucose, islets from C57BL/6J chow-fed mice cycled ∼16% of net glucose uptake. The cycling rate was further increased at 11 mmol/L glucose. Similar cycling rates were observed using islets from high fat–fed mice. Importantly, glucose cycling was abolished in <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mouse islets, confirming that G6pc2 opposes the action of the glucose sensor glucokinase by hydrolyzing G6P. The demonstration of high rates of glucose cycling in pancreatic islets explains why <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> deletion enhances GSIS and why variants in <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic> affect FBG in humans.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="sp1"><funding-source>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases<named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000062</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">DK07563</award-id><award-id rid="sp1">DK20593</award-id><award-id rid="sp1">DK59637</award-id><award-id rid="sp1">DK92589</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group id="sp2"><funding-source>Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems<named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000146</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">0955251</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Glucose-6-phosphatase catalyzes the hydrolysis of glucose-6-phosphate (G6P) to glucose and inorganic phosphate (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). It exists as a multicomponent system located in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and is composed of several integral membrane proteins, namely, a catalytic subunit (G6PC), a glucose transporter, and a G6P/inorganic phosphate antiporter (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Three G6PC isoforms have been identified, which are designated G6PC, G6PC2, and G6PC3 (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Each isoform is encoded by a separate gene with a distinct pattern of tissue-specific expression (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">G6PC</italic> is predominantly expressed in the liver, where it catalyzes the final step in gluconeogenesis and glycogenolysis (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">G6PC3</italic>, also known as <italic toggle="yes">UGRP</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">G6Pase-</italic><italic toggle="yes">β</italic>, is ubiquitously expressed (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Mutations that reduce G6PC3 activity result in neutropenia; however, the physiological function of G6PC3 is unclear (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic>, also known as <italic toggle="yes">IGRP</italic> (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), is selectively expressed in pancreatic islet β-cells (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). G6PC2 is a major autoantigen in both mouse (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) and human (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) type 1 diabetes.</p><p>Historically, the question as to whether glucose-6-phosphatase activity is present in islets has been controversial, though it is now generally agreed that activity is detectable, but at a lower level than that found in the liver (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). While a majority of studies agree that glucose-6-phosphatase activity exists in pancreatic islets, the issue as to whether the level of activity is enough to affect glucose-stimulated insulin secretion (GSIS), and therefore whether the activity is of biological significance, is currently unresolved. Sweet et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) concluded that, while glucose-6-phosphatase activity is present in rat islets, the level of activity is not enough to result in sufficient G6P hydrolysis so as to affect GSIS. However, two caveats have subsequently arisen with respect to this conclusion. First, in contrast to all other vertebrate species examined (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic> is a pseudogene in rats (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Second, in various rat models associated with impaired glucose tolerance, <italic toggle="yes">G6PC</italic> expression is induced such that G6P hydrolysis would be elevated (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Several articles have also addressed the issue of G6P hydrolysis in mouse islets. Early studies (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) suggested that, even though glucose-6-phosphatase activity is present in mouse islets, G6P hydrolysis does not occur. While seemingly counterintuitive, such a scenario would be possible if G6P entry into the ER lumen was blocked. However, later studies (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) challenged this conclusion and showed that the measurement of G6P hydrolysis within islets is critically dependent on assay conditions. More recently, we have shown that G6pc2 accounts for the low glucose-6-phosphatase enzyme activity detected in mouse islets (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) and that a global knockout (KO) of <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> in mice on both a mixed (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) and pure C57BL/6J genetic background (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) results in a mild metabolic phenotype characterized by an ∼15% decrease in fasting blood glucose (FBG) levels. These KO mouse data are consistent with recent genome-wide association studies (GWAS) showing that single nucleotide polymorphisms within the human <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic> gene are associated with variations in FBG levels (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Based on these observations, we hypothesize that G6PC2 forms a futile substrate cycle with the β-cell glucose sensor glucokinase (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) and acts as a negative regulator of basal GSIS by hydrolyzing G6P, thereby modulating β-cell glycolytic flux (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Consistent with this model, a reduction in <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> expression results in a leftward shift in the dose-response curve for GSIS, such that under fasting conditions blood glucose levels are reduced (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>A major caveat with this model for the function of G6PC2 is the fact that estimates of glucose cycling (GC) obtained by radiotracer studies of pancreatic islets are very low (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Because the glucose-6-phosphatase activity of G6PC2 is ∼40-fold lower than that of G6PC (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and because G6PC2 also possesses a phosphatidic acid phosphatase domain (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), the possibility exists that G6PC2 influences GSIS through a mechanism that is independent of its ability to hydrolyze G6P. We have revisited this issue using an alternate, novel stable isotope methodology. With this approach, we can demonstrate much higher levels of GC in islets than has previously been reported. Importantly, GC is abolished in <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mouse islets, suggesting that G6pc2 modulates GSIS, at least in part, through its ability to hydrolyze G6P, and thereby oppose the action of the β-cell glucose sensor glucokinase.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Research Design and Methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Animal Care</title><p>The animal housing and surgical facilities used for this study meet the standards set by the American Association for the Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care. The Vanderbilt University Medical Center Animal Care and Use Committee approved all the protocols that were used. Prior to islet isolation, mice were maintained either continuously on a standard rodent chow diet (calorie contributions: 28% protein, 12% fat, 60% carbohydrate [14% disaccharides]; LabDiet 5001; PMI Nutrition International) or on a high-fat diet (calorie contributions: 15% protein, 59% fat, 26% carbohydrate [42% disaccharides]; Mouse Diet F3282; BioServ) for 5–8 months. Food and water were provided ad libitum.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Generation of <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO Mice</title><p>The generation of <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice on a pure C57BL/6J genetic background has been previously described (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Islet Isolations</title><p>Islets were isolated from adult (8–12 months of age) male wild-type (WT) and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice, as previously described (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Isolated islets were incubated overnight in petri dishes in RPMI 1640 medium containing 11 mmol/L glucose. Aliquots of ∼100 islets were then transferred to 96-well plates and incubated for 24 or 72 h in RPMI 1640 medium containing 5 or 11 mmol/L glucose in a volume of 175 μL. Islets were incubated in either naturally labeled glucose or [1,2,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>7</sub>]glucose (D7-glucose) (98% isotopic purity per site; Cambridge Isotope Laboratories, Andover, MA). After the 24 or 72 h of incubation, islets were resuspended by pipetting and were pelleted by centrifugation. The supernatant was retained for the analysis of insulin content and glucose isotopomers, whereas the cell pellet was washed in PBS and then solubilized in passive lysis buffer (Promega) before quantitation of protein content using the Bio-Rad colorimetric protein assay.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Preparation of Glucose Derivatives</title><p>The supernatants collected after islet incubations were divided into three aliquots, and each was derivatized separately to obtain di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-isopropylidene propionate, aldonitrile pentapropionate, and methyloxime pentapropionate derivatives of glucose. For di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-isopropylidene derivatization, 20 μL of supernatant was mixed with 20 μL of 5 mmol/L [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>; 1,2,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>7</sub>]glucose (Cambridge Isotope Laboratories), which served as an internal standard. The derivatization then proceeded, as described previously (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), to produce glucose 1,2,5,6-di-isopropylidene propionate. The glucose aldonitrile pentapropionate and glucose methyloxime pentapropionate derivatives were produced as described previously (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Gas Chromatography–Mass Spectrometry Analysis</title><p>Gas chromatography–mass spectrometry analysis was performed using a 7890A Gas Chromatography System (Agilent) with an HP-5 ms capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm; Agilent J&amp;W Scientific) interfaced with a 5975C mass spectrometer (Agilent). One microliter of di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-isopropylidene, aldonitrile, or methyloxime derivatives was injected into a 270°C injection port in splitless mode. Helium flow was maintained at 0.88 mL/min. The column temperature was held at 80°C for 1 min, ramped at 20°C/min to 280°C and held for 4 min, then ramped at 40°C/min to 325°C. After a 5-min solvent delay, the mass spectrometer collected data in scan mode from mass/charge ratio (m/z) values of 100 to 500. Each derivative peak was integrated using a custom MATLAB function (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) to obtain mass isotopomer distributions (MIDs) for specific ion ranges.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Estimation of Total Glucose Concentration in the Presence of Deuterated Glucose</title><p>Because enzymatic methods for glucose quantification are sensitive to kinetic isotope effects, we used a gas chromatography–mass spectrometry–based method for quantification. The di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-isopropylidene glucose peak was integrated over a mass range from m/z of 301 (M + 0) to 321 (M + 20), and the ratio of the integrated ion counts of the glucose in the medium supernatant (M + 0 to M + 10) to the fully labeled [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>; 1,2,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>7</sub>]glucose internal standard (M + 11 to M + 20) was determined. We used known glucose standards that were derivatized and analyzed alongside the experimental samples in each run to build a standard curve, as follows:<disp-formula id="e1"><label>(1)</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745equ1.jpg"/></disp-formula>where [Sample] is the concentration of glucose in the supernatant sample, [INSTD] is the known concentration of the internal standard, (<italic toggle="yes">M + i</italic>) is the relative abundance of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>th mass isotopomer, <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> is the slope of the calibration curve, and <italic toggle="yes">b</italic> is its <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-intercept. Cell-free evaporation controls were collected at 24 and 72 h from replicate wells. The glucose concentration of these unlabeled samples was measured with a YSI 2300 STAT Plus Glucose &amp; Lactate Analyzer (YSI Life Sciences). An evaporation correction factor was calculated by dividing the average concentration of the 72-h cell-free controls by the average concentration of the 24-h cell-free controls, and all 72-h sample concentrations were divided by the correction factor.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Calculation of Glucose Uptake and Cycling</title><p>Net glucose uptake (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub>) was calculated from the change in medium glucose concentration from 24 to 72 h and expressed in picomoles/islet/hour, as follows:<disp-formula id="e2"><label>(2)</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745equ2.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>72</sub> is the extracellular glucose concentration at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>24</sub> is the glucose concentration at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> is the liquid volume in each well (175 μL), and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> is the number of islets in each well. To quantify GC, the rate of G6P hydrolysis (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>) was expressed as a percentage of<italic toggle="yes"> v</italic><sub>net</sub> using an equation derived from the model illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>GC is controlled by the action of glucokinase (GK) and G6PC2. Tracer glucose (D7-glucose) is converted to G6P (D7-G6P) through the action of the enzyme glucokinase at the rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>1</sub>. G6P is assumed to fully equilibrate with fructose-6-phosphate (F6P). The PGI-catalyzed isomerization of G6P to F6P results in an exchange of hydrogen at the second carbon (C2) of G6P. Any deuterium at C2 derived from the D7-glucose tracer is replaced by an unlabeled hydrogen derived from water during the reverse isomerization reaction. The action of G6PC2 counteracts the activity of GK, converting G6P to glucose at the rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>. <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>net</sub></italic> is equal to <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>1</sub> − <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>. Black circles represent a carbon bound to deuterium, and white circles represent a carbon with hydrogen bound.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f1.jpg"/></fig><p>Using the glucose concentration and relative isotopomer abundance measurements, GC (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub>) was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="e3"><label>(3)</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745equ3.jpg"/></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="e"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745equ4.jpg"/></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="e___1"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745equ5.jpg"/></disp-formula>In this equation, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> represents the natural logarithm of the ratio of M + 7 glucose abundance (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) to total M + 1 through M + 7 abundance (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), and <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> is the natural logarithm of the glucose concentration (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). The subscripts on <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> represent the time at which each measurement was obtained. Equation 3 was applied to estimate GC by using the measured di-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-isopropylidene glucose MIDs, corrected for natural isotope abundance (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), to calculate the relative abundances <italic toggle="yes">B</italic> (m/z 302–307) and <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> (m/z 308).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Calculation of Positional Enrichment</title><p>The MIDs of six ion fragments, with m/z values of 145, 173, 259, 284, 301, and 370, derived from all three glucose derivatives were compiled into a matrix and compared with theoretical distributions using a custom least squares regression program (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The program was used to estimate the relative abundance of each of the 128 possible hydrogen isotopomers of glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Previous studies (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) validated the positional enrichment methodology using glucose standards.</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A novel stable isotope methodology can be used to assess GC in pancreatic islets. The glucose isotopomers in the media sample are derivatized in three ways. Each derivative is distinct in structure and mass. The derivatives elute at different retention times and produce different ion fragments. The overlapping ion fragments are used to estimate the abundance of each of the possible 2<sup>7</sup> hydrogen isotopomers of glucose using custom integration and least squares (LSQ) regression programs. The changes in mass of the glucose in the medium, specifically the changes in mass at the second carbon position, are used to quantify cycling. Black circles represent a carbon bound to deuterium, and white circles represent a carbon with hydrogen bound. GC-MS, gas chromatography–mass spectrometry.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>Data were analyzed using a two-tailed Student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, with two samples assuming equal variance. The level of significance is indicated in the figure legends.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s12"><title>Results</title><sec id="s13"><title>Quantification of GC in WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO Islets Isolated From Chow-Fed Mice</title><p>During incubations with isolated islets, lower mass isotopomers of glucose would be expected to accumulate in the culture medium if a D7-glucose tracer is converted to D7-G6P through the action of glucokinase but is then converted back to D6-glucose through the action of G6pc2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). To address this hypothesis, we incubated WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets, which were isolated from chow-fed (CF) mice, in the presence of 5 mmol/L D7-glucose, and measured the MIDs of medium glucose samples collected at 24 and 72 h. We first examined the MIDs obtained from integrating the glucose 1,2,5,6-di-isopropylidene propionate derivative peak, which preserves all seven carbon-bound hydrogen atoms from the parent glucose molecule. After correcting for natural isotope abundance, we summed the relative abundances of the lower mass isotopomers from m/z values of 302 (M + 1) to 307 (M + 6) and normalized them to the total labeled glucose signal from M + 1 to M + 7. The results show a significant accumulation of total M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers in the incubation media from WT islets but no increase in the media from KO islets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>GC in WT or <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets isolated from CF mice and incubated in 5 mmol/L D7-glucose. <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>: The average relative abundance of lower mass isotopomers (M + 1 to M + 6) of the 1,2,5,6-di-isopropylidene propionate derivative fragment in the media from WT (black squares) or KO (white circles) islet incubations at 24 and 72 h. The relative abundances are corrected for natural stable isotope labeling (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) and normalized to the total labeled glucose signal from M + 1 to M + 7. The average relative abundance of the 24-h KO samples was subtracted from baseline values to correct for the isotopic purity of the D7-glucose tracer. In all experiments where tracer control samples were analyzed, the MID of the 24-h KO samples was nearly identical to the MID of the pure D7-glucose tracer (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>). <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>: The average estimated abundance ± SEM of the [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose isotopomer with deuterium loss at C2 in the media from WT (black bar) or KO (white bar; all experiments reported zero abundance) islet incubations at 72 h. <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>: Average GC ± SEM, reported as a percentage of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub>. WT islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4; WT islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4; KO islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4; KO islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4 incubations of 100 islets. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. WT islets. hr, hours.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f3.jpg"/></fig><p>Next, we examined the positional <sup>2</sup>H enrichment. Our model suggests that cycling of D7-glucose should result in accumulation of a specific M + 6 mass isotopomer of glucose with deuterium replaced by hydrogen at the C2 position (i.e., [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose). Least squares regression analysis using mass isotopomer data obtained from three glucose derivatives (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) enabled us to calculate the <sup>2</sup>H enrichment at each carbon position of glucose in the culture media. This calculation confirmed that the loss of deuterium at the C2 position of glucose from the fully labeled D7-glucose tracer accounted for the majority of the lower mass isotopomers that were formed in the media from WT islet incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Accumulation of the [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose mass isotopomer was not observed in the media from KO islet incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>).</p><p>Finally, using equations described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2"><sc>research design and methods</sc></xref>, with derivations provided in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Material</ext-link>, we calculated <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></ext-link>) and found that WT islets exhibited cycling rates that were ∼16% of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>). This is much higher than the 3% rate of GC previously reported by Khan et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), who used a radiotracer method to quantify GC in islets isolated from CF mice and incubated in 5.5 mmol/L glucose. In contrast, GC in KO islets was negligible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>). Taken together, these findings are consistent with our hypothesis that G6PC2 acts by hydrolyzing G6P, thereby opposing the action of glucokinase.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of GC and uptake among experimental groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Diet</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Glucose concentration&#x2028;(mmol/L)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> (pmol/islet/h)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (pmol/islet/h)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (%)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">WT</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7 ± 0.4 (4)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.3 (4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 ± 1 (4)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 ± 3 (4)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 ± 4 (4)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 ± 2 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 ± 0.1 (5)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1 ± 0.3 (5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 ± 2 (5)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 ± 3 (5)<sup>A</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 ± 3 (5)<sup>A/B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 ± 2 (5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 ± 1 (5)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 ± 0.3 (4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 ± 4 (5)<sup>A/B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 ± 5 (4)<sup>A/B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 ± 6 (5)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 ± 1 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HFF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 ± 1 (7)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 ± 0.4 (7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 ± 8 (7)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 ± 9 (7)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 ± 5 (7)<sup>B</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 ± 1 (7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Rate of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub>, and <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> results are reported as the mean ± SEM (number of incubations). In each column, groups were compared by ANOVA. If at least one mean value was significantly different, pairwise comparisons were performed by Tukey-Kramer test. Statistically separated groups are indicated by different letters (A and B).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Quantification of GC in WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO Islets Isolated From High Fat–Fed Mice</title><p>Both WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice fed a high-fat diet (i.e., high fat–fed [HFF] mice) have a ∼100 mg/dL elevation in FBG levels, though, as in CF mice, FBG levels remain ∼20 mg/dL lower in <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice compared with WT mice (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Based on this observation, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> would be similar in CF and HFF mouse islets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>). To address this hypothesis, we applied our stable isotope method to islets isolated from HFF mice.</p><p>Consistent with our model for the action of G6PC2 on GC, M + 1 to M + 6 glucose isotopomers accumulated in the media between 24 and 72 h in WT islet incubations only (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>). Further validation of the cycling model was provided by the positional <sup>2</sup>H enrichment results, which showed that the relative abundance of the [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose isotopomer with deuterium loss at the second carbon was greater in the WT islet incubations compared with the KO islet incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). We again calculated the rate of GC relative to <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub>. As expected, and consistent with the similar accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers observed in the HFF incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>), <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> was nearly identical between CF and HFF islets in 5 mmol/L glucose (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></ext-link>) and GC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>) were not statistically different between CF and HFF islets. As in CF islets, GC was completely abolished in KO islets from HFF mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>GC in WT or <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets isolated from HFF mice and incubated in 5 mmol/L D7-glucose. The same data are shown as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> but using islets obtained from HFF mice. WT islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5; WT islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5; KO islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5; KO islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5 incubations of 100 islets. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. WT islets. hr, hours.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Quantification of the Influence of Extracellular Glucose Concentration on GC in WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO Islets</title><p>An analysis of insulin secretion from perfused WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mouse pancreata suggests a parallel shift in the dose-response curve for GSIS to the left in the KO pancreata when glucose increased from 5 to 11 mmol/L (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). This parallel shift is indicative of a fixed <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>, since the rate of glucose phosphorylation by glucokinase (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>1</sub>) should be the same in both WT and KO pancreata at the same glucose concentration, with the difference in GSIS between the two curves being solely attributable to <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>). This situation could arise if either the transport of G6P into the ER lumen or the hydrolysis of G6P to glucose by G6pc2 was operating at <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>max</sub>, with the latter being supported by enzymatic studies (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Based on this observation, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> would be similar at 5 and 11 mmol/L, and that <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub><italic toggle="yes">/v</italic><sub>net</sub> would be reduced in response to the expected increase in <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> at elevated glucose concentrations. To address this hypothesis, GC was assessed at 11 mmol/L glucose using islets isolated from CF and HFF mice.</p><p>If <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub> was similar in the 5 and 11 mmol/L incubations, as hypothesized, the accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers of glucose in the medium would be similar. However, a significant increase in the accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers, consistent with an increase in <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>, was observed in CF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>) and HFF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>) islets. Even at the early 24-h time point, the accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers in the media is significant in CF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>) and HFF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref>) WT incubations, while the abundance of M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers in KO incubations does not change from the baseline. The accumulated M + 1 to M + 6 isotopomers in the WT media contain a significant abundance of the model-predicted [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose isotopomer with deuterium loss at the second carbon position, while this isotopomer is not present in the KO incubations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6<italic toggle="yes">B</italic></xref>). Unexpectedly, both CF and HFF WT islets exhibited increased cycling, relative to CF islets in 5 mmol/L glucose, driven by the significant increase in <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>, with rates quantified as ∼35–40% of net uptake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>). Once again, the cycling in KO islets was negligible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6<italic toggle="yes">C</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>GC in WT or G6pc2 KO islets isolated from CF mice and incubated in 11 mmol/L D7-glucose. The same data are shown as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> but using islets incubated in 11 mmol/L D7-glucose. WT islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5; WT islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5; KO islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4; KO islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4 incubations of 100 islets. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. WT islets. hr, hours.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f5.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>GC in WT or <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets isolated from HFF mice and incubated in 11 mmol/L D7-glucose. The same data are shown as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> but using islets obtained from HFF mice and incubated at 11 mmol/L glucose. WT islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7; WT islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7; KO islets at 24 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7; KO islets at 72 h, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7 incubations of 100 islets. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. WT islets. hr, hours.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="db140745f6.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s16"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study describes a novel method for quantifying GC in isolated pancreatic islets that is based on the use of a stable D7-glucose tracer and the model presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. We applied this method to islets isolated from WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice to investigate the role of G6pc2 in GC. In all WT islet incubations, a significant accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 glucose isotopomers was observed over 72 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), and a specific, model-predicted D6-glucose isotopomer, [1,3,4,5,6,6-<sup>2</sup>H<sub>6</sub>]glucose, accounted for most of the cycled glucose, as determined by a custom least squares regression algorithm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). GC in WT islets varied with the assay conditions and was estimated to be 16–40% of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets took up glucose from the media at rates similar to those of WT islets (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>), but no accumulation of M + 1 to M + 6 glucose isotopomers was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), and GC was negligible (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). These observations are consistent with our hypothesis that G6PC2 controls GC by opposing the action of glucokinase, thereby regulating glycolytic flux, and ultimately GSIS. In this manner, G6PC2 may play an important role in the regulation of FBG levels, a hypothesis supported by GWAS data linking <italic toggle="yes">G6CP2</italic> to FBG in humans (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).</p><p>WT islets isolated from CF mice and incubated in 5 mmol/L glucose cycled at a rate that was ∼16% of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Previous studies (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) using tritiated water quantified GC in isolated islets by measuring <sup>3</sup>H incorporation at carbon 2 of derivatized glucose. This method was not sensitive enough to quantify cycling in 3-h, 5.5 mmol/L glucose incubations using islets isolated from lean WT mice but, based on the extrapolation of data derived from <italic toggle="yes">ob/ob</italic> mouse islets, was used to estimate WT cycling rates at 3–4% of total uptake (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). While our novel method for measuring GC using stable isotopes requires longer incubation times, the simplicity and sensitivity are distinct advantages. Both the tritiated water method (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and our method for measuring GC rely on the assumption that G6P and fructose-6-phosphate are in a rapid and complete equilibrium. However, hydrogen isotopes alter the kinetics of the phosphoglucoisomerase (PGI) reaction such that equilibrium may not be complete. Nevertheless, previous work (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) suggests that the kinetic isotope effect of tritium reduces the <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>max</sub> of the PGI reaction more than deuterium, which potentially makes our stable isotope method more accurate in applying this assumption. We expect that the rates of other reactions in our model, including the reactions catalyzed by glucokinase (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>1</sub>) and G6pc2 (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>2</sub>), would be minimally affected by the presence of either <sup>2</sup>H or <sup>3</sup>H tracers because they do not involve hydrogen transfer. Both methods account only for G6P molecules that are completely cycled out of the cell and subsequently accumulate in the culture medium. Therefore, the calculated rates of GC will underestimate the true cycling rate catalyzed by G6pc2 if some of the resulting glucose molecules are redirected toward an alternative intracellular fate and do not reappear in the extracellular medium.</p><p>To investigate the effect of diet on GC, islets were isolated from HFF mice. Similar increased rates of G6P hydrolysis were observed in CF and HFF islets when glucose was increased from 5 to 11 mmol/L glucose (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which is consistent with our previous observation that the difference in FBG levels between WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice is similar in mice receiving both diets, despite elevated FBG levels in the HFF groups (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Interestingly, previous studies (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) reported a significant increase in GC in islets isolated from obese <italic toggle="yes">ob/ob</italic> mice relative to WT mice. Kahn and Efendic (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) showed that this increase was not due to hyperglycemia, which is characteristic of <italic toggle="yes">ob/ob</italic> mice. However, whether hyperlipidemia or the absence of leptin signaling influences GC in <italic toggle="yes">ob/ob</italic> mice is unclear. Furthermore, the magnitude of this previously reported enhancement of GC in <italic toggle="yes">ob/ob</italic> mouse islets could, in part, be due to the underestimation of cycling in lean WT mice.</p><p>Our method requires 72-h islet incubations in order to enrich the medium in lower mass isotopomers of glucose for quantification. Over this time period in nonphysiological conditions, the data suggest that the islets are losing some of their in vivo characteristics. <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice have a significantly lower FBG level than their WT littermates (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), and, consistent with this finding, isolated KO islets exhibited increased glycolytic flux (data not shown) and insulin secretion (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) in short-term assays. However, after 72 h in culture, insulin secretion between the WT and KO islets normalizes such that the concentration of insulin in the medium is not significantly different between WT and KO islets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 3</ext-link>). In addition, the estimated <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub>net</sub> between 24 and 72 h in WT and <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets is equivalent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>). While these glucose uptake data are consistent with the insulin secretion data (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 3</ext-link>), the acute insulin secretion assays predict increased glucose uptake in <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO islets relative to WT islets. Similarly, a surprising elevation in the rate of G6P hydrolysis was observed in CF and HFF islets incubated in 11 mmol/L glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6<italic toggle="yes">A</italic></xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). This observation is at odds with perfused pancreas data showing a parallel, leftward shift in the dose-response curve for GSIS in CF <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> KO mice (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In combination, these observations suggest that the islets are undergoing adaptation during the long assay incubation. We hypothesize that the KO islets adapt to the absence of G6pc2 by reducing glucose uptake, which would make biological sense in that elevated glucose metabolism has been shown to be toxic to β-cells (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). We also hypothesize that the ability of glucose to stimulate <italic toggle="yes">G6pc2</italic> expression (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) may explain the increase in <italic toggle="yes">v<sub>2</sub></italic>. This induction would not have been a factor in short-term insulin secretion experiments, given their short time course. Addressing these hypotheses and the molecular mechanisms behind islet adaptation to prolonged culture are clearly of interest and will be the subject of future experiments. Given these apparent effects of the long incubation time and any limitation in gas exchange in the 96-well plates used for the assay, future work will focus on using microfluidic devices specifically designed for islet culture (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), allowing the media volume, and thus the time in culture, to be reduced. Such experiments would also reveal whether the significant increase in glucose uptake at 11 mmol/L in HFF islets, but not in CF islets (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), is also an artifact of the long incubation times.</p><p>In conclusion, the data presented in this study suggest that GC in WT islets is greater than previously reported and that G6pc2 is responsible for this cycling. These findings are consistent with the GWAS linking <italic toggle="yes">G6PC2</italic> to the regulation of FBG levels (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains Supplementary Data online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1">http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db14-0745/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Article Information</title><p><bold>Acknowledgments.</bold> The authors thank P. Jacobson (Abbott Pharmaceuticals) for assistance with the initiation of this project. The authors also thank M. Brissova and A. Coldren (Vanderbilt University) for performing islet isolations.</p><p><bold>Funding.</bold> Research in the laboratory of R.M.O. was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant <award-id rid="sp1">DK-92589</award-id>. Research in the laboratory of J.D.Y. was supported by National Science Foundation grant CBET <award-id rid="sp2">0955251</award-id>. The Vanderbilt Islet Procurement and Analysis Core is supported by NIH grant <award-id rid="sp1">P60-DK-20593</award-id> to the Vanderbilt Diabetes Research Training Center and NIH grant <award-id rid="sp1">DK-59637</award-id> to the Vanderbilt Mouse Metabolic Phenotyping Center. M.L.W. and L.D.P. were both supported by Vanderbilt Molecular Endocrinology Training Program grant 5T32 <award-id rid="sp1">DK07563</award-id>.</p><p><bold>Duality of Interest.</bold> No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p><p><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> M.L.W. took the primary lead on glucose cycling studies and helped to write the manuscript. L.D.P. and I.T. helped to perform some of the glucose cycling experiments. R.M.O. and J.D.Y. helped to perform some of the glucose cycling experiments and write the manuscript. J.D.Y. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p><bold>Prior Presentation.</bold> Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 74th Scientific Sessions of the American Diabetes Association, San Francisco, CA, 13–17 June 2014.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mithieux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New knowledge regarding glucose-6 phosphatase gene and protein and their roles in the regulation of glucose metabolism</article-title>. <source>Eur J Endocrinol</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9116905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1530/eje.0.1360137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordlie</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucose-6-phosphatase structure, regulation, and function: an update</article-title>. <source>Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>215</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9270716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3181/00379727-215-44142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Werve</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newgard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Méchin</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berteloot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New lessons in the regulation of glucose metabolism taught by the glucose 6-phosphatase system</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>267</volume>:<fpage>1533</fpage>–<lpage>1549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1432-1327.2000.01160.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaftingen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The glucose-6-phosphatase system</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11879177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/0264-6021:3620513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1222414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit gene family</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>284</volume>:<fpage>29241</fpage>–<lpage>29245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19700406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.R109.025544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2785553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeser</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svitek</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and characterization of a human cDNA and gene encoding a ubiquitously expressed glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein</article-title>. <source>J Mol Endocrinol</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1677/jme.0.0290205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boustead</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeser</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and characterization of a cDNA and the gene encoding the mouse ubiquitously expressed glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein</article-title>. <source>J Mol Endocrinol</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1677/jme.0.0320033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yiu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impaired neutrophil activity and increased susceptibility to bacterial infection in mice lacking glucose-6-phosphatase-beta</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17318259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI30443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1797608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boztug</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Appaswamy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashikov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A syndrome with congenital neutropenia and mutations in G6PC3</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>360</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa0805051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2778311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steegers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular cloning of a pancreatic islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10078553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.48.3.531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bischof</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cloning and characterization of the human and rat islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein (IGRP) genes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>25197</fpage>–<lpage>25207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11297555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M101549200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Moving on from GWAS: functional studies on the G6PC2 gene implicated in the regulation of fasting blood glucose</article-title>. <source>Curr Diab Rep</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>768</fpage>–<lpage>777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24142592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11892-013-0422-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4041587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of the beta cell antigen targeted by a prevalent population of pathogenic CD8+ T cells in autoimmune diabetes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>8384</fpage>–<lpage>8388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0932778100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC166238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amrani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of diabetes by manipulation of anti-IGRP autoimmunity: high efficiency of a low-affinity peptide</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15908957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm1250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee-Chan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of CD4+ T cell-specific epitopes of islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein: a novel beta cell autoantigen in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>5306</fpage>–<lpage>5315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15843527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.174.9.5306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danke</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein-reactive CD4+ T cells in human subjects</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>2781</fpage>–<lpage>2789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16493034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.176.5.2781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarchum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trucco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santamaria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiLorenzo</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of novel IGRP epitopes targeted in type 1 diabetes patients</article-title>. <source>Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18358785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clim.2008.01.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2430381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perales</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malaisse</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hexose metabolism in pancreatic islets: the glucose-6-phosphatase riddle</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1849230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00238439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Najafi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grodberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matschinsky</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measurement and modeling of glucose-6-phosphatase in pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>272</volume>:<fpage>E696</fpage>–<lpage>E711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9142893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpendo.1997.272.4.E696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandramouli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostenson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Löw</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efendić</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucose cycling in islets from healthy and diabetic rats</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2180757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diab.39.4.456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laybutt</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glandt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Critical reduction in beta-cell mass results in two distinct outcomes over time. Adaptation with impaired glucose tolerance or decompensated diabetes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>2997</fpage>–<lpage>3005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12438314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M210581200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sturis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DePaoli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of beta-cell dysfunction in the male Zucker diabetic fatty rat</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1447</fpage>–<lpage>1457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diab.44.12.1447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Randle</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucose-6-phosphatase activity of mouse pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1968</year>;<volume>219</volume>:<fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4299799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/219857a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandramouli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostenson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence for the presence of glucose cycling in pancreatic islets of the ob/ob mouse</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1989</year>;<volume>264</volume>:<fpage>9732</fpage>–<lpage>9733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2656710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandramouli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostenson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of glucose cycling and the extent of equilibration of glucose 6-phosphate with fructose 6-phosphate in islets from ob/ob mice</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1898326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/bj2780353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1151348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pound</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeser</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>G6PC2: a negative regulator of basal glucose-stimulated insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>1547</fpage>–<lpage>1556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23274894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/db12-1067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3636628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeser</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Deletion of the gene encoding the islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase catalytic subunit-related protein autoantigen results in a mild metabolic phenotype</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>774</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17265032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-006-0564-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouatia-Naji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocheleau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Lommel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A polymorphism within the G6PC2 gene is associated with fasting plasma glucose levels</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>320</volume>:<fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18451265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1156849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erdos</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Variations in the G6PC2/ABCB11 genomic region are associated with fasting glucose levels</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>2620</fpage>–<lpage>2628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18521185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI34566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2398737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matschinsky</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Banting Lecture 1995. A lesson in metabolic regulation inspired by the glucokinase glucose sensor paradigm</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8549869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diab.45.2.223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iynedjian</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular physiology of mammalian glucokinase</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18726182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-008-8322-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2780631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrolonis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tummino</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Enzymatic characterization of the pancreatic islet-specific glucose-6-phosphatase-related protein (IGRP)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>13976</fpage>–<lpage>13983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14722102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M307756200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniewicz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephanopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring deuterium enrichment of glucose hydrogen atoms by gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>3211</fpage>–<lpage>3216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21413777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ac200012p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3562696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniewicz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephanopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accurate assessment of amino acid mass isotopomer distributions for metabolic flux analysis</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>7554</fpage>–<lpage>7559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17822305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ac0708893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Des Rosiers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Previs</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunengraber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Correction of 13C mass isotopomer distributions for natural stable isotope abundance</article-title>. <source>J Mass Spectrom</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8799277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9888(199603)31:3&lt;255::AID-JMS290&gt;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandramouli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostenson</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/>. <article-title>Glucose cycling is markedly enhanced in pancreatic islets of obese hyperglycemic mice</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>2413</fpage>–<lpage>2416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2184016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/endo-126-5-2413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouatia-Naji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnefond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baerenwald</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic and functional assessment of the role of the rs13431652-A and rs573225-A alleles in the G6PC2 promoter that are strongly associated with elevated fasting glucose levels</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>2662</fpage>–<lpage>2671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20622168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/db10-0389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3279535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malaisse</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malaisse-Lagae</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liemans</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ottinger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willem</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phosphoglucoisomerase-catalyzed interconversion of hexose phosphates: isotopic discrimination between hydrogen and deuterium</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2345541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00226187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efendic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence that increased glucose cycling in islets of diabetic ob/ob mice is a primary feature of the disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>E623</fpage>–<lpage>E626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7485473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpendo.1995.269.4.E623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narangoda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sundler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efendic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term leptin treatment of ob/ob mice improves glucose-induced insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>–<lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11439295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.ijo.0801628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tornovsky-Babaey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furth-Lavi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Glucose metabolism: key endogenous regulator of β-cell replication and survival</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Obes Metab</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 3</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22928570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1463-1326.2012.01646.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Easley</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocheleau</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piston</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative measurement of zinc secretion from pancreatic islets with high temporal resolution using droplet-based microfluidics</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>9086</fpage>–<lpage>9095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19874061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/ac9017692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2771320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocheleau</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGuinness</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piston</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microfluidic glucose stimulation reveals limited coordination of intracellular Ca2+ activity oscillations in pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>12899</fpage>–<lpage>12903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15317941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0405149101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC516492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>