
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4412563.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4412563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4412563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919745</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-30574</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and Molecular Identification of Nematode and Dipteran Parasites in an Australian Alpine Grasshopper (<italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic>)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Alpine Grasshopper Parasites</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names initials="KDL">Kate D. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byatt</surname><given-names initials="LJ">Lachlan J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names initials="NJ">Nichola J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolini</surname><given-names initials="RJ">Remo J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hose</surname><given-names initials="GC">Grant C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herberstein</surname><given-names initials="ME">Marie E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname><given-names initials="ML">Michelle L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Macquarie University, North Ryde, New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>School of Biological Sciences, University of Wollongong, Wollongong, New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Centre for Evolutionary Biology, School of Animal Biology, University of Western Australia, Crawley, Western Australia, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>School of Science and Health, University of Western Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names initials="RNC">Raul Narciso Carvalho</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Federal University of Viçosa, BRAZIL</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KU LB NH RB GH MH MP. Performed the experiments: KU LB NH MP. Analyzed the data: KU GH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KU MP. Wrote the paper: KU MP MH GH.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>kate_umbers@uow.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">251292</issue-id><elocation-id>e0121685</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-30 11:25:20.407"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Umbers et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Umbers et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0121685.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0121685.pdf"/><abstract><p>In alpine Australia, Orthoptera are abundant, dominant herbivores, important prey species, and hosts for parasites and parasitoids. Despite the central role of orthopterans in alpine ecosystems, the impact of parasites on orthopteran populations is under-explored. In this study we describe the relationship between parasite prevalence and host sex, body size and year of collection. We accessed an existing, preserved collection of 640 <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic> collected from across its range between 2007 and 2011. Upon dissection we collected juvenile parasites and used molecular tools to identify them to three families (Nematoda; Mermithidae, and Arthropoda: Diptera: Tachinidae and Sarcophagidae). The prevalence of nematodes ranged from 3.5% to 25.0% and dipterans from 2.4% to 20.0%. Contrary to predictions, we found no associations between parasite prevalence and grasshopper sex or size. Although there was an association between prevalence of both nematodes and dipterans with year of collection, this is likely driven by a small sample size in the first year. Our results provide a foundation for future studies into parasite prevalence within the alpine environment and the abiotic factors that might influence these associations.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This project was funded by the Australia &amp; Pacific Science Foundation, Macquarie University and the Australian Biological Resources Study. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="11"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Parasites are ubiquitous and can have profound impacts on host immunology, morphology, behavior and fitness. Host-parasite interactions built on single-host and single-parasite systems under laboratory conditions are becoming well understood, [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] but data on the impacts of parasite infection on host fitness in the field are scarce. A major obstacle in understanding the interactions between parasites and their hosts is the lack of basic knowledge of the prevalence and diversity of parasites. This is particularly true for Australia and crucial for understanding threatened ecosystems such as the Australian alpine region.</p><p>Many alpine insect species are highly abundant throughout the summer and occur in high densities in resource rich areas [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Such distributions can enhance parasite transmission due to increased contact with infected individuals [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and greater susceptibility to infection arising from the elevated stress of living under crowded conditions [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. For example, monarch butterflies (<italic toggle="yes">Danaus plexippus</italic>) reared at high densities have elevated stress responses and greater susceptibility to parasitism than those in low-density populations [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Given that alpine environments are not only harsh but stochastic, it is common that conditions vary greatly from year to year [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The combination of high population densities and non-trivial environmental stressors may facilitate the increased parasitism reported in a range of alpine insects [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Orthoptera are well-known as parasite vectors [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and there is some evidence to expect that host sex and size are related to prevalence. Zuk and McKean [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] summarise the relationship between parasite susceptibility in males and testosterone indicating that across taxa so far studied males have a higher susceptibility to parasites and carry higher parasite loads. For example, Miura and Ohsaki [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] showed that host-parasite interactions may be driving sexual size dimorphism in a Japanese catantopine grasshopper where larger females have fewer parasites.</p><p>Australia’s alpine region harbors a rich assemblage of grasshoppers [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and toward the end of Summer and into Autumn these dominant herbivores are very common. During their seasonal peak (March to May) and above 1500 m altitude <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic> (Acrididae: Oxyinae) is found in high density across its range and exhibits unusual attributes for a grasshopper such as fierce fighting in males [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and temperature-dependent colour change [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In laboratory colonies, adult <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> expelled unidentified worm-like parasites, larvae and pupae and these observations prompted this study. Thus, we investigated parasites of <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> to quantify and qualify infection in this dominant alpine species. Specifically, we aimed to: (1) identify parasites using molecular tools, (2) examine variation in parasite prevalence associated with year, sex and body.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Collection and dissection</title><p>Between 2007 and 2011 we established a preserved collection of <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> (n = 640) for genetic studies. Grasshoppers were collected in Kosciuszko National Park, NSW, Australia along Dead Horse Gap Walking Track and Merritt’s Nature Trail out of Thredbo Village (36°30′S 148°18′E) and the ‘Blue Calf T-Bar’ out of Guthega Village (36°23′S 148°22′E) (NSW National Parks and Wildlife Scientific License S12256). These three collection sites harbor members of a single interbreeding population [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Grasshoppers were caught by hand and identified using a field key [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and via the presence of a conical prosternal process [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Sex was determined by gross morphology, genitalia and colouration. Grasshoppers were cooled over night in a refrigerator and then stored in 70% ethanol for transport to Macquarie University by car.</p><p>Prior to dissection and as a proxy for body size, the dorsal midline of the pronotum (representing the narrowest length) was measured the using digital calipers (0–150 mm, Sontax Australia, Perth, Australia). Grasshoppers were then bisected along the medial line of the venter and the exoskeleton splayed to reveal the internal abdomen, thorax and head. Samples were systematically searched for parasites (Nematoda and Diptera). Dissections were performed using a stereo microscope (Olympus SZ40, Olympus, Japan), parasites were preserved in 70% EtOH until DNA extraction and remaining grasshopper parts useful for DNA extraction were returned to 70% EtOH.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Molecular identification of parasites</title><p>Parasite identification was confirmed by sequencing the 18S rDNA. Total DNA was extracted from a midsection of nematodes (1 cm sample sectioned aseptically with scalpel blade) and whole or half dipteran larvae using the Qiagen DNeasy tissue kit (Qiagen Australia). The manufacturers recommended protocol for DNA extraction from insect material was followed and included the following minor modifications. Samples were ground using a micropestle in a 1.5 mL Eppendorf tube before and after proteinaseK digestion, and an additional wash step was included during precipitation. Amplification of the 18S rDNA locus was initially achieved using the universal eukaryotic primers EukF- AACCTGGTTGATCCTGCCAG and EukR- CCTTCTGCAGGTTCACCTAC to obtain full-length 18S rDNA sequences for representative samples (DeLong 1992). Sequences generated from EukF and EukR amplicons were then used to develop taxa specific primers for subsequent analyses of all samples using a hemi-nested design. For screening nematode samples the secondary reaction included the primers EukF and nem595R- CGAAAAATCAACTACGGGCG, and the secondary primers for dipteran amplification were EukF and tach693R —ACCGGTAATACGCTTRCATACA. All reactions were performed using GoTaq Green Master Mix (Promega, Madison, USA) with the cycling conditions for EukF and EukR encompassing an initial denaturation of 3 min at 94°C; 35 cycles at 94°C for 30 s, 56°C for 30 s and 72° C for 2 min; and a final extension step at 72°C for 5 min. For secondary reactions the annealing temperature was increased to 60°C and primary product (1 μL) was used as DNA template.</p><p>Reactions were performed in an Eppendorf Mastercycler (Eppendorf, North Ryde, Australia). Amplicons were visualized by agarose gel electrophoresis (2% <italic toggle="yes">w/v</italic>) in TBE (TRIS, boric acid, EDTA; pH 8) with SYBR safe staining (Invitrogen, Mulgrave, Australia). Amplicon size was approximated against a HyperLadderII DNA marker (Bioline, Sydney, Australia). Amplicons were purified using the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen, Melbourne, Australia) and sequenced in the forward and reverse directions. Sequencing was performed on a 3130x1 genetic analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California) using the BigDye terminator kit (Applied Biosystems) and the standard run protocol for a 50 cm, 16 capillary array.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Sequencing and Phylogenetic analyses</title><p>Sequences of 18S rDNA were manually checked for read error and then assembled into optimized contigs using <sc>Geneious</sc> (version 5.5.6, Bioinformatics software Biomatters Ltd, New Zealand). Contigs covered 1409 and 655 nucleotides for the Nematoda and Diptera isolates, respectively. A BlastN search (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.gov">www.ncbi.gov</ext-link>) including only sequences with &gt;95% query coverage was performed to assign contigs to the lowest resolution taxonomic group. Sequences generated from this study were supplemented with publicly available sequences representing major lineages of Nematoda and Diptera (accession numbers given in <xref rid="pone.0121685.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A &amp; 1B</xref>) and aligned using ClustalW with default parameters [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The nucleotide sequences identified in this study were submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="JQ894729">JQ894729</ext-link>—<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="JQ894732">JQ894732</ext-link>).</p><fig id="pone.0121685.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121685.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic trees of the 18s rDNA gene analysed using Bayesian inference (BEAST) places the Nematoda isolates within the family Mermithidae and the Diptera isolates within two families, the Tachinidae and Sarcophagidae.</title><p>
<bold>Isolates from this study are indicated by a black circle (●).</bold> The Diptera tree (A) included 48 sequences and a total of 646 nucleotide positions. The Nematoda tree (B) included 46 sequences and a total of 1644 nucleotide positions. Posterior probabilities indicate statistical support at each branch node and are colour coded according to level of support (1: high, 0:low)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0121685.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Phylogenetic analysis was performed using Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo method implemented in BEAST v1.8.0 [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. For all analyses the random local molecular clock and the General Time Reversible substitution model accounting for estimates of invariable sites (I) and the gamma distribution parameter (G) were used. The analysis was conducted using a Bayesian skyride coalescent tree prior. We performed two independent analyses of 20 million generations that were combined after appropriate burnin (~10%) to produce 10,000 trees. Branch placement within the phylogenetic tree was used to assign isolates from this study to family level.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Correlates of parasite prevalence in Kosciuscola tristis</title><p>We tested whether prevalence of infection varied according to host sex, host body size, year of collection and stage of development. Of the 640 grasshoppers dissected, 103 were subadult and as such we could not confidently determine their sex. Thus, for our analysis of the effect of sex on prevalence we excluded subadult animals and used 385 male and 152 female adults (total n = 537). We used a Generalized Linear Model (link function = logit) with binomial error structure. Analyses were performed using the GLM function in the stats module of R version 2.14.0 (R Core Development Team 2011). Presence of parasite was the dependent variable with host sex, host body size, year of collection and stage of development as independent variables each tested separately. Analyses of Deviance were based on the chi-square test. We analyzed nematode and dipteran infection separately.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec007"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec008"><title>Molecular identification of parasites</title><p>We successfully amplified the 18S region for all 50 nematodes. For the 64 putative dipteran larvae collected, 50 18S sequences (from 49 grasshopper hosts) were confirmed Diptera, the remaining 14 were either host tissue mistaken for small larvae (4 samples) or failed extractions or amplifications likely due to extremely small amounts of starting tissue in those samples. A BlastN search of these isolates showed &gt; 95% sequence similarity to either Nematoda or Diptera genera. Representative sequences of Nematoda; MQ26 and MQ94 and Diptera; MQ127 and MQ132 were selected for phylogenetic analyses. Bayesian analysis placed the two Nematoda isolates (MQ26 and MQ94) within the Mermithidae family (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>). Nematoda samples clustered into two genetically distinct clades with 93.2% pairwise identity to each other. Both isolates showed highest identity (MQ26: 93.25%; MQ94: 96.00%) with <italic toggle="yes">Mermithidae</italic> sp. isolate JH-2004 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY284743">AY284743</ext-link>). Previous morphological studies suggest <italic toggle="yes">Mermithidae</italic> isolates in Australian grasshoppers may be related to <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">quirindeansis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">athysanota</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For the dipteran sequences, Bayesian analysis identified MQ127 as belonging to the Sarcophagidae flesh flies with 100% similarity to <italic toggle="yes">Sarcophaga bullata</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="DQ133067">DQ133067</ext-link>) (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>). In contrast, isolate MQ132 clustered within the Tachinidae (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>), a large and speciose family of parasitoid flies. MQ132 showed highest identity (99.23%) with <italic toggle="yes">Smidtia japonica</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AB699975">AB699975</ext-link>) and <italic toggle="yes">Senometopia cariniforceps</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AB465991">AB465991</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Patterns of parasite prevalence in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic>
</title><p>The prevalence of Nematoda in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> was 7.8% overall and ranged between 3.5% and 25.0% over the five-year study period (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0121685.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). When present, only a single nematode was found in any individual grasshopper. Of the two genetic variants identified by 18S rDNA sequencing, 36 of the 50 infected grasshoppers, were infected with Genus 1 (MQ94) and 14 with Genus 2 (MQ26) (Genus 1–2007: 4, 2008: 7, 2009: 7, 2010: 11, 2011: 7; Genus 2–2007: 2, 2008: 9, 2009: 3, 2010: 0, 2011: 0). There was a significant difference in the prevalence of infection by nematodes between years of collection with a peak in prevalence observed in 2007 (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), however this is most likely an effect of low sample size in 2007 (n = 28) and that these samples were collected at the very end of the season (May) (<xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Pooling all years, we found no significant difference in the prevalence of nematode infection with host size, sex or stage of development (Tables <xref rid="pone.0121685.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> &amp; <xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121685.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121685.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Patterns of parasite presence in <italic toggle="yes">Kosciscola tristis</italic>: (A) Relationship between grasshopper body size and whether or not they were infected.</title><p>(B) Prevalence of Nematoda and Diptera in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> over five years ranged between 3.5% to 21.4%. The overall prevalence of Nematoda and Diptera in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> (n = 640) was 7.8% and 7.7%, respectively, (C) Proportion of males and females infected with Nematoda and Diptera.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0121685.g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0121685.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121685.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Numbers of grasshoppers that were infected with Diptera and/or Nematoda parasites from 2007 to 2011.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0121685.t001g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0121685.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total N <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall Diptera prevalence (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall Nematoda Prevalence (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N females</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female pronotum mm±SD</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N females with Diptera (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N females with Nematoda (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N males</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male pronotum mm±SD</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N males with Diptera (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N males with Nematoda (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N infected subadults (Diptera, Nematoda)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (21)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76±0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (33)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55±0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89±0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66±0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07±0.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56±0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11[<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51±0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72±0.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83±0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42±0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6, 4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>640</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>49 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>50 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>152</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4.61±0.34</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14 (9)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>385</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.58±0.12</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>32 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>32 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11 (3)</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Overall numbers of infected individuals are presented, as well as numbers of females and males infected and their pronotum length (proxy for body size). Final row provides total counts for prevalence and averages for pronotum sizes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0121685.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121685.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Generalized Linear Model results of ecological correlates of infection by dipteran and nematode parasites.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0121685.t002g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0121685.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nematoda infection</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald—χ<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year of collection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.01</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of development</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diptera infection</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald—χ<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.04</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year of collection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&lt;0.01</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of development</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Combined infection</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wald—χ<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host sex</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female host body size</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year of collection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage of development</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The overall prevalence of Diptera ranged between 1.9% and 12.4% from 2007 to 2011, inclusive (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>; <xref rid="pone.0121685.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The majority of Diptera were from Tachinidae, only three individual Sarcophagidae were present. Similarly to Nematoda, there was a significant difference in the prevalence of infection by Diptera in different years (p &lt; 0.01, <xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; Tachinidae—2007: 2, 2008: 21, 2009: 1, 2010: 9, 2011: 14, from 2007 to 2011; Sacrophagidae—2007: 1, 2008: 0, 2009: 0, 2010: 0, 2011: 2; one grasshopper was infected with two Diptera, each of a different family). It seems that individual hosts can be infected with multiple larvae at once. Our initial visual inspection of the presence of Diptera larvae in individual <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> hosts varied between one and three with one larva found in 35 grasshoppers, two larvae in 13 grasshoppers and three larvae in one grasshopper, however, our molecular identification could not confirm this in all but one case where the same host was infected by Diptera from two families. Pooling data across years, there was no significant relationship between prevalence of Diptera infection and size of all grasshoppers, or of males and females separately (<xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There was also no significant difference in the prevalence of Diptera infection between the stage of development however we did see a difference between the sexes where male body size varied with infection but female body size did not (Tables <xref rid="pone.0121685.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> &amp; <xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). When combining Diptera and Nematoda infection we found no relationships between infection and any of the parameters included in the analysis (<xref rid="pone.0121685.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec010"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec011"><title>Molecular approach to parasite identification</title><p>We describe molecular identification of parasites from nematode and dipteran in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic>, an Australian alpine grasshopper. While morphology enables identification to phylum, molecular characterisation of isolates enabled finer-scale classification within phylum (Nematoda) and order (Diptera) to family level namely, Mermithidae, Sarcophagidae and Tachnididae. This is the first molecular analysis of these taxa in the Australian environment. Previous identifications of Mermithidae, Sarcophagidae and Tachindae in insect hosts in Australia have been based on morphological identifications [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The morphological approach can be limiting because characters used to identify both nematodes and dipterans are predominantly found in adult life stages [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. By applying molecular tools we identified juvenile parasite life-stages in preserved host material without having to rear them to final instar [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Parasite prevalence and life history</title><p>The overall prevalence of mermithids (Nematoda) in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> is similar to prevalence reported in other insect hosts [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Belonging to a group of water loving grasshoppers (Oxyinae) [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], the association between <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> and mermithid parasites may not be surprising given the preference of mermithids for moist soil conditions [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The mermithid transmission pathway in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> is not known but may include direct or indirect modes of transmission as in other herbivorous insects [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The effects of mermithids on grasshopper hosts include mortality [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and reduced fecundity [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> we have observed that grasshoppers survive mermithid emergence when held in captivity for days to weeks suggesting that mortality is not at least not an immediate outcome of mermithid emergence. Nevertheless, the presence of a mermithid parasite may impact one or more of several life history traits including, vulnerability to predation, microhabitat choice, fecundity and genital morphology [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</p><p>Phylogenetic inference placed <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic>’ parasitic dipterans in two families: Tachinidae and Sarcophagidae. These families are both known insect parasites and representative species have been identified in other Australian orthopteran hosts (e.g. Morabinae grasshoppers) [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Of the two families of Diptera we identified, the Sarcophagidae were less prevalent (found in three individual grasshoppers) while tachinids were common (found in 47 grasshoppers) (<xref rid="pone.0121685.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Adult tachinids are common in alpine and snowfall regions of Australia and have also been found in approximately half the grasshopper populations studied in New Zealand, USA and Sweden [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. We have observed tachinid pupae emerging from grasshoppers during high-temperature experimental treatments (&gt;35°C) (from which the grasshoppers survived) but we have not systematically collected data on emergence cues. Point of infection and persistence of tachinid larvae in hosts would be of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Characteristics of hosts and parasite prevalence</title><p>The pattern of parasite prevalence in <italic toggle="yes">K</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">tristis</italic> was varied among the three variables we measured for this study (host sex, host body size and year of collection). Although statistical differences are likely driven by a small sample size in 2007, our data show that parasite prevalence fluctuates from year to year but with no clear increase or decline over the five years studied (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Fluctuations in parasite prevalence from 2007 to 2011 may be a result of spatial and temporal heterogeneity of the alpine environment, but further monitoring is required to confirm this.</p><p>We found no relationship between parasite prevalence and host body size for nematodes, but we did for male body size and dipterans (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). This may indicate that the relationship between host size and parasite infection is species specific among Orthoptera. For example, in <italic toggle="yes">Parapodisima tanbaensis</italic> Miura and Ohsaki [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] found that larger females were less likely to be parasitised. However, in two species of grasshopper inhabiting tallgrass prairie, Laws and Joern (2012) showed that larger females were more likely to be infected than smaller females but a relationship between female size variability and parasite prevalence was not evident for an additional seven species studied. Similarly, in our study, grasshopper female body size showed no relationship with infection. Comparative studies across grasshoppers would provide a better perspective for understanding the complexities of host parasite energetics and its impact on body size [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><p>Finally, our data show no clear patterns between host sex and prevalence for either parasite phylum (<xref rid="pone.0121685.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). This was surprising as accounts of male sex-biased parasitism are numerous [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. For example, mate attraction behaviour may drive prevalence differences between the sexes [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] as in the tachinid parasite <italic toggle="yes">Ormia ochracea</italic>, which is attracted to the call of male crickets [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Although some studies have reported sex-biased parasitism in invertebrate hosts [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], our data are consistent with findings that sex biased parasitism in many arthropod hosts is lacking [<xref rid="pone.0121685.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</p><p>The host-parasite system that we describe in this study has an alpine distribution, the host is a superabundant herbivore, an important prey item, and is endemic to the Australian alpine region. The data contributed here enhance our understanding of the ecology of <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola</italic> grasshoppers and their parasites and provide a foundation for examining the field ecology of this interaction.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec014"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121685.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Database</label><caption><title>Table containing data on grasshoppers collected for this study and their parasite load.</title><p>(TXT)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0121685.s001.txt" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank James O’Hanlon for assistance in laboratory and Nikolai Tatarnic, Marlene Zuk, John Rotenbury, Ana Lopez-Llandres, Felicity Evans, Felipe Gawryszewski, Fernando Soley, James O’Hanlon, Natalie Alves, Kerinne Harvey, John Martin, Wade Tozer, Leanne Battams, Michelle Vines, Eliza Middleton, Katy Wilkins, Anja Klingenboek and Hanna Kokko for assisting with field collections. We also acknowledge the assistance of undergraduate students in BIOL316 Invertebrates: Diversity, Evolution and Behaviour for participation in some dissections.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0121685.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khokhlova</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serobyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Degen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <article-title>Krasnov BR Discrimination of host sex by a haematophagous ectoparasite</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2010.10.018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fritts</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lisek</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do gill parasites influence the foraging and antipredator behaviour of rainbow darters, <italic toggle="yes">Etheostoma caeruleum</italic>?</article-title>
<source>Anim Behav</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>817</fpage>–<lpage>823</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2011.07.015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<article-title>Disentangling the influence of parasite genotype, host genotype and maternal environment on different stages of bacterial infection in <italic toggle="yes">Daphnia magna</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>279</volume>: <fpage>3176</fpage>–<lpage>3183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2012.0509</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22593109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3385728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <article-title>Gowler Camden, Roode JC de Patterns of host-parasite adaptation in three populations of monarch butterflies infected with a naturally occurring protozoan disease: virulence, resistance, and tolerance</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>E235</fpage>–<lpage>E248</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/673442</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Wildlife of the Australian snow-country</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Chatswood</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Reed Books</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <article-title>May RM Regulation and stability of host-parasite population interactions: I. Regulatory processes</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>. <year>1978</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3933</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhaus</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crowding as a possible stress factor in insect disease</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>. <year>1958</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1931761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhulipala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oberhauser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crowding and disease: effects of host density on response to infection in a butterfly–parasite interaction</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2311.2009.01107.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sedcole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>A 20-year record of alpine grasshopper abundance, with interpretations for climate change</article-title>. <source>New Zeal J Ecol</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>. <article-title>A preliminary investigation into the host-parasite relationship of an alpine cricket (Orthoptera: Rhaphidophoridae). New Zeal</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedenbrug</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Larval parasitism of spring-dwelling alpine water mites (Hydrachnidia, Acari): a study with particular reference to chironomid hosts</article-title>. <source>Aquat Ecol</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10452-009-9301-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huth-Schwarz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Settele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>RFA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Factors influencing <italic toggle="yes">Nosema bombi</italic> infections in natural populations of <italic toggle="yes">Bombus terrestris</italic> (Hymenoptera: Apidae)</article-title>. <source>J Invertebr Pathol</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2012.02.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22349145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite load, body size, and age of wild-caught male field crickets (Orthoptera: Gryllidae): effects on sexual selection</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>1988</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>969</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2408912</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28581160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baker GL, Rajakulendran SV The influence of soil type and slope on the response to rainfall by nematode parasites of the wingless grasshopper, <italic toggle="yes">Phaulacridium vittatum</italic> (Sjostedt) (Orthoptera: Acrididae). Proceedings and abstracts, Vth International Colloquium on Invertebrate Pathology and Microbial Control, Adelaide, Australia, 1990.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laws</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Density-dependent reductions in grasshopper fecundity in response to nematode parasitism</article-title>. <source>Can Entomol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/n09-027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mongkolkiti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosford</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biological control of the grasshopper <italic toggle="yes">Hesperotettix viridis</italic> pratensis by the Nematode <italic toggle="yes">Mermis nigrescens</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Nematol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19322391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2619906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKean</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>.<article-title>Sex differences in parasite infections: Patterns and processes</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasit</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1024</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(96)80001-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8982783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohsaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mortality effects of the parasitoid flesh fly <italic toggle="yes">Blaesoxipha japonensis</italic> (Diptera: Sarcophagidae) in relation to body size of the adult grasshopper <italic toggle="yes">Parapodisma tanbaensis</italic> (Orthoptera: Catantopidae)</article-title>. <source>Appl Entomol Zool</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13355-013-0236-9</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rentz</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>.<source>Grasshopper Country</source>. <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UNSW Press</publisher-name>
<year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Turn the temperature to turquoise: cues for colour change in the male chameleon grasshopper (<italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic>) (Orthoptera: Acrididae)</article-title>. <source>J Insect Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1198</fpage>–<lpage>1204</lpage>. doi:16/j.jinsphys.2011.05.010. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2011.05.010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21708162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatarnic</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herberstein</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ferocious fighting between male grasshoppers</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49600</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049600</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3498212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herberstein</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Colour in insect thermoregulation: empirical and theoretical tests in the colour-changing grasshopper, <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Ins Phys</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2012.10.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23108152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatarnic</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holwell</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herberstein</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bright turquoise as an intraspecific signal in the chameleon grasshopper (<italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00265-012-1464-7</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Key</surname><given-names>KHL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>. <article-title>A temperature-controlled physiological colour response in the grasshopper, <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic> Sjöst. (Orthoptera: Acrididae)</article-title>. <source>Aust J Zool</source>. <year>1954</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tatarnic</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular phylogeny of the <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola</italic> grasshoppers endemic to the Australian alpine and montane regions</article-title>. <source>Invertebr Syst</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/IS12072</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slatyer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umbers</surname><given-names>KDL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Deep phylogeographic structure and recent differentiation in the flightless alpine grasshopper <italic toggle="yes">Kosciuscola tristis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-014-0204-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4203917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25273226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rehn</surname><given-names>JAG</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The grasshoppers and locusts (Acridoidea) of Australia. Family Acrididae: Subfamily Cyrtacanthacrldinae tribes Oxyini</chapter-title>
<source>Spathosternini. and Praxibulini</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CSIRO</publisher-name>
<year>1957</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2947</fpage>–<lpage>2948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17846036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <article-title>Rambaut A Bayesian Phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7</article-title>.<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1969</fpage>–<lpage>1973</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss075</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22367748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3408070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>GO</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Mermis quirindiensis n</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">sp</italic>. (Nematoda: Mermithidae), a parasite of locusts and grasshoppers (Orthoptera: Acrididae) in south-eastern Australia</article-title>. <source>Revue de Nématologie</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pharma.2014.05.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>GO</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<article-title>Description of the male and redescription of female <italic toggle="yes">Mermis athysanota</italic> Steiner 1921 (Nematoda, Mermithidae)</article-title>. <source>Revue de Nématologie</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pharma.2014.05.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blackith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>A tachinid parasite of Australian grasshoppers</article-title>. <source>Aust J Zool</source>. <year>1967</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>758</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<article-title>Larvae of <italic toggle="yes">Blaesoxipha</italic> Loew (Diptera: Sarcophagidae) and an unidentifiedtachinid (Diptera) parasitic in Acrididae (Orthoptera) in Australia</article-title>. <source>Aust J Entomol</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasitism of overwintering grasshoppers by mermithid nematodes</article-title>. <source>Aust J Entomol</source>. <year>1998</year>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-6055.1998.tb01549.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular barcodes for soil nematode identification</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>–<lpage>850</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1365-294x.2002.01485.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>MDB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hose</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nematode community structure in the brush-tailed rock-wallaby, <italic toggle="yes">Petrogale penicillata</italic>: implications of captive breeding and the translocation of wildlife</article-title>. <source>Exp Parasitol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2012.06.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenwick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> species in macropods</article-title>. <source>Exp Parasitol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>132</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2012.07.003</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Civantos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahnesjö</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forsman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immune function, parasitization and extended phenotypes in colour polymorphic pygmy grasshoppers</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2005.00494.x.</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>. <article-title>First records of mermithid nematodes (Nematoda: Mermithidae) parasitising stick insects (Insecta: Phasmatodea)</article-title>. <source>New Zeal J Zool</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03014220909510137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laws</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variable effects of dipteran parasitoids and management treatment on grasshopper fecundity in a tallgrass prairie</article-title>. <source>Bull Entomol Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007485311000472</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clift</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantification of the relationship between rainfall and parasitism of <italic toggle="yes">Phaulacridium vittatum</italic> (Sjöstedt) by mermithid nematodes in the Central Tablelands of South-Eastern Australia</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thong</surname><given-names>CHS</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Plant and Insect Nematodes</chapter-title>
<source>Nematode parasites of orthopterans</source>. <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<year>1984</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>GOP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>. <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Allomermis solenopsi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda: Mermithidae) parasitising the fire ant <italic toggle="yes">Solenopsi sinvicta</italic> Buren (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in Argentina</article-title>. <source>Syst Parasitol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11230-007-9102-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17912617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Attard</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carreno</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paré</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peregrine</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mermithid nematode infection in a colony of blue-winged grasshoppers (<italic toggle="yes">Tropidacris collaris</italic>)</article-title>. <source>J Zoo Wildl Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>488</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18817018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1638/2007-0179.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of the mermithid parasite Gasteromermis sp. (Nematoda: Mermithidae) on the drift behaviour of its mayfly host, <italic toggle="yes">Baetis bicaudatus</italic> (Ephemeroptera: Baetidae): a trade-off between avoiding predators and locating food</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1907</fpage>–<lpage>1913</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z96-215</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Morphological and behavioural sex reversal in mermithid-infected mayflies</article-title>. <source>P Roy Soc B</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>263</volume>: <fpage>907</fpage>–<lpage>912</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arizono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite-mediated allochthonous input: Do hairworms enhance subsidized predation of stream salmonids on crickets?</article-title>
<source>Can J Zool</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Latham</surname><given-names>ADM</given-names></name>.<article-title>Parasitism and the burrowing depth of the beach hopper <italic toggle="yes">Talorchestia quoyana</italic> (Amphipoda: Talitridae)</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kukal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kevan</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The influence of parasitism on the life history of a high arctic insect, <italic toggle="yes">Gynaephora groenlandica</italic> (Wöcke) (Lepidoptera: Lymantriidae)</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z87-022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hechinger</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<article-title>A metabolic and body-size scaling framework for parasite within-host abundance, biomass, and energy flux</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/670820</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sexual inequalities in Helminth infections: a cost of being a male?</article-title>
<source>Am Nat</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cade</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Senescence in field crickets (Orthoptera; Gryllidae): examining the effects of sex and a sex-biased parasitoid</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z99-191</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cade</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Acoustically orienting parasitoids: fly phonotaxis to cricket song</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1975</year>;<volume>190</volume>: <fpage>1312</fpage>–<lpage>1313</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.190.4221.1312</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wedekind</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Male-biased susceptibility to Helminth infection: an experimental test with a copepod</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>. <year>1998</year>
<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3546767</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Léonard</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasitism of damselflies (<italic toggle="yes">Enallagma boreale</italic>) by gregarines: sex biases and relations to adult survivorship</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z01-213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121685.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>LAD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sex differences in parasitic infections among arthropod hosts: is there a male bias?</article-title>
<source>Oikos</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2000.880211.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>