
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4412711.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4412711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4412711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-44547</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular Phylogeny Reveals High Diversity, Geographic Structure and Limited Ranges in Neotenic Net-Winged Beetles <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> (Coleoptera: Lycidae)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Phylogeny and Distribution of Neotenic Net-Winged Beetles</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masek</surname><given-names initials="M">Michal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palata</surname><given-names initials="V">Vaclav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names initials="TC">Timothy C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names initials="L">Ladislav</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<addr-line>Department of Zoology, Faculty of Science, Palacky University, 17. listopadu 50, 771 46, Olomouc, Czech Republic</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Córdoba-Aguilar</surname><given-names initials="A">Alex</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico, MEXICO</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LB. Performed the experiments: MM VP. Analyzed the data: MM VP LB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LB. Wrote the paper: MM TB LB.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>ladislav.bocak@upol.cz</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">251292</issue-id><elocation-id>e0123855</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-15 17:25:13.193"><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Masek et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Masek et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0123855.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0123855.pdf"/><abstract><p>The neotenic <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> net-winged beetles have strongly modified development where females do not pupate and retain larval morphology when sexually mature. As a result, dispersal propensity of females is extremely low and the lineage can be used for reconstruction of ancient dispersal and vicariance patterns and identification of centres of diversity. We identified three deep lineages in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> occurring predominantly in (1) Borneo and the Philippines, (2) continental Asia, and (3) Sumatra, the Malay Peninsula and Java. We document limited ranges of all species of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> and complete species level turnover between the Sunda Islands and even between individual mountain regions in Sumatra. Few dispersal events were recovered among the major geographical regions despite long evolutionary history of occurrence; all of them were dated at the early phase of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> diversification up to the end of Miocene and no exchange of island faunas was identified during the Pliocene and Pleistocene despite the frequently exposed Sunda Shelf as sea levels fluctuated with each glacial cycle. We observed high diversity in the regions with persisting humid tropical forests during cool periods. The origins of multiple species were inferred in Sumatra soon after the island emerged and the mountain range uplifted 15 million years ago with the speciation rate lower since then. We suppose that the extremely low dispersal propensity makes <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> a valuable indicator of uninterrupted persistence of rainforests over a long time span. Additionally, if the diversity of these neotenic lineages is to be protected, a high dense system of protected areas would be necessary.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic (P506/11/1757). MM and VP were additionally supported by the Internal Grant of the Palacky University (IGA_PrF_2014013) and TB was supported by the grant POST-UP funded by the European Science Foundation and the Ministry of Education of the Czech Republic (CZ.1.07/2.3.00/30.0004). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The lyropaeine net-winged beetles (Lycidae) are a rare example of developmental modifications between sexes [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The males undergo complete metamorphosis, passing through the pupal stage, to become fully winged adults, with body length varying from 1.3–10 mm [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In contrast, the females remain larviform when sexually mature and differ from larvae only in the structure of cuticle and opened sexual tract (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The neotenic development of females has several macroevolutionary consequences. First of all, the winglessness results in the very limited dispersal propensity of all net-winged beetles with larviform females. Males, although winged, fly only in short distances within the lowest strata of the tropical rainforests, when searching for females (personal observation). Further some lyropaeine beetles have very large bodied females unknown in non-neotenic lineages of net-winged beetles ("trilobite larvae", body length 30–70 mm, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). These females live for several years in the larval stage and produce a relatively low number of large eggs from which hatch larvae comparable in size to adult males [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Such a reproductive strategy is energetically costly and was hypothesized as a case of K-strategy [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The high female investment in offspring has also been similarly predicted also for other neotenics [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Unlike females, the conspecific males often have a very small body (6–10 mm in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>, but slightly over 1 mm in <italic toggle="yes">Alyculus</italic>), live only shortly in the adult stage [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and invest a minimum energy in offspring compared to females. Apparently, the different selective regime affects the males and results in very disparate adult morphology. Although information on these beetles remains incomplete and females are unknown for most species and genera, the significant morphological differences among large-bodied females were proved in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and <italic toggle="yes">Lyropaeus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and the previous studies support the parallel origins of extremely large females.</p><fig id="pone.0123855.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Female larvae, late instars.</title><p>A-C <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>, Bornean clade; A—from Borneo, Sabah, Mt. Kinabalu, B—Borneo, Sabah, Poring, C—Mindanao, New Bataan; D—<italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic>, Malaysia, Pahang, Cameron Highlands.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Forty-two species of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> are known and their ranges are limited to three major biodiversity hotspots [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]: Indo-Burma, Sundaland and the Philippines including Palawan [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> do not occur in continental China (except the southernmost part of Yunnan along Lao and Burman borders) or in the southern part of the Indian subcontinent (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0123855.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>.</title><p>The taxa were assigned to clades by the phylogenetic analysis and/or morphological similarity. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">testaceicollis</italic> Pic, 1921 is known in a damaged holotype and no diagnostic characters are available to evaluate its relationships.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The majority of elateroid beetles are winged and quite effective at dispersal. On the other hand, there are multiple lineages within Elateroidea with wingless to larviform females. These lineages, e.g. Omethidae: Telegeusinae, multiple lineages of Lampyridae, all Omalisidae and Plastoceridae, Elateridae: Cebrioninae, Agrypninae: Drilini and others, usually share with their close relatives the biology and differ only in an incomplete metamorphosis. The lycid neotenic females remain completely larviform, their dispersal ability is extremely low and they heavily depend on humid rainforests as their larvae need constant access to liquid food and even the winged males do not fly effectively. Additionally, they are relatively species rich and previous studies have suggested their persistence in stable habitats [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore, these neotenic beetles can be used as a model group for evolutionary and zoogeographical studies and their presence and <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> diversification can identify regions with uninterrupted persistence of the rainforests during climatic fluctuations. Herein, we present the multi-marker molecular phylogeny of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> and reconstruct the ancestral range and dispersal routes of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> in the Oriental region. The aim of this study is to recover the diversification history of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> and define ranges with occurrence of ancient lineages of the neotenic beetles in South East Asia. We suggest that these are biodiverse regions worthy of protection and whose constituent species would be in danger of extinction should the habitats be destroyed.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>The specimens were preserved in 96% ethanol in the field and stored in a freezer until DNA was isolated. The sampled localities included the Kinabalu and Emas National Parks (Access Licence JMK/MBS.1000-2/2(110) issued by the Sabah Biodiversity Council, and Permit Penyelidikan No TS/PTD/5/4Jld48(41) by Lembaga Pemegang Amanah Taman-Taman). Other material was collected outside protected areas and species included in the research are not protected by international or national laws. The sequenced specimens are deposited in the voucher collection of the Laboratory of Molecular Systematics, Faculty of Science, Olomouc, Czech Republic, only the voucher specimen of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ngi</italic> is deposited the Zoological Reference Collection, Raffles Museum of Biodiversity Research, National University of Singapore. The voucher numbers provide access to all sequenced DNA fragments deposited in GenBank (<xref rid="pone.0123855.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>).</p><sec id="sec003"><title>Laboratory methods and phylogenetic analyses</title><p>DNA was extracted following the standard protocol with Wizard SV96 kit (Promega) from the flight muscles and larval thoracic segments. Extraction yield was measured using a NanoDrop-1000 Spectrophotometer. PCR was performed in a 50 μl reaction volume with 0.5 U Taq polymerase, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 mM of dNTPs, 0.2 mM of each primer, and typically 30 ng of template. Cycle conditions were generally 2 min at 94°C, 30–60 sec at 94°C, 30–60 sec at 45–52°C, 1–2 min at 72°C (repeated steps 2–4 for 35–40 cycles), and 10 min at 72°C. Two nuclear DNA markers were included in the study: the complete 18S rRNA (~1900 bp), the D2 region of the 28S rRNA (630 bp). Three fragments of the mitochondrial genome were sequenced: the 800 bp <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic> 3′ region of <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic>, the 1200 bp fragment of <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> and adjacent <italic toggle="yes">tRNA</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Phe</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tRNA</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Glu</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">tRNA</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">Ser</italic> (the whole fragment referred as <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> further), and a fragment of <italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic> (530 bp). The used primers are listed in <xref rid="pone.0123855.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>. PCR products were purified using PCRu96 Plates (Millipore Inc.) and sequenced by an ABI 3130 automated sequencer using the Big Dye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit 1.1.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Sequence handling and phylogenetic analyses</title><p>Sequences were edited using the Sequencher 4.8 software package (Gene Codes Corp.). The protein-coding markers, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>., <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic> were aligned by ClustalW 1.83 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] under default settings. Length variable fragments, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>., 18S, 28S rRNA, <italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic>, and tRNA mtDNA fragments, were separately aligned using ClustalW 1.83, BlastAlign 1.2 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] under default parameters, and Muscle 3.6 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] under the gap opening parameter 2600 and gap extension parameter 240. All DNA fragments were concatenated for final analyses. Multiple alignment methods were chosen to test the impact of various procedures on the tree topology. Phylogenetic analyses were carried out under the likelihood criterion (ML) using RAxML 7.2.3 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and bootstrap support of branches (BS) were assessed by analyzing 100 pseudoreplicates. All genes and codon positions in the protein coding fragments were partitioned under the models proposed by jModelTest 0.1.1 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The dataset was additionally analyzed using the Bayesian inference (BI) implemented in MrBayes 3.2.2 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) was set for independent variability of parameters in individual coding and non-coding genes under the GTR+I+G model. Two runs, each with four chains ran simultaneously for 40 x 10<sup>6</sup> generations, with trees being sampled every 1000<sup>th</sup> generation, all fragments were partitioned and unlinked. The results were evaluated in Tracer 1.6 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The first 2 x 10<sup>6</sup> trees of the first run and 16 x 10<sup>6</sup> trees of the second run were discarded as burn-in and posterior probabilities (PP) at nodes were determined from the remaining trees in the analysis of the Muscle alignment, 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> and 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> generations were discarded as burn-in in analysis of the BlastAlign matrix and 21 x 10<sup>6</sup> and 12 x 10<sup>6</sup> generations in the analysis of the Clustal alignment. The convergence of all parameters was assessed when runs were combined and the effective sample size (ESS) was over 1000 in all analyses. We used the MP-based statistical dispersal-vicariance analysis implemented in RASP 2.1 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] for an ancestral range reconstruction on the best ML tree inferred from the Muscle alignment. We coded six geographical regions: (1) Continental Asia north of Isthmus Kra represented by Lao and Thai species (2) Peninsular Malaysia, (3) Sumatra, (4) Java, (5) Borneo and (6) the Philippines. Two regions were simultaneously allowed at node during optimization.</p><p>The relative age of nodes was estimated using penalized likelihood and cross-validation analysis as implemented in r8s 1.71 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The age of the in-group was arbitrary set to 100 as no fossils are available for calibration. We used previously inferred age of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] for an approximate estimation of the absolute age of critical dispersal events and speciation in Sumatra. Branch lengths were optimized on the preferred tree topology and a wide range of smoothing parameters were tested before final analysis. Sampling intervals for inferred divergences were obtained from 100 bootstrap pseudoreplicates as described in the r8s manual. The lineage-through-time (ltt) plot for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> was constructed from the inferred normalized tree using the Phytools package 0.4–05 in R ([<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://r-forge.r-project.org/projects/splits/">http://r-forge.r-project.org/projects/splits/</ext-link>).</p><p>Additionally, we estimated the time to the most recent common ancestor for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> using a Bayesian approach implemented in Beast 1.8.1 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The analysis was performed using the Muscle alignment and a GTR+I+G model as given by the AICc criterion in jModelTest 3.7 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], a relaxed molecular clock and an uncorrelated lognormal model of rate variation among branches. The <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> clade was fixed to have an age of 1.0 and subsequently calibrated with previously hypothesized age [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The data were partitioned according to the genes and codon positions in the protein coding genes, with each partition allowed independent parameters. Altogether 5 x 10<sup>7</sup> generations were run, trees sampled every 10,000 generations and 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> generations were erased as pre-stationary stage. Convergence and ESS were assessed in Tracer 1.5 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>There are no fossils available for more accurate dating of the tree and we depend on the previous estimation of origin of major net-winged beetle lineages [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Therefore, we specifically ask about the origin of the Philippine fauna (ancient colonization in the Oligocene / Lower Miocene 20–35 mya versus recent dispersal history during low sea stands in the Upper Pliocene and Pleistocene) and putative accelerated speciation in Sumatra when it was established in the present form about 15 mya [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec005"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Sequence variation</title><p>We concatenated the DNA sequences of five fragments: 18S rRNA (78 specimens), 28S rRNA (74 spec.), <italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic> (75 spec., published by Masek and Bocak [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]), <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic> (60 spec.) and <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> mtDNA (61 spec.). Amplification problems were commonly encountered when tissue was taken from larvae and as a result only 78.6% of markers were available for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>. The complete dataset of aligned 18S, 28S, <italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> DNA fragments contained 5086–5274 homologous positions depending on the applied alignment procedure (<xref rid="pone.0123855.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>); 1727–1816 characters were parsimony informative. The aligned 18S fragment contained 1873–1883 positions, (7.6% of the parsimony informative characters), 28S 637–641 positions (3.8%), <italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic> 530–723 positions (14.5%), <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic> 790 positions (24.7%), and <italic toggle="yes">nad5</italic> 1237–1284 positions (47.0%).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0123855.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>The length of DNA fragments and the numbers of informative characters in datasets (gaps considered as the 5<sup>th</sup> character).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0123855.t001g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Datasets</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All data</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18S rRNA</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28S rRNA</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">rrnL</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">nad5-tRNAs</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of spec.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ClustalW</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of char.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5087</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1875</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">637</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1255</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parsimony informative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1816</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">897</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BlastAlign</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of char.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5274</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1883</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">641</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1237</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parsimony informative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1727</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of char.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1873</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">638</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">790</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1284</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parsimony informative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1789</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">869</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Phylogeny and distribution</title><p>The topologies produced from BlastAlign, Muscle and Clustal alignments analyzed under maximum likelihood method (ML) and Bayesian inference (BI) were similar (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1A</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0123855.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1C</xref> Fig). The Platerodrilini were regularly inferred as monophyletic group with robust support (BS 96%, PP 98%). Only the ML analysis of the Muscle alignment did not recover Platerodini, when <italic toggle="yes">Alyculus</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">Microlyropaeus</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">Antennolycus</italic> were found as a sister to remaining Lyropaeinae. <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Horakiella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Pendola</italic> and related genera represented the basal grade within Platerodrilini (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> clade was consistently recovered as a subordinate branch within Platerodrilini (BS and PP 100%). <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> split in a Bornean clade (BS and PP 100%), Indo-Burman clade and (BS and PP 100%) and Malay/Sumatran clade (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>; BS 87%, PP 100%). The alternative topologies were recovered in the terminal clades: the relationships among Bornean species (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">curtus</italic> and two unidentified spp.) was unstable, the sister species of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">palawanensis</italic> were either <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">strbai</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ngi</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>) and variable relationships were recovered for <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">robinsoni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ijenensis</italic> within the Malay/Sumatran clade (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). The ancestral ranges were inferred using parsimony and the phylogenetic hypothesis produced by the ML analysis of the Muscle alignment (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). We identified Sumatra and Borneo as an ancestral range of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> with available distributional data (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Borneo was identified as an ancestral range of the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">foliaceus</italic> and related species from Borneo and Mindanao (i.e., <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">foliaceus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">curtus</italic> and three unidentified species). This lineage is designated as the Bornean clade in Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Further the basal lineage known from Laos and Thailand in two unidentified female larvae (VP2304, 2311) is designated as the Indo-Burman clade. Most species of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> are known from Sumatra and we identified the Malay Peninsula and Sumatra as ancestral range for twenty species of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>. The clade is designated as the Malay/Sumatran in <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref> and only two species of this clade are known from Borneo and a single species from Palawan.</p><fig id="pone.0123855.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic hypothesis for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> Pic, 1921 based on a maximum likelihood analysis of the Muscle alignment.</title><p>Numbers at the branches are maximum likelihood bootstrap values and Bayesian posterior probabilities.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone.0123855.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Reconstruction of ancestral ranges using statistical parsimony.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone.0123855.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>A—Relative age of nodes estimated using penalized likelihood.</title><p>The age of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> was arbitrarily set to 100. The lower axes show ageestimation in mya derived from the age of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> inferred at 47 mya by Bocak <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2008). B—Lineage-through-time pot for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>, the time axis is calibrated as in Fig 5A.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone.0123855.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123855.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Timing of the <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> radiation.</title><p>Estimated ages of nodes are based on Bayesian analysis of all fragments and Muscle alignment. The bars depict 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123855.g006.jpg"/></fig><p>Altogether 29 species of 42 formally described were available for DNA analyses and we assign species, which could not be sequenced, to three principal clades using morphology. Accordingly, eight species are assigned to the Bornean clade (five of them sequenced, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>): five from Borneo, two from the Philippines, and one from Sumatra (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The Indo-Burman clade (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>, voucher numbers VP2304, 2311) is known only in larvae and without adults we cannot confirm the association of the sequenced larvae with any of the previously described three species from the region, therefore these are placed in the clade only tentatively. The Malay/Sumatran clade is represented by 17 spp. in Sumatra, 6 spp. in Java, 4 spp. in Peninsular Malaysia, 2 spp. in Borneo and a single species in Palawan (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). Some species were represented in the sequenced material only by female larvae and could not be identified to the species level. As we suppose, that at least some of them are conspecific with Sumatran and Malay species described in males, we do not list them in <xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>.</p><p>As no fossils are available for calibration, the approximate estimation of absolute time was derived from the previous analysis, which dealt with whole family [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and dated the basal split of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> to 47 mya. The relatively ancient origin of Platerodini and <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> is supported by the fact that they represent one of the deep lineages in the phylogeny of net-winged beetles and that they are a morphologically very distinct group [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The age estimation of principal splits using penalized likelihood shows that <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> originated early in evolution of the Platerodrilini (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>) and the principal clades within <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> were established soon thereafter (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>). With the basal split in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> dated to 47 mya, the principal clades separated ~40 mya, the species from Borneo and Palawan or Mindanao split ~25 mya and the multiple splits giving origins of Sumatran clades are dated at ~17 mya. The ltt plot (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>) suggests increased diversification rate at the beginning of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> evolution and at ~17 mya. The diversification slowed down since ~12 mya to present.</p><p>Alternative dating using the Bayesian approach provided similar, only slightly shallower time estimation for important splits in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). The analysis was affected by the missing fragments and the 95% confidence intervals were large. Nevertheless, we can conclude that basal splits between lineages from Indo-Burma, Borneo and the Malay Peninsula are ancient and dated to ~35 mya, the splits Palawan or Mindanao species are dated to ~20 mya and the beginning of the radiation in the Sumatran clade to ~15 mya. There were not identified any dispersal events between major geographic regions during the Pliocene and Pleistocene low sea stands in the last 3 million years even when the uncertainty of the dating is considered (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec008"><title>Discussion</title><p>The current dataset presented here provides more data for study of relationships of neotenic net-winged beetle lineages than the previous study, which included only four individuals [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The phylogenetic analyses confirm that Lyropaeinae represent a monophylum, which consists of Lyropaeini, Alyculini and Platerodrilini, all of them with confirmed or previously proposed neotenic development of females. Further, all inferred topologies indicate that the large-bodied larviform females evolved independently in both lineages: in <italic toggle="yes">Lyropaeus</italic> Waterhouse, 1878 (<italic toggle="yes">sensu</italic> Masek <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]) in Lyropaeini and in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic> (Platerodrilini). The first larviform platerodriline females are reported from Northeastern India and they represent a sister clade to <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis depressus</italic> Pic, 1938 from Peninsular Malaysia in the present analyses. The available taxa from India are known only in the female larvae (terminals VP0030, 31, 34, <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) and further information is needed before their placement in <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic> is confirmed. The adults of further genera, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>., <italic toggle="yes">Horakiella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Pendola</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Microlyropaeus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Antennolycus</italic>, and several undescribed taxa (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>), are exclusively known in adult males, when about two hundred specimens are currently available in collections. Both the larvae and adult females of these genera remain unknown and their neoteny has been only inferred from the absence of females in collected samples, morphology of males (all males are small bodied, with reduced mouthparts and often with light coloured and weakly sclerotized apexes of antennae) and proven presence of neotenic females in related genera (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). Field research in South East Asia yielded several dozen large-bodied larvae, all morphologically distinct samples were sequenced and all of them represent various species of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis</italic>. Neotenic female development has already been reported for a few species of these genera: <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus paradoxus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ruficollis</italic> (Pic, 1942) (= <italic toggle="yes">Duliticola hoiseni</italic> Wong, 1996) and <italic toggle="yes">Macrolibnetis depressus</italic> Pic, 1928 [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Therefore, considering the high number of identified males and females exclusively in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>, we suppose that the adult larviform females of other genera are of a similar body size to males and that given their small size they have been overlooked until now.</p><sec id="sec009"><title>Phylogeography and diversification of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>
</title><p>The distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> is limited to the eastern part of the Oriental region (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The highest diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> is known from Sumatra (18 spp.), Borneo (7 spp.) and Peninsular Malaysia (5 spp.). Only a few species have been reported from Vietnam, Laos, Thailand and southernmost China ([<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and unpublished records from Hainan and Yunnan; Yun Li, pers. comm.). A similarly limited number of species is known from the Philippines (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Despite presumed ancient origin of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> supported by morphological and genetic divergence [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], the range of these neotenic beetles is limited to regions with stable occurrence of humid tropical forests and they are not able to readily expand their ranges during periods with favourable climatic conditions. Although other lycid lineages dispersed from the Oriental region to northern China and Japan in a high number of species, <italic toggle="yes">e</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">g</italic>., Metriorrhynchini [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> have their northernmost limits in Hainan and southern and south-western Yunnan.</p><p>The phylogeographic analysis suggests Borneo and Sumatra as an ancestral range of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>); <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">foliaceus</italic> and its relatives identified on the basis of similar robust parameres occur predominantly in Borneo and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">sinuatus</italic> and its relatives, characterized by the slender curved phallus and slender parameres, in Sumatra and continental Asia [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Three principal splits in the phylogeny of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> were designated as the Bornean (+Philippines), Malay/Sumatran (+ Java, Borneo, Palawan) and Indo-Burman clades (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The ranges and centres of diversity of these clades differ.</p><p>The Bornean clade contains five Bornean, two Philippine species and only a single species of the clade occurs in Sumatra (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">wongi</italic> from Northern Sumatra, not available for DNA analysis and assigned to the clade using morphology). The Philippine species represent a terminal lineage and a single colonization event to the Philippines was recovered in an early phase of diversification of the clade. The dating must be viewed as preliminary, nevertheless the approximate estimation of their age points to a similar age as recovered in Philippine <italic toggle="yes">Scarelus</italic> by Malohlava and Bocak [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], when mutation rate was used for dating in this distantly related lineage. The inferred age of ~25 my is close to the glacial maximum in the early Oligocene [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and tectonic activity of the Sulu-Cagayan Arc [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The neotenics are not able to disperse across the sea and the indication of Oligocene colonization of the terrains forming the present day Philippines suggest a dry-land connection with Borneo. The dependence on a land connection for dispersal is supported by the fact that neither <italic toggle="yes">Scarelus</italic> nor <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> were able to disperse to the Philippines in the Pleistocene when most of the shelf was subaerial and the overseas distances lower than now [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Similarly, other neotenics are missing even in close regions if these are isolated by sea (<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">g</italic>., the absence of neotenic leptolycines in Jamaica and other Caribbean islands [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]).</p><p>The Malay/Sumatran clade was represented in the current molecular analysis by 17 species. The ancestral range was identified in Sumatra (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>) and most species never dispersed outside of the eastern part of the Sunda Shelf, <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>., Sumatra, Java and Malaya. Only <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">borneensis</italic> Wittmer, 1966 (unavailable for DNA isolation), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">strbai</italic> Kazantsev, 2009 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">palawanensis</italic> Masek et Bocak, 2014 (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) occur in Borneo and Palawan. The molecular phylogeny supports an early origin of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">palawanensis</italic> (30 mya and 20 mya in penalized likelihood and Bayesian analyses, respectively) and no exchange between faunas of Borneo, Malaya and Sumatra during Pliocene and Pleistocene low sea levels [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0123855.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The geographically close, repeatedly connected terrains of Sumatra and the Malay Peninsula also hold different fauna at the species level and the number of dispersal between them is limited. The single dispersal from Sumatra to the Malay Peninsula was dated to ~18 or ~12 mya according to available analyses (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The other identified species pairs occurring in these regions had split in the Upper Oligocene and Lower Miocene (<italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus ngi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">major</italic>, 17mya), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">luteus</italic> represents an ancient lineage in the Malay/Sumatran clade and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">angustatus</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">sibayakensis</italic> clade separated from their relatives ~33 or 26 mya (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). We did not recover any more recent dispersal events (Figs <xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The fauna of Java was represented by a single species <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ijenensis</italic> Masek et Bocak, 2014 and this species was recovered as a sister to the diversified crown clade of Sumatran and Malay species. The Sumatran fauna is the only one, which is represented by a sufficient number of lineages to estimate the dynamics of their diversification. The ltt plot (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>) shows the increased diversification rate in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> at ~17 mya and subsequent slow down till present. Alternatively, this sequence of splits was dated to 15 mya using the Bayesian inference (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). We suppose that the emergence of Sumatra 15 mya [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and formation of the Barisan mountain range triggered diversification of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>. The stable rainforest conditions in those areas isolated during glacial minima resulted in populations with lower diversification rates in the last 10 my. Dense sampling of species and populations is needed for a comprehensive analysis of speciation rates and these results must be viewed as preliminary.</p><p>The low dispersal propensity favours in situ diversification and very limited exchange between major geographical regions. No <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> species has been found in more than a single island and/or a mountain region. The long-term sequence of connection and isolation periods in Southeast Asia during the last 2.7 my [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] provided favourable conditions for multiple dispersal events at least in the last several million years, but no dispersal events were identified in <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic>. The reasons for observed patterns include the above mentioned low dispersal propensity, but also the climatic conditions in the subaerial Sunda Shelf. The rainforests in South East Asia depend on the monsoon system, which developed after the uplift of the Himalayas, but these rich habitats covered a variable part of the shelf depending on climatic fluctuations. The cool periods resulted in aridisation of the interior of the shelf [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and the savannah regions might have prevented the exchange between centres of diversity in eastern and western mountain ranges, which obtained a higher amount of rainfall and house very diverse fauna of neotenics. Similarly, decreased diversity of termites was reported in previously arid regions by Gathorne-Hardy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0123855.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], but the preserved distribution patterns evolved in the described case during recent Pleistocene periods of climatic fluctuations. In contrast, the faunas of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> remained isolated in the ancestral ranges over much longer time span and we identified only several dispersal events and/or vicariance between these centres of diversity in the Miocene or earlier.</p><p>The low dispersal propensity of neotenic net-winged beetles also affects diversification within individual islands. We found the complete turn over with no species overlap between mountain ranges in Sumatra (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), from where the higher density of sampling was available. Altogether 18 species occur in Sumatra and most are closely related and belong to the terminal lineage designated as the Malay/Sumatran clade (<xref rid="pone.0123855.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>). The individual mountain systems house completely distinct faunas and no species was collected in two or more distant localities. The stability of the tropical forests since the uplift of the island is postulated to be a necessary condition for <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> evolution and long-term persistence of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> in Sumatra. Additionally, the extremely low dispersal propensity of larviform females contributes to the observed small ranges and the whole-year humid mountain forests in the Sumatran mountain massifs represent separate "islands" where populations of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> diversified in isolation. The protection of major forest complexes like the Leuser National Park is important, but our findings suggest that only a fragment of genetic diversity is housed even in such a large national park. If diversity of the organisms with limited dispersal propensity is to be protected, the preservation of rainforest habitats is needed in a form of an extensive network covering most of the mountain ranges in South East Asia.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec010"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123855.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>The Bayesian phylogenetic trees of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> inferred from the dataset aligned using (A) BlastAlign, (B) Clustal and (C) Muscle.</title><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123855.s001.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123855.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Taxonomic coverage, geographic origin, and GenBank accession numbers.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123855.s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123855.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>The locality data for <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> samples.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123855.s003.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123855.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>Primers used for PCR amplifications.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123855.s004.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to R. Bilkova for technical assistance, to A. F. S. L. Lok, E. Jendek, L. Dembicky and P. Pacholatko for donation of specimens, and to N. Gunter for comments on the manuscript and proofreading.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0123855.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple ancient origins of neoteny in Lycidae (Coleoptera): consequences for ecology and macroevolution</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>275</volume>: <fpage>2015</fpage>–<lpage>2023</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2008.0476</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2596372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivie</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palata</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular phylogeny and classification of Lyropaeini (Coleoptera: Lycidae) with description of larvae and new species of Lyropaeus</article-title>. <source>Raffl Bull Zool</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Masek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>The taxonomy and diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Platerodrilus</italic> (Coleoptera: Lycidae) inferred from molecular data and morphology of adults and larvae</article-title>. <source>ZooKeys</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>426</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.426.7398</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25147457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4137290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mjöberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mystery of the so called "Trilobite" or "Perty's larvae" definitely solved</article-title>. <source>Psyche</source>. <year>1925</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>, pl. 3–4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ATC</given-names></name>. <article-title>A new species of neotenous beetle, <italic toggle="yes">Duliticola hoiseni</italic> (Insecta: Coleoptera: Cantharoidea: Lycidae) from Peninsular Malaysia and Singapore</article-title>. <source>Raffl Bull Zool</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <source>Ontogeny and phylogeny</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1977</year>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levkanicova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of net-winged beetle larvae (Coleoptera: Lycidae) using three mtDNA fragments: a comparison of their utility</article-title>. <source>Syst Ent</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>GAB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>403</volume>: <fpage>853</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/35002501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignments through sequence weighting, position specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucl Ac Res</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>4673</fpage>–<lpage>4680</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC308517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Belshaw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katzourakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>BlastAlign: a program that uses blast to align problematic nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15310559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title>. <source>Nucl Ac Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1792</fpage>–<lpage>1797</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC390337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>RAxML-III: a fast program for maximum likelihood-based inference of large phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>JMODELTEST: phylogenetic model averaging</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1253</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msn083</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>754</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rambaut A, Suchard MA, Xie D, Drummond AJ. Tracer version 1.6. 2014. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yu Y, Harris AJ, He XJ. RASP (Reconstruct Ancestral State in Phylogenies) 2.1b. 2012. Available: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mnh.scu.edu.cn/soft/blog/RASP">http://mnh.scu.edu.cn/soft/blog/RASP</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ympev.2015.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25819445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Estimation absolute rates of molecular evolution and divergence times: a penalized likelihood approach</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a003974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phytools: An R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things)</article-title>. <source>Meth Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2148-7-214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2247476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cenozoic geological and plate tectonic evolution of SE Asia and the SW Pacific: computer-based reconstructions, model and animations</article-title>. <source>J Asian Earth Sci</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kazantsev</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>. <article-title>New taxa of Platerodrilini</article-title>. <source>Russ Ent J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sklenarova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chesters</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogeography of Poorly Dispersing Net-Winged Beetles: A Role of Drifting India in the Origin of Afrotropical and Oriental Fauna</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>e67957</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067957</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3694047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malohlava</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence of extreme habitat stability in a Southeast Asian biodiversity hotspot based on the evolutionary analysis of neotenic net-winged beetles</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>4800</fpage>–<lpage>4811</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04850.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20958816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zachos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billups</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends, rhythms, and aberrations in global climate 65 Ma to present</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>292</volume>: <fpage>686</fpage>–<lpage>693</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1059412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Voris</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Maps of Pleistocene sea levels in south-east Asia: shorelines, river systems and time duration</article-title>. <source>J Biogeogr</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1153</fpage>–<lpage>1167</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bocak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Phylogeny and classification of the family Lycidae (Insecta: Coleoptera)</article-title>. <source>Ann Zool</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>–<lpage>720</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mid-Pliocene sea level and continental ice volume based on coupled benthic Mg/Ca palaeotemperatures and oxygen isotopes</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc A</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>367</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2008.0222</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18854304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanebuth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stattegger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grootes</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid flooding of the Sunda Shelf: a Late glacial sea-level record</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>288</volume>: <fpage>1033e1035</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.288.5468.1033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biogeography and conservation in Southeast Asia: how 2.7 million years of repeated environmental fluctuations affect today's patterns and the future of the remaining refugial-phase biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Biodiv Cons</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A GIS-based vegetation map of the World at the last Glacial Maximum (25,000–15,000 BP)</article-title>. <source>Intern Arch</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123855.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gathorne-Hardy</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Syaukani</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eggleton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quaternary rainforest refugia in south-east Asia: using termites (Isoptera) as indicators</article-title>. <source>Biol J Linn Soc</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>