
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">440</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">plosone</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101285081</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PLOS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC4412630.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4412630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4412630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-38205</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Availability of Empty Zona Pellucida for Generating Embryonic Chimeras</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Development of a New Method for Embryo Aggregation</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="CH">Chi-Hun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names initials="YH">Young-Hee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="DK">Dong-Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names initials="JY">Jae Yeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uh</surname><given-names initials="KJ">Kyung-Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeom</surname><given-names initials="SC">Su-Cheong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names initials="C">Curie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="CK">Chang-Kyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Green Bio Science and Technology, Seoul National University, Pyeong Chang, Kangwon do, Korea</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>College of Agriculture and Life Science, Chonnam National University, Gwangju, Korea</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Agricultural Biotechnology, Animal Biotechnology Major, and Research Institute of Agriculture and Life Science, Seoul National University, Seoul, Korea</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff004">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>International Agriculture Technology Graduate School, Seoul National University, Pyeong Chang, Kangwon do, Korea</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff005">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Division of Nephrology, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiuchun</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>USA, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: C-HP. Performed the experiments: C-HP Y-HJ D-KL JYH K-JU. Analyzed the data: C-HP S-CY CA C-KL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: S-CY C-KL. Wrote the paper: C-HP.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>leeck@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">251292</issue-id><elocation-id>e0123178</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>05</month><year>2015</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2020-12-15 14:16:17.523"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 Park et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Park et al</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="pone.0123178.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0123178.pdf"/><abstract><p>In the present study we used an empty zona pellucida derived from hatched blastocysts as an alternative source for embryo aggregation and compared results with the conventional microwell method. Denuded 4-cell stage porcine embryos were aggregated by introduction into an empty zona or placement within a concave microwell. The present study showed that although the rate of aggregate formation was similar, the blastocyst rates and allocation of more cells to the inner cell mass (ICM) in the resultant aggregates were increased significantly more in the empty zona than in the microwell. Notably, using an empty zona showed no limitations with regards to the increased number of embryos aggregated or embryonic stages for aggregation, while partial or no aggregation frequently occurred in the microwell. The discrepancy may be due to the difference of microenvironments where the embryos were placed namely, the presence/absence of zona pellucida. We hypothesize the success of the empty zona in generating aggregates is due to the physical aggregation of individual embryos allowing closer contact between the blastomeres and/or embryos compared with a concave microwell. These results indicate that aggregation conditions could influence overall production efficiency and developmental potential of aggregates, suggesting physical restraint via empty zona that provide three-dimensional pressures is an important factor for successful embryo aggregation.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Biogreen 21 program (PJ01130012015) of Rural development administration and the Ministry of Food and Drug Safety (KFDA2013-18075), Republic of Korea. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>After the first chimeric mice were reported in the early 1960s [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], experimental chimera has served as a powerful research tool for studying cell lineage determination and for determining potency of various stem cells, as well as for generating gene-modified mice [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The chimera competency of embryonic stem (ES) cells and induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells in mice and embryo-embryo aggregation in pigs has recently been utilized for generating specific organs [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Mouse chimeras can be generated by combining 2 or more dissected or whole embryos [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and either by direct microinjection of ES cells into a host blastocyst [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] or by co-culture with a host diploid or tetraploid embryo [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Blastocyst injection is the most widely used method for producing ES cell chimeric mice. The current processes creating an ES-derived chimera with this technique is of limited use in other species where putative ES or iPS cells are lacking in chimera-forming abilities and in contributing to the germ-line [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Because cloned or tetraploid mouse embryos have impaired developmental potentials with a reduced cell number of blastocysts, embryo aggregation has been used as an attempt to compensate for this deficiency [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]; increasing the total cells in chimeric blastocysts by aggregating multiple embryos can improve the pregnancy rate and the yield of live-born pups [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] which is consistent with observations made in other mammalian species, (e.g. rabbits, horses and pigs) [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, pig embryo aggregates have shown increased OCT4 transcription levels and improved <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Currently, embryo aggregation is considered to be a practical and reliable method for generating experimental chimera in non-rodent species including pigs and primates [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Zona pellucida (ZP) is a specialized extracellular matrix surrounding the plasma membrane of mammalian oocytes having various roles in fertilization and development. During the fertilization process, ZP prevents polyspermic penetration through its physical hardness due to release of cortical granule contents [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. During preimplantation development, this cover plays a protective role for the embryo from rejection by the maternal immune system and from infectious agents [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Several investigations have focused on the absence of ZP and the potential impacts on <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> development [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The ZP may be involved in maintaining the cell arrangement of cleavage stage embryos to ensure subsequent successful cell lineage differentiation [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, the zona-dispersed demiembryos have shown imbalanced ratios of the inner cell mass (ICM) compared with the trophectoderm (TE) and altered expression of Cdx2 and Oct4 [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Zona removal (mechanically or by exposure to pronase) induces a transient alteration in DNA methylation status of mouse embryos [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Despite potential influences of the ZP dispersion on early embryo development, zona removal is apparently an inevitable step for aggregating embryos.</p><p>Embryonic chimeras are commonly generated by co-culture of 2- or 3-embryos within a concave microwell, which is a well-described method; however, this method is still hampered by some technical limitations [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. For example, embryos frequently fail to aggregate into a single embryo in droplets due to a very minor impact when handled. The aim of the study was to determine the availability of empty zonas an alternative source for embryo aggregation as previously determined in mice [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and its effects on the aggregation efficiency of porcine parthenogenetic and cloned embryos and cell distribution pattern in the resultant aggregates. During <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> embryo culture, the empty zona derived from a hatched blastocyst is considered as waste and thus is generally discarded at the end of experiments. In this study, the empty zona obtained from the porcine parthenotes on day 7 or 8 of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> culture was employed for embryo aggregation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>All animal studies were performed after receiving approval of the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of Seoul National University (IACUC approval No. SNU-140328-2, <xref rid="pone.0123178.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). Porcine ovaries were provided by the regional slaughterhouse (Pyeongchang, Korea).</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Oocyte maturation</title><p>Ovaries were collected from prepubescent gilts at a local slaughterhouse (Pyeongchang Co.) and transported to the laboratory in 0.9% (w/v) NaCl supplemented with 100 mg/mL streptomycin sulfate (Amresco, Solon, OH, USA) within 30 min at 37°C. Only cumulus-oocyte complexes (COCs) were collected and washed twice with DPBS supplemented with 0.01% polyvinyl alcohol). After washing, 40–50 COCs were transferred to 500 μL of an IVM medium (TCM-199; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 10 ng/mL epidermal growth factor (EGF), 1 μg/mL insulin (Sigma-Aldrich Corp., St. Louis, MO, USA), 4 IU/mL eCG (Intervet, Boxmeer, The Netherlands), hCG (Intervet) and 10% (v/v) porcine follicular fluid (pFF) and were cultured for 22 h. Next, the COCs were transferred to an IVM medium without hormones and were cultured for a further 22 h at 38.5°C in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 100% humidity.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Generation of parthenotes and cloned embryos</title><p>For generating parthenotes, matured oocytes were activated by an electric pulse (1.0 kV/cm for 60 μsec) in activation medium (280 mM mannitol, 0.01 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.05mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) using a BTX Electro Cell Manipulator (BTX, Holliston, MA, USA), followed by 4 h of incubation in PZM3 medium containing 2 mmol/L 6-dimethylaminopurine.</p><p>Adult fibroblast cells were obtained from abdominal skin biopsy of a female Yucatan minipig. The biopsy was performed under isoflurane anesthesia following ketamine (25 mg/kg) and xylazine (0.5 mg/kg) premedication.Growing cells at a density of 3 x 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well were transfected with 2 μg of linearized pEGFP-N3 or pDsRed2-N1 using Lipofectamine LTXTM Reagent (Invitrogen) as suggested by the manufacturer. At 24 h after transfection, the transfected cells were passaged and selected with 0.3 mg/mL of neomycin G418 (Gibco) for 3 weeks. Somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT) was performed as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Briefly, enucleation was conducted in DPBS supplemented with 0.4% bovine serum albumin (BSA) and 5 mg/mL cytochalasin B. Matured oocytes were enucleated by aspiration with an enucleation pipette (Humagen, Charlottesville, VA, USA). After enucleation, GFP- or RFP-positive cells were mechanically collected and introduced into the perivitelline space of an enucleated oocyte. Fusion of injected oocytes was induced in a fusion medium (280 mM mannitol, 0.001 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 0.05 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) by 2 DC pulses (1-sec interval) of 2.0 kV/cm for 30 μsec. After 1 h of incubation, reconstructed oocytes were electrically activated as described above. Post-activated oocytes were cultured in PZM3 for 144 h. Embryo culture conditions were maintained at 38.5°C in an atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, 5% O<sub>2</sub> and 100% humidity.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Aggregation process</title><p>Empty zona pellucida of various sizes (range, 150~300 μm in diameter) were collected (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) and washed free of any debris in DPBS with 0.2% BSA by gentle pipetting and stored in PZM3 with 0.2% BSA under the same embryo culture condition until use. At the end of the experiments, empty zona were reused in the same manner as described above. At 2 days of culture after electrical activation, the 4-cell stage parthenogenetic embryo ZPs were removed by short exposure to acidic Tyrode’s solution (Gibco). The denuded embryos were introduced into a slit in the empty zona using a micromanipulator with hollow glass needles (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) or placed into each concave microwell (300 μm in diameter, <xref rid="pone.0123178.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>), created by a smooth depression using darning needles, as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0123178.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Parthenogenetic blastocysts and zona pellucida (ZP).</title><p>After electrical activation, the embryos were cultured for 7 to 8 days. Blastocysts and freed ZP (asterisks) with various sizes and shapes were observed. <bold>(A)</bold> The thin, stretched, ruptured, empty zona were observed after shedding. <bold>(B)</bold> The empty zona with a large slit (solid arrowhead) or with a narrow slit (open arrowhead) were discarded. Only empty zona shaped like the video game icon "Pac-Man" with a proper slit size were collected. <bold>(B`)</bold> Bar in B`is 100 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="pone.0123178.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Injection of 4-cell stage embryos into empty zona.</title><p>After dissolving the zona pellucida (ZP), the denuded parthenotes at the 4-cell stage <bold>(A)</bold> were injected into the empty zona <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> micromanipulation with hollow glass needles <bold>(B-G)</bold>. Multiple embryos with various numbers were reconstructed using the empty zona method <bold>(H and I)</bold>. The embryos injected into an empty zonae were gently pressed around through the glass needle, causing them to bind together more tightly <bold>(J-L)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Differential staining and cell number counts</title><p>For examining the blastocyst cell counts, the numbers of ICM and total cells of individual aggregates collected on day 7 were counted by differential staining [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] using a fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data obtained in this study were analyzed using the GraphPad Prism statistical program (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). Data on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> developmental and aggregate formation rates were analyzed using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Dunnett’s test. Comparisons between the 2 groups were performed using Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests. All data were expressed as mean values ± standard error of the mean (SEM). A probability of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec009"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec010"><title>Empty zona collection after shedding of blastocysts</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="pone.0123178.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A</xref>, various empty zona sizes and shapes were obtained from late blastocysts on day 7 or 8 of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> culture. In this study, we did not use the empty zona from the embryos of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> fertilization to exclude the possibility of detrimental effects due to many dead sperm surrounding the ZP. The empty zona with relatively large slits (larger than twice the embryo's diameter) created during hatching were discarded because the aggregates tended to leak out through the large slit breaks (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>, solid arrowhead). Additionally, the empty zona with too narrow slits making injection into the denuded embryos difficult and in turn, possibly injuring their membranes during the injecting process were not used (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>, open arrowhead). Therefore, we used primarily the empty zona were similar to that in <xref rid="pone.0123178.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>`.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Introduction embryos into an empty zona</title><p>For this experiment, we used parthenogenetic embryos which can be easily generated and minimized possible artifacts from other embryo types; <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> fertilized embryos that show high incidence of aneuploidy caused by polyspermic penetration or mixed sexes and cloned embryos with poor development and labor-intensive process. The zona-removed 4-cell stage embryos were introduced into a slit in the empty zona using a micromanipulator (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). After injection, the embryos were gently pressed and squeezed around by rotating through hollow glass needles (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2H–2L</xref>), causing them to lie in closer contact. This step may not be critical, but produces a more efficient outcome in which embryos are weakly attached. Thus, partial aggregation that frequently occurs in a droplet could be reduced when this step was added (<xref rid="pone.0123178.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>). Once embryos are placed in an empty zona, they remain in contact even if rough handling or repeat pipetting occurs. The conventional aggregation was also conducted using the microwell method (<xref rid="pone.0123178.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Microenvironments and their impact on aggregation and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of aggregates</title><p>To determine the applicability for generating embryonic chimeras, we employed the empty zona method (n = 33) and the conventional microwell method (n = 35) to generate aggregates with multiple embryos (3X). After culturing for 48 h, although a few aggregates (n = 3) were obtained with a small number of blastomeres arrested, most (n = 32) underwent the well-formed compacted morula stage (full aggregation) when using the empty zona with an average size of 200 μm, progressing to the blastocyst stage (<xref rid="pone.0123178.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In the microwell method, not only full aggregation (n = 28), but also incomplete aggregates with separated blastocoel cavities (partial aggregation) and no aggregation (n = 7; <xref rid="pone.0123178.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>) were observed. The aggregates that failed to aggregate into a single blastocyst were excluded from further analyses. The overall aggregate formation was slightly lower in the microwell (81.3%) than in the empty zona method (96.0%), but was not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). However, the rate of blastocyst formation was significantly higher in aggregates derived from the empty zona method (92.7%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) than from the microwell (68.4%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and the control singletons derived from the denuded embryos (45.5%). At the end of culture (72 h), the number of total and ICM cells was determined using a differential staining technique (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>). The mean number of total cells (32.8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) was less in singletons than aggregated blastocysts in aggregates of the microwell (80.1) and empty zona (85.7) methods. However, the resultant blastocysts had significantly greater number of ICM cells and a higher ICM/total cell ratio in the EZ method (25.7 and 3.0, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared with the microwell method (14.3 and 5.2) and the control (6.8 and 6.1). This may be a result of many aggregates exhibiting a non-compacted ICM in the blastocysts derived from the microwell method (<xref rid="pone.0123178.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>), while such anomaly was rarely observed in aggregates produced by the empty zona method. The physical trapping by ZP can apparently impact aggregation formation of embryos and cell allocation in the resultant aggregates.</p><fig id="pone.0123178.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Representative images of differentially-stained porcine day 6 blastocysts.</title><p>A singleton <bold>(A)</bold> and 3X aggregate blastocyst with compact <bold>(B)</bold> or scattered or non-compact <bold>(C)</bold> inner cell mass (ICM). Using a conventional differential staining method, ICM were labeled with Hoechst 33342 (blue) and trophectoderm (TE) nuclei with propidium iodide (red); photographed under an epifluorescent microscope. Scale bars: 100 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0123178.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Developmental rate of triple-aggregated embryos produced using the EZ and conventional microwell methods.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0123178.t001g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.t001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Groups</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Number examined</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="2" align="center">Number (%)aggregated</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="2" align="center">Number (%)blastocyst</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Cell number</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (n)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICM</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control<xref rid="t001fn003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45<xref rid="t001fn004" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>‡</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(49.3 ± 2.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(45.5 ± 2.2)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 (12)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microwell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(81.3 ± 3.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(68.4 ± 2.4)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.1 (9)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">empty zona</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(96.0 ± 1.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(92.7 ± 2.0)<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.7 (10)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>The rates of aggregation and blastocyst formation were calculated in the embryo on day 5 at the morula stage and on day 7 at the blastocyst stage, respectively. The aggregates with only 1 or 2 blastomeres were also regarded as successful aggregation.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>ICM, inner cell mass</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p>
<sup>†</sup> denuded 4-cell embryos were individually cultured in microwells and developed to the blastocyst stage</p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p>
<sup>‡</sup> the mean value is the proportions of embryos that became morulae</p></fn><fn id="t001fn005"><p>Each group had 3 replicates. Values are expressed as mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM).</p></fn><fn id="t001fn006"><p>Within the same column, values with different letters (a, b, and c) in superscript are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Effect of increasing the number of embryos on aggregate formation</title><p>We tested the ability of empty zona to support aggregate formation and its developmental potential therefore, we examined the 4-cell stage embryo aggregates with various number of embryos in both methods. For this experiment, the denuded embryos were introduced into empty zona of various sizes (the ranges from 150 to 300 μm), depending on the number of embryos used for aggregation (from 2 to 8 embryos) and then cultured individually. A majority of the embryos assembled into a single aggregate <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> our method and progressed to the blastocyst stage (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). Of the embryos, only 5.3% exhibited partial aggregates but no failed aggregation was observed (data not shown). The aggregation formation (<xref rid="pone.0123178.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) did not differ from an increase in the number of embryos examined (75.0% for 2X, 91.7% for 3X, 83.4% for 4X, 91.7% for 5X, 79.2% for 6X, 91.7% for 7X and 91.7% for 8X). Similarly, the blastocyst formation rate among the groups was not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) in the current experimental setting. There was a slight increase in total cells in the resultant blastocysts, but did not translate into a proportional increase in the number of embryos. In contrast, the conventionally-derived aggregates were limited in the number of embryos that became well-formed blastocysts. Notably, most of the aggregates with 5 or more embryos (87%) did not form a single compact aggregate to be counted as full aggregation (<xref rid="pone.0123178.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>). These results indicate the empty zona method may provide a stable microenvironment for robust aggregate formation of embryos with no limitation on the number of embryos employed.</p><fig id="pone.0123178.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Aggregate formation and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of embryos using the empty zona method.</title><p>Chimeric morulae and blastocysts derived from 2 (2X), 3 (3X), 4 (4X), 5 (5X), 6 (6X), 7 (7X) and 8 (8X) aggregated embryos were photographed using an optical microscope. The embryos began to compact on day 2 of culturing after introduction and the majority developed to the blastocyst stage.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0123178.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Aggregate formation and developmental potentials of aggregates with various embryo numbers using the empty zona method.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0123178.t002g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.t002.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number examined</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Number (%) aggregated</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Number (%) blastocyst</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cell number<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>†</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>‡</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(53.8 ± 7.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(70.8 ± 10.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8 * (n = 8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(75.0 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(87.5 ± 12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9 (n = 7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(91.7 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(93.8 ± 6.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0 (n = 10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(83.4 ± 9.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(87.5 ± 12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.7 (n = 8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(91.7 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(85.4 ± 8.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6 (n = 9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(79.2 ± 12.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(100 ± 0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.8 (n = 8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(91.7 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(100 ± 0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.3 (n = 8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8X</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(91.7 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(91.7 ± 8.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.5 (n = 10)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>
<sup>†</sup> In the experiment of total cell number, the aggregated morula with the dissociated blastomeres (3 or 4) were downcounted as less as 1X (as represented in <xref rid="pone.0123178.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>; 5X and 8X were counted as 4X and 7X, respectively)</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>1X group is the denuded 4-cell stage embryos that were individually injected into the empty zona</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p>
<sup>‡</sup> the mean value is the proportions of embryo that became morulae</p></fn><fn id="t002fn004"><p>Within the same column, values with different asterisks are significantly different (* <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Each group has 4 replicates. Values are expressed as mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Cell allocation of cloned embryo aggregates expressing green fluorescent proteins (GFP) or red fluorescent proteins (RFP)</title><p>We verified the methodology could be applied to generate multi-transgenic animals. Using a fetal fibroblast cell strain, the 2 sublines that express GFP and RFP were established and used as nuclear donors for SCNT [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. <xref rid="pone.0123178.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the results of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of the transgenic embryos reconstructed using the GFP and RFP. The embryos expressing GFP (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) had significantly higher rates of cleavage (70.0 ± 6.5) and blastocyst formation (31.8 ± 2.8) than the RFP-expressing embryos (50.9 ± 5.2 and 16.2 ± 0.8, respectively). In total cell numbers, there was no significant difference between the GFP (38.3 ± 3.5) and RFP (32.6 ± 3.5) cloned blastocysts (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0123178.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Aggregate formation and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of cloned embryos expressing GFP and RFP.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="pone.0123178.t003g" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.t003.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number examined</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Number (%) cleaved</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Number (%) aggregated</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Number (%) blastocyst</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number oftotal cells</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(70.0 ± 6.5)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(31.8 ± 2.8)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9 ± 3.8<sup>a</sup> (n = 20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50.9 ± 5.2)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(16.2 ± 0.8)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 ± 3.5<sup>a</sup> (n = 18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP<sup>(4X)</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(77.9 ± 2.4)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(76.0 ± 6.2)<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0 ± 5.1<sup>b</sup> (n = 11)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFP<sup>(4X)</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(57.2 ± 4.7)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(46.7 ± 6.2)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.1 ± 6.4<sup>b</sup> (n = 8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP/RFP<sup>(4X)</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(70.3 ± 4.0)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(67.7 ± 5.1)<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.4 ± 3.1<sup>b</sup> (n = 10)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>GFP, green fluorescent protein; RFP, red fluorescent protein</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p>The cleavage rate was recorded 42–44 h post activation. All percentage data expressed are mean values ± standard error of the mean (SEM). Different letters (a, b, and c) in superscript indicate significant differences in mean values (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Data on blastocyst rate and total cells of RFP and aggregate groups was compared to the GFP group using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on this finding, 4-cell stage GFP and/or RFP embryos were aggregated <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the empty zona method. The comparison clearly shows the aggregation process could lead to an approximate 2-fold increase in overall blastocyst rates and total cell number of aggregates, compared with their intact counterparts (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, a significant difference was observed between GFP<sup>(4X)</sup> and RFP<sup>(4X)</sup> groups in aggregate formation and blastocyst rate. This trend was not detected when equal numbers of GFP/RFP<sup>(4X)</sup> were intermixed. In addition, to evaluate the extent of intermingling of embryonic cells in aggregates, the resultant aggregates with GFP/RFP embryos were imaged using a fluorescence microscopy to trace the cell distribution pattern in aggregates. The results showed all aggregates (4X) with intermingled GFP/RFP-positive cells (<xref rid="pone.0123178.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). In particular, GFP-positive cells tended to contribute to the ICM more than to the TE, while the cells expressing RFP broadly dispersed to both layers. However, there was no apparent tendency to allocate exclusively to the ICM or TE. The embryonic cells possessing a high potential for development are apparently more likely to contribute to the embryonic part, but not exclusively. Thus, these results may indicate that developmental capacity of component embryos in aggregates affects the overall aggregation efficiency and cell distribution pattern within resultant aggregates.</p><fig id="pone.0123178.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0123178.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Green fluorescent protein (GFP) and red fluorescent protein (RFP) expression in 4X cloned aggregates using the empty zona method.</title><p>Two cloned embryos derived from the GFP or RFP cell line were aggregated using the empty zona method. A cloned aggregate (4X) was photographed <bold>(A)</bold> and the cell distribution pattern traced using a fluorescent microscope.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="pone.0123178.g005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our data showed an increased blastocyst rate and number of total cells in aggregates than singleton, supporting the notion that embryo-to-embryo aggregation may rescue developmentally impaired embryos in aggregates [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, the blastocyst formation and the ICM cell number were significantly higher in the empty zona method than in the microwell method, whereas the total cell number in resultant aggregates was similar between the two methods. The only difference between the methods was the presence/absence of ZP, indicating its presence caused this difference. Although ZP is not fundamental for <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of early mouse embryos to the blastocyst stage, many studies have shown the possible impacts on zona removal in developing embryos. Notably, zona absence could lead to disrupted regulation of polarity and incorrect division patterns of early stage embryos. In pig embryos, the zona removal adversely affected blastocyst formation and zona-free sheep cloned embryos frequently exhibited a significant decrease in ICM cell number and the OCT4 transcripts at the blastocyst stage [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Note that, using free-zonae derived from blastocysts has already been tested in earlier studies on the effect of removal of the zona pellucida on subsequent development of blastocysts, but has only been done with half-ablated embryos or single blastomeres [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Given that the bisected embryos or single blastomeres cannot fill in the empty space of a host empty zona, even those with the zona-confined had weak interactions between blastomeres and abnormal growth patterns, which occurred in zona-dispersed counterparts [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The present study does not address directly the issue of whether zona removal has negative effects on early developing porcine embryos, but previous literature implicates ZP as an important component in some aspects of early embryonic development. These observations with the previous studies indicating indicate that ZP may have contributed to changes in cell fate and developmental potential of early pig embryos [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>The present results showed that using a microwell led to progressive increases in the rate of failed aggregation with increasing number of embryos aggregated. The zona-free embryos were easily separated from one another and frequently underwent the loss of blastomeres before the compacted morula stage [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], so it would seem that a simple coculture system using a microwell can actually create a deleterious microenvironment in denuded embryos. By contrast, the empty ZP in which the denuded embryos are restrained keeps them firmly attached together during the aggregation process thereby enabling them to fully aggregate. The empty zona method showed no limitation for aggregation regarding the number of embryos (8 or even higher) while the efficiency was diminished in the microwell method if the number of embryos (more than 4) was increased. We hypothesize the increase in cell-to-cell contact between embryos enhances aggregational capacity of the developing embryo. Thus, these results indicate the possible impacts that currently exist in conventional aggregation methods in relation with zona removal can be reduced using the empty zona method. Accordingly, using an empty zona with the proper size is important primarily to consider for embryo aggregation and may lie in the number of embryos used, allowing them to fill tightly in place. Together, empty zona provide a conducive and stable environment to ensure physical restraint of embryos, allowing for successful aggregate formation and preimplantation development. Apart from its availability, the present results also showed the total cells in the resultant blastocysts did not increase proportionally as increased number of embryos aggregated (more than 3). These results are in agreement with previous studies suggesting a possible mechanism of size regulation by controlling cell proliferation activity in aggregates [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Therefore, although aggregates with 4 or more embryos did not severely compromise their development <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, there may be no developmental advantage using more than 3 embryos.</p><p>Our results also showed that aggregation of cloned embryos enhanced blastocyst formation compared with intact cloned embryos, but differences in aggregate formation and blastocyst rate between embryos cloned from different donor cells were observed. In the present study, the varying developmental potential of cloned embryos resulted in reduced ability of embryos to aggregate, similar to a previous study [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Thus, these results indicate the combination of multiple embryos with different developmental potentials affects the overall aggregation efficiency and cell distribution pattern within resultant aggregates.</p><p>The impact of the embryonic stage on embryo aggregation and the optimal timing may vary for different species. Our previous observations showed the 4-cell stage is the optimal stage for aggregation of porcine embryos [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In preliminary experiments, we observed no limitation regarding the embryonic stages (1- to 8-cell stage) in aggregation formation <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the empty zona method (data not shown) indicating that using empty zona allows flexibility in choosing developmental stages of embryos for aggregation. Accordingly, after introduction into an empty zona, the embryo can immediately be transferred into a recipient without requiring additional culture periods until becoming a single aggregate [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This is a significant advancement because generating live pig chimeras from transferred blastocysts is technically challenging since the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> culture systems of porcine embryos are still considered suboptimal [<xref rid="pone.0123178.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p><p>Herein, we determined the availability of empty zona as an alternative source for embryo-embryo aggregation. A novel technique for embryo aggregation, the empty zona method, provides a physical space using a natural component, which allows a greater opportunity for physical contact between embryos for successful aggregation to occur. Additionally, it allows safe and easy handling of embryo during <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments, while the denuded embryo tends to become sticky and fragile. Based on the present findings, the empty zona method can generate embryonic chimeras with greater efficiency than the conventional microwell method and can be applied to practical chimera production systems for other mammalian species. However, further confirmation by <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies is needed to validate <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> results of this method.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec016"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123178.s001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Aggregation efficiency of triple embryos produced using the conventional microwell method with or without pressing around.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123178.s001.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123178.s002" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Approval of the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC).</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123178.s002.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123178.s003" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>The microwell aggregation of 4-cell stage embryos.</title><p>The microwell aggregation was conducted by placing the denuded embryos in a smooth depression using darning needles. Two, three, four and five aggregates are shown.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123178.s003.tiff" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0123178.s004" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Representative images of differentially-stained porcine day 6 blastocysts.</title><p>Inner cell mass (ICM) cells are shown in blue and TE cells are shown in red. Porcine day 6 chimeric blastocysts with well formed (A) a few, scattered (B) and disaggregated (C) ICM. Scale bars: 100 μm.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pone.0123178.s004.tif" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are thankful to Chang-Mook Park, DVM (Gangwon-do Veterinary Service Laboratory) for providing pig ovaries.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0123178.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tarkowski</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mouse chimaeras developed from fused eggs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1961</year>
<volume>190</volume>: <fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>860</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13775333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/190857a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadjantonakis</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vintersten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Aggregation chimeras: combining ES cells, diploid, and tetraploid embryos</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>530</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-59745-471-1_15</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19266342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2913464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kato-Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Generation of rat pancreas in mouse by interspecific blastocyst injection of pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>142</volume>: <fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>799</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2010.07.039</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20813264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umeyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Blastocyst complementation generates exogenic pancreas in vivo in apancreatic cloned pigs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>4557</fpage>–<lpage>4562</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1222902110</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23431169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3607052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mouse embryonic chimeras: tools for studying mammalian development</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>130</volume>: <fpage>6155</fpage>–<lpage>6163</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14623817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.00893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Formation of germ-line chimaeras from embryo-derived teratocarcinoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1984</year>
<volume>309</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6717601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/309255a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simple and efficient production of embryonic stem cell-embryo chimeras by coculture</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>4582</fpage>–<lpage>4585</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8506303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.90.10.4582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC46556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Polejaeva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitalipov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stem cell potency and the ability to contribute to chimeric organisms</article-title>. <source>Reproduction</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>145</volume>: <fpage>R81</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/REP-12-0396</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23221011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3678546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abramow-Newerly</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Derivation of completely cell culture-derived mice from early-passage embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>8424</fpage>–<lpage>8428</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8378314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.90.18.8424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC47369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaide</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increasing the cell number of host tetraploid embryos can improve the production of mice derived from embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod.107.067116</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scholer</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Oct4 distribution and level in mouse clones: consequences for pluripotency</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1209</fpage>–<lpage>1219</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.966002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC186284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leu</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scholer</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pluripotency deficit in clones overcome by clone-clone aggregation: epigenetic complementation?</article-title>
<source>EMBO J</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>5304</fpage>–<lpage>5312</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14517267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/emboj/cdg507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC204490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siriboon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Production of viable cloned miniature pigs by aggregation of handmade cloned embryos at the 4-cell stage</article-title>. <source>Reprod Fertil Dev</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/RD12243</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23544704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ka</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>. <article-title>In vitro development and cell allocation of porcine blastocysts derived by aggregation of in vitro fertilized embryos</article-title>. <source>Mol Reprod Dev</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1436</fpage>–<lpage>1445</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mrd.20728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Terashita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiradate</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Improving the quality of miniature pig somatic cell nuclear transfer blastocysts: aggregation of SCNT embryos at the four-cell stage</article-title>. <source>Reprod Domest Anim</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0531.2010.01614.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20412512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biology of mammalian fertilization: role of the zona pellucida</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>–<lpage>1059</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1556174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI115684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC442960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrathall</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nauwynck</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is the zona pellucida an efficient barrier to viral infection?</article-title>
<source>Reprod Fertil Dev</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/RD09230</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of various procedures on the viability of mouse embryos containing half the normal number of blastomeres</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Fertil</source>
<year>1983</year>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6887141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1530/jrf.0.0690315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nijs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Steirteghem</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of different biopsy methods of blastomeres from 2-cell mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3204155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/oxfordjournals.humrep.a136831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Togashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Developmental ability of zona-free mouse embryos is influenced by cell association at the 4-cell stage</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7669859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1095/biolreprod53.1.78</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellersieck</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of monozygotic twin mouse embryos from the time of blastomere separation at the two-cell stage to blastocyst</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1237</fpage>–<lpage>1247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod.109.082982</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2874505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ribas</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCorquodale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mauricio</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmut</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of zona pellucida removal on DNA methylation in early mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16221985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1095/biolreprod.105.046284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eakin</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadjantonakis</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Production of chimeras by aggregation of embryonic stem cells with diploid or tetraploid mouse embryos</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1145</fpage>–<lpage>1153</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nprot.2006.173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2883166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kashiwazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanoi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Sexing of half-embryos produced by microsurgical bisection of mouse morulae and production of chimeric mouse of defined sex composition by aggregating two sexed half-embryos</article-title>. <source>Exp Anim</source>
<year>1988</year>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1538/expanim1978.37.2_127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3396629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Production of multiple transgenic Yucatan miniature pigs expressing human complement regulatory factors, human CD55, CD59, and H-transferase genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e63241</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063241</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23704897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3660325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thouas</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korfiatis</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trounson</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simplified technique for differential staining of inner cell mass and trophectoderm cells of mouse and bovine blastocysts</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12513888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1472-6483(10)61960-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moulavi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hajian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forouzanfar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abedi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostadhosseini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Nuclear transfer technique affects mRNA abundance, developmental competence and cell fate of the reconstituted sheep oocytes</article-title>. <source>Reproduction</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>145</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/REP-12-0318</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23401598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Developmental potential of single blastomeres of the rabbit egg</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Fertil</source>
<year>1968</year>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5715682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1530/jrf.0.0170527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Willadsen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A method for culture of micromanipulated sheep embryos and its use to produce monozygotic twins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1979</year>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">570249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/277298a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Modlinski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of the zona pellucida in the development of mouse eggs in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Embryol Exp Morphol</source>
<year>1970</year>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5473304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of extracellular matrices and growth factors on the development of isolated porcine blastomeres</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>. <year>1991</year>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>927</fpage>–<lpage>936</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1095/biolreprod44.5.927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanism of size regulation in mouse embryo aggregates</article-title>. <source>J Embryol Exp Morphol</source>
<year>1982</year>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7183736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Misica-Turner</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oback</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eichenlaub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oback</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Aggregating embryonic but not somatic nuclear transfer embryos increases cloning efficiency in cattle</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17050861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1095/biolreprod.106.050922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsunari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maehara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Generating porcine chimeras using inner cell mass cells and parthenogenetic preimplantation embryos</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e61900</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061900</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23626746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3633951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0123178.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>X-linked gene transcription patterns in female and male in vivo, in vitro and cloned porcine individual blastocysts</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e51398</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051398</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3517569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>