
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1558</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101532965</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals, LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5542272</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5542272.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5542272</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5542272</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28654422</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.18013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">18013</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression and its correlation with survival is tumour molecular subtype dependent in glioblastoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murnyák</surname><given-names initials="B">Balázs</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kouhsari</surname><given-names initials="MC">Mahan C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hershkovitch</surname><given-names initials="R">Rotem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kálmán</surname><given-names initials="B">Bernadette</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marko-Varga</surname><given-names initials="G">György</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klekner</surname><given-names initials="Á">Álmos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names initials="T">Tibor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Division of Neuropathology, Institute of Pathology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Debrecen, Debrecen, Hungary</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Institute of Diagnostics, Faculty of the Health Sciences, University of Pecs, Pecs, Hungary</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Molecular Pathology Unit, Markusovszky Teaching Hospital, Szombathely, Hungary</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Division of Clinical Protein Science &amp; Imaging, Department of Biomedical Engineering, Lund University, Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="A5"><sup>5</sup> Department of Neurosurgery, Faculty of Medicine, University of Debrecen, Debrecen, Hungary</aff><aff id="A6"><sup>6</sup> Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience, King's College London, London, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic toggle="yes">Tibor Hortobágyi,</italic><email>hortobagyi@med.unideb.hu</email>, <email>tibor.hortobagyi@kcl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>28</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">296373</issue-id><fpage>46348</fpage><lpage>46362</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2017-08-08 00:08:19.563"><day>08</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2017 Murnyák et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link> (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348.pdf"/><abstract><p>Overexpression of PARP1 exists in various cancers, including glioblastoma (GBM). Although PARP1 inhibition is a promising therapeutic target, no comprehensive study has addressed PARP1's expression characteristics and prognostic role regarding molecular heterogeneity in astrocytomas including GBM. Our aim was to evaluate PARP1's associations with survival, WHO grade, lineage specific markers, and GBM transcriptomic subtypes. We collected genomic and clinical data from the latest glioma datasets of The Cancer Genome Atlas and performed PARP1, ATRX, IDH1, and p53 immunohistochemistry on GBM tissue samples. We demonstrated that PARP1 gain and increased mRNA expression are characteristics of high-grade astrocytomas, particularly of Proneural and Classical GBM subtypes. Additionally, higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels exhibited an inverse correlation with patient survival (p&lt;0.005) in the Classical subgroup. <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> (p=0.006), and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> (p=0.015) mutations were associated with increased PARP1 expression and PARP1 protein level correlated with <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> loss and p53 overexpression. Furthermore, higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression together with wildtype <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> indicated shorter survival (p=0.039). Therefore, due to subtype specificity, <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression level and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutation status are reliable marker candidates to distinguish Proneural and Classical subtypes, with prognostic and therapeutic implications in GBM.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>glioma</kwd><kwd>glioblastoma</kwd><kwd>p53</kwd><kwd>PARP1</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Glioblastoma (GBM) is a highly aggressive and the most prevalent primary brain tumour in adults. GBM has a dismal outcome, the median survival is typically less than 2 years [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The current treatment consists of maximal surgical resection of the tumour followed by concurrent chemo- (TMZ, temozolomide) and radiation therapy (RT) [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Despite extensive efforts to improve treatment, GBM is still resistant to current postoperative therapies making GBM a compelling field of cancer research [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Improving the outcome requires novel diagnostic approaches and effective treatment strategies [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>The biological basis of the resistance involves many factors, including molecular heterogeneity, and impaired DNA repair mechanisms. Currently, targeting the poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase 1 (PARP1) DNA repair protein in GBM is a new and promising aspect in clinical trials [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. PARP1 is a nuclear protein, and is normally involved in DNA repair and the maintenance of genomic stability [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. PARP1 binds to DNA strand breaks and produces a poly (ADP-ribose) chain from NAD<sup>+</sup> substrate which signals the cell to initiate DNA damage repair. The role of PARP1 has been already investigated in brain diseases [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and its overexpression has been reported in various tumour types, such as breast, ovary, skin, colorectum, lung and brain [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Upregulated PARP1 can enhance the anti-apoptotic property of tumours resulting in resistance to DNA damaging therapeutic agents [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. PARP inhibitors (PARPi) sensitize tumour cells to radiotherapy and to chemotherapeutic agents. The inhibitors attach to the catalytic domain of the protein thereby blocking synthesis of ADP-ribose polymers. Consequently, the cellular responses to DNA damage do not occur, leading to cell death [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Although all GBMs share common histological features, they individually vary at their molecular level resulting in significant differences in terms of prognosis and response to treatment [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In the last decade, numerous high-scale genomic profiling studies were performed to elucidate the biology of GBM. In addition, large scale functional proteomics studies were performed, where ENCODE software developments were used to integrate RNA-Seq and its correlation to protein expression, and regulation in GBM patients [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The proteogenomic initiative runs as a HUPO (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.HUPO.org">www.HUPO.org</ext-link>) disease initiative, recently reported on [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In a comprehensive analysis by The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) project, dysregulation of p53, Rb and receptor tyrosine kinase pathways were identified [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Recently, several glioma lineage and GBM subtype specific molecular alterations were described, indicating a diversity amid similar histological types. The identification of isocitrate dehydrogenase 1 and 2 (<italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">IDH2</italic>) mutations was a breakthrough in the field of GBM research. Soon after it became an important diagnostic and prognostic marker in gliomas [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. To date, GBM can be divided into IDH-wildtype and mutant based on their IDH status [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic> together with Alpha Thalassemia/Mental Retardation Syndrome X-linked (<italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> status are reliable diagnostic and prognostic markers for the astrocytoma lineage and they are also relevant in GBM stratification. Beyond that, GBM was further divided into four molecular subtypes: Classical (CL), Mesenchymal (ME), Proneural (PN) and Neural (NE), based on their chromosomal structural alterations, copy number alterations (CNAs), point mutation status and gene expression profiles [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>Although the efficiency of PARP1 inhibition was already established in GBM, its molecular characteristics and prognostic role regarding molecular heterogeneity is not fully understood. The aim of our study is to analyse the role of PARP1 using the latest genomic datasets of the TCGA, and an independent clinical cohort (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, we hereby present the first comprehensive study that evaluate I) <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> CNAs and mRNA expressions, II) its usefulness in GBM subtype prognosis, and III) the associations of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> with specific astrocytoma molecular markers. Finally, IV) we demonstrate a close link between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> that can serve as a prognostic and diagnostic marker for GBM.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The overview of the analysis strategy for <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> characterisation used in this study</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>Genomic and transcriptomic characteristics of PARP1 in GBM</title><p>We first analysed <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mutations and copy numbers of GBM specimens in the TCGA database via cBioPortal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbioportal.org/public-portal/">http://www.cbioportal.org/public-portal/</ext-link>). Only two <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> somatic mutations were observed (V948I and A709T) in GBM. Information on CNA data was available for 562 GBM samples. <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> exhibited a low-level gain and heterozygous deletions in more than 14% and 6% of the cases, respectively. On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> amplification was infrequent (0.35%), however homozygous deletion was not observed.</p><p>Next, we examined the relative <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA levels in GBM. The database included 135 adult GBM cases with DNA sequencing, CNAs and mRNA expression data according to the screening criteria detailed in Materials and Methods. In addition, an increased expression was observed (z-score ≥1) in 20.74% (28/135) of the cases.</p><p>Lastly, for determining the possible regulation mechanisms associated with <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression values, we evaluated the correlation between CNAs and mRNA levels. A significant expression difference was found between heterozygous deletion and diploid (p=0.005), gain and diploid (p&lt;0.001), as well as heterozygous deletion and gain statuses (p&lt;0.001). These results demonstrate a close link between the copy number and gene expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>PARP1 copy number and expression levels in GBM subtypes and glioma WHO grades</title><p>Association between copy number alterations (CNAs) and mRNA expressions of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in GBM <bold>(A)</bold>. <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression level z-scores in different grades of astrocytomas <bold>(B)</bold> and in GBM subtypes <bold>(C)</bold>. The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme (WHO grade IV) &amp; brain lower grade glioma (WHO grade II &amp; III) TCGA datasets were used for the analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels are increased in higher grade astrocytomas</title><p>To examine the significance of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in malignant transformation of astrocytomas, the Brain Lower Grade Glioma (TCGA, Provisional) dataset was investigated through cBioPortal. Altogether, CNA data of 169 lower grade tumours (55 grade II and 114 grade III astrocytomas) were added to the 562 GBM samples. We found, that grade II tumours have the lowest CNA rate (0.036) followed by grade III astrocytomas (0.167) and grade IV GBM (0.215), and high <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> copy numbers correlate with higher histological grades (p&lt;0.001) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Homozygous deletions occurred in only 0.1% of the grade II tumours. <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> amplification was also rare, found in only 0.3% of GBMs. In total, mRNA expression data were available for 97 lower-grade astrocytomas (29 grade II and 67 grade III tumours). Increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA levels were found in the high-grade tumours as opposed to grade II astrocytomas (GII vs. GIII, p=0.003, and GII vs. GIV, p&lt;0.001). Although <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression was increased in both grade III and IV tumours, there were no significant changes between those two grades (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> CNAs showed significant differences in distribution among WHO grades (p&lt;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Mutation status of <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> genes are associated with <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expressions</title><p>We evaluated the <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression signature in the context of the genetic heterogeneity of GBM. We analysed the association between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels and the mutation status of astrocytoma lineage specific genes such as <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>. We discovered that samples carrying mutated <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> (p=0.006) and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> (p=0.015) were associated with higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression levels (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The IDH status of GBMs did not show any association with PARP1 expression. The TCGA dataset contains only the IDH and <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> status of the tumours (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). To examine the association between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> status, cases were classified into wildtype (n=92) and mutant <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> (n=43) tumours. Next, mutant <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> samples were further divided into missense (n=33) and null (n=10) mutations in order to investigate the mutation effects on <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expressions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression was higher in <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutated cases (p=0.015) than in its wildtype counterpart. Importantly, there was no significant changes between missense and null <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Correlations between the mRNA expressions of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> and key molecular glioma markers</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Key glioma markers</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">N</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Meanz-score</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">± SE<sup>1</sup></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">p-Value</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">95% CI<sup>2</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.006</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.124</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.367</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mutant</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.375</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">IDH</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.457</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mutant</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.015</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.943</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mutant</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.550</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(Significant p-values are marked in bold.)</p><p><sup>1</sup>Standard error; <sup>2</sup>confidence of interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Patient characteristics with available sequencing, CNA, and mRNA expression data</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain lower grade glioma (TCGA, provisional) (n=97)</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma multiforme (TCGA, provisional) (n=135)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis age (years)</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.31 ± 13.14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.59±13.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(range: 20-74)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(range: 21-89)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Overall survival (months)</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.76 ± 22.17</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33 ± 12.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>WHO grade</bold><sup>1</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> II</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> IV</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mutant</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">IDH</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mutant</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> status</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Missense mut.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Null mut.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wild-type</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>WHO grade was unknown in one sample.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Association between <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene status and <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression in glioblastoma</title><p><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression was higher in mutated <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> cases <bold>(A)</bold>, but only missense <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations showed significant difference compared to wild-type <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold>. The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme, provisional dataset was used for the analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Immunohistochemical expression of PARP1 is correlated with ATRX and p53</title><p>We immunohistochemically studied PARP1 in a series of GBMs to evaluate its potential differential expression in association with key markers at protein levels. PARP1 staining was primarily localized in the nucleus of tumour cells, consistent with previous studies [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Ninety percent (54/60) of all cases were PARP1 positive, while 10% (6/60) were negative. The relationships between PARP1 and ATRX, IDH1 and p53, respectively, were also evaluated. In our clinical cohort, PARP1 IHC expression was significantly associated with the expression of p53 (p=0.0281) and ATRX (p=0.002) but not with that of IDH1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Immunohistochemical staining pattern for various markers in a clinical cohort of glioblastoma</title><p>Immunohistochemical positive and negative staining for IDH1<sup>R132H</sup>, positive and negative staining patterns of ATRX and p53, high and low nuclear expression of the PARP1. Original magnification: x200. Scale bar: 100 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Immunohistochemical expression of PARP1 and its relationship with key molecular glioma markers</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">PARP1 IHC expression</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">p-Value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3894</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mean ± SD*</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.69 ± 6.45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.52 ± 9.18</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p53 expression</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.0281</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IDH1 expression</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6316</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ATRX expression</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Negative</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.0020</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(Significant p-values are marked in bold).</p><p>*Standard deviation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA levels are increased in PN and CL GBM subtypes</title><p>In the exploration of the subtype-specific role of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in GBM, we identified that PN and CL subtypes showed an increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). More specifically, PN (mean z-score: 0.801) and CL (mean z-score: 0.375) subtypes have the highest average <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA level, followed by ME (mean z-score: -0.121) and NE (mean z-score: -1.049), respectively.</p><p>Simultaneously, we also assessed whether <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> CNAs were related to specific GBM subtypes. CNAs information on transcriptional subtypes were available for 475 cases. We found that the PN subtype had the highest CNA rate (0.275), followed by the ME (0.226), NE (0.224), and CL (0.129) subtypes. <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> copy number gains were observed in all subtypes: ME (4.4%), PN (4.4%), CL (2.9%) and NE (2.3%). Heterozygous deletion of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> was found in 3.4% of ME GBMs. PARP1 amplification occurred only in CL and ME subtypes (0.2-0.2%) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>High PARP1 expression is associated with shorter survival in CL GBM subtype</title><p>To assess the clinical relevance of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in GBM, we examined the association between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression and the overall survival in TCGA GBM samples. The mean overall survival (OS) of the TCGA patients was 13.3 months. GBM cases were assigned into PARP1-high (n=68) and PARP1-low (n=67) groups, using median <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression z-score as cut off value. Although patients with PARP1-low expression had longer survival, there were no statistically significant differences observed between the groups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Kaplan–Meier plot of overall survival (OS) stratified by high and low <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression in GBM (A) and in Classical GBM subgroup (B). The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme, provisional dataset was used for the analysis. (Significance was assessed by the log-rank method.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>The mean OS of TCGA patients across different GBM subtypes was the following: CL=12.7; PN=19.8; ME=11.7, and NE=7.7 months. Kaplan-Meier survival analysis indicated that patients of the PARP1-low group had statistically significant shorter overall survival time compared with their PARP1-high counterpart (p=0.031) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). No significant differences were noted in the survival values between the PARP1-low, and -high expression cohorts of other GBM subtypes.</p><p>We also investigated whether <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic>'s genetic signatures were related to the clinicopathological characteristics of GBM patients. No significant associations were observed between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> status and age and sex (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title>High <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> level together with wildtype <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> predict a shorter survival in GBM</title><p>We analysed cumulative effects of p53 and PARP1 on survival with GBM. TCGA samples were further classified according to their <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutation status: I) <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic><sup>mut</sup>/PARP1-high (n=29); II) <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic><sup>mut</sup>/PARP1-low (n=14); III) <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic><sup>WT</sup>/PARP1-high (n=39); and IV) <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic><sup>WT</sup>/PARP1-low (n=53). We found, that GBM patients with wild-type <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene and PARP1-high level have a shorter survival (p=0.039) compared to the other groups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Kaplan–Meier plot of overall survival (OS) stratified by the combination of high and low <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutation status in GBM. The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme, provisional dataset was used for the analysis. (Significance was assessed by the log-rank method.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_8"><title><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> status is associated with the p53 pathway</title><p>To extend our investigations, the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> status and the p53 pathway (<italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic> (p21), <italic toggle="yes">MDM2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> (p14), and <italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic>) was also examined. Regarding mRNA expressions, PARP1 displayed significant correlation with <italic toggle="yes">TP53, CDKN1A</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). Accordingly, mRNA expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> (p=0.003), and <italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic> (p=0.004) were increased in PARP1-high, and <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic> (p=0.009) was increased in PARP1-low GBMs (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels showed correlation with copy number alterations of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic> genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). More specifically, <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels were decreased in homozygously deleted <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> (p=0.013) cases, and increased in cases with <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic> gain (p=0.026) when we compared CNAs to the diploid variants of the genes. However, there was no significant association between <italic toggle="yes">MDM2</italic> CNAs and <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Relationship between mRNA expressions of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> and components of the p53 pathway</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Genes</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Kendall's tau b</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Spearman's rho</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cor. coef.</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Value</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cor. coef.</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.187</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.001</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.272</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.001</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.629</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.587</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MDM2</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.111</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.168</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.953</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.004</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.961</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.004</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.004</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.005</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.007</italic></bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Association between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> and p53 pathway in glioblastoma</title><p>A gene-gene interaction network presenting the correlation between PARP1 and the general members of p53 pathway in GBM according to mRNA expressions <bold>(A)</bold>. The associations of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression levels with <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic> copy number alterations in GBM <bold>(B)</bold>. The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme, provisional dataset was used for the analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g007.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>The impact of PARP1-low and high mRNA expression levels in the p53 pathway</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Genes</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">PARP1 levels<sup>1</sup></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1">p-Value</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1">± SE<sup>2</sup></th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1">95% CI<sup>3</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.227</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.009</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.117</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.029</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.560</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.387</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MDM2</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.363</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.240</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.819</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.472</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.717</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.614</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.366</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.718</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.151</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.647</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.278</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.003</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.828</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.178</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.520</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.052</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">0.004</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.787</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.150</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(Significant p-values are marked in bold.)</p><p><sup>1</sup>Mean mRNA z-scores; <sup>2</sup>standard error; <sup>3</sup>confidence of interval.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>The impact of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels on p53 pathway-related genes in glioblastoma</title><p>The mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic> was increased in PARP1-high group, whereas <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic> (p21) mRNA expression was higher in PARP1-low group. The TCGA glioblastoma multiforme, provisional dataset was used for the analysis. Level of significance: * (p &lt; 0.05), ** (p &lt; 0.01), and *** (p &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Glioblastoma is one of the most assiduously studied cancer, yet the majority of patients are still resistant to the conventional therapies [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Thus, the identification of novel biomarkers to improve the management of GBM is an ongoing and challenging task [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although PARP1 inhibition is a potential therapeutic target in GBM [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], its efficiency in the context of heterogeneity is unknown. Therefore, we performed an integrated bioinformatic analysis to evaluate <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic>'s genetic signature, and prognostic role regarding the molecular diversity of the tumour. Moreover, the correlations between PARP1 and three routinely used glioma markers detected by IHC were also tested in a clinical GBM cohort.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> is overexpressed in a variety of cancers [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], including glioblastoma [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression has been reported in paediatric high-grade astrocytomas, medulloblastoma, and ependymoma [<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Furthermore, in GBM stem cells (GSCs), the combination of PARPi and TMZ may represent a valuable strategy to reverse the stem cells’ chemo-resistance. <italic toggle="yes">Tentori et al</italic>. found, that PARPi together with TMZ exerted synergistic anti-tumour effects in eight out of ten GSC lines. Moreover, the dose reduction of TMZ is associated with the sensitivity of each cell line to PARPi as single agent [<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Recent bioinformatic analysis of TCGA datasets revealed that <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression is restricted to higher grade tumours, and partially caused by genomic gain. Our findings underline that PARP1 is a marker candidate of higher-grade in astrocytomas, presumably because higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression facilitates the repair of damaged DNA and, thereby, overcomes the genetic instability characteristics of tumour cells [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>Given this complex heterogeneous nature of GBM, it is relevant to investigate PARP1's associations with key molecular markers [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The importance of <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations in the early development and the progression of astrocytic glioma lineage is well-known [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These markers also have treatment and prognostic relevance [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and their mutation status can distinguish astrocytomas from oligodendrogliomas, as well as secondary from primary GBM [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression can occur in both IDH-wild type and mutated GBMs. Although there was no statistically proven association between PARP1 expression and IDH mutation status, a recent study reported that 2-hydroxyglutarate produced by mutated IDH induces PARP inhibitor sensitivity in patient-derived primary glioma cells and genetically matched tumour xenografts [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], which has therapeutic implications. On the other hand, higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression levels were tightly associated with <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations. <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> alterations occur in the vast majority of lower-grade astrocytomas and <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic>-mutated (secondary) GBMs [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Somatic mutations in <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> play important roles in gliomas, particularly in the tumorigenesis of lower grade astrocytomas and <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic>-mutated GBMs [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Considering that the inhibition of PARP1 enzyme is dose-dependent [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], our results indicate that PARP inhibitors could be more effective in <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutated tumours, where <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels are usually increased.</p><p>Although high-throughput technologies are widely used for diagnostic purposes, there is still a need to improve the IHC-based stratification of GBM with the integration of molecular data [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Consistent with a previous study [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], PARP1 IHC expression was observed in the majority of clinical GBM cases. To date, the IHC detection of key molecular markers is possible and highly informative: I) using <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic><sup>R132H</sup> mutation specific antibody [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]; II) most <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> mutations result in undetectable <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> expression by IHC [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; and III) mutated p53 protein accumulates in the nucleus of tumour cells [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Furthermore, we have demonstrated that IHC expression of PARP1 has an inverse correlation with <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic>, and linear correlation with p53 staining. These observations suggest that PARP1 IHC expression along with p53 overexpression and <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> loss can be promising predictive markers for PARPi in GBM.</p><p>This study investigates for the first time, to our knowledge, the genomic signature and prognostic significance of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in GBM subtypes. We hereby present evidence, that <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> can distinguish PN and CL from the other subtypes as increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression was increased in these two subtypes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Our data showed that high <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels were associated with shorter survival in the CL group. It was previously presented that CL GBM is characterized by <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> amplification and wild-type <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>, whereas PN is characterized by both <italic toggle="yes">IDH1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations and <italic toggle="yes">PDGFRA</italic> amplification [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These results indicate that PARP1 and p53 are suitable markers to distinguish PN and CL subtypes, and have a prognostic relevance in GBM.</p><p>In our previous study, we demonstrated that p53 immunopositivity correlates with <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutational status, except for certain mutation types [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In GBM, we found that PARP1 IHC expression is correlated with p53 positive cases. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">PAPR1</italic> mRNA levels were higher in samples with <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations. Importantly, the detection of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> null mutations is not accurate by IHC due to the truncated protein [<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Beside the increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels in <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutated cases, there was no statistical difference between missense and null mutated samples.</p><p>Both PARP1 and p53 play important roles in maintaining genomic integrity [<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Several studies have shown that genomic instability is usually correlated with poor prognosis [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It has been previously reported that high level of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression is often associated with poor overall survival in cancer [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although there is a trend towards shorter survival of PARP1-high patients as compared to PARP1-low patients, no significant differences were observed when all GBMs were considered. Interestingly, we found a significantly shorter survival in PARP-high patients with wildtype <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) – possibly because not only <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations but also an impaired p53 pathway can facilitate tumour progression [<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The p53 signalling pathway mediates several cellular processes including growth arrest, angiogenesis, apoptosis, and DNA repair [<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is widely accepted, that the progression and recurrence of glioblastoma is related to p53 pathway abnormalities in 87% of primary GBM [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. To gain insights into the interaction between p53 and PARP1, we investigated and found that <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> showed association with <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> deletions and <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic> gain (both <italic toggle="yes">CDKN2A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MDM4</italic> are components of the p53 pathway) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). These two genetic alterations are frequent in GBM, and result in abnormal p53 signalling in tumour cells [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> was negatively correlated with <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic>, which is a downstream member of the p53 cascade involved in the p53-mediated G1 arrest. This observation suggests that down-regulated <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A</italic> cannot inhibit the Cyclin E-CDK2 complex in GBMs with higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels. Consequently, it can result in an augmented cell-cycle activity and absence of apoptosis [<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Furthermore, it has been reported, that low levels of 53BP1 could predict resistance to PARP inhibitors, because 53BP1 depletion reduces the cytotoxicity of PARP inhibitors [<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Consistent with this notion, we found an overall low expression of <italic toggle="yes">TP53BP1</italic> in GBM with higher levels in high-PARP1 cases.</p><p>In conclusion, <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> expression was increased in GBM at both mRNA and protein levels. To best of our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate the relevance of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> in the context of specific molecular markers and subtypes of GBM. We have demonstrated that increased <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels show positive correlation with increasing tumour grades in gliomas Higher <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression levels were associated with <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations. An IHC analysis in an independent clinical cohort also confirmed this relationship. Our results revealed that <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> levels were increased in the PN and CL subtypes and correlated with shorter survival in CL GBMs. The observed subtype-specificity suggests that PARP1, together with p53, is not only a diagnostic marker to differentiate PN and CL subtypes, but also a predictive marker of shorter survival and poor therapy response in the CL subgroup. We also pointed out that there is a close interplay between PARP1 and the members of the p53 pathway in GBM. Our results support the therapeutic role of PARP inhibitors in high-grade gliomas with the caveat that molecular heterogeneity needs to be taken into account.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4_1"><title>TCGA datasets</title><p>Genetic alterations of <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic>, somatic mutation, CNA, and mRNA expression (z-score, RNA Seq V2 RSEM) data were collected from two TCGA cohorts: Glioblastoma Multiforme (TCGA, Provisional) and Brain Lower Grade Glioma (TCGA, Provisional) using the cBioPortal for Cancer Genomics (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbioportal.org">www.cbioportal.org</ext-link>). The relative expression of each gene and the gene expression distribution in a reference population were examined. The reference population was, either, all tumours that are diploid for the gene in question or, when available, have a normal adjacent tissue. The returned value indicates the number of standard deviations away from the mean of expression in the reference population (z-score) [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In cBioPortal, copy numbers are computed using the GISTIC (Genomic Identification of Significant Targets in Cancer) algorithm, which identifies the putative copy number level as follows: I) high-level amplification, II) low-level gain, III) diploid, IV) heterozygous deletion, or V) homozygous deletion [<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p>Clinicopathological data for each patient including: age, sex, and survival time, was compiled from the TCGA portal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tcga-data.nci.nih.gov">www.tcga-data.nci.nih.gov</ext-link>) and tabulated with genetic data. Cases for the analysis were selected according to the following criteria: I) only patients older than 18 years with available clinical data were included, considering that paediatric GBM represents a distinct molecular and genetic background (see reviews [<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]); II) oligodendrogliomas and mixed gliomas were omitted; III) tumours with complete genomic data (available somatic mutations, CNA, and mRNA expression information) were selected for the <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression analysis. Altogether, 135 WHO grade IV glioblastoma and 96 lower grade astrocytomas (grade II &amp; grade III) were assembled for the present analyses. The clinicopathological parameters, and key marker status of the cases are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. GBM subtypes were accessible on 119 cases, with the following distribution: 57 ME, 43 CL, 16 PN, and 5 NE.</p><p>The relationships between <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> mRNA expression and the overall patient survival were analysed by dividing the samples into PARP1-low and PARP1-high expression groups, based on median mRNA expression z-score in TCGA dataset.</p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title>Patients with GBM</title><p>Samples were obtained from 60 patients (30 males and 30 female) diagnosed with GBM between 2006 and 2014 at the first author's affiliated institute. The mean age at diagnosis was 58.47 ± 9.03 years (range 30.21- 76.67 years). After surgical removal, sections were cut and stained with haematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E) from formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded (FFPE) blocks. All the histopathological specimens were reviewed and diagnosed by a neuropathologist (TH) according to World Health Organization (WHO) criteria [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This research protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the University of Debrecen.</p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>Immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis was carried out as previously described [<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Briefly, the staining was performed on 4-μm-thick FFPE sections using the manufacturers’ protocols. At first, sections were deparaffinised in xylene and rehydrated in a graded series of ethanol. Heat-induced epitope retrieval was performed utilizing citrate buffer (pH 6.0). After blocking endogenous peroxidase activity, sections were incubated with primary antibodies (anti-p53, anti-ATRX, anti-IDH1, and anti-PARP1) for 6 hours at room temperature. Specifications of the antibodies are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>. Visualization was achieved with SuperSensitive<sup>™</sup> One-step Polymer-HRP Detection System on Leica Bond Max<sup>™</sup> automated IHC stainer, employing 3,3′-diaminobenzidine (DAB), then followed by counterstaining with hematoxylin. Adequate positive and negative controls (with omission of the primary antibodies) were included in the immunohistochemical experiments.</p><table-wrap id="T6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Specifications of the antibodies used for immunohistochemical staining</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibodies</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalogue numbers</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manufacturer</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilutions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>anti-ATRX</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPA001906</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>anti-IDH1</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DIA-H09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dianova</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>anti-p53</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DO-7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dako</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>anti-PARP1</bold></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ab6079</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abcam</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Cases with ≥10 % stained cells were defined as positive for IDH1 and p53 [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A cut-off point of 10 % was considered for the evaluation of presence or absence of nuclear ATRX [<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. All FFPE sections were scored in a blinded manner by two independent observers (MC &amp; RH). The expression of all IHC markers was determined semi-quantitatively. Ten randomly selected high-power fields (or the entire tumour if the sample was smaller) were examined in each neurosurgical specimen.</p><p>The PARP1 expression was evaluated based on the distribution of positive cells. The percentage of positivity was scored as follows: “0” (&lt;5%, negative), “1” (5–25%, sporadic), “2” (25–50%, focal), or “3” (&gt;50%, diffuse). For the statistical analysis, negative and sporadic staining was combined as low PARP1 staining and focal and diffuse nuclear staining as high PARP1 staining.</p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title>Statistical and data analyses</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed using R software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) and SPSS 21.0 software (SPSS Inc., IL, USA). Comparisons between groups were calculated with Pearson's Chi-square (χ2) test for categorical variables applying Yates' correction when required. The association between mRNA levels was measured using the Kendall's tau and Spearmann's correlation test. The difference in mRNA expression levels, between groups was calculated using a two-tailed Student's t-test. Kaplan–Meier method and Log-Rank (Mantel-Cox) test were used for overall survival measurements. Differences were significant when p&lt;0.05.</p><p>Gene-gene interaction network to demonstrate p53 pathway and <italic toggle="yes">PARP1</italic> interaction was generated by the GeneMania Cytoscape 3.4.0 application. Physical, co-expression and gene-gene interactions were evaluated [<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS AND FIGURES</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-08-46348-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2090" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>The Authors do not have any conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>GRANT SUPPORT</bold></p><p>This study was supported by the New National Excellence Program of the Ministry of Human Capacities; ÚNKP-16-3 (BM), the Hungarian Brain Research Program (NAP) – Grants No. KTIA_13_NAP-A-II/7 and KTIA_13_NAP-A-V/3, AGR_PIAC_13-1-2013-0008, and GINOP-2.3.2-15-2016-00043 (TH &amp; ÁK).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular heterogeneity in glioblastoma: potential clinical implications</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25785247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2015.00055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4347445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyarzún</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemoresistance in high-grade gliomas: relevance of adenosine signalling in stem-like cells of glioblastoma multiforme</article-title><source>Curr Drug Targets</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25174341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldape</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zadeh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reifenberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Deimling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glioblastoma: pathology, molecular mechanisms and markers</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source><year>2015</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00401-015-1432-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murnyák</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Csonka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegyi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Méhes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klekner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Occurrence and molecular pathology of high grade gliomas]. [Article in Hungarian]</article-title><source>Ideggyogy Sz</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24358686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nile</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyndman</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaze</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mairs</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation in vitro of PARP-1 inhibitors, rucaparib and olaparib, as radiosensitisers for the treatment of neuroblastoma</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>621</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27515310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-016-2656-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4982014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doubrovina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moynahan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP inhibitors in clinical use induce genomic instability in normal human cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0159341</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27428646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0159341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4948780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacza</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horváth</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komjáti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabó</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busija</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP inhibition improves the effectiveness of neural stem cell transplantation in experimental brain trauma</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12851710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Görlach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benyo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacza</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harkany</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of neuronal nitric oxide synthase-mediated activation of poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase in traumatic brain injury: neuroprotection by 3-aminobenzamide</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2003</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14580948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0306-4522(03)00482-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reina-San-Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dantzer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerases in double-strand break repair: focus on PARP1, PARP2 and PARP3</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25017100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.yexcr.2014.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livraghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP inhibitors in the management of breast cancer: current data and future prospects</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>188</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26268938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12916-015-0425-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4535298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csonka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murnyák</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szepesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurucz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klekner</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 (PARP1) and p53 labelling index correlates with tumour grade in meningiomas</article-title><source>Folia Neuropathol</source><year>2014</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5114/fn.2014.43782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domagala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huzarski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gugala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domagala</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP-1 expression in breast cancer including BRCA1-associated, triple negative and basal-like tumors: possible implications for PARP-1 inhibitor therapy</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2011</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21409392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10549-011-1441-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohgaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dessen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jourde</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Patre</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schüler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Probst-Hensch</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiorka</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baeza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonekawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic pathways to glioblastoma: a population-based study</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>6892</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-04-1337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostovenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichti</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenyö</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbloom</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omenn</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LaBaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroes</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhlén</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hober</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of ENCODE resources to characterize novel proteoforms and missing proteins in the human proteome</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25369122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/pr500564q</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichti</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shavkunov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostovenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulman</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezhilarasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroes</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskal</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenyö</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oksuz</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated chromosome 19 transcriptomic and proteomic data sets derived from glioma cancer stem-cell lines</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24266786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/pr400786s</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omenn</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Na</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Chromosome-Centric Human Proteome Project for cataloging proteins encoded in the genome</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22398612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.2152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network</collab></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive genomic characterization defines human glioblastoma genes and core pathways</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>455</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature07385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2671642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angenendt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mankoo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallia</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLendon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An integrated genomic analysis of human glioblastoma multiforme</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1164382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2820389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reifenberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Deimling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figarella-Branger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavenee</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohgaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiestler</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleihues</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 2016 World Health Organization classification of tumors of the central nervous system: a summary</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27157931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00401-016-1545-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akutsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemistry on IDH 1/2, ATRX, p53 and Ki-67 substitute molecular genetic testing and predict patient prognosis in grade III adult diffuse gliomas</article-title><source>Brain Tumor Pathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26968173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10014-016-0260-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killela</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitman</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaphy</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Wilde</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosemberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oba-Shinjo</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bettegowda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipp</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Frequent ATRX, CIC, FUBP1 and IDH1 mutations refine the classification of malignant gliomas</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22869205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3443254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verhaak</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoadley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purdom</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Kelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated genomic analysis identifies clinically relevant subtypes of glioblastoma characterized by abnormalities in PDGFRA, IDH1, EGFR, and NF1</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20129251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ccr.2009.12.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2818769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calogero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Condorelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraggetta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>La Corte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridolfo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP-1 protein expression in glioblastoma multiforme</article-title><source>Eur J Histochem</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>e9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22472897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4081/ejh.2012.e9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3352138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vuurden</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulleman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedekind</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandertop</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Würdinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noske</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspers</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cloos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP inhibition sensitizes childhood high grade glioma, medulloblastoma and ependymoma to radiation</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>984</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22184287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3282104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinschmidt-DeMasters</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP1 expression in pediatric central nervous system tumors</article-title><source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19533660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/pbc.22141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tentori</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci-Vitiani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciccarone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelacchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Runci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pallini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caiafa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological inhibition of poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 modulates resistance of human glioblastoma stem cells to temozolomide</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24593254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2407-14-151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3975727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyuchenko</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotova</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulaeva</surname><given-names>OI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirpichnikov</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Studitskiy</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP1 Inhibitors: antitumor drug design</article-title><source>Acta Naturae</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4610162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulkowski</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corso</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purshouse</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fons</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra-Gorur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2-Hydroxyglutarate produced by neomorphic IDH mutations suppresses homologous recombination and induces PARP inhibitor sensitivity</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>eaal2463</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28148839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scitranslmed.aal2463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5435119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haince</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Déry</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendzel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP1-dependent kinetics of recruitment of MRE11 and NBS1 proteins to multiple DNA damage sites</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M706734200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Mercier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Neve</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trepant</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rorive</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decaestecker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simplified approach for the molecular classification of glioblastomas</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e45475</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0045475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3445522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLendon</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigner</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A monoclonal antibody IMab-1 specifically recognizes IDH1 R132H, the most common glioma-derived mutation</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2009</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19818334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2788025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skardelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonzheim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mühleisen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schittenhelm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATRX immunostaining predicts IDH and H3F3A status in gliomas</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol Commun</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27311324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40478-016-0331-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4910252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murnyák</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical correlates of TP53 somatic mutations in cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>64910</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.11912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27626311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5323125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz de Almodovar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Murcia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP-1 modifies the effectiveness of p 53-mediated DNA damage response</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1108</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1205169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesierska-Gadek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranftler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological ageing: role of p53 and PARP-1 tumor suppressors in the regulation of terminal senescence</article-title><source>J Physiol Pharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>77</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stracquadanio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grawenda</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeron-Medina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Giner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goding</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cygan</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The importance of p53 pathway genetics in inherited and somatic cancer genomes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27009395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc.2016.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6854702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yfantis</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of breast cancer outcome with status of p53 and MDM2 SNP309</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2006</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>911</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jnci/djj245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The p53 pathway: positive and negative feedback loops</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2899</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.onc.1208615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>53BP1 depletion causes PARP inhibitor resistance in ATM-deficient breast cancer cells</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>725</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27613518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-016-2754-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5017014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dogrusoz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antipin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reva</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cBio cancer genomics portal: an open platform for exploring multidimensional cancer genomics data</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22588877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-12-0095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3956037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dogrusoz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dresdner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative analysis of complex cancer genomics and clinical profiles using the cBioPortal</article-title><source>Sci Signal</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>pl1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23550210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scisignal.2004088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4160307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic signatures of pediatric high-grade glioma: no longer a one-act play</article-title><source>Semin Radiat Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25219808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.semradonc.2014.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4170681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartzentruber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korshunov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontebasso</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quang</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tönjes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hovestadt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kool</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Driver mutations in histone H3. 3 and chromatin remodelling genes in paediatric glioblastoma</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>482</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22286061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature10833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csonka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murnyák</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szepesi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bencze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bognár</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klekner</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hortobágyi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of candidate immunohistochemical prognostic markers of meningioma recurrence</article-title><source>Folia Neuropathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27543769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5114/fn.2016.60088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montojo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuberi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GeneMANIA: fast gene network construction and function prediction for Cytoscape</article-title><source>F1000Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25254104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12688/f1000research.4572.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4168749</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>