
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Mol Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Mol. Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">835</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sfesd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8902617</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Molecular Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0952-5041</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1479-6813</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Society for Endocrinology Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5148799</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5148799.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5148799</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5148799</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856505</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/JME-16-0186</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JME160186</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptomic changes throughout post-hatch development in <italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic> pituitary</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="lrh">E M PRITCHETT and others</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Chicken pituitary transcriptome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchett</surname><given-names initials="EM">Elizabeth M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names initials="SJ">Susan J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Carl J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Animal and Food Science</institution><addr-line>University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware, USA</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Animal Science</institution><addr-line>Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa, USA</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence should be addressed to E M Pritchett; Email: <email>empritch@udel.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">280713</issue-id><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-14 02:25:16.890"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017 The authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The authors</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><inline-graphic xlink:href="88x31.jpg"/> This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jme-58-43.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="jme-58-43.pdf"/><abstract><p>The pituitary gland is a neuroendocrine organ that works closely with the hypothalamus to affect multiple processes within the body including the stress response, metabolism, growth and immune function. Relative tissue expression (rEx) is a transcriptome analysis method that compares the genes expressed in a particular tissue to the genes expressed in all other tissues with available data. Using rEx, the aim of this study was to identify genes that are uniquely or more abundantly expressed in the pituitary when compared to all other collected chicken tissues. We applied rEx to define genes enriched in the chicken pituitaries at days 21, 22 and 42 post-hatch. rEx analysis identified 25 genes shared between all time points, 295 genes shared between days 21 and 22 and 407 genes unique to day 42. The 25 genes shared by all time points are involved in morphogenesis and general nervous tissue development. The 295 shared genes between days 21 and 22 are involved in neurogenesis and nervous system development and differentiation. The 407 unique day 42 genes are involved in pituitary development, endocrine system development and other hormonally related gene ontology terms. Overall, rEx analysis indicates a focus on nervous system/tissue development at days 21 and 22. By day 42, in addition to nervous tissue development, there is expression of genes involved in the endocrine system, possibly for maturation and preparation for reproduction. This study defines the transcriptome of the chicken pituitary gland and aids in understanding the expressed genes critical to its function and maturation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>chicken</kwd><kwd>pituitary</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>development</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The avian pituitary gland is a neuroendocrine organ that works closely with the hypothalamus to regulate multiple processes within the body including the stress response, reproduction, metabolism, growth and immune function. The hypothalamus receives neuronal and endocrine signals from the brain and body and synthesizes releasing hormones that are sent to the pituitary gland to either inhibit or stimulate the production of several hormones that will directly affect other tissues (i.e. growth hormone (GH)) or stimulate the release of further protein products (i.e. adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH)). The posterior pituitary gland, or the neurohypophysis, is composed of nervous tissue and is connected to the hypothalamus via the median eminence. Neurosecretory terminals within the posterior pituitary store and release arginine, vasotocin (AVT) and mesotocin that are synthesized in the supraoptic nucleus and paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus, respectively. Releasing hormones synthesized by the hypothalamus are transported to the anterior pituitary gland through the hypophyseal blood portal system and regulate the production and release of various endocrine hormones (ACTH, GH, LH, FSH and TSH). Relative tissue expression analysis (rEx) was used to compare the chicken pituitary gland transcriptome to the transcriptome of all other tissues our laboratory has analyzed in the broiler chicken across three time points: days 21, 22 and 42 post-hatch. Previous work focusing on the morphometric changes of broiler chickens post-hatch identified two distinct growth periods: one from day of hatch through day 14, and one from day 14 to day 42 or typical market age (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). The days discussed fall into the second growth phase. These days were also chosen as part of a larger heat stress study conducted in our laboratory. The pituitary gland is a complex tissue in that it contains many different cell types, and signals are sent through neural endocrine, paracrine and autocrine networks. The messages received by the pituitary gland lead to many changes within the tissue and results in tissue plasticity. The results of this analysis identify the expression levels of genes in the pituitary gland that are either more abundant or are unique to this particular tissue at specific points in development. These data confer a better understanding of the genes and pathways that are critical to the function of the pituitary gland.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Animal housing and tissue collection</title><p>Male Ross 708 broiler chickens (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) were obtained on the day of hatch from Mountaire Hatchery (Millsboro, DE, USA) and placed in large-colony houses on the University of Delaware farm (Newark, DE, USA). Husbandry and management followed all standards and procedures as approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee (AACUC #(27) 03-12-14R). Standard broiler feed (corn-soy), which met all NRC requirements (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">National Research Council 1994</xref>), and water were supplied, and animals had <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> access throughout the trial. Birds were humanely killed and the pituitaries were collected on 21, 22 and 42 days post-hatch as part of a larger study. Whole pituitaries were placed into liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C until further analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA isolation, cDNA synthesis, Rnaseq library preparation and qRT-PCR validation</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from whole pituitary glands (8–20 mg depending on age) from individual birds using the Qiagen RNeasy Mini Kit (Germantown, MD, USA). Total RNA quantity was measured using a Qubit Fluorometer, and quality was assessed by fragment analysis. A total of 15 pituitary glands from day 21, 10 from day 22 and 10 from day 42 were used for individual Rnaseq library preparation using the Illumina Stranded RNAseq kit (San Diego, CA, USA). All 35 samples were sequenced at the Delaware Biotechnology Institute (DBI) Sequencing and Genotyping center using the Illumina HiSeq 2500 sequencer. All libraries were sequenced to a depth of 20–30 million reads per library. The reads were aligned to the <italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>, ver 4 genome sequence, identified and counted using software packages Bowtie, Tophat and Cufflinks, and expression levels were reported as fragments per kilobase of gene per million mapped reads (FPKM) values for further analysis (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Trapnell <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Langmead &amp; Salzberg 2012</xref>). Three biological replicates for each day (day 21, 22 and 42) were used for cDNA synthesis using the SuperScript First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR (Invitrogen). cDNA concentration was determined using the Qubit Fluorometer and diluted to 30 ng/µL for PCR. qRT-PCR was performed using Fast SYBR green master mix (Applied Biosystems) on the Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR system for the following genes: glycoprotein alpha subunit (<italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic>), follicle-stimulating hormone beta (<italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic>), growth hormone (<italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>), proopiomelanocortin (<italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic>), prolactin (<italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic>) and thyroid-stimulating hormone beta (<italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic>). Each qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>) was performed in triplicate, and analysis was completed using the delta Ct method. All sequencing data generated in the current project have been uploaded in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus application and are accessible through GEO series, accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE89297">GSE89297</ext-link>.
<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used for qRT-PCR transcriptome validation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Forward primer</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reverse primer</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GCAACGTGCTGTGTAGCAAAG 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ TGGTTCTCTATCTTCACATTGCCTT 3′</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ CGTACAGGGTAGAGCCAACGA 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GGCCCTCAAAAGGCTGAAC 3′</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">GH</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GCTTCAAGAAGGATCTGCACAA 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GCGCCGGCACTTCATC 3′</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GCTACGGCGGCTTCATGA 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ CGATGACGTTTTTGAACAGA 3′</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ TTGGGCGGGTTCATTCTG 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ GGCCGTCCCAGTGAGAGTAA 3′</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic></td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ TGGCCATCAACACCACCAT 3′</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5′ CGTTGCTGTCCCGTGTCA 3′</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl-fn0"><p>Primer sequences used in qRT-PCR validation of transcriptomic data comparing expression levels between days 21, 22 and 42. Alpha subunit of glycoproteins (<italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic>), follicle-stimulating hormone, beta (<italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic>), growth hormone (<italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>), proopiomelanocortin (<italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic>), prolactin (<italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic>) and thyroid-stimulating hormone, beta (<italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Relative tissue expression analysis</title><p>The gene expression of the pituitary gland was compared to the expression of other tissues (abdominal fat pad, heart fat pad, breast muscle, cerebellum, heart, liver, duodenum, jejunum, ileum, spleen, retina, pineal and hypothalamus) analyzed by our laboratory following the relative tissue expression (rEx) protocol outlined by Bailey and coworkers (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bailey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Each day the expression was analyzed independently, and maximum FPKM values for each gene in the pituitary gland were compared to the median FPKM value of each gene in all other collected tissues with the following calculation:
<disp-formula id="E0001"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43equ1.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>The log<sub>2</sub> distribution was used to normalize the data and apply a <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. Resulting genes that were greater than two standard deviations from the mean and with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than 0.05 were considered enriched in the pituitary gland. The enriched expression of these particular genes is thought to provide the unique functions of the pituitary gland or is critical to the overall function of the pituitary gland at that point in development. The enriched genes were uploaded to AmiGO 2 for gene ontology (GO) term analysis (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Carbon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2009</xref>), PathRings for pathway analysis (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2015</xref>) and WebGIVI for text mining and the identification of iTerms (L Sun &amp; CJ Schmidt, unpublished observations).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Starting gene lists and final enriched genes by day are available in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jme.endocrinology-journals.org/cgi/content/full/16-0186/DC1">Supplementary Tables 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6</ext-link> (see section on <xref ref-type="sec" rid="supp1">supplementary data</xref> given at the end of this article) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jme.endocrinology-journals.org/cgi/content/full/16-0186/DC1">Supplementary Tables 1, 2 and 3</ext-link>; starting gene list for days 21, 22 and 42, respectively; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jme.endocrinology-journals.org/cgi/content/full/16-0186/DC1">Supplementary Tables 4, 5 and 6</ext-link>; final enriched gene list for days 21, 22 and 42, respectively). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> shows a Venn diagram of the number of enriched pituitary genes shared (intersects) and differing (complement) between time points. A total of 25 enriched pituitary genes were shared between all three time points. Day 21 and day 22 were chosen for collection as part of a larger study and share 295 enriched genes compared to all other tissues. By day 42, there are 407 enriched genes not shared with day 21 and 22.
<fig fig-type="figure" id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of enriched genes in the chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary gland by day. Total number of enriched genes after relative tissue expression analysis in the whole pituitary gland at post-hatch days 21, 22, and 42.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43-g001.jpg"/></fig>
</p><sec><title>Day 21 and day 22: 295 shared genes</title><p>The 295 enriched genes shared between day 21 and day 22 grouped into the following GO terms: structure development (75 genes), neurogenesis (35 genes), neuron differentiation (26 genes) and nervous system development (43 genes). More specific GO terms associated with the 295 shared genes are neuron cell–cell adhesion (4 genes), oligodendrocyte differentiation (8 genes) and regulation of gliogenesis (9 genes). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> shows PathRings output for 295 shared genes between D21 and D22. Significant pathways and genes are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>.
<fig fig-type="figure" id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>PathRings output for 295 shared enriched genes between days 21 and 22 in chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary glands. Significance, determined by the Fisher Exact Test, is indicated by color. Blue is not significant while yellow to maroon is <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value 0.05–0.0001, respectively. DB, developmental biology; NS, neuronal system; ST, significant pathways are signal transduction; Ttos, transmembrane transport of small molecules.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43-g002.jpg"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Significant pathways in PathRings and the enriched genes within each pathway for 295 shared genes between days 21 and 22 in the chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary gland.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pathway</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene symbol</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transduction</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADORA1, ARHGEF4, CHRDL1, CNTN1, COL9A3, EGF, ERBB4, FZD10, GFAP, GNAO1, GPR17, GREM2, GRM3, GRM7, GRPR, HRH3, NPBWR1, NRG3, NTRK2, PDE4A, PDE8B, RAMP1, WNT11, WNT6, WNT7B</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuronal system</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACNG4, CHRNA4, GABRA3, GRIA4, GRIK2, GRIK3, KCNK2</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transmembrane transport of small molecules</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANO4, AQP4, ASIC4, GABRA3, SGK2, SLC13A5, SLC15A2, SLC26A4, SLC30A8, SLC44A5, SLC6A9</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developmental biology</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANK2, CHL1, CNTN1, CNTN2, COL9A3, LAMA1, NFASC, NTN1, SLIT1, UNC5A</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl-fn1"><p>DB, developmental biology; NS, neuronal system; ST, signal transduction; Ttos, transmembrane transport of small molecules.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Several genes within the signal transduction pathway and developmental biology pathway were related to axon connection formation and axonal organization (<italic toggle="yes">CNTN1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CNTN2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">NFASC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">LAMA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SLIT1</italic>), as well as neurite outgrowth (<italic toggle="yes">EGF</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ERBB4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">NRG3</italic>). Additionally, glutamate (<italic toggle="yes">GRM3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GRM7</italic>) and GABA (<italic toggle="yes">GABRA3</italic>) receptors and genes related to synaptic transmission and messaging (<italic toggle="yes">ASIC4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HRH3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CHL1</italic>) were enriched at days 21 and 22 when compared to all other tissues.</p></sec><sec><title>Day 21: 74 genes; day 22: 92 genes</title><p>Days 21 and 22 share a large portion of enriched genes; however, there are genes unique to each day. Further investigation of the individual days in AmiGO2 indicates an enrichment of genes associated with neuronal morphogenesis and synapse structure and organization at day 21 (<italic toggle="yes">SYNDIG1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RELN</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LRRTM1</italic>). At day 22, the uniquely enriched genes are related to neurite outgrowth, axonal migration, oligodendrocyte differentiation and myelination (<italic toggle="yes">FA2H</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">GLDN</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PLP1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">EPHA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PTGDS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PTGS1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">STMN4</italic>). Two immune-related genes were also enriched in day 22: histone deacetylase 11 (<italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic>) and complement regulatory protein CD59 molecule (<italic toggle="yes">CD59</italic>). Although these genes were uniquely enriched in the pituitary gland at day 22, the mean FPKM for these genes at days 21 and 22 were both high in comparison to day 42 ((<italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic>: day 21: 75.27, day 22: 84.64, day 42: 6.53); (<italic toggle="yes">CD59</italic>: day 21: 467.2, day 22: 505.7, day 42: 54.0)).</p></sec><sec><title>Day 42: 407 genes</title><p>At day 42, there are 407 unique genes with the following GO terms: pituitary gland development (11 genes), endocrine system development (15 genes), hormone metabolic process and regulation of hormone levels (28 genes) and cell–cell signaling (18 genes) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). In addition to endocrine-related GO terms, neurogenesis (34 genes) and nervous system development (42 genes), GO terms were also present within day 42 enriched genes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> shows the pituitary-specific iTerms and genes output from WebGIVI for the day 42 time point. At day 42, expression of endocrine-related genes such as <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic> increased and the following fold changes were seen in the transcriptomic data between days 22 and 42: <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic> 2700-fold, <italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic> 3000-fold, <italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic> (alpha subunit for FSHB, TSHB LHB) 1600-fold, <italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic> 2300-fold, <italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic> 6800-fold and <italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic> 2600-fold. To validate these robust transcriptomic changes, qRT-PCR results are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>.
<fig fig-type="figure" id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Adapted WebGIVI output for chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary iTerms and enriched genes expressed at day 42. Adapted WebGIVI output for general ‘pituitary’ iTerms. Red circles indicate iTerms generated by WebGIVI. Black outlined circles indicate genes from the enriched gene input list. Gray lines (edges) show connections between genes and iTerms. Blue filled genes are pituitary transcription factors. Orange filled genes are receptors for hypothalamus releasing hormones. Green filled genes are beta subunits of follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) and thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43-g003.jpg"/></fig>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Inverse Delta <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>t</sub> values for six genes comparing days 21, 22, and 42 chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) post-hatch pituitary gene expression. Alpha subunit of glycoproteins (<italic toggle="yes">CGA</italic>), follicle stimulating hormone, beta (<italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic>), growth hormone (<italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>), pro-opiomelanocortin (<italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic>), prolactin (<italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic>), and thyroid stimulating hormone, beta (<italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic>) were used to validate increased expression seen in the transcriptome between days 21, 22, and 42. Inverse Delta <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>t</sub> values are shown. Errors bars constructed using one standard error from the mean.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43-g004.jpg"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Gene ontology (GO) terms and enriched genes within each term for chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) day 42 pituitary glands.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene ontology (GO) term</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold># of genes in GO term</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene symbol</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pituitary gland development</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRD2, GHRHR, ISL1, LHX3, PAX6, PITX1, PITX2, POU1F1, SIX3, TBX19, WNT5A</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine system development</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGA, CRHR1, DRD2, GHRHR, ISL1, LHX3, NR5A1, PAX6, PITX1, PITX2, POU1F1, RFX6, RFX8, SIX3, TBX19, WNT5A</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of hormone levels</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGA, CPE, CRHR1, DIO2, DRD2, ESR1, FOXL2, GHRHR, GHSR, ILDR1, INHBA, NR5A1, PASK, PCSK1, POMC, PRL, RFX6</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell–cell signaling</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2CD4C, CACNA1B, CADPS, CGA, CHRNA3, CPE, CRHR1, DRD2, GABRG1, GHRHR, GHSR, GPR149, HTR1B, INHBA, KLF4, LHX5, LOC100858799, P2RX2, PDYN, PENK, PITX2, POMC, SYT4, WNT5A</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Day 21, day 22 and day 42: 25 shared genes</title><p>The 25 enriched genes mean FPKM values for each day are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>. Enriched genes were uploaded to WebGIVI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>) and AmiGO2 GO terms system development (<italic toggle="yes">COL11A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">DNAH5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">GPC3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SIX6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SOX3</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TRAPPC4</italic>) and sensory organ development (<italic toggle="yes">COL11A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SIX6</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SOX3</italic>). These genes include transcription factors and genes whose products code for structural proteins and are associated with the extracellular matrix.
<fig fig-type="figure" id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Adapted WebGIVI output for chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary iTerms and 25 shared enriched genes expressed at days 21, 22 and 42. Adapted WebGIVI output for 25 genes enriched at all three time points and corresponding iTerms. Red circles indicate iTerms generated by WebGIVI. Black outlined circles indicate genes from the enriched gene input list. Gray lines (edges) show connections between genes and iTerms.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jme-58-43-g005.jpg"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Mean FPKM values for 25 shared genes between days 21, 22 and 42 in the chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary gland.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Description</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day 21</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day 22</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day 42</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADIRF</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adipogenesis regulatory factor</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.722</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CASR</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium-sensing receptor</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL11A1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collagen, type XI, alpha 1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.17</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.74</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNAH5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynein, axonemal, heavy chain 5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM135B</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family with sequence similarity 135, member B</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM3B</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family with sequence similarity 3, member B</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.98</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPC3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glypican 3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.17</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.82</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC101749214</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized LOC101749214</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC101749680</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized LOC101749680</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC101749716</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized LOC101749716</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC101749894</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homeobox protein Nkx-2.2-like</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.42</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC101750727</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized LOC101750727</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1777.2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1074.13</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">958.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC421690</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vacuolar protein 8-like</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MATN4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matrilin 4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDGA2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAM domain containing glycosylphosphatidylinositol anchor 2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.16</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.98</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOV10L1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mov10l1, Moloney leukemia virus 10-like 1, homolog (mouse)</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYT1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelin transcription factor 1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NALCN</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium leak channel, non-selective</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.27</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NKX2-2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK2 homeobox 2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.34</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNF182</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ring finger protein 182</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX homeobox 6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.92</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SORCS1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sortilin-related VPS10 domain containing receptor 1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.65</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.97</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.99</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.04</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAPPC4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trafficking protein particle complex 4</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.72</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.12</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.17</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UMODL1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uromodulin-like 1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl-fn2"><p>Mean FPKM values in the pituitary gland for 25 shared enriched genes in days 21, 22 and 42 when compared to all other tissues (abdominal and heart fat, breast muscle, cerebellum, heart, liver, duodenum, jejunum, ileum, spleen, retina, pineal and hypothalamus).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Transcription factors</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl5">Table 5</xref> shows the transcription factors (TF) enriched by day. In the 295 expressed genes shared between days 21 and 22, there are 14 enriched transcription factors. AmiGO 2 analysis resulted in GO terms negative regulation of neurogenesis and negative regulation of nervous system development (<italic toggle="yes">NTN1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHOX2B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SOX8</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">VAX1</italic>). Thirty transcription factors were enriched at day 42 when compared to all other tissues. AmiGO2 analysis resulted in two notable GO terms: pituitary gland development (<italic toggle="yes">LHX3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TBX19</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">POU1F1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PAX6</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ISL1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PITX1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PITX2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SIX3</italic>) and endocrine system development (8 genes listed previously and NR5A1 and RFX6). Two transcription factors were present in all three days studied: Myelin Transcription Factor 1 (<italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic>) and NK2 Homeobox 2 (<italic toggle="yes">NKX2-2</italic>). <italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic> is a DNA-binding protein with an expression pattern that indicates a potential role in regulating oligodendrocyte differentiation. In the developing and adult central nervous system, <italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic> expression correlates with oligodendrocyte cell growth (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">NKX2-2</italic> is a gene associated with gliogenesis and may play a role in differentiation of oligodendrocyte progenitor cells (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Rousseau <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2006</xref>).
<table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Transcription factors enriched at days 21, 22 and 42 in chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) pituitary glands.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Day(s)</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold># of enriched genes</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TF symbol</bold></th><th valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TF description</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days 21, 22 and 42</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 genes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NKX2-2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK2 homeobox 2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYT1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myelin transcription factor 1</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days 21 and 22</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 genes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXC2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box C2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXL1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box L1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iroquois homebox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LHX2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIM homeobox 2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Msh homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPAS3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuronal PAS domain protein 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NTN1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netrin 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLIG3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligodendrocyte transcription factor 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHOX2B</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired like homeobox 2B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POU3F1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POU class 3 homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX8</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY-box 8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST18</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suppression of tumorigenicity 18, zinc finger</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBX22</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-box 22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral anterior homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 21</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 genes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR2E1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear receptor subfamily 2 group E member 1</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 22</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 genes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DLX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal-Less homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HES6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hes family BHLH transcription factor 6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC427656</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box protein L1-like</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX10</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY-box 10</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 42</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407 genes</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHURC1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Churchill domain containing 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMBX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diencephalon/mesencephalon homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESR1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrogen receptor 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBJ murine osteosarcoma viral oncogene homolog</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXG1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box G1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXL2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box L2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HES5</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hes family BHLH transcription factor 5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IRF6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interferon regulatory factor 6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INHBA</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibin beta A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISL1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISL LIM homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LHX3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIM homeobox 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEUROD1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuronal differentiation 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEUROG1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurogenin 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NHLH2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nescient helix-loop-helix 2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR4A3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear receptor subfamily 4 group A member 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR5A1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear receptor subfamily 5 group A member 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAX6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired box 6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PITX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired like homeodomain 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PITX2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired like homeodomain 2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POU1F1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POU class 1 homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRRX2</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paired related homeobox 2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAX</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retina and anterior neural fold homeobox</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBPJL</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombination signal binding protein for immunoglobulin kappa J region like</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFX6</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory factor X6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHOXF1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhox homeobox family member 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX1</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX homeobox 1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX3</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX homeobox 3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMAD7</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMAD family member 7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBX19</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-box 19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBX20</td><td valign="bottom" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-box 20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl-fn3"><p>Transcription factors (TF) present within enriched genes separated by day. # of enriched genes corresponds to total genes (including TF) that were enriched in each category.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Day 21 and 22: shared and unique enriched genes</title><p>Relative tissue expression analysis for days 21 and 22 results in similarly enriched genes involved in nervous tissue development (axon formation and neurite outgrowth) and signaling (GABA and glutamate receptors). Acid sensing ion channel subunit family member 4 (<italic toggle="yes">ASIC4</italic>) is a sodium channel involved in signal transduction and is known to have highest expression in the brain (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Grunder <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). Histamine Receptor H3 (<italic toggle="yes">HRH3</italic>) is a receptor for histamine, which is involved in neurotransmitter release and pituitary hormone secretion (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nuutinen &amp; Panula 2010</xref>). Uniquely enriched genes at days 21 and 22 indicate a shift from neuronal morphogenesis and synapse organization at day 21 to neurite outgrowth and myelination at day 22. This may be indicative of a developmental change from morphogenesis to maintenance of the nervous tissue, and it is unclear if this fluctuation between morphogenesis and maintenance continues throughout development. Two immune-related genes were also enriched in day 22: <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CD59</italic>. Histone deacetylases are a group of enzymes that interact with histones to regulate transcription. <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> is the most novel of the group and is placed in its own category, class IV. <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> regulates the expression of interleukin 10 (<italic toggle="yes">IL10</italic>), and immune tolerance and suppression can promote <italic toggle="yes">IL10</italic> expression in mice macrophages, whereas chromatin changes in macrophages increased <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> recruitment to <italic toggle="yes">IL10</italic> gene, inhibiting <italic toggle="yes">IL10</italic> production (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Villagra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Studies investigating <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> found abundant transcripts are detected in the brain, skeletal muscle, kidney and testis; however, little is known about its function in healthy tissues (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Deubzer <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Because <italic toggle="yes">HDAC11</italic> is a unique histone deacetylase, and it is possible it has functions that are unknown or not typically associated with histone deacetylases (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">CD59</italic> is a cell surface glycoprotein that inhibits the assembly of the membrane attack complex (MAC) during complement attack (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). Activation of the complement attack can lead to inflammation and lysis of cells and needs to be highly regulated. <italic toggle="yes">CD59</italic> inhibits MAC osmolytic pore formation thereby protecting cells (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). It is possible that development of the pars tuberalis and the macrophages within this region result in enrichment of these immune-related genes at days 21 and 22 but not day 42 and may provide anti-inflammatory functions during neuronal development. Overall, the focus of the pituitary gland at days 21 and 22 appears to be focused on developing and maintaining nervous tissue connections and signaling.</p></sec><sec><title>Day 42 enriched genes</title><p>By day 42, gene expression suggests a shift in the focus of the pituitary gland through maturation from strictly nervous tissue development and signaling to endocrine- and hormone-related functions. Most notably, there is the robust increase in expression of peptide hormone genes <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">FSHB</italic>. This change in enriched genes could be in preparation for reproduction. In addition to receptors for releasing hormones from the hypothalamus, and beta subunits of follicle-stimulating hormone (<italic toggle="yes">FSH</italic>) and thyroid-stimulating hormone (<italic toggle="yes">TSH</italic>), two other genes of interest are carboxypeptidase E (<italic toggle="yes">CPE</italic>) and deiodinase type 2 (<italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic>). <italic toggle="yes">CPE</italic> is a carboxypeptidase B-like enzyme involved in peptide and neurotransmitter synthesis and processing of neuropeptides. Immunohistochemical studies in the rat have shown immunoreactivity within all components of the hypothalamic-neurohypophyseal system (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Lynch <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 1990</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">CPE</italic> has prohormone processing functions in neuroendocrine cells and directs proopiomelanocortin (<italic toggle="yes">POMC</italic>) to the secretory pathway where it is later cleaved to produce ACTH (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Dhanvantari <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> converts thyroxine (T<sub>4</sub>) to triiodothyronine (T<sub>3</sub>), the main metabolic hormone important for neuronal development and differentiation in the brain (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Noda 2015</xref>). Circulating levels of T<sub>4</sub> are transported across the blood–brain barrier to astrocytes by organic anion-transporting polypeptide (OATPs) transporters and converted by <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> to T<sub>3</sub>. T<sub>3</sub> is important for neuron, microglia, astrocyte and oligodendrocyte development and function and thyroid hormone dysfunction can influence these processes (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Karlsson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2016</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> expression is also involved in seasonal reproduction in birds and is expressed during long day conditions. The increased day length leads to an increase in T<sub>3</sub> which then stimulates the release of FSH and luteinizing hormone (LH) for reproduction (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Karlsson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2016</xref>). The exact location of <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> expression in the brain is still under investigation although it is thought to be exclusively expressed in the glial compartment (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Egri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2016</xref>). This research shows expression in the pituitary gland suggesting future work should identify the location of <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> mRNA within the pituitary.</p><p>Dopamine receptor D2 (<italic toggle="yes">DRD2</italic>) and somatostatin receptor 5 (<italic toggle="yes">SSTR5</italic>) are receptors found in the brain. <italic toggle="yes">DRD2</italic> is expressed in lactotrophs and inhibits prolactin release. <italic toggle="yes">SSTR5</italic> is involved in the regulation of GH and TSH. Both <italic toggle="yes">DRD2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SSTR5</italic> are also involved in ACTH release in pituitary tumors (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Tani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).</p><p>Calcium-dependent secretion activator (<italic toggle="yes">CADPS</italic>) and synaptotagmin IV (<italic toggle="yes">SYT4</italic>) gene products are involved in the calcium-dependent vesicle-mediated exocytosis of neurotransmitters and peptides in conjunction with plasma membrane-associated and vesicle integral membrane SNAREs. <italic toggle="yes">CADPS</italic> is essential in exocytosis of dense-core vesicles (used for exocytosis of biogenic amines and peptides) in the pituitary gland and is involved in secretion of serotonin and other neurotransmitters in <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Wassenberg &amp; Martin 2002</xref>)<italic toggle="yes">. SYT4</italic> is a synaptotagmin that is a member of the vesicle integral membrane SNARE genes. Once hormones are produced, they are stored in secretory granules where extracellular signals induce fusion with the plasma membrane and subsequent release (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Moore <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">SYT4</italic> is an inhibitor of regulated exocytosis (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Wassenberg &amp; Martin 2002</xref>).</p><p>Cocaine- and amphetamine-regulated transcript (<italic toggle="yes">CARTPT</italic>) is an anorectic peptide that is expressed in the hypothalamus and the anterior pituitary. In the anterior pituitary, <italic toggle="yes">CARTPT</italic> is present in corticotrophs, gonadotrophs, lactotrophs and thyrotrophs. <italic toggle="yes">CARTPT</italic> mRNA expression is regulated by corticosterone and corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) from the hypothalamus via corticotropin-releasing hormone receptor 1 (CRHR1). Intracerebroventricular injections of <italic toggle="yes">CARTPT</italic> lead to elevated ACTH and corticosterone levels, suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">CARTPT</italic> can activate the hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal (HPA) axis and may be involved in the processes of the HPA axis, such as the stress response (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Mo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2015</xref>). Similarly, gastrin-releasing peptide (<italic toggle="yes">GRP</italic>) is a neuropeptide that affects AVP and CRH secretion from the hypothalamus and acts directly at the pituitary gland by increasing the effects of AVP and CRH release on corticotrophs (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Olsen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Day 21, 22 and 42: 25 shared enriched genes</title><p>Of the 25 shared genes between days 21, 22 and 42, genes related to the extracellular matrix (ECM) were enriched. The ECM organizes and fills the space between cells and is composed of glycosaminoglycans and fibrous proteins such as collagen and elastin. The ECM not only provides support to surrounding cells but also influences proliferation, differentiation and survival (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Alberts <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). ECM gene collagen type XI alpha 1 (<italic toggle="yes">COL11A1</italic>) encodes for an alpha chain of a minor fibrillary collagen and is important for extracellular matrix organization and has been associated with cell proliferation and migration (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Mio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Shen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2016</xref>). Matrilin-4 (<italic toggle="yes">MATN4</italic>) is in the matrilin family of proteins and is a recently characterized extracellular matrix protein that is expressed in a variety of tissues, including the brain (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Wagener <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). The pituitary gland is involved in nervous tissue and endocrine signaling and displays tissue plasticity in response to signals from the hypothalamus. This plasticity is necessary to accommodate the conditions of development (i.e. initiation reproductive maturation), and the ECM is an important component of tissue growth and maintenance throughout life. In addition to enrichment for specific ECM genes, there are also enriched genes involved in cell proliferation and differentiation. Glypican 3 (<italic toggle="yes">GPC3</italic>) interacts with the ECM to influence cell cycle control. <italic toggle="yes">GPC3</italic> is a glypican member within the family of heparin sulfate proteoglycans anchored to the cell surface that interact with extracellular ligands to influence cell processes, like growth, and function during morphogenesis and tissue repair (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Bernfield <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 1999</xref>). Glypicans are predominately expressed in the central nervous system and have been associated with negative regulation of cell proliferation (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Sung <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2003</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Enriched transcription factor genes</title><p>Transcription factors (TF) control the rate of transcription and are essential to pituitary cell development, differentiation and function (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Mizokami <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Because of their influential functions, transcription factors that may be associated with particular points in development of the pituitary gland were identified. Within the 295 enriched genes shared between days 21 and 22, 14 transcription factors were enriched. Netrin 1 laminin related (<italic toggle="yes">NTN1</italic>) and ventral anterior homeobox 1 (<italic toggle="yes">VAX1</italic>) are both related to axon guidance in the developing nervous system. <italic toggle="yes">NTN1</italic> specifically directs the development and migration of luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone neurons in the forebrain (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Schwarting <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). During embryonic development, <italic toggle="yes">VAX1</italic> is responsible for limiting the areas in which fibroblast growth factor 10 (<italic toggle="yes">FGF10</italic>) can induce pituitary-specific development and ensures that only a single pituitary develops (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bharti <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Paired like homeobox 2B (<italic toggle="yes">PHOX2B</italic>) is critical during embryonic development to regulate neural tube progenitor cells to exit the cell cycle and differentiation to a particular type of neuron (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dubreuil <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2000</xref>). Two transcription factors are associated with neurogenesis (<italic toggle="yes">POU3F1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">NPAS3</italic>), whereas suppression of tumorigenicity 18 (<italic toggle="yes">ST18</italic>) is uniformly expressed in the brain and is associated with pro-apoptotic and pro-inflammatory functions in fibroblasts (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Lastly, two genes are associated with the alpha peptide of glycoprotein hormones (CGA). In humans and mice, Msh Homeobox 1 (<italic toggle="yes">MSX1</italic>) has been associated with CGA expression and is localized in growth hormone and thyroid-stimulating hormone cells of the anterior pituitary (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Mizokami <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). LIM Homeobox 2 (<italic toggle="yes">LHX2</italic>) is a transcription factor known to repress the CGA promoter (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Susa <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2006</xref>) and has a direct role in the development of the posterior pituitary gland (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Several transcription factors normally associated with embryonic development at days 21 and 22 were identified; however, the presence of these genes in post-hatch birds suggests these genes may continue to influence development through axonal guidance (<italic toggle="yes">VAX1</italic>) and limiting the growth of pituitary-related cell types (<italic toggle="yes">NTN1</italic>).</p><p>Thirty transcription factors are enriched at day 42 and several are involved in endocrine-related processes. POU class 1 homeobox 1 (<italic toggle="yes">POU1F1</italic>) is a pituitary-specific transcription factor that is responsible for the activation of <italic toggle="yes">GH</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PRL</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TSHB</italic> gene transcription (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Pfaffle <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 1993</xref>) and is critical for proper pituitary development (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Nuclear receptor subfamily 5 group A member 1 (<italic toggle="yes">NR5A1</italic>) functions in the development of LH- and FSH-expressing cells and T-box 19 (<italic toggle="yes">TBX19</italic>) is restricted to corticotrophs where it binds the POMC promoter and affects the expression of ACTH (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Lim homeobox 3 (<italic toggle="yes">LHX3</italic>) and Forkhead box L2 (<italic toggle="yes">FOXL2</italic>) are associated with positive regulation of the CGA promoter (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Susa <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Neuron differentiation 1 (<italic toggle="yes">NEUROD1</italic>) has been identified as a transcription factor involved in corticotroph differentiation and POMC gene expression (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Tani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Regulatory factor X6 (<italic toggle="yes">RFX6</italic>) is a newly characterized transcription factor expressed primarily in pancreatic tissues and may regulate pancreatic development. The paralogous gene, regulatory factor X7 (<italic toggle="yes">RFX7</italic>), is also recently characterized in humans and is expressed in several tissues, particularly the brain (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aftab <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2008</xref>) but was not shown to be enriched in our data. It is surprising that a transcription factor most commonly associated with the pancreas (<italic toggle="yes">RFX6</italic>) is present in the pituitary gland at day 42 rather than the paralogous transcription factor normally associated with brain tissue (<italic toggle="yes">RFX7</italic>); however, the brain is an insulin-sensitive organ and perhaps <italic toggle="yes">RFX6</italic> is present in the chicken pituitary gland to assist in insulin-related processes (i.e. insulin receptors, glucose uptake).</p><p>Two pituitary enriched transcription factors found in all days, <italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">NXK2-2</italic>, are both related to oligodendrocyte differentiation, proliferation and maturation. <italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic> is a DNA-binding protein with an expression pattern that indicates a potential role in regulating oligodendrocyte differentiation. In the developing and adult central nervous system, <italic toggle="yes">MYT1</italic> expression correlates with oligodendrocyte cell growth (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">NKX2</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">2</italic> is associated with gliogenesis and may play a role in the differentiation of oligodendrocyte progenitor cells (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Rousseau <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). The presence of these TFs in all days indicates the need for continued oligodendrocyte proliferation. This proliferation may accommodate new connections between the pituitary gland and other brain regions, specifically the hypothalamus, and may be important for establishing and maintaining the connections within the hypothalamo–pituitary axis. Other neuronal-related TFs independent of those identified at days 21 and 22 were enriched at day 42 (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">CHURC1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">DMBX1</italic>). These transcription factors should be explored further to determine the temporal relationship as it is possible these TFs are necessary to establish the endocrine-related processes within the pituitary gland. TF results also point to a maturation shift from prominently neuronal-related TFs at day 21/22 to endocrine-related TFs at day 42.</p><p>In summary, there is a transcriptome focus on nervous tissue development, signaling and maturation at days 21 and 22 post-hatch. By day 42, there is a shift from strictly nervous tissue gene expression toward endocrine-related processes, possibly indicating maturation in preparation for reproduction. The results of this study lead to valuable insight into the genes involved in the pituitary gland at several points in development, particularly related to maturation. Future work aims to utilize fluorescent in situ hybridization techniques to investigate the location of particular mRNA transcripts within the pituitary such as <italic toggle="yes">DIO2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">RFX6</italic>. Future work should investigate the transcriptomic differences, particularly related to neuronal and endocrine maturation, as a function of age in male broiler chicken pituitary glands by collecting additional time points in future trials. The pituitary gland is a tissue that contains many different cell types and exerts many physiological changes based on the input received from the body and the environment. Whole tissue transcriptomics is informative but cellular transcriptomic changes that may have important physiological impacts may be lost or not as robust. Single-cell transcriptomic data could further elucidate the cellular transcriptomic differences that may influence the development and function of the pituitary gland. Single-cell transcriptome analysis would allow for identification of more prevalent cell types and the transcriptomic changes throughout development.</p></sec></sec><sec id="supp1"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>This is linked to the online version of the paper at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1530/JME-16-0186">http://dx.doi.org/10.1530/JME-16-0186</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Declaration of interest</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest that could be perceived as prejudicing the impartiality of the research reported.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This project was supported by Agriculture and Food Research Initiative Competitive Grant 2011-67003-30228 from the United States Department of Agriculture National Institute of Food and Agriculture.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contribution statement</title><p>E M P, C J S and S J L conceived and designed the experiments. E M P and C J S performed the experiments. E M P and C J S analyzed the data. E M P, C J S and S J L contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. E M P wrote the paper.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Matheus Reis for his help in conducting the bird trial, members of the Schmidt Laboratory for assistance during necropsies and Dr Erin Brannick and Dr Robert Dyer for aiding in proper collection of the pituitary gland. Special thanks to Schmidt Lab member Blair Schneider for assistance with pituitary gland RNA preparation.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aftab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Semenec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih-Chieh Chu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of novel human tissue-specific RFX transcription factors</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>226</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-8-226</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18673564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2533330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The extracellular matrix of animals</article-title>. In <source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source>, edn 4. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Garland Science</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaildrat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogenesch</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Night/Day changes in pineal expression of &gt;600 genes. Central role of Adrenergic/cAMP signaling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>284</volume>
<fpage>7606</fpage>–<lpage>7622</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.m808394200</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19103603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2658055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reizes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lincecum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zako</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Functions of cell surface heparan sulfate proteoglycans</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>729</fpage>–<lpage>777</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.68.1.729</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertuzzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnheiter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Lack of the ventral anterior homeodomain transcription factor VAX1 leads to induction of a secondary pituitary</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>878</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.056465</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21247964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3035091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn615</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2639003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castinetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellsworth</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potok</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brinkmeier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raetzman</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carninci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Molecular mechanisms of pituitary organogenesis: In search of novel regulatory genes</article-title>. <source>Molecular and Cellular Endocrinology</source>
<volume>323</volume>
<fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2009.12.012</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2909473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deubzer</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schier</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oehme</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haendler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>HDAC11 is a novel drug target in carcinomas</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Cancer</source>
<volume>132</volume>
<fpage>2200</fpage>–<lpage>2208</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.27876</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanvantari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaoutova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Carboxypeptidase E, a prohormone sorting receptor, is anchored to secretory granules via a c-terminal transmembrane insertion</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bbib15698n</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pattyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goridis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The Phox2b transcription factor coordinately regulates neuronal cell cycle exit and identity</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>5191</fpage>–<lpage>5201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11060244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1242/dev.127.23.5191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reglodi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fulop</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gereben</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Pituitary adenylate cyclase-activating polypeptide (PACAP) regulates the hypothalamo-pituitary-thyroid (HPT) axis via type 2 deiodinase in male mice</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.2015-1982</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27046436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cueto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asselbergs</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atadja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Cloning and functional characterization of HDAC11, a novel member of the human histone deacetylase family</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>277</volume>
<fpage>25748</fpage>–<lpage>25755</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111871200</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11948178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geisler</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rainier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Acid-sensing ion channel (ASIC) 4 gene: Physical mapping, genomic organisation, and evaluation as a candidate for paroxysmal dystonia</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Human Genetics</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>672</fpage>–<lpage>676</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.ejhg.5200699</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11571555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Protection of xenogeneic cells from human complement-mediated lysis by the expression of human DAF, CD59, and MCP</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunology and Medical Microbiology</source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2001.tb00521.x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11720816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallahshahroudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagenblad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A domestication related mutation in the thyroid stimulating hormone receptor gene (TSHR) modulates photoperiodic response and reproduction in chickens</article-title>. <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology</source>
<volume>228</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygcen.2016.02.010</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26873630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nature Methods</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of a CD59 analogue from large yellow croaker <italic toggle="yes">Pseudosciana crocea.</italic></article-title>
<source>Molecular Immunology</source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>3661</fpage>–<lpage>3671</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2007.04.006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17531319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braas</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Carboxypeptidase E (CPE): immunocytochemical localization in the rat central nervous system and pituitary gland</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>1592</fpage>–<lpage>1599</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2332799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.10-05-01592.1990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6570069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A functional polymorphism in COL11A1, which encodes the alpha1 chain of type XI collage, is associated with susceptibility to lumbar disc herniation</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Human Genetics</source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>1277</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/522377</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17999364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2276353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizokami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egashira</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takekoshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osamura</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumae</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Expression of MSX1 in human normal pituitaries and pituitary adenomas</article-title>. <source>Endocrine Pathology</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12022-008-9021-7</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18379900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) stimulates cocaine- and amphetamine-regulated transcript gene (CART1) expression through CRH type 1 receptor in chicken anterior pituitary</article-title>. <source>Molecular and Cellular Endocrinology</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2015.09.007</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26363222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>HPH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andresen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugwitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machen</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Biosynthesis and secretion of pituitary hormones: dynamics and regulation</article-title>. <source>Archives of Physiology and Biochemistry</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1076/apab.110.1.16.903</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11935396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Research Council</collab>
<year>1994</year>
<source>Nutrient Requirements of Poultry</source>, <edition>9th ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Washington, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berndt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Myelin transcription factor 1 (Myt1) modulates the proliferation and differentiation of oligodendrocyte lineage cells</article-title>. <source>Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2003.10.001</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Possible role of glial cells in the relationship between thyroid dysfunction and mental disorders</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Cellular Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncel.2015.00194</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26089777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4452882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuutinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panula</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Histamine in neurotransmission and brain diseases</article-title>. <source>Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</source>
<volume>709</volume>
<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4419-8056-4_10</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21618891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knigge</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Gastrin-releasing peptide stimulation of corticotropin secretion in male rats</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>130</volume>
<fpage>2710</fpage>–<lpage>2716</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.130.5.2710</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1315254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaffle</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heimann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Pit-1 and pituitary function</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pediatric Endocrinology</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/JPEM.1993.6.3-4.229</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7920987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nutt</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betensky</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iafrate</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ligon</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowitch</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Expression of oligodendroglial and astrocytic lineage markers in diffuse gliomas: use of YKL-40, APOE, ASCL1, and NKX2-2</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuropathology and Experimental Neurology</source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>1149</fpage>–<lpage>1156</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.jnen.0000248543.90304.2b</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17146289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Persia</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feierstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingham</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saylor</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Comparison of a modern broiler line and a heritage line unselected since the 1950s</article-title>. <source>Poultry Science</source>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>2610</fpage>–<lpage>2619</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2009-00055</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19903960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarting</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raitcheva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bless</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ACkerman</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Netrin 1-mediated chemoattraction regulates the migratory pathway of LHRH neurons</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Neuroscience</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03094.x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14750959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>COL11A1 is overexpressed in recurrent non-small cell lung cancer and promotes cell proliferation, migration, invasion and drug resistance</article-title>. <source>Oncology Reports</source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>877</fpage>–<lpage>885</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2016.4869</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27373316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Growth promotion of HepG2 hepatoma cells by antisense-mediated knockdown of glypican-3 is independent of insulin-like growth factor 2 signaling</article-title>. <source>Experimental and Molecular Medicine</source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2003.34</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14508064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Susa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Cofactor CLIM2 promotes the repressive action of LIM homeodomain transcription factor LHX2 in the expression of porcine pituitary glycoprotein hormone alpha subunit gene</article-title>. <source>BBA Gene Structure and Expression</source>
<volume>1759</volume>
<fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbaexp.2006.08.004</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17005264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izumiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Differential gene expression profiles of POMC-related enzymes, transcription factors and receptors between non-pituitary and pituitary ACTH-secreting tumors</article-title>. <source>Endocrine Journal</source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1507/endocrj.K10E-389</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21383526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>TopHat:discovering splice junctions with RNA-seq</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp120</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19289445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2672628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villagra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glozak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atadja</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The histone deacetylase HDAC11 regulates the expression of interleukin 10 and immune tolerance</article-title>. <source>Nature Immunology</source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1673</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19011628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3925685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobbe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aszodi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Characterization of the mouse matrilin-4 gene: A 5′ antiparallel overlap with the gene encoding the transcription factor RBP-I</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/geno.2001.6589</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11549321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahakian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rock-Klotz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente-Suarez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinilla-Ibarz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Histone deacetylase inhibitor LAQ824 augments inflammatory responses in macrophages through transcriptional regulation of IL-10</article-title>. <source>Journal of Immunology</source>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>3986</fpage>–<lpage>3996</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1001101</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3998678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassenberg</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>TFJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Role of CAPS in dense-core vesicle exocytosis</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Science</source>
<volume>971</volume>
<fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2002.tb04464.x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12438120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behl</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alikhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The transcription factor ST18 regulates proapoptotic and proinflammatory gene expression in fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>FASEB Journal</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>3956</fpage>–<lpage>3967</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.08-111013</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2574028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prefontaine</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tollkuhn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Genetic control of pituitary development and hypopituitarism</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Genetics and Development</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2005.04.011</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garbarino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>PathRings: a web-based tool for exploration of ortholog and expression data in biological pathways</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-014-0430-y</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25982732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4436019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>