
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci. Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BSR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6435540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6435540.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6435540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6435540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30487163</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20181953</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>6</subject><subject>34</subject><subject>7</subject><subject>51</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>LipG a bifunctional phospholipase/thioesterase involved in mycobacterial envelope remodeling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santucci</surname><given-names initials="P">Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Point</surname><given-names initials="V">Vanessa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poncin</surname><given-names initials="I">Isabelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexandre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crauste</surname><given-names initials="C">Céline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serveau-Avesque</surname><given-names initials="C">Carole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galano</surname><given-names initials="J">Jean Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spilling</surname><given-names initials="C">Chistopher D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalier</surname><given-names initials="JF">Jean-François</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7478-300X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names initials="S">Stéphane</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Aix-Marseille Univ, CNRS, LISM, IMM FR3479, Marseille, France</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institut des Biomolécules Max Mousseron (IBMM), UMR 5247, Université de Montpellier, CNRS, ENSCM, 15 Avenue Charles Flahault, 34093 Montpellier Cedex 5, France</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Aix-Marseille Univ, CNRS, Centrale Marseille, ISM2, Marseille, France</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of Missouri, One University Boulevard, St. Louis, MO 63121, U.S.A.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Stéphane Canaan (<email>canaan@imm.cnrs.fr</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">324163</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20181953</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-20 21:25:32.817"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2018 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953.pdf"/><abstract><p>Tuberculosis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is currently one of the leading causes of death from an infectious agent. The main difficulties encountered in eradicating this bacteria are mainly related to <bold>(i)</bold> a very complex lipid composition of the bacillus cell wall, <bold>(ii)</bold> its ability to hide from the immune system inside the granulomas, and <bold>(iii)</bold> the increasing number of resistant strains. In this context, we were interested in the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic>) gene located upstream to the <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> cluster which is described as being crucial for the production of cell wall components and required for the bacilli adaptation and survival in mouse macrophages<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Using biochemical experiments combined with the construction of deletion and overexpression mutant strains in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>, we found that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a cytoplasmic membrane-associated enzyme that displays both phospholipase and thioesterase activities. Overproduction of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> decreases the glycopeptidolipids (GPL) level concomitantly to an increase in phosphatidylinositol (PI) which is the precursor of the PI mannoside (PIM), an essential lipid component of the bacterial cell wall. Conversely, deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> gene in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> leads to an overproduction of GPL, and subsequently decreases the strain susceptibility to various antibiotics. All these findings demonstrate that LipG is involved in cell envelope biosynthesis/remodeling, and consequently this enzyme may thus play an important role in mycobacterial physiology.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antibiotics</kwd><kwd>cell-envelope</kwd><kwd>lipolytic enzymes</kwd><kwd>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</kwd><kwd>phospholipid homeostasis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>With more than 10 million new cases and almost 1.6 million deaths in 2017, tuberculosis (TB) caused by the etiologic agent <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>) still remains the deadliest infectious disease worldwide [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The current antibiotherapy, which is a combination of four antibiotics (i.e. isoniazid (INH), rifampicin (RIF), pyrazinamide, and ethambutol), allows to heal 95% of infected people with active disease when administered under directly observed therapy [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This treatment is, however, not effective enough to overcome the emergence of multidrug and extensively drug-resistant strains of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. More recently, some totally drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> strains have also been detected, which are virtually incurable [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Most of the time this antibiotic resistance is directly related to the unique mycobacterial cell wall composition which is an essential factor contributing to virulence, pathogenesis, and survival of the bacilli. Therefore, identifying proteins and mechanisms involved in the biosynthesis and/or remodeling of this complex structure could lead to the development of new therapeutics to control and fight TB.</p><p>Indeed, amongst all bacterial phyla, <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> and more specifically <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, possess an unusual cell envelope with a specific architecture constituted by lipids which may represent up to 40–60% of the dry weight of the cell, as compared with only 5–10% in other bacteria [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The outer membrane is an extremely hydrophobic barrier mainly composed of long-chain mycolic acids (MAs) and several atypical lipids, which are responsible for the high intrinsic tolerance of the bacteria to various antibiotics [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Moreover, it is now acknowledged that most of these lipids play important roles in the viability and/or virulence of the bacteria [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. As a consequence, the structural characterization of these complex lipids, as well as their biosynthetic pathways have been the subject of many studies in the past decade with the aim of identifying putative therapeutic targets [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref>].</p><p>Of particular interest, the synthesis of MAs involves two fatty acid synthase (FAS) enzymatic complexes, FAS-I and FAS-II [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. FAS-I synthesizes <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> medium chain fatty acids (C16–18 and C24–26) as acyl-CoA derivatives, which are further elongated by the FAS-II complex to form the C48–64 meromycolic chains, a major component of the envelope arabinogalactan layer [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The various methyltransferases closely interact with enzymes belonging to the FAS-II system to functionalize meromycolate chains by adding specific chemical modifications (such as cyclopropane, methyl, hydroxyl, and ketone) [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14–18</xref>]. Amongst the eight putative methyltransferases identified in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv genome, the <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> gene cluster; i.e. <italic toggle="yes">mmaA1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Rv0645c</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">mmaA2</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Rv0644c</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">mmaA3</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Rv0643c</italic>), and <italic toggle="yes">mmaA4</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Rv0642c</italic>); is essential for chemical group introduction and functionalization of Mas, thus participating actively in the envelope integrity/virulence of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, these <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> genes are also clustered with the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene, which is highly conserved amongst mycobacterial species and encodes for LipG (LipG<sub>MTB</sub>), a putative lipase/esterase which has been recently described as a carboxylesterase [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv genome encodes for 36 lipolytic enzymes annotated as putative esterases, lipases, cutinases, or phospholipases based on their sequence homology and the presence of the consensus G-x-S-x-G motif, characteristic of the α/β hydrolase-fold family [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref>]. LipG<sub>MTB</sub> has been classified within the Lip family which includes 24 members [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This enzyme possesses approximately 50% sequence identity with the EstB protein from <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter calcoaceticus</italic> and 43% with the putative hydrolase PA3586 from <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1. Interestingly, the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene has been annotated as essential for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv survival within primary murine cells by transposon site hybridization [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Due to its high conservation and its peculiar location upstream to the <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> cluster, which is crucial for the production of cell wall components and so for the mycobacterial envelope integrity, the potential physiological function of LipG deserves to be studied and deciphered.</p><p>In this context, <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene from <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv has been cloned, expressed, purified, and fully biochemically characterized. Since its potential important role in mycobacterial lifecycle makes LipG<sub>MTB</sub> an attractive target for future therapeutic developments against TB, inhibition studies on pure recombinant enzyme were also conducted with two recent families of antitubercular compounds; namely, oxadiazolone-core (<bold>OX</bold>) derivatives [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and monocyclic analogs of Cyclophostin and Cyclipostins analogs (<bold>CyC</bold>) [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28–30</xref>] which affect the growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and in infected macrophages.</p><p>In order to investigate the physiological function of LipG in mycobacterial species, both deletion and overexpression mutant strains have been generated into the surrogate strain <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>. By using phenotypic assays, subcellular location, <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> modeling, lipid extraction followed by TLC analysis, and susceptibility testing via the resazurin microtiter assay (REMA), we determined that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a cytoplasmic membrane-associated enzyme involved in phospholipids remodeling and cell wall integrity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Experimental procedures</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Bacterial strains and culture conditions</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> DH10β and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C41 (DE3)/pLyS strain were cultured in LB broth or Terrific Broth (Invitrogen, France). <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 <italic toggle="yes">groEL1ΔC</italic> [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] strains were cultured in Middlebrook 7H9 broth (BD Difco, Le Pont-de-Claix, France) supplemented with 0.05% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Tween-80 and 0.2% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) glycerol (Sigma–Aldrich, Saint-Quentin Fallavier, France) (7H9-S). When needed, ampicillin and kanamycin (Euromedex, Souffelweyersheim, France) were added to the medium at final concentrations of 100 and 50 µg/ml for both <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and mycobacterial species, respectively. Hygromycin B (Euromedex) was used at a final concentration of 200 and 50 µg/ml for recombinant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and recombinant mycobacteria, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>
<italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> analyses</title><p>Genomic sequences of <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> and its orthologs were obtained from the NCBI database. <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv, <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium leprae</italic> TN, <italic toggle="yes">M. marinum</italic> M, and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> genomic clusters were re-adjusted manually based on the genomic annotations provided by the Mycobrowser database [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The amino acid sequence of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv LipG and its orthologs were aligned using Multalign software [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and results were displayed using ESPrit 3.0 software [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The percentage of identity between the different orthologs was generated with the Clustal Ω multiple sequence alignment program (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalo/</ext-link>). A 3D model of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv LipG (LipG<sub>MTB</sub>) was also generated, by using the I-TASSER server [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and visualized with PyMOL software (The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, version 1.8 Schrödinger, LLC). Electrostatic surface potentials of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> model structure was built using freely available PDB2PQR web service [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The electrostatic potential data thus generated, were further visualized using the PyMOL APBS Tools 2 plugin [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Construction of recombinant plasmids, expression and purification of recombinant LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> ORF encoding LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein, was amplified from <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv genomic DNA by polymerization chain reaction, using primers containing the attB1, Shine–Dalgarno, 6× His, and a TEV (tobacco etch virus) NIa site sequences at the 5′-end and the attB2 recombination site at the 3′-end (Supplementary Table S1, P1<sub>MTB</sub> and P2<sub>MTB</sub>). The resulting PCR fragments were cloned using the Gateway® technology (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, U.S.A.) into the pDonR221 entry vector, and then into the pDEST14 expression vector (pDEST14<italic toggle="yes">::lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic>). A similar strategy was used to clone the <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> ORF encoding LipG<sub>MS</sub> protein. PCR was performed with P1<sub>MS</sub> and P2<sub>MS</sub> primers (Supplementary Table S1), thus giving the pDEST14::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> construct. DNA sequences of recombinant clones were analyzed by GATC Biotech (Ebersberg, Germany). The newly generated pDEST14<italic toggle="yes">::lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> was used as a template for generating pDEST14<italic toggle="yes">::lipG<sub>MTB</sub><sup>S123A</sup></italic>by PCR mutagenesis using specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P3 and P4). The resulting plasmids pDEST14<italic toggle="yes">::lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic>, pDEST14<italic toggle="yes">::lipG<sub>MTB</sub><sup>S123A</sup></italic>, and pDEST14::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> were used to transform <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C41 (DE3)/pLyS strain harboring the pRare plasmid (Novagen).</p><p>For protein expression, 1 L of Terrific Broth medium was inoculated with the recombinant strains at initial OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05, and was further incubated at 37°C and 200 rpm. When the OD<sub>600</sub> reached 0.6, cells were put on ice for 30 min. Then, 0.5 mM isopropyl-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside was added to the medium and the culture was further incubated at 17°C under shaking. After 18 h of incubation, cells were pelleted, re-suspended in 30 ml of ice-cold lysis buffer (50 mM Tris/HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Triton X-100, 0.25 mg/ml lysozyme), and stored at −80°C. To purify recombinant LipG<sub>MTB</sub> or LipG<sub>MS</sub>, the supernatant (S1) obtained after cell lysis and centrifugation at 17000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 30 min, was stored at 4°C. Pellet was then re-suspended in lysis buffer, sonicated twice for 30 s with 30 s breaks between each cycle, solubilized by stirring at 4°C for 1 h using a magnetic bar, and further centrifuged at 17000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 30 min (giving S2 supernatant). Both supernatants (S1 and S2) were pooled and loaded on to a Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA affinity column previously equilibrated with buffer A (10 mM Tris/HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl). The column was washed with buffer A before performing elution with buffer A and 125 and 250 mM of imidazole. Fraction purity was assessed on SDS/PAGE. The corresponding 35 kDa protein band was further analyzed by tryptic digestion and MS. Pure protein was concentrated to 0.5–1 mg/ml, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at −80°C.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Biochemical characterization and inhibition of rLipG<sub>MTB/MS</sub>
</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Esterase activity assay</title><p>The esterase activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> or rLipG<sub>MS</sub> was determined as described previously [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrophenyl (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP) esters with different carbon chain lengths were used as substrates, including <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP acetate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C2), butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C4), caproate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C6), caprylate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C8), caprate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C10), laurate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C12), myristate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C14), and palmitate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C16). Stock solution (200 mM) of each substrate was freshly prepared in acetonitrile. Release of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP was monitored at 410 nm and pH 8 using a 96-well plate spectrophotometer (PowerWave™, Bio-Tek Instruments) and quantitated using a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP calibration curve (10 µM to 0.5 mM) with <sub>(λ = 410 nm)</sub> = 6.0 mM<sup>−1</sup>. Enzymatic reactions were performed at 37°C over a period of 20 min in a 96-well microplate filled with 10 mM Tris buffer (pH 8.0) containing 150 mM NaCl with 0.5% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Triton X-100 to a final volume of 200 µl. In each well, 2 mM of substrate and 1 µg of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> (0.15 µM final concentration) were added. Activities were expressed in international units (U), corresponding to 1 µmol of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP released per min. Specific activities (S.A) were expressed as U/mg of pure enzyme. Experiments were done in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Phospholipase A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub> activities assay</title><p>The phospholipase A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub> activities of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> and rLipG<sub>MS</sub> were monitored continuously using BODIPYH dye-labeled phospholipids: PED-A<sub>1</sub> (N-((6-(2,4-DNP)Amino)Hexanoyl)-1-(BODIPYH FL C5)-2-hexyl-<italic toggle="yes">sn</italic>-glycero-3-phosphoethanolamine) and red/green BODIPYH PC-A<sub>2</sub>(1-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-(6-BODIPYH558/568-aminohexyl)-2-BODIPYH FLC5-<italic toggle="yes">sn</italic>-glycero-3-phosphocholine), respectively, as previously described [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Briefly, substrate stock solutions (50 µM) were prepared in ethanol. All enzyme activities were assayed in 10 mM Tris (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl. Enzymatic reactions were performed at 25°C for 60 min in a final volume of 200 µl containing 1.5 µg rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> (0.23 µM final concentration) and 5 µM substrate. The release of BODIPYH (BFCL5) (Life Technologies) was recorded at λ<sub>exc</sub> = 485 nm and λ<sub>em</sub> = 538 nm using a 96-well plate fluorimeter (Fluoroskan Ascent, Thermo Fisher Scientific). Each experiment was done in triplicate. Enzymatic activities were quantitated using a BFCL5 calibration curve (0.08–200 pmoles). S.A were expressed in mU of fatty acid (or BFLC5) released per mg of pure protein (mU.mg<sup>−1</sup>). One unit correspond to the release of one µmol of product release per min. PLA<sub>1</sub> from <italic toggle="yes">T. lanuginosus</italic> and Bv PLA<sub>2</sub> (Sigma–Aldrich) were used as positive standards for the PLA<sub>1</sub> and the PLA<sub>2</sub> activities, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Thioesterase activity assay</title><p>Hydrolysis of palmitoyl-Coenzyme A (palmitoyl-CoA) (Sigma–Aldrich) was used to measure thioesterase activity. After the hydrolysis of the thioester bond, the free sulphur on CoA is attacked by DTNB (5-5′-Dithio-bis 2-nitrobenzoic acid) (Sigma–Aldrich) which releases a measurable nitrophenyl group, TNB<sup>2−</sup> (5-Thio-2-nitrobenzoate) ion detectable at 415 nm. Fresh stock solution of palmitoyl-CoA (1 mM) and DTNB (0.4 mM) were prepared in water. Palmitoyl-CoA and DTNB were added in each well of a 96-well plate at final concentration of 10 µM. The thioesterase activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> or rLipG<sub>MS</sub> (30 µg) was compared with that of TesA (Rv2928) [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and LipY [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] used as positive and negative controls, respectively. Triplicate assays were done at 37°C in 10 mM Tris (pH 8.0) 150 mM NaCl buffer. The absorbance at 415 nm was continuously measured and the release of TNB<sup>2−</sup> was quantitated using a calibration curve (0.5–30 nmoles).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Enzymatic inhibition assays using OX derivatives, CyC analogs, and Orlistat</title><p>The six oxadiazolone derivatives (<bold>OX</bold>); i.e. <bold>M<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>PPOX, iBPOX, iB<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX, HPOX, H<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX</bold>, and <bold>BePOX</bold>; were synthesized as described previously [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The five <bold>CyC</bold> analogs; i.e. <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub>, CyC<sub>7α</sub>, CyC<sub>7β</sub>, CyC<sub>8α</sub></bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>8β</sub></bold>; were synthesized according to [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref>].</p><p>Inhibition experiments were performed using the classical enzyme-inhibitor pre-incubation method, as described previously [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Stock solutions (10 mM) of each <bold>CyC</bold> and <bold>OX</bold> inhibitor, as well as <bold>Orlistat</bold> were prepared in DMSO. rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was pre-incubated for 30 min at 25°C with each compound at various inhibitor molar excess (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub>), related to 1 mol of enzyme, ranging from 1 to 200. Sample of the incubation medium (1.0 µg rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>) was then collected for measuring the enzyme residual activity using the colorimetric assay with the substrate <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C6, as described above. The variation in the residual activity allowed to determine the inhibitor molar excess which reduced the enzyme activity to 50% of its initial value (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub>) [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Thereby, a <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub> value of 0.5 is corresponding to a 1:1 stoichiometric ratio between the enzyme and the inhibitor, and is therefore the highest level of inhibitory activity that can be achieved. In each case, control experiments were done in the absence of inhibitor but with the same volume of solvent. It is worth noting that DMSO at a final volume concentration of less than 10% has no effect on the enzyme activity. Inhibition dose–response curves were fitted in Kaleidagraph 4.2 Software (Synergy Software). Results are expressed as mean values ± S.D. of at least three independent assays.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Creation of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis MSMEG_1352</italic> disrupted strain</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> gene encoding LipG<sub>MS</sub> was amplified with 500-bp flanking regions by PCR using <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 genomic DNA as template and specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P9 and P10). PCR product of ∼2000 bp was cloned into pJET1.2/blunt vector following manufacturer’s instructions giving pJET<italic toggle="yes">-lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic>. Recombinant plasmid was then digested with NruI, and a hygromycin resistance cassette amplified from pUC-Hygro using primer (Supplementary Table S1, P17 and P18). The resulting blunt-ended PCR product was cloned in order to disrupt <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> gene. This new plasmid, pJET<italic toggle="yes">-lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> which contains an inactive version of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> gene was used as template for amplifying an allelic exchange substrate by using specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P9 and P10). Approximately 300 ng of purified PCR product was electroporated into electro-competent <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155 strain harboring pJV53 plasmid, and cells were plated on to Middlebrook 7H10 agar medium supplemented with 50 µg/ml of both kanamycin and hygromycin and incubated at 37°C during 5 days as previously described [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Finally, recombinant clones were analyzed by PCR using P7-P8 and P11-P12 primers’ pairs (Supplementary Table S1).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Creation of overexpression/complementation vectors</title><p>ORFs <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> were amplified by PCR with specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P5–P6 and P7–P8) containing NdeI and BamHI restriction sites in 5′ and 3′ ends, respectively. Digested and purified products were cloned into the pVV16 mycobacterial expression vector in frame with the <sub>6</sub>His-tag located in C-terminal position giving the pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> and pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> complementation plasmids allowing a constitutive production of recombinant LipG. <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> ORFs was also cloned within a homemade pMyC Gateway® vector, allowing a strong overexpression following acetamide induction, thus giving pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic>. Competent <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup> 155, <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis groEL1ΔC</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub> ::Hyg</italic> cells were prepared as previously described [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and were electroporated with a single pulse of 2.5 kV, 25 µF, and 1000 Ω by using a Gene Pulser Xcell™ Electroporation System (Bio-Rad). Selection was achieved by plating cells on complete Middlebrook agar medium supplemented with the proper antibiotic.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>Subcellular fractionation and immunoblotting</title><p>Recombinant <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis groEL1ΔC</italic> harboring pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> and pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> were cultured in 7H9-S medium supplemented with 50 µg/ml kanamycin until OD<sub>600</sub> was approximately 1–1.5. Cells were harvested for 10 min at 4000×<italic toggle="yes"><bold>g</bold></italic>, then washed twice with PBS (pH 7.4) buffer containing 0.05% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Tween-20, and re-suspended in lysis buffer (PBS pH 7.4 containing EDTA and 1 mM PMSF). Cells were then disrupted by using a French pressure cell at 1100 <italic toggle="yes">psi</italic>. Subcellular fractionation was performed as previously described [<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, the cell lysate was centrifuged two times at 1000×<italic toggle="yes"><bold>g</bold></italic> at 4°C in order to remove unbroken cells. Supernatant (total lysate) was further centrifuged two times at 27000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> at 4°C to separate cell wall/membrane from the cytoplasmic fraction. The pellet containing insoluble material was washed twice with PBS (pH 7.4) to remove any cytoplasmic contaminant, and supernatant containing the cytoplasmic fraction was further ultracentrifuged at 100000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 90 min at 4°C to remove any membrane contaminant. Each fraction was loaded and separated on to 12% SDS/PAGE and transferred on to a nitrocellulose membrane using a Trans-Blot Turbo Transfer System (Bio-Rad). Immunoblotting of 6× His-tagged proteins was performed using anti-HisProbe™ HRP conjugate (Thermo Fisher Scientific). MSMEG_0220 was used as the control for subcellular location, and immunoblotting was performed by using rabbit polyclonal antibodies [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and horseradish peroxidase–conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (Sigma-Aldrich). Revelation was achieved using Pierce™ ECL Western Blotting substrate solution (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and visualized with a ChemiDoc™ MP Imaging System (Bio-Rad).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>Genapol® extraction and immunoblotting</title><p>Approximately 10 uOD<sub>600</sub> of recombinant cells cultured in 7H9-S medium supplemented with 50 µg/ml kanamycin at OD<sub>600</sub> ∼1-1.5 were harvested for 10 min at 4000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold>. Cells were washed twice in PBS (pH 7.4) buffer containing 0.05% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Tween-20 and surface-exposed proteins were isolated by incubating cells with PBS containing 0.5% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) Genapol®-X080 (Sigma–Aldrich) at room temperature [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Control samples were treated with a PBS buffer without Genapol®-X080. After approximately 30 min, all supernatants were collected and precipitated with 12% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) trichloroacetic acid. Finally, samples were separated on to 12% SDS/PAGE and immunoblotting was achieved as described above.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title>Dynamic subcellular location using fluorescence microscopy</title><p>Gene encoding superfolder GFP (sfGFP) was amplified from pKD4-<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> plasmid with specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P13–P15 and P14–P15) which were cloned in pMV261 and pVV16 vectors at either EcoRI/HindIII or only HindIII restriction sites. Thus, creating pMV261::<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> and pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP. Rv0646c</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> ORFs were amplified by PCR with specific primers (Supplementary Table S1, P5–P6 and P7–P8) containing NdeI and BamHI restriction sites in 5′ and 3′ ends, respectively. Digested and purified products were cloned into the pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> in frame with the <italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> gene and thus generating a translational fusion. <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> was electroporated with 1.5 µg of pMV261::<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> and these latter constructs; recombinant clones were selected on to specific medium and overexpression of the two chimeric proteins were checked by immunoblotting as described above. Recombinant strains were cultured until OD<sub>600</sub> reaches ∼1-1.5, and then harvested by centrifugation at 4000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 10 min. Cells were washed once in PBS (pH 7.4) buffer, and bacterial suspension (5 µl) was spotted between a coverslip of 170 µm thickness and a 1.5% agarose-PBS pad. Bacteria were analyzed by snapshot imaging at room temperature using an Olympus FV1000 confocal microscope and 100× oil-objective. Exposure time was 800 ms for both phase-contrast and fluorescence images (λ<sub>exc</sub>\λ<sub>em</sub> = 490/530 ±10 nm). Images recorded were processed using the open source program ImageJ 1.51K (NIH, U.S.A.).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-10"><title>Lipid extraction and analysis</title><p>Mycobacterial strains were grown in 1 l of 7H9-S broth until an OD<sub>600</sub> of ∼1 was reached, except when using acetamide inducible strains where cells were collected at specific time points. Cultures were then centrifuged at 4000<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 15 min at 4°C and washed twice with distilled water. Pellets were lyophilized overnight and weighed to determine the exact mass of bacterial dry extract for normalization calculations.</p><p>MAs methyl esters (MAMEs) and fatty acids methyl esters (FAMEs) were extracted following previously described protocol [<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Approximately, 10 mg of cellular dry weight were re-suspended in 2 ml TBAH (40% <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>, Sigma–Aldrich) and incubated at 100°C overnight. Then 4 ml of CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>, 300 µl CH<sub>3</sub>I, and 2 ml of water were added to the mixture and incubated for 1 h at room temperature under shaking. Sample was centrifuged and the lower organic phase was kept, washed three times with distilled water, dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and then concentrated under nitrogen stream. Finally, 3 ml of DTT were added to the dried extract, and sonication was performed for 10 min in a water bath. Sample was centrifuged for 10 min at 4000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> to remove any precipitate. The DTT layer was evaporated and the residue was re-suspended in 100 µl of DTT. The same volume of extract containing MAMEs and FAMEs were separated on 1D TLC using hexane/ethyl acetate (19:1, <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) as eluent, and revealed by using a 10% phosphomolybdic acid solution in absolute ethanol.</p><p>Total lipids were extracted as previously described [<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, lipids from dry extract were incubated for 16 h with CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH (1:2; <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>), at room temperature under shaking. Residual lipids were re-extracted for 16 h with the same solvents, but using alternative ratios (1:1 and 2:1 <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>). All the three organic phases were pooled and concentrated under reduced pressure. Samples were re-suspended in a CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH solution (3:1, <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>), and washed with 0.3% (<italic toggle="yes">w/v</italic>) NaCl in water. Organic and aqueous phases were separated by centrifugation 4000×<bold><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></bold> for 10 min, and only the organic phases were conserved and dried over MgSO<sub>4</sub>. Samples were finally evaporated under a nitrogen stream, weighed, and re-suspended in a CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH solution (3:1, <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>).</p><p>Equal volume of extract containing glycopeptidolipids (GPLs) were separated on TLC (Silica Gel 60, Merck) by using CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH (90:10, <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) as eluent and further visualized by vaporization of 20% (<italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) sulphuric acid in ethanol. Phospholipid analyses were carried out by using both 1- or 2D TLC. Mono-dimensional TLC were performed by loading the same volume of extract and using CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH-H<sub>2</sub>O (65:25:4; <italic toggle="yes">v/v/v</italic>) as eluent. Concerning bi-dimensional TLC, the first dimension was resolved by using CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH-H<sub>2</sub>O (65:25:4; <italic toggle="yes">v/v/v</italic>) as solvent system 1, and CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH-CH<sub>3</sub>COOH-H<sub>2</sub>O (80:12:15:3; <italic toggle="yes">v/v/v/v</italic>) as solvent system 2. Phospholipids were visualized by vaporization of a copper acetate/orthophosphoric acid mixture prepared by mixing a copper acetate saturated solution with a 85% (1:1, <italic toggle="yes">v/v</italic>) aqueous orthophosphoric acid solution. Phospholipid standards were purchased from Sigma–Aldrich. Finally, each resolved plate was heated at 120°C for 5–10 min, scanned using a ChemiDoc™ MP Imaging System (Bio-Rad), and densitometric analyses was performed using the ImageLab™ software version 5.0 (Bio-Rad) allowing to determine the relative content of each sample.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-11"><title> REMA for MIC determination</title><p>Susceptibility testing was performed using the Middlebrook 7H9 broth microdilution method. All assays for each strain were carried out at least in triplicate. MICs against the various <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> bacterial strains were determined in 96-well flat-bottom Nunclon Delta Surface microplates with lid (Thermo Fisher Scientific) using REMA method [<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Briefly, log-phase bacteria were diluted to a cell density of 5 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml in 7H9-S medium. Then 100 µl of the above inoculum (i.e. 5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) was added to each well containing 100 µl of 7H9-S medium, serial two-fold dilutions of the selected antibiotics (RIF or INH), <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], <bold>HPOX</bold> [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], or <bold>Orlistat</bold> to a final volume of 200 µl. Growth controls containing no inhibitor (<italic toggle="yes">i.e.</italic>, bacteria only), inhibition controls containing 50 μg/ml kanamycin and sterility controls (i.e. medium only) without inoculation were also included. Plates were incubated at 37°C in a humidity chamber [<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] to prevent evaporation for 3–5 days. Then, 20 µl of a 0.02% (<italic toggle="yes">w/v</italic>) resazurin solution was added to each well, and the plates were incubated at 37°C for color change from blue to pink or violet and for a reading of fluorescence units (FU). Fluorescence corresponding to the resazurin reduction to its metabolite resorufin was quantitated using a Tecan Spark 10M multimode microplate reader (Tecan Group Ltd, France) with excitation at 530 nm and emission at 590 nm. Fluorometric MICs were determined by fitting the RFU% sigmoidal dose–response curves [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] in Kaleidagraph 4.2 software (Synergy Software). MIC values determined as the lowest compound concentrations inhibiting 50% of growth were defined as the MIC<sub>50</sub>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec4"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec4-1"><title>LipG is a highly conserved mycobacterial protein</title><p>Gene <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> encoding LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein was not only found within <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> genome. Genomic context containing <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene and its orthologs was indeed surprisingly highly conserved within many mycobacterial species. In <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis, Rv0646c</italic> is surrounded by an essential uncharacterized gene (<italic toggle="yes">Rv0647c</italic>) and the <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> cluster composed of four <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> genes (<italic toggle="yes">mmaA1–4</italic>) encoding proteins involved in MAs maturation processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Interestingly, the occurrence and genome organization of <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> clusters are also highly conserved in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis, M. leprae, M. marinum</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> genomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), with two copies of genes encoding for LipG proteins in <italic toggle="yes">M. marinum, M. abscessus</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">M. ulcerans</italic> genomes. Multiple sequence alignment of these various LipG proteins and sequence comparison, revealed a high level of amino-acid conservation, also with some consensus amino-acids blocks between each mycobacterial species [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] (Supplementary Figure S1). The LipG characteristics (i.e. sizes of genes/proteins and sequence identities) from different mycobacterial strains are summarized in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Each of these proteins possess a molecular weight ∼32 kDa, with the number of amino acids ranging from 301 to 324. Taken together, all these findings suggest that the cluster including the <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> gene may be dedicated to a common mycobacterial feature either in strict pathogenic, opportunistic, or non-pathogenic strains.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Genomic organization of <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> clusters in mycobacterial species</title><p>Schematic organization of the <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> genomic loci from <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis, M. leprae, M. marinum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> were designed based on the Mycobrowser database [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> genes are represented in yellow whereas genes involved in MAs maturation processes are in black. Furthermore, a conserved ORF encoding a putative ABC transporter was highlighted in red. Co-ordinates of each gene cluster are indicated in kb. Scale represents 500 bp.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Conservation and characteristics of mycobacterial LipG proteins</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycobacterial species/strains</th><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">LipG and orthologs</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene ID</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein size (aa)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1TFN1"><sup>1</sup></xref> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">888065</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> AF2122/97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mb_0665c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">1091775</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> BCG Pasteur 1173P2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">BCG_0695c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">4697156</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. canetti</italic> CIPT 140010059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MCAN_06451</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">10986452</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. leprae</italic> TN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ML_1899</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">910591</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. marinum</italic> M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MMAR_0981</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">6225233</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>1</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MMAR_0983</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">6225235</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. ulcerans</italic> Agy99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MUL_0733</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">4552132</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>1</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">314</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MUL_0735</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">4552134</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">303</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. abscessus</italic> ATCC 19977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MABS_3878</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">5967421</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MABS_3880</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">5966346</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG<sub>1</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> mc<sup>2</sup>155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">4534086</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LipG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1TFN1"><label>1</label><p>Amino-acid sequence identity related to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec4-2"><title>Cloning, expression purification, and biochemical characterization of LipG<sub>MTB</sub>
</title><p>In an attempt to characterize LipG biochemical activities more finely, to confirm its carboxylesterase properties [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and also to decipher the physiological role of this protein, the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MSEG_1352</italic> genes have been cloned. The respective recombinant rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> and rLipG<sub>MS</sub> were produced in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C41 (DE3)/pLyS strain harboring the pRare plasmid. rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> and purification was achieved using Ni<sup>2+</sup>-NTA affinity chromatography, yielding ∼1 mg of pure recombinant protein per culture liter. The purity and the expected molecular weight (∼35 kDa) were confirmed by 12% SDS/PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A) and MALDI-TOF analysis.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Purification and biochemical characterization of recombinant rLipG<sub>MTB</sub></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Purity assessment of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>. rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> (5 µg) was loaded on to 12% polyacrylamide gel. Unstained protein molecular weight marker was used as standard (Euromedex). (<bold>B</bold>) Carboxylesterase S.A determination on <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-ester substrates with chain lengths varying from C2 to C16. (<bold>C</bold>) Thioesterase activity measurements corresponding to palmitoyl-CoA hydrolysis. (<bold>D</bold>) PLA<sub>1</sub> and PLA<sub>2</sub> activity using fluorescent phospholipids. TL PLA<sub>1</sub>, Bv PLA<sub>2</sub>, and LipY were used as positive and negative controls, respectively. (<bold>E</bold>) PLA<sub>1</sub> enzymatic activity of the rLipG<sub>MTB</sub><sup>S123A</sup> compared with rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>. Results are expressed as relative activity in %. Each result is expressed as mean values ± S.D. of at least three independent assays. Abbreviation: Bv PLA<sub>2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">Bee venom</italic> PLA<sub>2</sub>, TL PLA<sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">T. lanuginosus</italic> lipase PLA<sub>1</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g2.jpg"/></fig><p>The esterase activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was first assayed using <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP esters with various carbon chain lengths ranging from C2 to C16 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). Whatever their chain length, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was able to hydrolyze all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP esters, therefore displaying a large substrate specificity as previously reported by Rastogi et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While similar S.A were obtained with short <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C4 and medium <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C8 esters (mean S.A = 4.26 ± 0.11 U/mg). However, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> exhibited a clear significant preference for <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C6 ester with a S.A value of 6.12 ± 0.17 U/mg. For <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP esters carrying more than eight carbon atoms, this S.A dropped sharply to 2.6 ± 0.18, 2.1 ± 0.21, 0.53 ± 0.08, and 0.19 ± 0.01 U/mg for <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C10, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C12, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C14, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C16, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). Interestingly, amongst the Lip protein family member’s, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> substrate specificity using <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP esters was similar to those of the esterase’s LipU and LipR [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>The lipase activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> has also been tested using a large panel of triacylglycerol (TAG) substrates, such as trioctanoin and triolein using the pH-stat technique, and pomegranate oil-coated TAG method [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In all cases, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was not able to hydrolyze any of these TAGs, even when using highly sensitive fluorogenic TAG substrates [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. It is well known that lipases differ from esterases by their ability to hydrolyze long-chain acylglycerols at the oil–water interface, whereas esterases can only hydrolyze substrates with short- or medium-fatty acid chains [<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. From these findings, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> could be considered as a true carboxylesterase, as recently proposed by Rastogi et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>Due to its genomic localization in the same cluster as the <italic toggle="yes">mmaA</italic> genes encoding for methyltransferase proteins, it is tempting to suggest that rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> might also be able to hydrolyze the thioester bond of acyl-CoA or MA intermediates as previously shown for Cut6 (<italic toggle="yes">Rv3802c</italic>). Cut6 is an essential bifunctional phospholipase A and thioesterase enzyme belonging to the Cutinase-like family proteins from <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Thioesterases are a group of enzymes that catalyze the hydrolysis of a thioester bond between a carbonyl group and a sulphur atom. Here, the hydrolysis of palmitoyl-CoA was used to measure the thioesterase activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> also exhibited a thioesterase activity with an S.A value of 2.10 ± 0.59 mU/mg. It is noteworthy that this value is of the same order of magnitude as that of TesA, a thioesterase of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] with a S.A of 5.95 ± 0.85 mU/mg.</p><p>In order to investigate further rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> enzyme activity, its phospholipase activity was also investigated. Interestingly, rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was able to hydrolyze only fluorescent phospholipids present at the <italic toggle="yes">sn−1</italic> stereospecific position with S.A value of 2.75 ± 0.25 mU/mg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D) suggesting that rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a strict PLA<sub>1</sub>. <italic toggle="yes">T. lanuginosus</italic> lipase PLA<sub>1</sub> (TL PLA<sub>1</sub>) and <italic toggle="yes">Bee venom</italic> PLA<sub>2</sub> (Bv PLA<sub>2</sub>) were used as positive controls for the PLA<sub>1</sub> and PLA<sub>2</sub> activities, respectively.</p><p>Finally, since Rastogi et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] had proposed that the catalytic machinery was governed by Ser<sup>123</sup>, we thus generated by site-directed mutagenesis a rLipG<sub>MTB</sub><sup>S123A</sup> variant, in which this Ser<sup>123</sup> residue was mutated into an Ala residue. As predicted, no enzyme activity was observed with fluorescent-phospholipids, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-substrates or palmitoyl-CoA with this inactive mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E and data not shown). Taken together, these data provide full evidence that Ser<sup>123</sup> contained in the consensus sequence G<sup>121</sup>A<bold>S</bold>MG<sup>125</sup> is the catalytic residue responsible for the enzyme activity, and consequently, confirms that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a true serine hydrolase. More specifically and given the level of S.A reached with the various substrates investigated, our results suggest that rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a phospholipase A<sub>1</sub> enzyme which also displays esterase and thioesterase activities.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-3"><title>rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> is inhibited by OX derivatives and CyC analogs</title><p>Two series of recently reported antitubercular inhibitors discovered in our laboratory (<bold>OX</bold> derivatives and <bold>CyC</bold> analogs), exhibit activity against enzymes by forming a covalent bond with the catalytic serine or cysteine residue in their active sites [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref>]. In order to further investigate the ability of these compounds to efficiently inhibit the lipolytic activity of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>, six <bold>OX</bold> derivatives (i.e. <bold>M<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>PPOX, iBPOX, iB<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX, HPOX, H<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX</bold>, and <bold>BePOX)</bold> [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]; and five <bold>CyC</bold> analogs (i.e. the <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub>, CyC<sub>7α</sub>, CyC<sub>7β</sub>, CyC<sub>8α</sub></bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>8β</sub></bold>) [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] were then tested for inhibition of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>. In our previous work, whereas <bold>iB<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX</bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>7β</sub></bold> and <bold>CyC<sub>8α</sub></bold> exhibited strong activity against both extracellular and intramacrophagic <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>; <bold>iBPOX</bold> and <bold>H<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX</bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>7α</sub></bold> and <bold>CyC<sub>8β</sub></bold> were found active on infected macrophages only [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In contrast, <bold>HPOX</bold> and <bold>BePOX</bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> efficiently block <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> with no activity against intracellular bacilli [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. <bold>Orlistat</bold> which has been previously reported as an inhibitor of LipG was used as positive control [<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The chemical structures of the 12 compounds used in this study are provided in Supplementary Figure S2.</p><p>rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> was inactivated by all the six <bold>OX</bold> derivatives, with medium 60.6% to good 93.8% inhibition levels at <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub> = 100 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The best inhibitors were <bold>HPOX, M<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>PPOX</bold>, and <bold>H<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX</bold>, which displayed inhibitor molar excess leading to 50% enzyme inhibition, i.e. <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub> values of ∼3.0 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Amongst the <bold>CyC</bold> analogs, <bold>CyC<sub>7β</sub>, CyC<sub>8α</sub></bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>8β</sub></bold> exhibited very weak inhibitory effects up to a high molar excess <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub> = 100. Whereas, a strong dose-dependent inhibition was observed with <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> and <bold>CyC<sub>7α</sub></bold> (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). In particular, <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> was found to react almost stoichiometrically with rLipG<sub>MTB</sub>, as confirmed by its <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub> value of 0.98. It is noteworthy, that <bold>Orlistat</bold>, used as reference inhibitor, displayed only a moderate inhibitory activity against pure rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> with only 69.5% inhibition at <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub> = 100 and a <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub> value of 15.2, similar to those of <bold>iB<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX, iBPOX</bold>, and <bold>BePOX</bold>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Inhibition of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> after a 30-min incubation period with each inhibitor<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T2TFN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compounds</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">% inhibition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x<sub>I50</sub></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x<sub>I</sub> = 4</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x<sub>I</sub> = 100</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MmPPOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0 ± 3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>iBpPPOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5 ± 3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6 ± 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>iBPOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 ± 0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.3 ± 0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HpPPOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.8 ± 4.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8 ± 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HPOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5 ± 1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8 ± 5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.9</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BePOX</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 ± 0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8 ± 1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CyC<sub>7α</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4 ± 0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.4 ± 1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CyC<sub>7β</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 ± 0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6 ± 2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CyC<sub>8α</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 ± 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3 ± 2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CyC<sub>8β</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 ± 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0 ± 1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.4 ± 4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.4 ± 2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.98</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Orlistat</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 ± 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.5 ± 5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2TFN1"><label>1</label><p>Inhibition data (% of initial activity), at inhibitor molar excess (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub>) of 4 and 100 related to 1 mol of enzyme. Results are expressed as mean values ± S.D. of at least three independent assays. The inhibitor molar excess leading to 50% lipase inhibition, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I50</sub>, was determined as described in <bold>Experimental procedures</bold> section.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Inhibition studies of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> by OX derivatives and CyC analogs</title><p>Residual activities of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> measured on <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C6 as substrate. Effects of increasing molar excess (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub>) of compounds (<bold>A</bold>) <bold>M<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>PPOX, H<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>PPOX, HPOX</bold>, and (<bold>B</bold>) <bold>CyC<sub>7</sub></bold><sub>α</sub>, <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> and <bold>Orlistat</bold> on the rates of hydrolysis of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP-C6. LipG<sub>MTB</sub> was pre-incubated at various inhibitor molar excess (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>I</sub>) for 30 min at 25°C. Kinetic assays were performed as described in <bold>Experimental procedures</bold> section. Results are expressed as mean values ± S.D. of three independent assays.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec4-4"><title>rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> and rLipG<sub>MS</sub> are peripheral membrane protein</title><p>Although LipG<sub>MTB</sub> has been identified in the membrane fraction of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv by using proteomic profiling approach [<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> experiments performed using SignalP 4.1 server [<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] revealed that neither a peptide signal for the general secretion pathway or for the twin-arginine translocation pathway, nor a Type VII consensus secretion motif YxxxD/E were present in the primary sequence of LipG proteins. In this context, recombinant <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> strains, overexpressing either rLipG<sub>MS</sub> (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> gene) or rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene) cloned under the control of the <italic toggle="yes">hsp60</italic> promoter in frame with a C-terminal 6× His-tag, were subjected to subcellular fractionation followed by immunoblotting experiments. The well-characterized cell wall exported monoglyceride lipase, MSMEG_0220, was used as control for cell fractionation [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In each case, both proteins were found only within the cell wall fraction and not in the soluble cytoplasmic fraction suggesting that LipG is a membrane/cell wall-associated protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A,B). Additional differential detergent extraction of surface-exposed mycobacterial proteins using Genapol®-X080 [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], followed by precipitation and immunoblotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C), demonstrated that LipG protein remains associated with the pellet fraction. This results suggest that this enzyme would not be accessible to the detergent and thus is not a surface-exposed protein. In contrast, MSMEG_0220 was found within the supernatant fraction, as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). All these data strengthen the fact that mycobacterial LipG are peripheral proteins, interacting with the inner leaflet of the cytoplasmic membrane.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Subcellular location of LipG proteins</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>,<bold>B</bold>) Subcellular localization of LipG<sub>MS</sub> and LipG<sub>MTB</sub> in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis groEL1ΔC</italic> determined by ultracentrifugation. Recombinant cells expressing 6× His-tagged LipG were lysed, total lysate (TL), cytoplasm (Cyt), and cell wall (CW) fractions were separated by ultracentrifugation. Samples were loaded on to 12% SDS/PAGE and immunoblotted using HisProbe reagent. The exported MSMEG_0220 was used as control. (<bold>C</bold>) Determination of cell-surface-exposition of LipG<sub>MS</sub> and LipG<sub>MTB</sub> in <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis groEL1ΔC</italic> by detergent extraction. Recombinant cells expressing 6× His-tagged LipG were treated with PBS-buffer or with PBS-buffer containing Genapol®-X080 detergent. Pellet (P) and supernatant (S) fractions containing cytoplasmic and surface-exposed proteins respectively, were separated by centrifugation. Samples were loaded on to 12% SDS/PAGE and immunoblotted using HisProbe reagent. The exported MSMEG_0220 was used as a control. (<bold>D</bold>) Fluorescence microscopy analysis of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis groEL1ΔC</italic> strains carrying either WT <italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> gene or <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub>-sfGFP</italic> translational fusions. Cells were analyzed in both phase contrast (upper panel) and fluorescent channels (bottom panel). Scale bars represent 1 µm. (<bold>E</bold>) Electrostatic potential of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> 3D model. The electrostatic surface potentials were displayed color-coded on to a van der Waals surface using the PyMOL Molecular Graphics System (version 1.8, Schrödinger, LLC). Red and blue colors represent net negative and positive charges, while white color represents overall neutral positions, respectively Black lines are showing the catalytic pocket. Two rotations of 90° were performed in order to provide a better view of the high potential area on top of the protein. (<bold>F</bold>) Position of positively charged residues in LipG<sub>MTB</sub> 3D model. Positives residues were highlighted in orange. The two rotations of 90° were conserved in order to provide a better view of the positively charged residues on top of the protein. An arginine-rich patch has been identified and position of the respective residues (R<sup>234</sup>, R<sup>237</sup>, R<sup>238</sup>, R<sup>260</sup>, R<sup>264</sup> and R<sup>270</sup>) are marked with black arrows.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g4.jpg"/></fig><p>To go further, the dynamic location of LipG within living cells was investigated by using fluorescence microscopy [<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Gene fusions between <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">MSMEG_1352</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> gene encoding the sfGFP [<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] were generated and used to transform <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> cells. Recombinant clones harboring stable fusions (Supplementary Figure S3) with a constant and important expression level were grown to mid-log exponential phase (i.e. OD<sub>600</sub> = 1) in classical 7H9-S medium and further analyzed by fluorescence microscopy. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D (right panel), the strains harboring LipG<sub>MTB</sub>-sfGFP chimeric construct emitted a strong fluorescence signal mainly localized at the periphery of the inner mycobacterial cell membrane. In contrast, the fluorescence signal of the recombinant strain expressing only a wild-type sfGFP was less intense and diffuse through the cytoplasmic compartment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D, left panel). Similar results were obtained when the bacteria was processed either at early exponential phase (i.e. OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.2) or at the stationary phase (i.e. OD<sub>600</sub> = 3). These findings strongly suggest that the resulting chimeric LipG proteins remain clustered into the bacterial cytoplasmic membrane whatever the phase of bacterial growth.</p><p>To get structural insights concerning LipG<sub>MTB</sub> and its potential interaction within the cytoplasmic membrane, a 3D structural model was built using the I-TASSER server [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The X-ray structure of <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces lividans</italic> methylesterase RdmC (PDB id: 1Q0R), solved at 1.45 Å resolution was used as a template [<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. This generated model revealed that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is a serine hydrolase constituted by 11 α-helices and 8 β-strands that are forming a central β-sheet (Supplementary Figure S4) as previously described [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A putative catalytic triad composed by Ser<sup>123</sup>, Asp<sup>251</sup>, and His<sup>279</sup> is located within a highly accessible active site surrounded by hydrophobic residues forming the catalytic pocket (Supplementary Figure S4). In an effort to better characterize the molecular interactions that might govern LipG binding on to the inner cell membrane, the electrostatic surface potential of the previously built 3D model structure of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> (Supplementary Figure S4) was generated and is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>E,F. Interestingly, a positive electrostatic patch located opposite to the active site, on top of the model structure, was found. Notably, this specific amino-acid patch is mainly constituted by six arginine residues highly conserved in several LipG orthologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>E,F and Supplementary Figure S5). Such arginine residues, which are indeed known to play important role in protein binding to zwitterionic and anionic glycerolipid polar head groups [<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], might thus contribute to the binding of LipG to the cytoplasmic membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>E,F).</p></sec><sec id="sec4-5"><title>Disruption of MSMEG_1352 triggers cell wall modifications</title><p>In order to identify the physiological role of the LipG proteins within the mycobacterial lifecycle, a <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis MSMEG_1352</italic> disrupted strain named <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic>, in which the gene has been interrupted with a hygromycin resistance cassette, as well as a <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> complemented strain (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic>) were produced (Supplementary Figure S6). When grown in 7H9-S medium for 48 h at 37°C, no significant differences in growth rate were observed between the WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic> strains. Interestingly, when the strains were grown on to 7H11TG agar plates (i.e. 7H11 medium supplemented with 0.02% Tween 80 and 0.2% glycerol), no differences in colony morphologies were observed with naked eyes. In contrast, when agar plates were spot-inoculated on to the same medium devoid of detergent and observed under a stereomicroscope, the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> mutant strain harbored a slightly smoother and rounder phenotype than the WT and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). This finding would suggest that disruption of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> may trigger some minor cell surface modifications (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). TLC analysis of total lipid extract reveals that disruption of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> induces a slight but significant overproduction of GPLs by 1.35-fold compared with WT strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). In contrast, no detectable changes were observed within FAMEs and MAMEs levels as well as phospholipid content between each strain (Supplementary Figure S7A,B).</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Disruption of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> triggers cell-wall modifications and decreases antibiotics susceptibility</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Colony morphology of WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted and complemented strains. Recombinant strains were grown in 7H9-S before being spotted on to Middlebrook 7H11 agar plate devoid of Tween-80. Images are representative of two independent experiments. (<bold>B</bold>) GPL analysis of WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted and complemented strains. Cells were grown in 7H9-S until OD<sub>600 nm</sub> ∼1–1.5. Lipid extraction was followed by TLC (left panel) and densitometry analysis (right panel). Results are expressed as mean ± S.D. of total GPL level from three independent experiments, where WT level was arbitrarily adjusted to 1 relative unit. Statistical analysis was performed by using the Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. Relative GPL level from <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted mutant were compared with the WT where * corresponded to a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt;0.05. Relative GPL level from <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> complemented strain were compared with the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted mutant where # corresponded to a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt;0.05. (<bold>C</bold>) Antibiotic susceptibility of WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted and complemented strains. Susceptibility toward INH, RIF, and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> were determined using the REMA. Fluorometric MIC<sub>50</sub>s were determined by fitting the RFU% sigmoidal dose–response curves. Graph fitting are representative of three independent assays performed in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g5.jpg"/></fig><p>Although bacterial cell wall remodeling (including misregulation of GPL production) may also affect biofilm/pellicle formation, neither global nor visible modifications where observed amongst the WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic> strains regarding pellicle formation (Supplementary Figure S7C) in 7H9-S medium containing either glycerol or acetate as carbon source.</p><p>Since the mycobacterial cell wall is the first effective barrier against bactericidal compounds, we hypothesized that increase in GPLs could also play an important role in cell wall integrity. To answer this question, the WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic> strains were subjected to antibiotic susceptibility testing toward standard antibiotics INH and RIF, using the REMA method [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The effects of <bold>Orlistat, HPOX</bold> as well as the <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> inhibitor on the growth of each strains were also investigated.</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Susceptibility testing of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> WT and mutant strains</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">MIC<sub>50</sub> (µg/ml)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3TFN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Fold change compared with WT</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INH</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIF</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orlistat</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CyC<sub>17</sub></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INH</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIF</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orlistat</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CyC<sub>17</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×6.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×15.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp<sub>MTB</sub></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">×1.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3TFN1"><label>1</label><p>MIC<sub>50</sub> values corresponding to the compound minimal concentration leading to 50% growth inhibition have been determined by the REMA method and are expressed as mean values of three independent assays performed in duplicate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>It is noteworthy that the respective MIC<sub>50</sub> values obtained with INH (0.76 µg/ml), RIF (1.4 µg/ml), and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> (0.56 µg/ml) against the WT strain are in accordance with previously published studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Regarding <bold>Orlistat</bold>, this well-known serine hydrolase inhibitor [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] is able to impair <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> growth with an MIC<sub>50</sub> of 0.97 µg/ml. Surprisingly, deletion of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> leads to an increased drug tolerance toward the four compounds. As depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, MIC<sub>50</sub> of INH, RIF, <bold>Orlistat</bold>, and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> against the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> strain amounted to 2.9, 3.3, 6.5, and 9.6 µg/ml, respectively, thus corresponding to a respective fold change compared with the WT strain of ×2.0, ×4.3, ×6.7, and ×15.7. The complementation of the mutant strain with the pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> restored the drug susceptibility with mean MIC<sub>50</sub> fold change compared with WT strain of approximately ×1.2 to ×1.3.</p><p>Similar results were obtained with <bold>HPOX</bold> inhibitor. MIC<sub>50</sub> values of 8.4 and 18.4 µg/ml were obtained for the WT and <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> strains, respectively; leading to a fold change compared with the WT strain of ×2.2. However, with this compound the complementation with pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> vector only partially restored the drug susceptibility with an intermediate MIC<sub>50</sub> value of 12.2 µg/ml (i.e. fold change compared with WT strain of approximately ×1.5).</p><p>Finally, we also carried out these experiments by performing complementation of the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> strain with the pVV16::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> vector (<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg Comp<sub>MTB</sub></italic>). Interestingly, production of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein was perfectly able to restore the drug susceptibility, suggesting that the two proteins may possess similar enzymatic activities and/or physiological functions (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>To further confirm this result, the recombinant rLipG<sub>MS</sub> was produced, purified, and biochemically characterized as described above for rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> (Supplementary Figure S8 and Table S2). Both pure rLipG<sub>MS</sub> and rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> proteins thus exhibit the same substrate specificity toward <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP ester substrates, the best S.A being also found with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP caproate (C6). Moreover, rLipG<sub>MS</sub> was also able to hydrolyze acyl-CoA and phospholipids as substrates, confirming that the substrate specificity is well conserved between the two proteins. Despite their similar reactivity pattern with various esters, we noticed, however, that the rLipG<sub>MS</sub> was more active than its ortholog (Supplementary Table S2). Interestingly, these differences where only observed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> using pure proteins, but not during <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-complementation with the <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> gene during <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments as described above.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-6"><title>Overexpression of lipG<sub>MTB</sub> impacts free fatty acids and phospholipids homeostasis</title><p>Despite the observed impact of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> gene disruption on to the penetration/diffusion of the latter antitubercular molecules within the mycobacterial envelope, no clear detectable phenotype has been observed. To overcome such issue, a recombinant strain harboring the pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> plasmid which allows a strong overproduction of the LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein upon acetamide induction, has been constructed. Approximately 6 and 24 h following induction by acetamide, total lipid extraction was performed on cell cultures either in exponential (OD<sub>600</sub> ∼1–1.5) or stationary (OD<sub>600</sub> ∼3–4) phase, respectively. The effect of LipG<sub>MTB</sub> overproduction was scrutinized by TLC analysis. As expected from our previous results which showed a slight increase in GPL production in absence of LipG<sub>MS</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A,B), in the strain overproducing LipG<sub>MTB</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A), a clear drop in GPLs production was observed at 6 h (61 ± 8%) and 24 h (51 ± 12%) post-induction when compared with the WT strain harboring the empty pMyC vector as reference. However, in contrast with <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic>, the fact that <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv does not produce GPLs may suggest a different functional role of LipG in this latter mycobacteria. This prompted us to further analyze other lipid subclasses. Accordingly, a semi-quantitative analysis of <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> strains harboring pMyC and pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> revealed that the overproduction of the protein significantly increases the level of FAMEs by 1.42-fold and 1.25-fold compared with control strain at 6 and 24 h post-induction, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B), without affecting MAMEs level or ratio.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>LipG<sub>MTB</sub> impacts free fatty acids and phospholipids biosynthesis</title><p>Mycobacterial cultures harboring pMyC and pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> were grown in 7H9-S medium until reaching OD<sub>600 nm</sub> ∼0.5, then 0.2% of acetamide was added inside the culture medium. Cells were collected at 6 or 24 h post-induction corresponding to exponential or stationary phase, lyophilized and the same amount of dry cell weight was use for lipid extraction. After normalization, the same volume of each sample was loaded on to TLC. (<bold>A</bold>) Global GPL levels are decreasing in an <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> overexpression strain. Lipid extracts of each samples were analyzed by TLC followed by densitometry analysis. (<bold>B</bold>) FAMEs levels are increasing in an <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> overexpression strain. Lipid extracts of each samples were analyzed by TLC followed by densitometry analysis. In each case, results are expressed as mean ± S.D. of each respective total lipid species levels from at least two independent experiments, where control strain level at t<sub>6 h</sub> was arbitrary adjusted to 1 relative unit. (<bold>C</bold>) Phospholipid biosynthesis is increased in an <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> overexpression strain. Lipid extracts of each samples were analyzed by TLC followed by densitometry analysis. TLC was performed with CHCl<sub>3</sub>-MeOH-H<sub>2</sub>O (65:25:4; <italic toggle="yes">v/v/v</italic>) as eluent and PI overproduction is indicated with a red asterisk (left panel). Lipid sample from <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> at t<sub>6 h</sub> was also co-injected with pure PI standard as control lane, to clearly identify PI as an overproduced subspecies. Histograms correspond to densitometry analysis at t<sub>6 h</sub>. Results are displayed as intensity ratio where phospholipids levels from the pMyC::<italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> strain were divided by the phospholipids levels from the pMyC strain (right panel). Results are expressed as mean ± S.D. from three independent experiments. Statistical analysis was performed by using the Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test where * correspond to a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt;0.05. Abbreviation: PI, phosphatidylinositol.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-38-bsr20181953-g6.jpg"/></fig><p>Regarding phospholipid levels, surprisingly overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> slightly increases the phospholipid level of phosphatidylethanolamine (PE) and phosphatidylglycerol (PG) subspecies (1.75- and 1.07-fold in comparison with the control strain, respectively), but more importantly, this overproduction drastically impacts phosphatidylinositol (PI) production with a fold-change related to the control strain of ×2.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). These results were further confirmed by using 2D-TLC analysis, where a nice and efficient separation of all species of phospholipids allowed to confirm a consequent increase in PI biosynthesis upon LipG<sub>MTB</sub> overproduction (Supplementary Figure S9).</p><p>Altogether, the increase in the levels of both FAMEs and specific subclass of phospholipids suggest that the LipG<sub>MTB</sub> acyl-CoA-thioesterase activity may be the predominant biochemical activity <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, and that the products of the reaction are directly influencing cell wall phospholipids composition.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is one of the most successful infectious agents worldwide. Therefore, understanding the molecular mechanisms responsible for its pathogenesis remains one of the most important challenges in TB fundamental research. By using highly elaborate genetic screens, several independent teams have indeed tried to identify the genes required for <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> bacterial survival [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. These approaches have highlighted the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> which is required for adaptation and survival of the bacilli in mouse macrophages [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Interestingly, this gene has been annotated as encoding a putative lipase/esterase protein based on the presence of a G-x-S-x-G consensus pentapeptide motif. More importantly, the <italic toggle="yes">Rv0646c</italic> gene encoding LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is widely conserved through the <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium</italic> genus and is associated with a gene cluster involved in MAs maturation processes [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Strikingly, bioinformatics analysis demonstrated that this gene is highly conserved in both slow- and fast-growing mycobacteria, and even in the obligate intracellular parasite <italic toggle="yes">M. leprae</italic>. This latter unusual pathogen is harboring a genome with a large number of inactivated pseudogenes which are not required anymore <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> [<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. However, amongst the 24 genes encoding lipolytic enzymes from the Lip family in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, only <italic toggle="yes">lipE, lipU</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> are conserved in <italic toggle="yes">M. leprae</italic>, thus reinforcing an essential role played by these enzymes in intracellular survival and proliferation [<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In this study based on biochemical characterization of rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein associated with microbiology experiments, we uncovered the potential role of this enzyme in mycobacterial lipid metabolism.</p><p>In accordance with a recent report, we confirmed that recombinant LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein is an esterase acting preferentially on medium chain-length substrates [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. More interestingly, we also found that the protein was able to hydrolyze phospholipids at the <italic toggle="yes">sn−1</italic> position and cleave the thioester bond from palmitoyl-CoA, showing that rLipG<sub>MTB</sub> possesses esterase and phospholipase, as well as thioesterase activities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Both phospholipase and thioesterase activities have been already observed by Parker et al. [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], who described that <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis Rv3802c</italic> gene (<italic toggle="yes">cut6</italic>) encodes a functional phospholipase/thioesterase protein. Using radiolabeled phospholipids coupled with TLC analysis, the authors showed that Cut6 was not only able to act on PE, PC, and phosphatidylserine (PS) molecules [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], but that it was also able to hydrolyze both palmitoyl- and decanoyl-CoA, suggesting that the protein may act as an acyl donor <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p><p>The fact that LipG was required for adaptation and survival within macrophages, prompted us to investigate the inhibitory properties of two new series of serine hydrolase inhibitors active against <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref>]. During <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> inhibition experiments on pure protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the best inhibitors from the two series of compounds were <bold>HPOX</bold> (for the <bold>OX</bold> derivatives) on the one hand, and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> (for the <bold>CyC</bold> analogs) on the other hand; two molecules that are only active against extracellularly growing <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> strain [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In the case of <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold>, this result was <italic toggle="yes">a posteriori</italic> predictable. Following activity-based protein profiling experiment coupled with proteomics analyses [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], LipG was indeed found as a potential target of this compound from a lysate of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (unpublished data). However, its low coverage (21% sequence identity) with only five distinct peptide sequences identified together with a peptide score ∼2.0–3.4 (given by SequestHT algorithm) made that this protein was below our threshold and was not selected. Conversely, LipG was not identified from similar ABPP experiments performed with <bold>HPOX</bold> directly on living <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> cells [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We recently demonstrated that both the <bold>OX</bold> and <bold>CyC</bold> families of compound are multitarget inhibitors, which are probably displaying pleiotropic and cumulative effects toward mycobacterial Ser- and Cys-containing enzymes involved in lipid metabolism and/or cell wall maintenance, thus leading to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth arrest [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. From these findings and despite their strong inhibitory effect <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> on pure LipG enzyme, we thus proposed that <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>
<bold>HPOX</bold> and <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> preferentially impair other previously identified target enzymes such as the Ag85 complex or the thioesterase TesA rather than LipG<sub>MTB</sub>.</p><p>Based on proteomic analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> membrane fraction, it has been recently proposed that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> may be localized to the cell surface and directly interact with the host immune system [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, bioinformatics analysis did not reveal the presence of any secretion signals or specific motifs, which may indicate that the protein is surface exposed. Herein, using different cell-fractionation approaches, we demonstrated that LipG<sub>MTB</sub> is associated with the membrane fraction [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], but not translocated across the cytoplasmic membrane and remains a cytoplasmic protein which is mainly peripheral (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). It has been described that such peripheral proteins require either a lipophilic attachment (i.e. acylation) or the presence of basic residues positively charged [<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] which induce electrostatic interaction with the acidic and negatively charged phospholipids head-groups, thus allowing anchoring of the protein within the cytoplasmic membrane [<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Based on our 3D structure model, surface electrostatic potential analysis allows identification of a region on top of the active site mainly composed by positively charged residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>E,F). This area is essentially constituted by a C-terminal cluster of arginine residues fully conserved in numerous LipG proteins (Supplementary Figure S5). Since this type of electrostatic interaction has already been described for a mycobacterial protein involved in acyl-CoA metabolism [<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], one can assume that this cluster of Arg residues would play an important role in LipG binding to the cell membrane, and thus for its physiological function.</p><p>In contrast with Cut6, which is known for being secreted and acting outside the mycobacterial cell [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], LipG<sub>MTB</sub> and LipG<sub>MS</sub> are presumably hydrolyzing cytoplasmic substrates. Two distinct strategies were employed: (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>) the generation of a <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> disrupted strain which was <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-complemented with either <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub></italic> or <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> and (<italic toggle="yes">ii</italic>) the generation of a <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MTB</sub></italic> heterologous overexpression strain which were useful in identifying the potential physiological role of LipG proteins and to define their substrates <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. On one hand, the observed increase in GPLs production due to <italic toggle="yes">lipG</italic> gene disruption (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) resulted in a significant reduced susceptibility to RIF, INH, <bold>Orlistat, HPOX</bold>, and above all <bold>CyC<sub>17</sub></bold> for which the highest fold change compared with WT strain in MIC<sub>50</sub> value has been reached (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Since RIF and INH are inhibiting specifically cytoplasmic targets, we hypothesized that such increase in GPL will affect cell wall fluidity and integrity; which subsequently impacts the penetration of the main two first-line anti-TB drugs [<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Such results are in agreement with Khoo et al. work [<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] who reported that <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> GPLs positive serovar were less sensitive to ethambutol than GPLs negative serovar, and concluded that hydrophobic GPLs production may alter cell wall permeability and correlate with antibiotic tolerance [<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. In other hand, the overproduction of the LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein leads to a significant increase in the FAMEs level (1.42-fold and 1.25-fold at 6 and 24 h post-induction, respectively), but more importantly a decrease in GPLs levels within <italic toggle="yes">M. smegmatis</italic> concomitant to an increase in level of phospholipid species and more particularly, the phosphatidyl inositol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). However this is not the first time that such modifications of the cell wall composition have been observed. Similar phenotypes with drastic alteration of FAMEs/MAMEs and phospholipid subspecies levels have already been described in 2009, by Meniche et al. [<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> The authors demonstrated that overexpression of the <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic> gene <italic toggle="yes">NCgl2775</italic> encoding a functional thioesterase/phospholipase protein leads to an increase in MAs production concomitantly with a decrease in glycerophosphoslipids levels [<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. A similar result was also obtained when the MSMEG_6394 protein (i.e. NCgl2775 and Cut6 orthologs) was overproduced, which prompted the authors to propose that this kind of bifunctional enzyme is may be able to regulate membrane compositions under specific conditions [<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].</p><p>Since not all the mycobacterial strain are GPLs producers, especially <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> H<sub>37</sub>Rv, we postulated that this phenotype was more an indirect effect, than a direct catabolic process transposable to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>.</p><p>From all these findings, it is tempting to propose that LipG is mainly acting as a thioesterase dedicated to phospholipid metabolism <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. In a large number of bacteria, the contribution of thioesterase proteins to phospholipid biosynthetic process is however not well-defined. For example, in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, glycerol starvation leads to an increase in acyl-ACP and a drastic diminution of phospholipid levels. Overexpression of TesA, a type I thioesterase, drastically reduced the accumulation of long-chain acyl-ACP species, probably by rerouting free fatty acids to phospholipids [<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. It has also been proposed that the <italic toggle="yes">ybgC</italic> gene encoding a functional acyl thioesterase is playing a role in phospholipid metabolism in Gram-negative bacteria [<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81–83</xref>]. Astonishingly, this latter enzyme is known for interacting with a large number of proteins dedicated to phospholipid homeostasis, such as the acyl-carrier protein, the glycerol 3-phosphate acyltransferase (PlsB), and the PS synthase (PssA) [<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Such systems dedicated to phospholipids have not been described so far in mycobacteria, but a similar multicomponent complex is involved in MA biosynthesis [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Overall, it might be possible that some proteins work together in order to respond to specific stimuli and thus modulate biological membrane composition and fluidity. Such a physiological process has also been reported in eukaryotic cells, where upon inflammatory stimulus, the acyl-CoA thioesterase 7 (ACOT7) converts acyl-CoA molecules into free fatty acids, thus triggering a remodeling of phospholipid containing unsaturated long (≥C<sub>20</sub>)-acyl chains in macrophages [<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>].</p><p>Finally, PI is known for being an essential and abundant phospholipid species within mycobacterial cytoplasmic membrane [<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>], but also for being a major precursor for complex glycoconjugated lipids such as phosphatidyl mannosides, lipomannan, or lipoarabinomannan [<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Observation of an important increase in PI subspecies during LipG<sub>MTB</sub> overproduction may also impact the formation of such glycolipids that are highly contributing to virulence and modulation of the host immune response. The potential role of the LipG<sub>MTB</sub> protein within these pathways is currently under investigation in our laboratory and may bring new insight concerning the biosynthesis of such complex lipids, but also the role of this highly conserved protein during host–pathogen cross-talk.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec6"><title>Supporting information</title><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title>Primers used in this study. Restrictions sites or mutated codons are indicated in bold</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4013" position="anchor"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Specific activities (S.A) of rLipG proteins. Experiments were performed with same amount of rLipGMTB or rLipGMS following the procedures described in Material and Methods.</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4020" position="anchor"/></table-wrap><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>LipG proteins multiple sequence alignment</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4027" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>Chemical structure of CyC analogs and OX derivatives used in this study</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4034" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title>Western-Blot analysis of recombinant strains expressing LipG or LipG-sfGFP translational fusions.</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4041" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><title>3D model of LipGMTB protein and identification of a putative catalytic triad.</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4048" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><title>Arginine-rich patch conservation and composition</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4055" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F12" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><title>Schematic representation of <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> strain construction and validation</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4068" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F13" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><title>Biofilm phenotypes and lipid analysis of WT, <italic toggle="yes">lipG<sub>MS</sub>::Hyg</italic> and complemented strains</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4081" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F14" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><title>Purification and biochemical characterization of recombinant rLipG<sub>MS</sub></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4090" position="anchor"/></fig><fig id="F15" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure S9</label><caption><title>Phosphatidylinositol identification by two-dimension TLC analysis</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" mimetype="pdf" xlink:href="bsr20181953_Supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e4098" position="anchor"/></fig></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank E. Cascales for providing the pKD4-<italic toggle="yes">sfGFP</italic> plasmid. Special thanks are addressed to Dr Chantal de Chastellier, Prof Sophie Bleves and Dr Eric Durand for their advice and continuous support. P.S., J.-F.C. and S.C. would like to thank Orane Chabiron, Loic Marcelly and Pauline Théolissat for technical assistance. We also thank Dr Thierry Durand for his precious help and advice in chemical synthesis of oxadiazolone compounds. This work has benefited from the facilities and expertise of the Platform for Microscopy of the Institut de Microbiologie de la Méditerranée FR3479 CNRS.</p></ack><sec id="sec7" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the CNRS; the Aix-Marseille Université; and the Ph.D. fellowship from the Ministère Français de l’Enseignement Supérieur, de la Recherche et de l’Innovation.</p></sec><sec id="sec9" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author contribution</title><p>P.S., J.-F.C., and S.C. conceived and designed research. P.S., V.P., I.P., C.S.-A., and J.-F.C. performed the experiments. P.S., V.P., C.-S.A., J.-F.C., and S.C. contributed to data analysis and interpretation. C.C., J.M.G., A.G., and C.D.S. provided chemical compounds. P.S., J.-F.C., and S.C. wrote the manuscript. This work was proposed and supervised by S.C.</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term>CyC</term><def><p>cyclophostin and cyclipostins analogs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DTNB</term><def><p>5-5′-Dithio-bis 2-nitrobenzoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAME</term><def><p>fatty acid methyl ester</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAS</term><def><p>fatty acid synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPL</term><def><p>glycopeptidolipid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INH</term><def><p>isoniazid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MA</term><def><p>mycolic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAME</term><def><p>MA methyl ester</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OX</term><def><p>oxadiazolone-core derivative</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>palmitoyl-CoA</term><def><p>palmitoyl-Coenzyme A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>phosphatidylinositol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>NP</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-nitrophenyl</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PS</term><def><p>phosphatidylserine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>REMA</term><def><p>resazurin microtiter assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIF</term><def><p>rifampicin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>S.A</term><def><p>specific activity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>sfGFP</term><def><p>superfolder GFP</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TAG</term><def><p>triacylglycerol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TB</term><def><p>tuberculosis</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>WHO</collab> (<year>2017</year>) <source>Global Tuberculosis Report 2017</source>, <comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/gtbr2017_main_text.pdf">http://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/gtbr2017_main_text.pdf</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zumla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nahid</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Advances in the development of new tuberculosis drugs and treatment regimens</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd4001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23629506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yew</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of drug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Int. J. Tuberc. Lung Dis.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1320</fpage>–<lpage>1330</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19861002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yew</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of drug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: update 2015</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Tuberc. Lung Dis.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1276</fpage>–<lpage>1289</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5588/ijtld.15.0389</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velayati</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masjedi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farnia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabarsi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanavi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>ZiaZarifi</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Emergence of new forms of totally drug-resistant tuberculosis bacilli: super extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis or totally drug-resistant strains in iran</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.08-2427</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The envelope layers of mycobacteria with reference to their pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Adv. Microb. Physiol.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2911(08)60016-8</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9328647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The cell envelope of tubercle bacilli</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb.)</source>
<volume>95</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>), <fpage>S155</fpage>–<lpage>S158</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2015.02.024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25819158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrakchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laneelle</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Mycolic acids: structures, biosynthesis, and beyond</article-title>. <source>Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2013.11.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24374164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neyrolles</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Guilhot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Recent advances in deciphering the contribution of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> lipids to pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb.)</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2011.01.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21330212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quemard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Um</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>inhA, a gene encoding a target for isoniazid and ethionamide in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>263</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8284673</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8284673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilcheze</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hazbon</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colangeli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transfer of a point mutation in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> inhA resolves the target of isoniazid</article-title>. <source>Nat. Med.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1027</fpage>–<lpage>1029</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1466</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16906155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>New approaches to target the mycolic acid biosynthesis pathway for the development of tuberculosis therapeutics</article-title>. <source>Curr. Pharm. Des.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>4357</fpage>–<lpage>4378</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1381612819666131118203641</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4568743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Besra</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Pathway to synthesis and processing of mycolic acids in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.18.1.81-101.2005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC544180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawelczyk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The molecular genetics of mycolic acid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Spectr.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>MGM2</fpage>–<lpage>0003-2013</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26104214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/microbiolspec.MGM2-0003-2013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The envelope of mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.64.070195.000333</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7574484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veyron-Churlet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrini</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mourey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbib</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Protein-protein interactions within the Fatty Acid Synthase-II system of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> are essential for mycobacterial viability</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>1161</fpage>–<lpage>1172</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04334.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15554959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veyron-Churlet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bigot</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrini</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verdoux</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malaga</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The biosynthesis of mycolic acids in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> relies on multiple specialized elongation complexes interconnected by specific protein-protein interactions</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>353</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>–<lpage>858</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2005.09.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16213523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantaloube</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veyron-Churlet</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haddache</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbib</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> FAS-II dehydratases and methyltransferases define the specificity of the mycolic acid elongation complexes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e29564</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0029564</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22216317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3245277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brosch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Deciphering the biology of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> from the complete genome sequence</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>393</volume>, <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/31159</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raynaud</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laneelle</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Oxygenated mycolic acids are necessary for virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in mice</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.01882.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10844652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Rv0646c, an esterase from M. tuberculosis, up-regulates the host immune response in THP-1 macrophages cells</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biochem.</source>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-018-3303-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29388150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camus</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medigue</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Re-annotation of the genome sequence of Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Rv</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>2967</fpage>–<lpage>2973</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-148-10-2967</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diomande</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dedieu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalier</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MmPPOX inhibits <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> lipolytic enzymes belonging to the hormone-sensitive lipase family and alters mycobacterial growth</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e46493</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046493</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3460867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedieu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serveau-Avesque</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Mycobacterial lipolytic enzymes: a gold mine for tuberculosis research</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source>
<volume>95</volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2012.07.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22819994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirakova</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abomoelak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolattukudy</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A novel lipase belonging to the hormone-sensitive lipase family induced under starvation to utilize stored triacylglycerol in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>281</volume>, <fpage>3866</fpage>–<lpage>3875</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M505556200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16354661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1523426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rengarajan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide requirements for Mycobacterium tuberculosis adaptation and survival in macrophages</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>8327</fpage>–<lpage>8332</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0503272102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1142121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bénarouche</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Audebert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Oxadiazolone derivatives, new promising multi-target inhibitors against <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Chem.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioorg.2018.08.025</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30212765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benarouche</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gnawali</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Cyclipostins and Cyclophostin analogs as promising compounds in the fight against tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>11751</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-11843-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28924204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5603573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santucci</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delattre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Cyclophostin and Cyclipostins analogues, new promising molecules to treat mycobacterial-related diseases</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.12.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29241819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viljoen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fourquet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camoin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paudal</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Cyclipostins and cyclophostin analogs inhibit the antigen 85C from <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>293</volume>, <fpage>2755</fpage>–<lpage>2769</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA117.000760</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29301937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5827452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noens</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anandhakrishnan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehebauer</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmanns</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Improved mycobacterial protein production using a <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> groEL1DeltaC expression strain</article-title>. <source>BMC Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6750-11-27</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21439037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3076238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapopoulou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The MycoBrowser portal: a comprehensive and manually annotated resource for mycobacterial genomes</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb.)</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2010.09.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20980200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corpet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>10881</fpage>–<lpage>10890</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/16.22.10881</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2849754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC338945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gouet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Deciphering key features in protein structures with the new ENDscript server</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>W320</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku316</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4086106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>I-TASSER server for protein 3D structure prediction</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-40</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18215316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2245901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kucukural</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>I-TASSER: a unified platform for automated protein structure and function prediction</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2010.5</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2849174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolinsky</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>PDB2PQR: an automated pipeline for the setup of Poisson-Boltzmann electrostatics calculations</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>W665</fpage>–<lpage>667</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh381</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC441519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolinsky</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czodrowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klebe</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PDB2PQR: expanding and upgrading automated preparation of biomolecular structures for molecular simulations</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>W522</fpage>–<lpage>W525</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm276</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1933214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sept</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Electrostatics of nanosystems: application to microtubules and the ribosome</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>10037</fpage>–<lpage>10041</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.181342398</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11517324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC56910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedieu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serveau-Avesque</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Identification of residues involved in substrate specificity and cytotoxicity of two closely related cutinases from <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e66913</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066913</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23843969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3699616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaugnatti</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aschtgen</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blangy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A phospholipase A1 antibacterial Type VI secretion effector interacts directly with the C-terminal domain of the VgrG spike protein for delivery</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.13292</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26714038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyguen</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fourquet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camoin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spilling</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and Structural Characterization of TesA, a Major Thioesterase Required for Outer-Envelope Lipid Biosynthesis in Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol.</source>
<volume>430</volume> (<issue>24</issue>), <fpage>5120</fpage>–<lpage>5136</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2018.09.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30292819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brust</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecoufle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuaillon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dedieu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis lipolytic enzymes as potential biomarkers for the diagnosis of active tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e25078</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0025078</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21966416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3178603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Point</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diomande</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Synthesis and kinetic evaluation of cyclophostin and cyclipostins phosphonate analogs as selective and potent inhibitors of microbial lipases</article-title>. <source>J. Med. Chem.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>10204</fpage>–<lpage>10219</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm301216x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23095026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3518039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilieva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spilling</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupureur</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Rat hormone sensitive lipase inhibition by cyclipostins and their analogs</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>952</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2015.01.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25678014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4340684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilieva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupureur</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Spilling</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Synthesis and comparison of the biological activity of monocyclic phosphonate, difluorophosphonate and phosphate analogs of the natural AChE inhibitor cyclophostin</article-title>. <source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>7529</fpage>–<lpage>7534</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2015.10.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Point</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diomande</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Synthesis and kinetic evaluation of cyclophostin and cyclipostins phosphonate analogs as selective and potent inhibitors of microbial lipases</article-title>. <source>J. Med. Chem.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>10204</fpage>–<lpage>10219</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm301216x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23095026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3518039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Placidi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Point</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadenne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serveau-Avesque</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>New lipase assay using Pomegranate oil coating in microtiter plates</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2015.09.004</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26343557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Kessel</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfull</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Recombineering in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth996</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goude</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Electroporation of mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>1285</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-2450-9_7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25779313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezwan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laneelle</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Breaking down the wall: fractionation of mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>J. Microbiol. Methods</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2006.05.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhouib</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douchet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chahinian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Caro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characterization of an exported monoglyceride lipase from <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> possibly involved in the metabolism of host cell membrane lipids</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>408</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20070745</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17784850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2267359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhouib</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daffe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Canaan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A monoacylglycerol lipase from <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> Involved in bacterial cell interaction</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>192</volume>, <fpage>4776</fpage>–<lpage>4785</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00261-10</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2937407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cascioferro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delogu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stringaro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arancia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PE is a functional domain responsible for protein translocation and localization on mycobacterial cell wall</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>1536</fpage>–<lpage>1547</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18028308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.06023.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daleke</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cascioferro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Punder</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ummels</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conserved Pro-Glu (PE) and Pro-Pro-Glu (PPE) protein domains target LipY lipases of pathogenic mycobacteria to the cell surface via the ESX-5 pathway</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>19024</fpage>–<lpage>19034</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.204966</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3099717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slayden</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the lipids of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic></article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Med.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21341079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1385/1-59259-147-7:229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Extraction and purification of mycobacterial mycolic acids</article-title>. <source>Bio-Protocol</source>
<volume>4</volume> (<issue>20)</issue>, <fpage>e1265</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21769/bioProtoc.1265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meniche</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labarre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Sousa-d’Auria</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huc</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tropis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of a stress-induced factor of Corynebacterineae that is involved in the regulation of the outer membrane lipid composition</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>191</volume>, <fpage>7323</fpage>–<lpage>7332</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01042-09</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2786555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomino</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swings</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Portaels</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Resazurin microtiter assay plate: simple and inexpensive method for detection of drug resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>2720</fpage>–<lpage>2722</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.46.8.2720-2722.2002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12121966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC127336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walzl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkenhagen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hengstschläger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwanzer-Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A simple and cost efficient method to avoid unequal evaporation in cellular screening assays, which restores cellular metabolic activity</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Appl. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chahinian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boitard</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubes</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Comeau</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Distinction between esterases and lipases: a kinetic study with vinyl esters and TAG</article-title>. <source>Lipids</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11745-002-0946-7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12216836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barkley</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rino</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> Rv3802c encodes a phospholipase/thioesterase and is inhibited by the antimycobacterial agent tetrahydrolipstatin</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e4281</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004281</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19169353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2625445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cazenave-Gassiot</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S.Q.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Targeting lipid esterases in mycobacteria grown under different physiological conditions using activity-based profiling with tetrahydrolipstatin (THL)</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M113.029942</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24345785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3916645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobos</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belisle</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive proteomic profiling of the membrane constituents of a <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> strain</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1284</fpage>–<lpage>1296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M300060-MCP200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Predicting secretory proteins with SignalP</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>1611</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28451972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-4939-7015-5_6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belardinelli</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Green Fluorescent Protein as a protein localization and topological reporter in mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>Tuberculosis (Edinb.)</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tube.2017.04.001</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28610783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5598767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedelacq</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabantous</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terwilliger</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Waldo</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Engineering and characterization of a superfolder green fluorescent protein</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1172</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16369541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mantsala</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of aclacinomycin methylesterase with bound product analogues: implications for anthracycline recognition and mechanism</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>, <fpage>39006</fpage>–<lpage>39013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M304008200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whited</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Johs</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>The interactions of peripheral membrane proteins with biological membranes</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lipids</source>
<volume>192</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemphyslip.2015.07.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26232665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arbuzova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honig</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlint</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The role of electrostatic and nonpolar interactions in the association of peripheral proteins with membranes</article-title>. <source>Curr. Top. Membr.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1063-5823(02)52012-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeiler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>An Antibacterial beta-lactone kills <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> by disrupting mycolic acid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201709365</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29067779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6104829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genes required for mycobacterial growth defined by high density mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2003.03425.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gawronski</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dejesus</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ioerger</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akerley</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-resolution phenotypic profiling defines genes essential for mycobacterial growth and cholesterol catabolism</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e1002251</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002251</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21980284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3182942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eiglmeier</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Massive gene decay in the leprosy bacillus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>409</volume>, <fpage>1007</fpage>–<lpage>1011</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35059006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Multifaceted role of lipids in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium leprae</italic></article-title>. <source>Future Microbiol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb-2016-0173</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28287297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusdottir</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieslander</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez Molina</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> very-long-chain fatty acyl-CoA synthetase: structural basis for housing lipid substrates longer than the enzyme</article-title>. <source>Structure</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1062</fpage>–<lpage>1070</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2012.03.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22560731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Cutinase-like proteins of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: characterization of their variable enzymatic functions and active site identification</article-title>. <source>FASEB J.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1694</fpage>–<lpage>1704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.08-114421</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2698651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarathy</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dartois</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The role of transport mechanisms in <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> drug resistance and tolerance</article-title>. <source>Pharmaceuticals (Basel)</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1210</fpage>–<lpage>1235</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ph5111210</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24281307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3816664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarboe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torrelles</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Altered expression profile of the surface glycopeptidolipids in drug-resistant clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>, <fpage>9778</fpage>–<lpage>9785</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.14.9778</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cronan</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of fatty acid synthesis in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in the absence of phospholipid synthesis and release of inhibition by thioesterase action</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>176</volume>, <fpage>2814</fpage>–<lpage>2821</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.176.10.2814-2821.1994</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC205434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunaway-Mariano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The YbgC protein encoded by the ybgC gene of the tol-pal gene cluster of <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> catalyzes acyl-coenzyme A thioester hydrolysis</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>516</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(02)02533-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gully</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouveret</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A protein network for phospholipid synthesis uncovered by a variant of the tandem affinity purification method in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200500115</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16294310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masilamani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cian</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalebroux</surname><given-names>Z.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Salmonella Tol-Pal reduces outer membrane glycerophospholipid levels for envelope homeostasis and survival during bacteremia</article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>86</volume>
<fpage>pii: e00173</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.00173-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6013679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29735519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>V.Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vivekanandan-Giri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pennathur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Inflammatory stimuli induce acyl-CoA thioesterase 7 and remodeling of phospholipids containing unsaturated long (&gt;/ = C20)-acyl chains in macrophages</article-title>. <source>J. Lipid Res.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1174</fpage>–<lpage>1185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.M076489</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5454516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crick</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Phosphatidylinositol is an essential phospholipid of mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>, <fpage>30092</fpage>–<lpage>30099</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M004658200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haites</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McConville</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Billman-Jacobe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Function of phosphatidylinositol in mycobacteria</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>280</volume>, <fpage>10981</fpage>–<lpage>10987</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M413443200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crellin</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C.-Y.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Metabolism of plasma membrane lipids in Mycobacteria and Corynebacteria</article-title>. In <source>Lipid Metabolism</source>, <publisher-name>InTech</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>