
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Chem Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Chem. Biol.</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101231976</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature chemical biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4450</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-4469</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6366861</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6366861.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6366861</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6366861</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS1511130</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30559427</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41589-018-0183-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS1511130</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA1511130</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Affinity-based capture and identification of protein effectors of the growth regulator ppGpp</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Boyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names initials="P">Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Rosario</surname><given-names initials="A">Amanda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names initials="RA">Robert A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pentelute</surname><given-names initials="BL">Bradley L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laub</surname><given-names initials="MT">Michael T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1.</label>Department of Biology</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2.</label>Department of Chemistry</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3.</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4.</label>Koch Institute for Cancer Research</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5.</label>Center for Environmental Health Sciences MIT, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA 02139</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6.</label>Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT, Cambridge, MA 02142</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1">Author Contributions B.W., P.D. and B.L.P. designed and synthesized capture compounds. D.D. performed phylogenetic analyses. A.D.R. analyzed proteomics data. R.A.G helped with X-ray structure determination. B.W. performed all other experiments. B.W. and M.T.L designed experiments, analyzed data, prepared figures, and wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>corresponding author <email>laub@mit.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">329126</issue-id><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="nihms-submitted"><date><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>06</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-released-under-embargo"><date><day>08</day><month>02</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-22 13:25:15.123"><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-1511130.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="correction-forward" vol="15" page="756" journal-id="Nat Chem Biol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pubmed" xlink:href="31076737"><article-title>Author Correction: Affinity-based capture and identification of protein effectors of the growth regulator ppGpp.</article-title><date><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31076737</pub-id></related-article><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P2">The nucleotide ppGpp is a highly conserved regulatory molecule in prokaryotes that helps tune growth rate to nutrient availability. Despite decades of study, how ppGpp regulates growth remains poorly understood. Here, we develop and validate a capture-compound mass spectrometry approach that identifies &gt;50 putative ppGpp targets in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>. These targets control many key cellular processes and include 13 enzymes required for nucleotide synthesis. We demonstrate that ppGpp inhibits the <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of all purine nucleotides by directly targeting the enzyme PurF. By solving a structure of PurF bound to ppGpp, we design a mutation that ablates ppGpp-based regulation, leading to a dysregulation of purine nucleotide synthesis following ppGpp accumulation. Collectively, our results provide new insights into ppGpp-based growth control and a nearly comprehensive set of targets for future exploration. The capture compounds developed will also now enable the rapid identification of ppGpp targets in any species, including pathogens.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Guanosine tetraphosphate or pentaphosphate, denoted as (p)ppGpp, is a universally conserved second messenger in bacteria and archaea that helps regulate cell growth<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. In the Gram-negative bacterium <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and many other species, (p)ppGpp is rapidly produced following amino acid starvation during the so-called stringent response<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. The synthetase RelA, which associates with ribosomes and senses uncharged tRNAs in the A-site during amino-acid starvation, can produce millimolar levels of pppGpp from ATP and GTP within minutes<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>). (p)ppGpp can also be synthesized by the enzyme SpoT in response to starvation for other nutrients, including various fatty acids, phosphate, and certain carbon sources<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. SpoT also harbors a hydrolase domain that can remove the 3’-pyrophosphate from (p)ppGpp, helping to reset cells following (p)ppGpp induction<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> produces GppA, a phosphatase that efficiently converts pppGpp to ppGpp such that the latter is the dominant species<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">ppGpp down-regulates DNA replication, transcription, translation, and various metabolic pathways<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. These changes help bacteria enter into a dormant state that enables them to survive starvation, stress, and antibiotics. ppGpp is also critical for biofilm formation and virulence of many pathogens<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Despite its central importance to bacterial physiology and nearly five decades of study, precisely how (p)ppGpp regulates cell growth remains incompletely understood as the full set of effector proteins is unknown. Over the years, ~25 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> proteins have been reported to bind or be inhibited by ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). However, the physiological relevance of these targets remains largely untested, with the exception of RNA polymerase (RNAP) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>). ppGpp binds RNAP at two sites to suppress the expression of rRNA and ribosomal protein genes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>), while also activating some genes involved in amino-acid synthesis<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">A more comprehensive identification of ppGpp targets is needed to fully understand the physiological impacts of ppGpp on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, and other bacteria. Two recent studies used <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>ifferential-<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>adial-<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>apillary-<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>ction-of-<italic toggle="yes">l</italic>igand-<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>ssays, or DRaCALAs, to screen for (p)ppGpp effectors<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. This assay measures the mobility of radiolabeled ppGpp on nitrocellulose filters treated with lysate from cells overproducing a single protein and thus requires the laborious construction of overexpression libraries. As a non-equilibrium assay, DRaCALA also likely misses targets with fast off-rates. Application of DRaCALA to <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> identified 7 targets, including five GTPases involved in ribosomal biogenesis<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. For <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, it identified 12 putative new targets and 9 known ppGpp-binding proteins, but missed 11 others that bind ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, underscoring that assay’s high false-negative rate<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Here, we designed and synthesized ppGpp-peptide conjugates for covalently capturing ppGpp-binding proteins in cell lysates with subsequent identification by mass spectrometry. Our systematic approach identified 56 hits from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, including almost all previously characterized effectors. We validate the new proteins identified, and then focus on one, PurF, which catalyzes the committed step of <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> purine synthesis. Structural, biochemical, and genetic analyses indicate that the inhibition of ATP and GTP synthesis through PurF is an important, but largely overlooked, aspect of ppGpp-based growth control. More generally, our development of ppGpp capture compounds provides a global view of how ppGpp controls growth and candidate effectors for future study.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>ppGpp inhibits growth independent of targeting RNAP</title><p id="P7">RNA polymerase (RNAP) is often regarded as the primary target of ppGpp in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. To assess whether ppGpp can inhibit growth independent of its effects on RNAP, we generated a strain harboring (i) mutations in <italic toggle="yes">rpoC</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">rpoZ</italic>, hereafter called RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>), that abrogate ppGpp binding to RNAP<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and (ii) the plasmid pRelA’, which carries an IPTG-inducible fragment of the ppGpp synthetase RelA that constitutively produces ppGpp<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. We also generated a wild-type (WT) control strain harboring the same pRelA’ plasmid. Addition of IPTG inhibited growth of both strains on LB agar plates in a dose-dependent manner, though less effectively for the RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain compared to the WT control (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>). The inhibition was ppGpp-dependent as expression of a catalytically-inactive RelA’(D275G) had no detectable effect on growth.</p><p id="P8">The difference in IPTG-sensitivity could indicate that the RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain grows better than the WT following ppGpp accumulation. Alternatively, it could reflect a difference in RelA’ levels in the two strains. Consistent with the latter, we found that when grown in M9GAV (M9+<underline>g</underline>lucose+<underline>a</underline>mino acids+<underline>v</underline>itamins), a synthetic rich medium (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1b</xref>), the RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain produced less RelA’ protein (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 1c</xref>) and less cytoplasmic ppGpp at the same concentration of IPTG (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>). To circumvent this complication, we adjusted the IPTG dosage so that post-induction ppGpp levels would be roughly equal for the two strains, reaching 1 nmol/OD<sub>600</sub>, or ~1.5 mM in cytoplasm, after 30 min (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>). Strikingly, in these conditions the growth of both strains was similarly inhibited following an induction of RelA’ (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1d</xref>) indicating that ppGpp can arrest cell growth through effectors other than RNAP.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Design and synthesis of photo-crosslinkable ppGpp analogs</title><p id="P9">To understand how ppGpp regulates growth independent of RNA polymerase, we sought to systematically identify the protein effectors of ppGpp by covalently capturing these effectors via photocrosslinking chemistry<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. We designed a series of “crosslinkable” ppGpp variants, each possessing a diazirine crosslinker and a biotin residue as an affinity handle (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). When added to cell lysates, these molecules should bind ppGpp effectors and, upon UV-activation, covalently biotinylate them to enable affinity enrichment, with subsequent identification through mass spectrometry (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p><p id="P10">We synthesized crosslinkable ppGpp molecules by conjugating ppGpp to peptides furnishing the crosslinker and biotin. We used Fmoc chemistry to synthesize four peptide precursors, each with a bromoacetyl group and a spacer; the length of this spacer was varied to maximize the likelihood of efficient protein capture (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). The peptides were conjugated to ppGpp analogs bearing a thiophosphate nucleophile, ppGpp(5’βS) and ppGpp(3’βS), which were synthesized using the GDP pyrophosphokinase YjbM<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> and thiophosphate-analogs of ATP and GDP (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2a-b</xref>). In total, we generated 8 crosslinkable ppGpp variants at milligram scales (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2c-d</xref>) that were combined and used as a cocktail. Although the peptide moiety attached to the ppGpp analogs could, in principle, interfere with binding to target proteins, we noted that in known ppGpp-effector complex structures at least one β-phosphate of ppGpp remains solvent-exposed (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Mass spectrometry identification of ppGpp effectors</title><p id="P11">To identify ppGpp effectors, we used <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain AT713, a lysine and arginine auxotroph that facilitates stable-isotope labeling in culture, or SILAC, mass spectrometry experiments<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. We generated two lysates, one from cells grown with heavy isotope-labeled lysine/arginine and the other from cells grown with regular lysine/arginine (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). We added crosslinkable ppGpp to both lysates, but added an excess of unmodified ppGpp only to the unlabeled lysate. After UV exposure to drive crosslinking, the two reactions were combined and biotinylated proteins were enriched by streptavidin pull-down, followed by trypsin-digestion and mass-spectrometry to identify tryptic fragments with an enrichment of heavy isotopes (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2e</xref>).</p><p id="P12">We performed this capture-identification approach on three independent biological replicates. In total, the mass spectrometry identified 290 cytoplasmic proteins with at least two unique peptides in at least two replicates (<xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Dataset</xref>). Importantly, peptide fragments from 20 of 28 proteins shown previously to bind or be inhibited by ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> had high (&gt; 2.8, or 1.5 on a log<sub>2</sub> scale) heavy-to-light ratios (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). These observations indicated that our SILAC-based mass spectrometry approach has high sensitivity for identifying ppGpp-binding proteins. Of the 8 proteins not identified, 7 had no peptide fragments detected in our mass spectrometry (5 of these 7 are not highly expressed during exponential phase growth<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>) and one, RpoC, was detected but had a heavy-to-light ratio &lt; 2.8, possibly because its binding site cannot accommodate our crosslinkable ppGpp<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P13">To generate a list of possible ppGpp effectors, we selected those proteins with average heavy-to-light ratios greater than 2.8, yielding 56 hits, or ~20% of the 290 proteins identified (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref>). This set included 17 proteins involved in translation and 32 metabolic enzymes. The translation-related proteins included 15 GTPases that participate in various aspects of ribosome biogenesis and the translation process itself<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. These proteins each bind tightly to GTP and/or GDP, and, perhaps not surprisingly, also bind the structurally similar nucleotide ppGpp, although not all GTPases were identified in our screen. The metabolic enzymes identified participate in multiple pathways, many of whose functions are essential to growth in our culturing conditions (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The targeting of some, or all, of these enzymes by ppGpp may contribute to the growth arrest of cells, including in the RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain where RNA polymerase is ppGpp-insensitive. To test this hypothesis, we sought to validate these metabolic enzymes as ppGpp-binding proteins.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> validation of candidate ppGpp effector proteins</title><p id="P14">We recombinantly expressed and purified 7 enzymes shown previously to bind ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and 11 new hits, chosen to span the range of heavy-to-light ratios above 2.8, and then tested the ability of each to bind ppGpp using ITC (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). For 15 of these 18 hits, we observed sigmoidal or hyperbolic isotherms during titrations with ppGpp, with <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> values for ppGpp ranging from ~1 μM for the tightest binders up to several hundred μM for the weakest. These data demonstrate that the capture compound approach has high sensitivity and identified both strong and weak binders of ppGpp.</p><p id="P15">To further validate these hits, beyond just their ability to bind ppGpp, we reconstituted the known biochemical reactions catalyzed by 13 of the targets identified, including 7 hits not previously implicated as ppGpp targets (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). For each reaction, key substrates and allosteric effectors were included at levels approximating their steady-state concentrations in exponential-phase, glucose-fed <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic><sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> (see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Online Methods</xref>). We found that ppGpp at 1 mM activated GpmA by ~50% and inhibited SpeC, Gpt, Hpt, Gsk, and PurF more than 75% each, with 7 others showing more modest (&lt; 20%) effects.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>ppGpp drives a decrease in purine nucleotide synthesis</title><p id="P16">One of the enzymes inhibited only partially by ppGpp was Upp, uracil phosphoribosyltransferase (PRTase, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3a</xref>). This modest effect could reflect the moderate K<sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> of Upp for ppGpp (47 μM) and the fact that ppGpp competes for binding to Upp with GTP, which was initially included at 1 mM (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3b</xref>). Although GTP levels are in the low mM range during exponential growth<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>, they may drop during the stringent response in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic><sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. Strikingly, we found that if GTP levels were reduced to 100 μM, ppGpp became a much more potent inhibitor of Upp (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3b</xref>). Thus, a decrease in GTP during the stringent response may potentiate the ability of ppGpp to inhibit Upp, and other enzymes that rely on GTP.</p><p id="P17">To directly test whether ppGpp triggers a change in the levels of GTP, we extracted and profiled soluble metabolites from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells using hydrophilic chromatography in tandem to mass spectrometry (pHILIC-MS). We profiled the WT control and RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strains, each expressing RelA’, or RelA’(D275G) as a control. Strikingly, we found that the levels of all guanosine 5’-nucleotides (GTP, GDP, and GMP) decreased significantly following RelA’ induction in both the WT control and RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strains (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>, left), while ppGpp accumulated in both strains, as expected (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). The strains in this experiment were grown in M9GAV, a medium in which cells must synthesize their purine nucleotides <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. Thus, our results strongly indicate that ppGpp blocks the <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of guanosine 5’-nucleotides, and does so independent of its effects on transcription through binding to RNAP.</p><p id="P18">We did not see a significant decrease in ATP or other adenosine 5’-nucleotides after inducing ppGpp (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>, right). However, we hypothesized that ppGpp may block the synthesis of adenosine nucleotides and also decrease its consumption, leading to minimal net change in the abundance of adenosine 5’-nucleotides. To directly test this idea, we pulse-treated MG1655 cells in M9GAV medium with <sup>13</sup>C<sub>2</sub><sup>15</sup>N-glycine either before or 5-minutes after ppGpp induction, a building block for purine synthesis (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3b</xref>). Metabolites were then extracted from cells over time and the incorporation of heavy isotopes into purine nucleotides was monitored by LC-MS. The rate of both ATP and GTP synthesis decreased by ~65% following ppGpp induction, based on the initial velocity of heavy-glycine incorporation into adenosine and guanosine 5’-nucleotides, respectively (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>). These results demonstrated that ppGpp inhibits the <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of all purine nucleotides.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>ppGpp inhibits <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> purine synthesis by targeting PurF</title><p id="P19">How does ppGpp block <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of purine nucleotides? <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, like most organisms, assembles non-purine building blocks into IMP, which then feeds into the synthesis of adenosine and guanosine nucleotides (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>). No enzymes specific to IMP biosynthesis have previously been implicated as ppGpp targets, but our screen identified PurF, which catalyzes the first step of the pathway<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>). PurF is a glutamine amido-PRTase that consists of an N-terminal glutaminase (Glnase) domain, a middle PRTase domain, and a helical sequence at the C-terminus. The enzyme forms a homotetramer in solution<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. During catalysis, ammonia generated at the Glnase center is channeled to the PRTase center where it substitutes the diphosphate group in pRpp to give rise to 5’-phosphoribosylamine<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>). Using ITC, we found that ppGpp binds two sites in the PurF tetramer, with identical <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>D</sub> of 1.6 μM (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>, left). Titrating in ppGpp also led to strong inhibition of PurF activity <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, and the inhibition was competitive with respect to the substrate pRpp (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>).</p><p id="P20">To assess whether ppGpp targets PurF <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, we examined metabolite profiles of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> before or after ppGpp induction via pRelA’. IMP biosynthesis requires ten sequential steps, the first eight of which take input only from PurF activity<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3b</xref>). Strikingly, for WT control cells grown in M9GAV, we observed a dramatic (&gt;30-fold) decrease of all three detectable intermediates downstream of PurF, as well as IMP, following the induction of ppGpp (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>). These results strongly support the conclusion that ppGpp targets PurF <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. GMP and AMP, two other known PurF inhibitors<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> cannot account for the observed inhibition of PurF as their abundance also dropped upon RelA’ expression (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>). Similar, though less pronounced, decreases in the IMP synthesis intermediates was seen for the RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain suggesting that ppGpp may affect purine synthesis both transcriptionally and post-transcriptionally (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>ppGpp binding disrupts the PRTase active site of PurF</title><p id="P21">To better understand how ppGpp directly inhibits PurF, we solved a crystal structure of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PurF bound to ppGpp to a resolution of 1.95 Å (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). The asymmetric unit of the crystal was a PurF tetramer with D2 symmetry (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d</xref>). The ppGpp binding sites are located where Glnase domains interact across a two-fold symmetry axes. Pairs of binding sites overlap across this two-fold axis, precluding the binding of ppGpp to one site if the neighboring site is occupied, which explains why the symmetric tetramer only binds two ppGpp molecules (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d-e</xref>). The electron density for all sites was equivalent, indicating that ppGpp binds in both possible orientations with one half occupancy (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4e</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4b</xref>). The nucleotide adopts a compact conformation in which all four phosphate groups coordinate a Mg<sup>2+</sup> cation with a slightly distorted square-planar octahedral configuration (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4c</xref>, also see <xref rid="S12" ref-type="sec">Online Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Notably, PurF adopts an inactive conformation in complex with ppGpp, based on comparison to a prior structure in complex with the substrate analog, carboxylic pRpp (cpRpp) that is thought to represent the active state<sup><xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4d</xref>). In particular, the fourth α-helix of the PRTase domain, which normally constitutes part of the active site in the cpRpp analog-bound, active conformation, appears partially unwound in our ppGpp-bound structure (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>). Additionally, binding of ppGpp appears to disrupt a loop near the Glnase active site and promote contacts between this loop and the C-terminal helix of PurF (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4d</xref>, left). The C-terminal helix is thus drawn away from the PRTase active site (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>) such that the side chain of Asp484 no longer stabilizes the dipole of α-helix-4 of the PRTase domain, as it does in the active, cpRpp-bound state (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4d</xref>, right). These observations are consistent with our finding that ppGpp competitively inhibits PurF (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>) even though it binds at an allosteric site. In agreement with this competitive-inhibition model, the presence of pRpp at 0.5 mM, an order of magnitude higher than the <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>m</sub> of this substrate<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>, strongly diminished binding by ppGpp in ITC studies (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>, right).</p><p id="P23">The binding of ppGpp to PurF involved four basic residues from one or both subunits: Arg45, Arg58, His59, and Arg62 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>). The side chain of each residue appears to stabilize the anionic phosphate cluster of ppGpp through electrostatic interactions, with one Arg62 π-stacking to the guanine base. The guanine base also acts as a hydrogen-bond donor to the Ala82 backbone and the Asn48 side chain whose orientation is stabilized by hydrogen-bonding to the backbone of Ser81 (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>). To validate these interactions, we purified PurF variants in which Arg45, Asn48, Arg58, His59 or Arg62 was mutated to Ala, and assayed each mutant for binding to and inhibition by ppGpp. Strikingly, both R45A and R62A completely abolished binding to ppGpp, while R58A and H59A increased the <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>D</sub> by 16 and 39 fold, respectively (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>). Each of these four mutations rendered PurF insensitive to ppGpp up to 1 mM, while retaining activity comparable to, or even slightly higher, than the WT PurF in the absence of ppGpp (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>PurF is inhibited by ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></title><p id="P24">To assess whether the ppGpp-PurF interaction seen <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> also occurs <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, we introduced the R45A mutation into <italic toggle="yes">purF</italic> at its native locus on the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> chromosome. Importantly, although PurF(R45A) is incapable of binding to ppGpp, it preserves a wild-type level of catalytic activity and remained sensitive to the known feedback inhibitors AMP and GMP (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5a</xref>). We transformed the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> mutant, and a WT strain for comparison, with the pRelA’ plasmid and then grew each strain to mid-exponential phase in M9GAV before inducing the production of ppGpp. We extracted metabolites immediately before and at several time points after inducing ppGpp for up to 15 minutes. Notably, ppGpp accumulated at comparable rates and plateaued 8 minutes post-induction at a similar level in both strains (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5b</xref>). We found that IMP, GMP, GDP, and GTP all decreased substantially in the wild-type, but not as much in the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> strain (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c</xref>). In fact, the summed levels of all guanosine nucleotides, including (p)ppGpp, and of all adenosine nucleotides increased significantly in the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> mutant but not the WT (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5d</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5b</xref>).</p><p id="P25">These results support the conclusion that PurF(R45A) is not properly inhibited by ppGpp leading to an increased production of purine nucleotides relative to the wild-type strain. However, our metabolite profiling indicated that intermediate species downstream of PurF, namely GAR, FGAR and AICAR, still decreased in the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> mutant (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5e</xref>). These decreases likely reflect the inhibition of pRpp synthase by ADP<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>, which accumulates in both strains following ppGpp induction, probably from the AMP generated concomitantly with ppGpp production (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5e</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5b-d</xref>). In the wild type, ADP levels initially increased while pRpp levels decreased, followed by recovery of both to pre-induction levels. In contrast, the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> mutant showed higher and sustained accumulation of ADP and a concomitant, continued decrease in pRpp over the 15 min time course. Notably, accumulation of two inhibitors of the PurF(R45A), AMP and GMP (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c</xref>, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5b-d</xref>), in the mutant strain did not lead to the recovery of pRpp levels to those observed in the wild type, indicating that a limitation of pRpp production is the primary cause of the depletion of IMP-biosynthesis intermediates in the <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> strain.</p><p id="P26">In sum, our metabolite profiling indicates that <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> harboring a ppGpp-insensitive PurF(R45A) accumulates purine nucleotides following ppGpp induction, likely because of continued synthesis by the PurF(R45A) mutant and a decrease in consumption due to rRNA synthesis inhibition. Taken all together, our results strongly support the conclusion that PurF is normally inhibited by ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and that relieving this inhibition leads to a dysregulation of purine nucleotide synthesis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P27">ppGpp plays a central role in regulating the growth rate of virtually all prokaryotes. Despite its importance and intense study over several decades, a comprehensive list of ppGpp targets has been elusive. Development of a capture compound for systematically identifying its effectors by mass spectrometry provides an unprecedented global view of how ppGpp regulates cellular activities in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Our approach identified 56 candidate ppGpp-binding proteins, including almost all of those previously identified, and more than 25 not previously implicated as targets (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P28">Notably, some proteins identified bound to ppGpp with a <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>D</sub> in the mid-to-high micromolar range, but 1 mM ppGpp had no significant impact of their biochemical activities <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. For these proteins, enzymatic inhibition by ppGpp may require the inclusion of substrates, co-factors, or other proteins present in cell lysates but not included <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Some of these proteins may also represent false positives, or have been identified by interacting with a <italic toggle="yes">bona fide</italic> ppGpp effector and getting crosslinked as a result of their close proximity. Detailed studies, like done here for PurF, are needed to validate the candidates identified and assess their <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> relevance.</p><p id="P29">ppGpp has long been known to inhibit DNA replication, transcription, translation, and various anabolic processes<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>, but the set of direct effectors had been elusive. In <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, ppGpp directly binds to RNAP, and RNAP is often considered the primary target of ppGpp. However, cells producing a variant of RNAP that no longer binds ppGpp are still growth inhibited by ppGpp (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1d</xref>) indicating transcription-independent mechansisms for inhibiting cell growth. Our capture compound-based method identified dozens of putative targets that control a wide range of cellular and metabolic processes, suggesting that ppGpp orchestrates the shut-down of many physiological processes in parallel.</p><p id="P30">One highly enriched set of putative targets were GTPases, 15 of which are conserved proteins involved in translation and ribosome biogenesis<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For EF-G, EF-Tu, and IF2, the binding of ppGpp instead of GTP disrupts translation <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic><sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. How ppGpp affects the other GTPases is not known, but likely leads to a similar disruption in translation. Testing the physiological relevance of individual GTPases as targets will be difficult as mutations that eliminate binding of ppGpp to one or even several GTPases may have little effect on translation. This difficulty may highlight a key feature of ppGpp-based control; targeting multiple GTPases is a potentially fail-safe mechanism for inhibiting translation.</p><p id="P31">Another highly enriched set of ppGpp targets are enzymes involved in nucleotide metabolism. (p)ppGpp was previously shown to block GTP synthesis in the distantly-related Gram-positive <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> by inhibiting the guanylate kinase Gmk<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. Blocking GTP synthesis was suggested to be important for inhibiting rRNA transcription, which relies on GTP as the initiating nucleotide<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>, as (p)ppGpp does not target <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> RNAP. However, we found that GTP synthesis is also blocked in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> suggesting that blocking GTP synthesis has a broader relevance during the stringent response. Lowering GTP levels may significantly slow growth as GTP is needed for transcription and translation. The decrease in GTP also potentiates ppGpp as a competitor for some GTP-activated enzymes, as shown here for Upp, and a drop in GTP synthesis may prevent the excessive accumulation of ppGpp, enabling an eventual resetting of the stringent response and a resumption of cell growth.</p><p id="P32">How does ppGpp inhibit purine nucleotide biosynthesis? Prior studies found that ppGpp inhibits the salvage of guanine and hypoxanthine nucleobases or nucleosides by targeting Hpt and Gpt<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>, two proteins also identified here (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>). In addition, our results demonstrate that ppGpp blocks <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> purine synthesis by directly targeting PurF, which catalyzes the first dedicated step of the pathway. We found that ppGpp strongly inhibits PurF <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>) and the induction of ppGpp <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> led to a significant decrease in metabolites downstream of PurF (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>) as well as a decrease in the rates of purine nucleotide synthesis (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>). Notably, in cells producing PurF(R45A), which retains wild-type PurF activity and regulation except by ppGpp, we found that purine nucleotide levels increased significantly following ppGpp induction compared to the wild type (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5d</xref>), underscoring the physiological relevance of PurF as a direct target.</p><p id="P33">In sum, our work indicates that inhibiting nucleotide synthesis is a critical facet of growth control by ppGpp in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, and probably other bacteria, with PurF a key, direct target. More broadly, our capture-compound approach indicates that ppGpp regulates cell growth by targeting a range of cellular and metabolic processes, and the specific targets identified can now be examined in detail. Our capture compounds can also be used to rapidly identify the stringent-response effectors in a range of microbes, including pathogens, many of which rely on ppGpp to survive in their hosts<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. A comparison of effectors in phylogenetically diverse organisms will also begin revealing how the stringent response has evolved.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Online Methods</title><sec id="S13"><title>Growth conditions</title><p id="P34"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> was grown in LB (10 g/L NaCl, 10 g/L tryptone, 5 g/L yeast extract) or M9-based defined media. All solid media contained 1.2% agar. M9 base medium (14 g/L Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>-7H<sub>2</sub>O, 3 g/L KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g/L NaCl, 1 g/L NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 30 μM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) was made into defined media by supplementing nutrients as follows:</p><p id="P35">M9G-casamino acids medium: 1.0% glucose, 0.2% casamino acids and 25 μM Fe(SO<sub>4</sub>)-EDTA chelate.</p><p id="P36">M9G-amino acid-vitamin (M9GAV) medium: 0.4% glucose, 0.25% each of L-serine and L-threonine, 0.0375% each of L-asparagine and L-glutamine, 0.015% each of all 16 other natural amino acids, and 1X Kao &amp; Michayluk Vitamins.</p><p id="P37">SILAC medium: 0.4% glucose, 0.0125% each of L-asparagine and L-glutamine, 0.01% each of L-arginine and L-lysine (regular or <sup><bold>13</bold></sup>C- and <sup><bold>15</bold></sup>N-labeled), 0.005% each of all 16 other natural amino acids and 1X Kao &amp; Michayluk Vitamins.</p><p id="P38">Cells were cultured at 37 °C and 200 rpm on an orbital shaker (for liquid cultures). Prior to liquid-culture growth, individual colonies were selected by growth overnight on LB agar plates. Antibiotics were used at the following concentrations: carbenicillin (100 μg/mL), kanamycin (50 μg/mL), chloramphenicol (25 μg/mL) and tetracycline (12.5 μg/mL), unless otherwise noted.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Plasmid construction</title><p id="P39">See <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref> for all DNA oligo primer sequences used in this study.</p><p id="P40">The IPTG-inducible RelA’ expression plasmid (pR1–1His) was modified from pALS13 (ref <sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>), a gift from Susan Lovett (Brandeis University). To insert an octahistidine tag at the C-terminus of the RelA’ open reading frame, the plasmid was PCR-amplified with primers “R1–1 His8ins RP” and “R1–1 His8ins RP” and the PCR reaction treated with DpnI prior to transformation into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5α. pR1–1His were extracted from a transformant.</p><p id="P41">Plasmids for recombinant protein production were constructed from a vector backbone (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 6</xref>) and a PCR fragment of the target protein-coding sequence (insert DNA, <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 7</xref>) through Gibson Assembly. pET30-His<sub>6</sub>-Sumo-CfaN and pTXB1-Ub-Cfa were generous gifts from Tom Muir (Princeton)<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P42">Single-point mutagenesis were performed on expression plasmids for PurF (pG23–1Cfa) and RelA’. Briefly, the original plasmid was PCR-amplified using primer pairs bearing the desired mutation and each PCR reaction was treated with DpnI prior to transformation into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5α. Mutant plasmids were extracted from transformants.</p><p id="P43">See <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 8</xref> for a summary of plasmids in this study.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Construction of <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> strain</title><p id="P44">The <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> strain (ML2912) was also constructed in an MG1655 (ML006) background through lambda recombineering<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. ML006 harboring pKD46 and expressing the Lambda recombinase was electroporated with a <italic toggle="yes">kan</italic><sup>R</sup> fragment amplified from pKD4 with primers “G23–1 K46:Kan FP” and “G23–1 K46:Kan RP”. Recombinants were selected on LB plates containing 10 μg/mL kanamycin and 100 μg/mL carbenicillin at 30 <sup>o</sup>C to maintain pKD46. Then, a recombinant clone expressing the Lambda recombinase was electroporated with the primer “G23–1 R45A Rec”. This second recombination displaced the <italic toggle="yes">kan</italic><sup>R</sup> cassette and restored the <italic toggle="yes">purF</italic> gene, but harboring the desired mutation. Recombinants were selected for purine autotrophy on M9-Glucose-casamino acids plates at 37 <sup>o</sup>C to drive the loss of pKD46. The desired mutation was confirmed by Sanger sequencing and the absence of unexpected mutations was confirmed by whole-genome sequencing.</p><p id="P45">See <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 9</xref> for all strains used in this study.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Protein Expression</title><p id="P46">All recombinant proteins used in this study were expressed in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3) harboring the corresponding expression plasmid. Expression strains were grown in LB containing the appropriate antibiotics at 37 <sup>o</sup>C to OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.6. The culture was then cooled to 18 <sup>o</sup>C and then induced by the addition of 200 μM IPTG. Cells were harvested 16 to 24 hours post-induction.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Purification of proteins without an affinity tag</title><p id="P47">Expression plasmids for PurA from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (G27–1nt) and PurF from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (G23–1nt) encoded the exact ORF of each protein. These proteins were purified following similar strategies, as exemplified by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PurA as follows. Cell pellets from 1 L expression culture (wet weight ~ 10 grams) was resuspended in 40 mL lysis buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 50 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM DTT, 20 μg/mL lysozyme and 1 mM PMSF. Cells were disrupted through sonication and the lysate was cleared at 15,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10min. The supernatant was then treated with 75 mg protamine sulfate followed by vortexing. Precipitate that emerged was pelleted at 30,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 1 hour, and the cleared lysate was applied to a DEAE sepharose column (16/150, ~30 mL bed volume) equilibrated with buffer A (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl2 and 5 mM DTT). The column was then washed with 50 mL 5% buffer B (buffer A + 1M NaCl), and bound protein was eluted at using a linear gradient with the percentage of buffer B increasing from 5 to 55% within 200 mL. Peak fractions for PurA (15 mL) were combined and a saturated (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> solution at 0 <sup>o</sup>C was added to reach 55% saturation. Precipitated protein was removed, and (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> was added to the mother liquor to 65% saturation. Protein precipitated at this stage had high purity as was examined by SDS-PAGE. The protein was re-dissolved in gel-filtration buffer (20 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 1 mM TCEP) and refined over a Superdex-200 increase (10/300) column.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Purification of His<sub>6</sub>-tagged proteins</title><p id="P48">With the exception of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> YjbM (G1–2), His-tagged proteins were purified following the standard protocol described below. Cell pellet from 1 L expression culture was resuspended in 25 mL lysis buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl pH = 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 20 μg/mL lysozyme and 1 mM PMSF. Cells were disrupted through sonication and the lysate was cleared at 30,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 1 hour. Cleared lysate was applied to 4 mL Ni-NTA resin equilibrated with the lysis buffer, and allowed to flow through by gravity. The Ni-NTA resin was washed with 5x column volumes of wash buffer 1 (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 500 mM NaCl, 10 mM imidazole, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM TCEP) and 10x column volumes of wash buffer 2 (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 25 mM imidazole, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM TCEP). Bound protein was eluted with 3X column volumes of elution buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 300 mM imidazole, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP and 15% (v/v) glycerol).</p><p id="P49">For the purification of His<sub>6</sub>-YjbM, cells were lysed in a buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl and 1 mM DTT, and neat glycerol was mixed into the lysate for 15% (v/v) final concentration immediately following lysis. After adsorpting protein from the lysate, the Ni-NTA resin was washed with 10x column volumes of wash buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl, 35 mM imidazole, 1 mM TCEP, and 15% (v/v) glycerol) and bound protein was eluted with 3X column volumes of elution buffer (wash buffer with 500 mM imidazole). Protein in eluate was concentrated and refined over a Superdex-200 increase (10/300) column.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Removal of affinity tags</title><p id="P50">To avoid interference from oligo-histidine sequences, most proteins used for hit-validation experiments were removed from affinity tags. Standard procedures for thrombin cleavage, sumo-protease cleavage, and thiol cleavage for this purpose are described below.</p><p id="P51">To remove the N-terminal His<sub>6</sub> tag of recombinant proteins expressed from the pET28b vector, thrombin (Sigma) was reconstituted in 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 20% (v/v) glycerol at 100 U/mL. Eluates off the Ni-NTA column were dialyzed against 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and then treated with thrombin (10 U per μmol cleavage sites) at RT overnight. Cleavage was monitored by SDS-PAGE and more thrombin and cleavage time was applied if necessary. Upon completion, the cleavage mixture was treated with 10 mM TCEP, concentrated and refined over a Superdex-200 increase (10/300) column.</p><p id="P52">To remove the N-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-Sumo tag fused to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PyrH (G25–1Sumo) and GuaB (G30–1Sumo), proteins off the Ni-NTA column were exchanged into a Sumo-cleavage buffer containing 20 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl and 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM TCEP. The tagged protein was then treated with Sumo protease (1mg per μmol cleavage sites) at RT for 2 hrs. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PyrH generated in <italic toggle="yes">situ</italic> from G25–1Sumo was used directly for biochemical assays. Cleavage mixture of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GuaB (G30–1Sumo) was subject to a reverse Ni-NTA process to clean up residual uncleaved protein. The combined flowthrough and wash was then concentrated and refined over a Superose-6 increase (10/300) column.</p><p id="P53">Proteins fused to a C-terminal Cfa-His<sub>6</sub> were exchanged into the intein-cleavage buffer containing 20 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0, 150 mM NaCl, and 1 mM TCEP, and treated with 100 mM sodium 2-mercaptoethanesulfonate (MESNa), 100 mM L-cysteine and 20 mM TECP at pH 7.0 and RT overnight. Note that this treatment substituted a Cys residue for the Cfa-His<sub>6</sub> tag, harnessing the auto-catalytic, N-terminal cleavage activity of inteins<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Cleavage was monitored by SDS-PAGE and, if necessary, allowed to progress further at 37 <sup>o</sup>C. Upon completion, the cleavage mixture was extensively dialyzed against the intein-cleavage buffer and then subject to a reverse Ni-NTA process to remove residual uncleaved protein. The combined flowthrough and wash was concentrated and refined over a Superdex-200 increase (10/300) column.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Size-exclusion chromatography (SEC)</title><p id="P54">With the exception of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> YjbM and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GuaB, SEC of all recombinant proteins was run in a buffer containing 20 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM TCEP. Up to 20 mg protein was injected in 1 mL and peak fractions were collected. SEC buffer for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GuaB included 150 mM KCl in place of NaCl. SEC buffer for YjbM contained 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl, 1 mM TCEP, and 15% (v/v) glycerol.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Synthesis of native and crosslinkable ppGpp</title><p id="P55">ppGpp was synthesized following procedures described by Steinchen et al.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Briefly, 10 mM GDP and 12 mM ATP were mixed with 5 μM YjbM (final concentrations, molarity in monomers for YjbM). The mixture was incubated at 37<sup>o</sup>C for 4 hrs. ppGpp was then purified by Mono Q anion exchange chromatography followed by precipitation using LiCl and ethanol. The precipitate was lyophilized to give a colorless powder. ppGpp(3’βS) was synthesized from ATPγS and 1.2 equivalence of GDP, and ppGpp(5’βS) from GDPβS and 1.2 equivalence of ATP using otherwise identical procedures.</p><p id="P56">All bromoacetylated peptides were synthesized using standard Fmoc chemistry<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> (see <xref rid="SD4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Note 1 for details</xref>). Coupling-deprotection cycles were performed with Fmoc-Gly-OH, Fmoc-Lys(Alloc)-OH, and Fmoc-Gly-OH (in this order), and the N-terminal amine was biotinylated. Thereafter, The Alloc group protecting the Lys side chain was removed by treatment with Pd(PPh<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>, and the branch were synthesized by coupling-deprotection cycles with Fmoc-photoMet-OH followed by a spacer amino acid. The N-terminus of the branch was then bromoacetylated with 40 μL bromoacetic anhydride with the presence of DIEA, and the peptide was cleaved from the resin and purified over a semi-preparative reverse phase (RP)-HPLC.</p><p id="P57">Crosslinkable ppGpp was synthesized by conjugating each bromoaceylated peptide (<bold>3a</bold>-<bold>d</bold>) to equimolar ppGpp(3’βS) (for <bold>1a-d</bold>) or to ppGpp(5’βS) at pH = 6.2 (for <bold>2a-d</bold>) at 42 <sup>o</sup>C for 2 hr. Each conjugate was purified from a 2-μmol scale reaction using a MonoQ (5/50) column at 4 <sup>o</sup>C using a linear gradient of buffer A (5 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0) and buffer B (5 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0, 1M NaCl). Crosslinkable ppGpp were stable at −80 <sup>o</sup>C for at least three months. For MS analysis, each conjugate was first adsorbed to C18-Ziptips (Millipore) for desalting followed by elution in 50% (v/v) acetonitrile containing 1 mM ammonium formate. The eluate was then analyzed by a Bruker Daltonics APEXIV 4.7 Tesla Fourier Transform Ion Cyclotron Resonance Mass Spectrometer (FT-ICR-MS).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Effector capture and enrichment from <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> lysate</title><p id="P58"><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> AT713 was cultured in the SILAC medium containing either regular lysine and arginine (the light medium) or <sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub><sup>15</sup>N<sub>2</sub>-lysine and <sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub><sup>15</sup>N<sub>4</sub>-arginine (the heavy medium). Lysates were prepared in 20 mM HEPES-Na 7.0, 100 mM NaCl, 0.2 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), and 10 μg/mL lysozyme at 4.5 mg / mL protein. <bold>1a-d</bold> and <bold>2a-d</bold> were mixed in equimolar for a 0.5 mM cocktail. Then, two reactions were assembled in adjacent wells on a 96-well plate chilled on ice. The effector-capture reaction consisted of 540 μg protein from the heavy lysate, 100 μM crosslinkable ppGpp cocktail, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>. The control reaction consisted of 540 μg protein from the light lysate, 100 μM crosslinkable ppGpp cocktail, 5 mM native ppGpp, 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 1.5 mM MnCl<sub>2</sub>. After exposure to 365-nm UV lamp for 2 minutes, reactions were then combined and extensively exchanged in a 10kDa-MWCO concentrator into a buffer containing 20 mM HEPES-Na and 200 mM NaCl. At this stage, 50 μg protein was saved for input control, and the rest was concentrated to 100 μL, diluted with 400 μL RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% SDS, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 1% Triton X-100) and incubated overnight with 200 μL MyOne Streptavidin C1 dynabeads (Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 4 <sup>o</sup>C. On the second day, the protein in supernatant (flowthrough) was sampled for Western blotting and then removed, and the dynabeads were washed at 4 <sup>o</sup>C twice with RIPA buffer, once with 0.1 M Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, twice with 100 mM Tris 8.0, 5 M guanidinium chloride (GuHCl) and twice more with RIPA buffer. Bound protein was eluted through boiling the dynabeads in 40 μL SDS-PAGE loading dye containing 2 mM biotin.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Tryptic fragment preparation</title><p id="P59">For input controls, the lysate mixture (50 μg protein) was treated with 10 mM DTT at 56 <sup>o</sup>C for 1 hr followed by 55 mM iodoacetamide at RT for 1 hr in the dark, and then digested with 1 μg trypsin (Promega) at RT overnight. Thereafter, the sample was acidified with formic acid (5% final concentration) and applied to C18 SpinTips (Protea Biosciences). After washing with 0.1% formic acid in water, tryptic fragments were eluted with 80% acetonitrile in water containing 0.1% formic acid. The eluate was dried in a speedvac and reconstituted in 100 μL and then diluted 1:50 both in 0.1% formic acid, and 5 μL dilute was used for LC-MS2 analysis.</p><p id="P60">Eluates from streptavidin dynabeads were first resolved on a 12% SDS-PAGE, which was subsequently stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB), revealing three major protein bands, the streptavidin at 13 kDa, EF-Tu at 40 kDa and EF-G at 80 kDa. The gel lane for each eluate was excised and regions below the 15-kDa or above the 200-kDa marker were trimmed off. The lane was further divided into three samples and processed separately: the EF-Tu and EF-G bands (sample A), the fragment below EF-Tu (sample B), and the rest (sample C). The gel fragments were diced into 1-mm pieces, and then treated with 10 mM DTT at 56 <sup>o</sup>C for 1 hr followed by 55 mM iodoacetamide at RT for 1 hr in the dark. After a brief wash with 0.1 M NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub>, gel pieces were dehydrated with acetonitrile, dried in a speedvac, and re-hydrated with a minimal volume of 6 ng/μL trypsin in 0.1 M NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub> for digestion at RT overnight. Thereafter, tryptic fragments were extracted by four shrinking-swelling iterations. In each iteration, gel pieces were first dehydrated with 5% formic acid in 50% (v/v) acetonitrile (first two iterations) or neat acetonitrile (second two). Supernatant containing tryptic fragments was then removed for collection and gel pieces were re-swelled with 0.1 M NH<sub>4</sub>HCO<sub>3</sub> in water. The combined supernatant was dried in a speedvac and reconstituted in 50 μL 0.1% formic acid. 5 μL was used for LC-MS2 analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>LC-MS2 based proteomics</title><p id="P61">Tryptic fragments were separated by RP-HPLC (Thermo Easy nLC1000) using a precolumn (made in house, 6 cm of 10 μm C18) and a self-pack 5 μm tip analytical column (12 cm of 5 μm C18, New Objective) over a 140 minute gradient before nanoelectrospray using a QExactive mass spectrometer (Thermo). Raw mass spectral data files (.raw) were searched using Proteome Discoverer 2.1 (Thermo) and Mascot version 2.4.1 (Matrix Science). Mascot search parameters were: 10 ppm mass tolerance for precursor ions; 15 mmu for fragment ion mass tolerance; 2 missed cleavages of trypsin; fixed modification were carbamidomethylation of cysteine; variable modifications were methionine oxidation, <sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub><sup>15</sup>N<sub>2</sub> (K) and <sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub><sup>15</sup>N<sub>4</sub> (R). Only peptides with a Mascot score greater than or equal to 25 and an isolation interference less than or equal to 30 were included in the data analysis.</p><p id="P62">Effector capture and LC-MS2 identification was performed on three biological replicates. SILAC quantification was obtained using the area of the precursor-ion peaks. In the case of missing detection of the light or heavy ion, a SILAC ratio of 10 or 0.1 was arbitrarily assigned. The values were then normalized to the median relative protein quantification ratios obtained from the corresponding loading controls. SILAC ratio of a unique peptide sequence was calculated as the mean of all precursor ions that match the sequence regardless of modifications. SILAC ratio of a protein was calculated as the mean of all unique peptides mapped to the protein. Only proteins detected in at least two replicates each by at least two unique tryptic fragments were reported. SILAC ratios were converted to log<sub>2</sub> units and, for each protein, the mean and p-value for that log<sub>2</sub>(SILAC ratio) &lt; 1 was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Metabolic profiling of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></title><p id="P63">Overnight starter culture in M9GAV was diluted to OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.005 in fresh medium, grown at 37 <sup>o</sup>C to OD<sub>600</sub> reached between 0.2 and 0.3, and then treated with inducers or labeling reagents. Untreated control samples were harvested from the same culture 1 minute prior to the treatment. RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> mutant strains: ML2916 (+ pR1–1His) and ML2917 (+pR1–1His(D275G)) were treated with 50 μM or 150 μM IPTG for growth tests and ppGpp quantification (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c-d</xref>); samples for metabolite profiling were collected 15-min following treatment by 150 μM IPTG (Figs. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3a-b</xref> and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). Wild-type control strains, ML2914 (+ pR1–1His) and ML2915 (+pR1–1His(D275G)) were treated with 50 μM or 150 μM IPTG for growth tests and ppGpp quantification (Figs <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">1c-d</xref>); samples for metabolite profiling were collected 10-min following treatment by 75 μM IPTG (Figs. <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3a-b</xref> and <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). MG1655 strain ML2920 and <italic toggle="yes">purF</italic>(R45A) strain ML2924, both harboring pR1–1His, were induced by 40 μM IPTG for hydrophilic metabolite profiling (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c-e</xref> and <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 5b-c</xref>). ML2920 was also treated by 0.63% <sup>13</sup>C<sub>2</sub><sup>15</sup>N-glycine, uninduced or 5-minute post induction by 40 μM IPTG for hydrophilic metabolite profiling (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>).</p><p id="P64">Experimental procedures for metabolite extraction were modified from those described by Park et al.<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. Briefly, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cells were collected on a 0.22-μm hydrophilic PVDF membrane by vacuum filtration and immediately immersed in ice-cold lysis solvent, a methanol-acetonitrile-water mixture in a volume ratio of 40:40:20 containing 0.05% (v/v) Metabolomics Amino Acid Mix Standard solution (Cambridge Isotope Laboratories, MSK-A2–1.2) as the internal standard (ISTD). Lysates were briefly sonicated and diluted by the lysis solvent to 1.0 OD<sub>600</sub> cells per mL solvent.</p><p id="P65">(p)ppGpp was quantified over a MonoQ 5/50 column: lysate equivalent to 1.0 OD<sub>600</sub> cells were transferred to 3.0 mL aqueous solution of 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0 and applied to the column after passing through a 0.22-μm syringe filter. (p)ppGpp were eluted at 4 <sup>o</sup>C using a linear NaCl gradient at pH = 8.0 and the peak areas were interpolated to a working curve of external ppGpp standards.</p><p id="P66">Metabolites other than (p)ppGpp were quantified with pHILIC-MS as follows: lysates cleared from debris were lyophilized and reconstituted in 200 μL water and 2 uL were injected into a ZIC-pHILIC 150 × 2.1 mm (5 μm particle size) column (EMD Millipore) running at 0.15 mL / min. Metabolites were eluted using a linear gradient between solvent A (20 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 0.1% ammonium hydroxide); and solvent B (acetonitrile), with the percentage of solvent B decreasing from 80–20% over 20 min. For relative quantifications, a peak area of 1.0×10<sup>4</sup> was arbitrarily assigned to undetected metabolites. Then, peak area was normalized to the ISTD amino acid with the closest retention time and ionized by the same charge for fold change calculation. For absolute quantifications for AMP, ADP, ATP, GMP, GDP and GTP, external standards containing these nucleotides at a series of concentrations were prepared in the presence of 0.25% ISTD (v/v). Note that this ISTD concentration is identical to that in reconstituted samples. Absolute quantification was achieved by interpolation of ISTD-normalized peak areas to a working curve of external standards.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>PurF expression, purification and biochemical reconstitution</title><p id="P67">PurF used for crystallization was expressed without affinity tag from the plasmid “G23–1nt” (<xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). PurF variants used for biochemical and ITC analyses were expressed with an auto-cleaving Cfa-His<sub>6</sub> tag from the “G23–1Cfa” plasmid and related mutants<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. Expression was carried out in BL21(DE3) hosts in LB and induced at 18 <sup>o</sup>C for 20 hours with 200 μM IPTG. Lysate containing tagless PurF was first treated with protamine sulfate (8 mg per gram cell pellet) to precipitate nucleic acids and the cleared lysate was then fractionated over a DEAE-sepharose column. Peak fractions were combined and then subject to fractionation with (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Precipitates collected between 40% and 47.5% saturation (4 <sup>o</sup>C) were dissolved in the size-exclusion chromatography (SEC) buffer (20 mM HEPES-Na 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 1mM TCEP). PurF-Cfa-His<sub>6</sub> was purified over a Ni-NTA column using standard protocols and the eluate was treated with 100 mM sodium 2-mercaptoethanesulfonate (MESNa), 100 mM L-cysteine and 20 mM TECP at pH 7.0 and RT overnight. Note that this treatment substituted a Cys residue for the Cfa-His<sub>6</sub> tag<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. The cleavage mixture was extensively dialyzed against the SEC buffer and then subject to a reverse Ni-NTA process. All PurF proteins were refined over a Superdex-200 column running in SEC buffer prior to analytical applications.</p><p id="P68">Biochemical analysis was performed in 100-μL reactions in a 96-well plate at 25 <sup>o</sup>C. Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 5 mM glutamine, 5 mM ATP, 5 mM glycine, 50 nM PurF, 1 μM <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PurD, 3.75 mM PEP, 0.5 mM NADH, pyruvate kinase and lactate dehydrogenase (10 units/mL each), and the indicated amounts of pRpp-Mg and ppGpp-Mg. Absorbance of each reaction was monitored for the absorbance at 340 nm (A340) every 15 seconds.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>X-ray crystallography of the PurF-ppGpp complex</title><p id="P69">Crystals were grown by hanging drop vapor diffusion with drops containing 2 μL of protein (25 mg/mL PurF in 20 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM TCEP, 5 mM ppGpp and 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) mixed with 2 μL of well solution (0.1 M HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 24% PEG3350 and 4% iPrOH) at 18 <sup>o</sup>C. After 5 days crystals were looped out of the drop and frozen in liquid nitrogen without any cryo-protectant added. Diffraction data were collected at the APS, using the NE-CAT beamline 24-IDC on a Pilatus 6M detector.</p><p id="P70">Diffraction data were indexed, integrated, and scaled using HKL2000<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>. The phase problem was solved by molecular replacement with PHASER<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> using chain A of PDB entry 1ECJ as a search model<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. The resulting solution was isomorphous with 1ECJ, with a D2 symmetric tetramer in the asymmetric unit. The model was refined using PHENIX<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> with manual model building in COOT<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Ramachandran statistics: 96.36% favored, 3.64% allowed, 0% outlier.</p><p id="P71">Modeling of ppGpp in the binding sites was complicated by the overlap between adjacent sites across a two-fold non-crystallographic symmetry (NCS) axis. Readily interpretable density for the guanosine base was observed at a low contour level in the non-overlapping part of each site but the density for the phosphates was in a large mass of density spanning the NCS axis in which individual atom positions could not be readily visualized because the density was clearly the average of two overlapped NCS-related copies of ppGpp. It was evident from the compactness of the density in the overlap region that the phosphate groups must be coordinated by a divalent cation, so 0.5 occupancy model structures with Mg<sup>+<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> coordinated were placed in both possible orientations and refined with tight constraints on the Mg coordination. The best result was achieved with a conformation in which the four phosphates interacted with the ion with nearly ideal square-planar octahedral geometry. As expected, the refined occupancy of the NCS-related copies did not deviate significantly from the starting value.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Isothermal titration calorimetry</title><p id="P72">ITC was performed using VP-ITC MicroCalorimeter (Malvern Panalytical). ppGpp-Mg in SEC buffer was injected at 10 nmol/injection to hit protein loaded in the sample cell. All proteins titrated were SEC-purified. ppGpp and MgCl<sub>2</sub> were originally prepared as 100 mM and 1 M stock solution in water, respectively. The ppGpp-Mg solution was assembled immediately prior to use by diluting ppGpp and MgCl<sub>2</sub> in the SEC buffer at 2 mM for the titration of Upp and PurA, or 1 mM for the titration of all other proteins. Protein concentrations (counted as monomer) in the sample cell were 240 μM for GdhA, 200 μM for Gpt, Hpt, Upp, and PurA, and 100 μM for SpeC, Gsk, PurF, GmpA and Mpl, 50 μM for Gnd, His<sub>6</sub>-FolC, His<sub>6</sub>-Cmk, His<sub>6</sub>-Idh and His<sub>6</sub>-Pgk. For the titration of PurA, 1 mM inosine monophosphate (IMP) was also supplemented to both ligand and protein solutions. Blank titrations were performed with protein-free SEC buffer in the sample cell.</p><p id="P73">ITC data were processed using Origin software (MicroCal), which automatically integrates heat signal and calculates the molar enthalpy change (ΔH<sub>m</sub>) and the overall ligand-to-receptor molar ratio ( [L]/[R] ) at each injection. ΔH<sub>m</sub> was first corrected by subtracting the corresponding blank-titration data.</p><p id="P74">Sigmoidal Δ<italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>m</sub> – [L]/[R] relationships were seen in titrations of SpeC, Upp, PurF, PurA, Gpt, Hpt, where Δ<italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>m</sub> approximated zero at the end of titration. These datasets were fitted to a single-site model with both stoichiometry (n) and <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>D</sub> as variables. Sigmoidal isotherms were also seen in the titrations of Gsk and GdhA by ppGpp-Mg with Δ<italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>m</sub> approximated a non-zero value. We attributed this residual Δ<italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>m</sub> to a second, weak binding site and hence fitted these dataset to a sequential two-site model. Finally, if Δ<italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>m</sub> attenuated hyperbolically with [L]/[R], the dataset was also fitted to a single-site model, but with stoichiometry (n) fixed at one site per subunit. Such isotherms were seen in titrations of GmpA, Mpl, Gnd, His<sub>6</sub>-FolC, His<sub>6</sub>-Cmk, His<sub>6</sub>-Idh, His<sub>6</sub>-Pgk and two PurF mutants (R58A and H59A).</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Biochemical validation of other candidate ppGpp-binding protein</title><sec id="S30"><title>General considerations</title><p id="P75">With one exception (ornithine decarboxylase), all biochemical assays were performed in 96-well plates at 25 <sup>o</sup>C in a Spectramax M5 plate reader (Molecular Devices). Volume of each reaction was 100 μL unless noted otherwise. Absorbance of each reaction was monitored for the absorbance at 340 nm (A340) every 15 seconds. Water-soluble small-molecule reagents were dissolved in water and pH adjusted to 7.4. Nucleobases (guanine, hypoxanthine and uracil) were reconstituted in 0.1 M NaOH. All above chemicals were diluted to 10X working concentration in water immediately prior to use. Recombinant proteins were SEC-purified and diluted in SEC buffer to 10X working concentration. Typically, a reaction was assembled by first mixing all components except one essential substrate. The left-out substrate was then simultaneously transferred to multiple wells at <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 to initiate the reaction.</p><p id="P76">Biochemical activities that directly produce or consume NADH were monitored real-time by the absorption at 340 nm (A<sub>340</sub>) of the reaction. Other activities were, if possible, coupled to the production or consumption of NADH to enable real-time monitoring. In particular, production of ADP was quantitatively coupled to the stoichiometric consumption of NADH via the activity of excess pyruvate kinase (PK, type-III from rabbit muscle, Sigma) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH, from rabbit muscle, Roche) by the following reaction:</p><p id="P77">ADP + PEP + NADH + H<sup>+</sup>→ ATP + lactate + NAD<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P78">PEP is phosphoenolpyruvate. To this end, a 20X PK-LDH mixture was prepared in water, which contained PEP (monopotassium salt from Roche, 75 mM), NADH (disodium salt from Roche, 10 mM), PK and LDH (200 units/mL each)<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Uracil phosphoribosyltransferase (Upp) assay</title><p id="P79">Upp catalyzes the production of uridine monophosphate (UMP) from uracil and pRpp:</p><p id="P80">uracil + pRpp → UMP + PPi</p><p id="P81">UMP was then phosphorylated to UTP by the activities of uridylate kinase PyrH and nucleoside diphosphate kinase Ndk (both purified in this study).</p><p id="P82">UMP + 2ATP → UTP + 2ADP</p><p id="P83">PK-LDH then coupled ADP production to the consumption of NADH. The overall reaction was:</p><p id="P84">uracil + pRpp + 2 PEP + 2 NADH + 2H<sup>+</sup> → UTP + PPi + 2 lactate + 2 NAD<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P85">Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 0.2 mM uracil, 1mM pRpp, 5 mM ATP, 100 nM Upp, 1 μM each <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> PyrH and Ndk, 1X PK-LDH mixture and indicated amounts of GTP-Mg and/or ppGpp-Mg.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (Gpt) assay</title><p id="P86">Gpt catalyzes the production of guanosine monophosphate (GMP) from guanine and pRpp. GMP was then phosphorylated to GTP by the activities of guanylate kinase Gmk and nucleoside diphosphate kinase Ndk (both purified in this study). These kinase activities were coupled to NADH consumption by the activities of PK-LDH. The overall reaction was:</p><p id="P87">guanine + pRpp + 2 PEP + 2 NADH + 2H<sup>+</sup> → GTP + PPi + 2 lactate + 2 NAD<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P88">Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 0.2 mM guanine, 5 mM ATP, 200 nM Gpt, 1 μM each <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> Gmk and Ndk, 1X PK-LDH mixture and indicated amounts of pRpp-Mg or ppGpp-Mg.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Adenylosuccinate synthase (PurA) assay</title><p id="P89">PurA ligates asparate to IMP to form adenylosuccinate. The reaction was coupled to the hydrolysis of GTP:</p><p id="P90">IMP + GTP + aspartate → adenylosuccinate + GDP + Pi</p><p id="P91">GDP was then phosphorylated by ATP with Ndk, and the concomitant formation of ADP was coupled to NADH consumption by PK-LDH. The overall reaction was:</p><p id="P92">IMP + aspartate + PEP + NADH + H<sup>+</sup> → adenylosuccinate + Pi + lactate + NAD<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P93">Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 2 mM L-aspartate, 1 mM IMP, 2 mM ATP, 300 nM PurA, 1 μM <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> Ndk, 1X PK-LDH mixture and indicated amounts of GTP-Mg and/or ppGpp-Mg.</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Inosine/guanosine kinase (Gsk) assay</title><p id="P94">Gsk catalyzes the phosphorylation of inosine (Ino) or guanosine (Guo) using ATP:</p><p id="P95">Ino(Guo) + ATP → IMP(GMP) + ADP</p><p id="P96">PK-LDH further coupled ADP production to the consumption of NADH. The overall reaction was:</p><p id="P97">Ino(Guo) + PEP + NADH + H<sup>+</sup> → IMP(GMP) + lactate + NAD<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P98">Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 500 nM Gsk, 1X PK-LDH mixture and the indicated amounts of ATP-Mg, ppGpp-Mg and Ino or Guo.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>IMP dehydrogenase (GuaB) assay</title><p id="P99">GuaB catalyzes the oxidization of IMP into xanthosine monophosphate (XMP) and the concomitant production of NADH from NAD<sup>+</sup>:</p><p id="P100">IMP + NAD<sup>+</sup> → XMP + NADH</p><p id="P101">Due to the low substrate concentration, reactions were setup at 200-μL scale to ensure accuracy of the absorbance readout. In assays with the presence of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 2 mM NAD+, 300 nM <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GuaB and indicated amounts of IMP and ppGpp-Mg. For the Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free assay, GuaB was subject to SEC in a Mg<sup>2+</sup>-free buffer, MgCl<sub>2</sub> was excluded from the reaction buffer, and ppGpp lithium salt was used in place of ppGpp-Mg complex.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>Hypoxanthine (Hx) phosphoribosyltransferase (Hpt) assay</title><p id="P102">Hpt catalyzes the production of IMP from Hx and pRpp. IMP was oxidized into XMP by excess GuaB to produce NADH. The overall reaction was:</p><p id="P103">Hx + pRpp + NAD<sup>+</sup> → XMP + PPi + NADH + H<sup>+</sup></p><p id="P104">Each reaction contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 0.2 mM Hx, 2 mM NAD<sup>+</sup>, 30 nM Hpt, 3 μM <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> GuaB, and indicated amounts of pRpp or ppGpp-Mg.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>Ornithine decarboxylase (SpeC) assay</title><p id="P105">SpeC converts ornithine into putrescine and bicarbonate:</p><p id="P106">L-ornithine + H<sup>+</sup> → CO<sub>2</sub> + putrescine</p><p id="P107">Each reaction (200 μL) contained 50 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM TCEP, 100 nM SpeC and indicated amounts of GTP-Mg or ppGpp-Mg, and the reaction was started by addition of 1 mM ornithine and allowed to proceed at 37 <sup>o</sup>C in a water bath for 3 minutes. The reaction was stopped by the addition of 100 μL chloroform and vortexing. The aqueous layer was quantitatively recovered, diluted to 1 mL, and was treated with 100 μL 1 M phthalic anhydride in chloroform at 37 <sup>o</sup>C for 10 minutes with vigorous shaking. Upon phase separation, 500 μL aqueous layer was applied to a Mono Q 5/50 column (GE Healthcare). Derivatives of ornithine and putrescine were eluted at 4 <sup>o</sup>C using a linear gradient of buffer A (5 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0) and buffer B (5 mM HEPES-Na pH 7.0, 1M NaCl), with the percentage of buffer B increasing from 15 to 50% within 10.5 mL. Samples of pure ornithine and putrescine were derivatized and analyzed under the same conditions to identify their derivatives in the chromatogram.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S38"><title>Statistics.</title><p id="P108">For metabolite quantification, one independent culture of the strain of interest was grown and harvested for each replicate. In enzyme-kinetic assays, each replicate was a reaction assembled with the same set of substrate/auxiliary enzyme preps, but with different dilutions of the enzyme of interest. In all relevant figure panels, values of mean ± range (n = 2) or mean ± S.D. (n = 3) were reported and the exact n value is described in each figure legend.</p><p id="P109">Two-tailed Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> tests reported in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c-d</xref> were performed with assumptions for Gaussian distribution and equal variance. The degrees of freedom for all tests was 4, for n = 3 in each set.</p></sec><sec id="S39"><title>Reporting Summary.</title><p id="P110">Further information on experimental design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this article.</p></sec><sec id="S40"><title>Data Availability.</title><p id="P111">Structural data for the PurF-ppGpp complex used to generate <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d-f</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4b-d</xref> have been deposited in RCSB PDB (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org/">https://www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>) with an identifier 6CZF. Raw proteomic LC-MS2 data as sources of Tables <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref> and the <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Dataset</xref> have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository with the dataset identifiers PXD010402 and 10.6019/PXD010402. All other data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article (and its <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Information files</xref>) or are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Reporting summary</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1511130-supplement-Reporting_summary.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d36e2039" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Dataset</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1511130-supplement-Supplementary_Dataset.xlsx" orientation="portrait" id="d36e2043" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figures and Tables</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1511130-supplement-Supplementary_Figures_and_Tables.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d36e2047" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Note</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NIHMS1511130-supplement-Supplementary_Note.docx" orientation="portrait" id="d36e2051" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S41"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P112">We thank M. Guo, J. Kraemer, and P. Culviner for comments on the manuscript. We thank T. Muir (Princeton University) and S. Lovett (Brandeis University) for providing protein expression vectors. This research made use of the Pilatus detector (RR029205) at the NE-CAT beamline 24-IDC (GM103403) of the Advanced Photon Source (DE-AC02–06CH11357). We thank members of the Drennan lab for collecting the diffraction data at APS. We thank the Koch Institute Swanson Biotechnology Center (Biopolymer and Proteomic Core Facility) for help with quantitative mass spectrometry and the Whitehead Institute Metabolite Profiling Core Facility for measuring metabolite levels. Instrumentation resources from the Biophysical Instrumentation Facility for the Study of Complex Macromolecular Systems (NSF-0070319), the Structural Biology Core Facility, and the BioMicro Center in the Department of Biology at MIT are gratefully acknowledged. This work was supported by a fellowship from the Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research to B.W. and an NIH grant to M.T.L. (R01GM082899), who is also an Investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p id="P113">Competing Financial Interests Statement</p><p id="P114">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tenson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Hauryliuk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<article-title>The RelA/SpoT homolog (RSH) superfamily: distribution and functional evolution of ppGpp synthetases and hydrolases across the tree of life</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, doi:<comment>ARTN</comment>
<fpage>e23479</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0023479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3153485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21858139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potrykus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>ppGpp is the major source of growth rate control in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02357.x</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4556285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauryliuk</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tenson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<article-title>Recent functional insights into the role of (p)ppGpp in bacterial physiology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3448</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25853779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4659695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<article-title>Diversity in (p)ppGpp metabolism and effectors</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2015.01.012</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25636134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4380541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haseltine</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<article-title>Synthesis of guanosine tetra- and pentaphosphate requires the presence of a codon-specific, uncharged transfer ribonucleic acid in the acceptor site of ribosomes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>1564</fpage>–<lpage>1568</lpage> (<year>1973</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4576025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.70.5.1564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC433543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarubbi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Characterization of the <italic toggle="yes">spoT</italic> gene of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>264</volume>, <fpage>15074</fpage>–<lpage>15082</lpage> (<year>1989</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2549050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mechold</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Potrykus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential regulation by ppGpp versus pppGpp in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>6175</fpage>–<lpage>6189</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt302</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23620295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3695517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanjee</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Houry</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<article-title>Direct binding targets of the stringent response alarmone (p)ppGpp</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1043</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2012.08177.x</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22812515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potrykus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>(p)ppGpp: Still Magical?</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.62.081307.162903</pub-id> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18454629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalebroux</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<article-title>ppGpp: magic beyond RNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2720</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22337166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13198741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>ppGpp Binding to a Site at the RNAP-DksA Interface accounts for its dramatic effects on transcription initiation during the stringent response</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>823</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2016.04.029</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27237053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4912440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Traxler</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>The global, ppGpp-mediated stringent response to amino acid starvation in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>1128</fpage>–<lpage>1148</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2008.06229.x</pub-id> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18430135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3719176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zbornikova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rejman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<article-title>Novel (p)ppGpp binding and metabolizing proteins of Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>9</volume>, doi:<comment>ARTN</comment>
<fpage>e02188</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/mBio.02188-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5845004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29511080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellows</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Grundling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<article-title>ppGpp negatively impacts ribosome assembly affecting growth and antimicrobial tolerance in Gram-positive bacteria</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>E1710</fpage>–<lpage>1719</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1522179113</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26951678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4812758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Overexpression of the <italic toggle="yes">relA</italic> gene in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>266</volume>, <fpage>3760</fpage>–<lpage>3767</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1899866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Capture compound mass spectrometry: a technology for the investigation of small molecule protein interactions</article-title>. <source>Assay Drug Dev Technol</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/adt.2006.039</pub-id> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17638538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinchen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Catalytic mechanism and allosteric regulation of an oligomeric (p)ppGpp synthetase by an alarmone</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>13348</fpage>–<lpage>13353</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1505271112</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26460002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>Functional and quantitative proteomics using SILAC</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>958</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2067</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17139335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burkhardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantifying absolute protein synthesis rates reveals principles underlying allocation of cellular resources</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>157</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>–<lpage>635</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.02.033</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24766808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4006352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstraeten</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Versees</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<article-title>The universally conserved prokaryotic GTPases</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>542</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00009-11</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21885683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3165542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Absolute metabolite concentrations and implied enzyme active site occupancy in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>. <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.186</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19561621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2754216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cashel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>Regulation of bacterial ppGpp and pppGpp</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.29.100175.001505</pub-id> (<year>1975</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">170852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Messenger</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Zalkin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<article-title>Glutamine phosphoribosylpyrophosphate amidotransferase from <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> - purification and properties</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>254</volume>, <fpage>3382</fpage>–<lpage>3392</lpage> (<year>1979</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">372191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krahn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Coupled formation of an amidotransferase interdomain ammonia channel and a phosphoribosyltransferase active site</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>11061</fpage>–<lpage>11068</lpage>, doi:Doi <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/Bi9714114</pub-id> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9333323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dandanell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hove-Jensen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Willemoes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nucleotides, nucleosides, and nucleobases</article-title>. <source>EcoSal Plus</source>
<volume>3</volume>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/ecosalplus.3.6.2</pub-id> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26443734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hove-Jensen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Switzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Phosphoribosylpyrophosphate synthetase of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>. Properties of the purified enzyme and primary structure of the <italic toggle="yes">prs</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>261</volume>, <fpage>6765</fpage>–<lpage>6771</lpage> (<year>1986</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3009477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>The nucleotide-binding site of bacterial translation initiation factor 2 (IF2) as a metabolic sensor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>13962</fpage>–<lpage>13967</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0606384103</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1599896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>SGE</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<article-title>ppGpp inhibition of elongation factors Tu, G and Ts during polypeptide synthesis</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>. <volume>197</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage> (<year>1984</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6392824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF00327920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Direct Regulation of GTP Homeostasis by (p)ppGpp: a critical component of viability and stress resistance</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.08.009</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22981860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3483369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krasny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Gourse</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<article-title>An alternative strategy for bacterial ribosome synthesis: <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> rRNA transcription regulation</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>4473</fpage>–<lpage>4483</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600423</pub-id> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC526457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochstadt-Ozer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>The regulation of purine utilization in bacteria. V. Inhibition of purine phosphoribosyltransferase activities and purine uptake in isolated membrane vesicles by guanosine tetraphosphate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <volume>247</volume>, <fpage>7067</fpage>–<lpage>7072</lpage> (<year>1972</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4343167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Molecular mechanism and evolution of guanylate kinase regulation by (p)ppGpp</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>749</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.12.037</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25661490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4336630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Design of a split intein with exceptional protein splicing activity</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>. <volume>138</volume>, <fpage>2162</fpage>–<lpage>2165</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.5b13528</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4894280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>6640</fpage>–<lpage>6645</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.120163297</pub-id> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC18686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Salt effect accelerates site-selective cysteine bioconjugation</article-title>. <source>ACS Cent Sc</source>.<volume>i</volume>
<issue>2</issue>, <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>646</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscentsci.6b00180</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5043432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27725962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Metabolite concentrations, fluxes and free energies imply efficient enzyme usage</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>. <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>482</fpage>–<lpage>489</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.2077</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27159581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4912430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
<article-title>Key driving forces in the biosynthesis of autoinducing peptides required for staphylococcal virulence</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>10679</fpage>–<lpage>10684</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1506030112</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26261307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4553796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otwinowski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<article-title>Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source>. <volume>276</volume>, <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0076-6879(97)76066-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27754618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Phaser crystallographic software</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Crystallogr</source>. <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>658</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889807021206</pub-id> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2483472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchmore</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krahn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zalkin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Crystal structure of glutamine phosphoribosylpyrophosphate amidotransferase from <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.5560070104</pub-id> (<year>1998</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9514258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2143822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source>. <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909052925</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2815670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name> &amp; <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<article-title>Features and development of Coot</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source>. <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>, doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>ppGpp can inhibit growth independent of its effects on RNA polymerase.</title><p id="P115">(a) Schematic of ppGpp binding to two sites in RNA polymerase to drive global transcriptional changes, including downregulation of ribosome components and upregulation of amino acid biosynthesis genes.</p><p id="P116">(b) The strains indicated (left) were grown on LB plates with the concentration of IPTG indicated to induce the expression of RelA’ or the inactive RelA’(D275G).</p><p id="P117">(c) Levels of ppGpp in the WT control and RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strains, each harboring pRelA’, grown in M9GAV with the concentration of IPTG indicated added at t=0. Data points represent mean of two independent replicates, with bars indicating range.</p><p id="P118">(d) Growth curves for the WT control and RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strains harboring the indicated plasmid, grown in M9GAV medium with the indicated amount of IPTG added at OD<sub>600</sub>=0.25.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1511130-f0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Overview of capture compound mass spectrometry approach for identifying ppGpp targets.</title><p id="P119">(a) Diagram of the capture compounds synthesized. Compounds <bold>1a-d</bold> and <bold>2a-d</bold> are peptide conjugates of ppGpp(3’βS) and ppGpp(5’βS), respectively. The peptide moieties furnish a diazirine crosslinker and a biotin residue (top right), with a variable spacer residue between the crosslinker and the ppGpp derivative (bottom, right).</p><p id="P120">(b) Schematic of the SILAC mass spectrometry approach. Cells were grown either with the heavy-isotope amino acids Lys<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> and Arg<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> (top) or not (bottom). Crosslinkable ppGpp (far left) was then added to cell lysates either alone or with an excess of ppGpp, followed by UV exposure to trigger crosslinking. Captured proteins were enriched based on affinity to streptavidin, and, upon trypsin digestion, sequenced by MS2. Proteins that interact specifically with ppGpp should yield tryptic fragments with large heavy/light ratios.</p><p id="P121">(c) Plot of mean heavy/light ratios for each protein identified, n=3 (also see <xref rid="SD2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Dataset</xref>). Dotted line indicates threshold used to select hits listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Brown symbols denote previously known ppGpp targets (see <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1511130-f0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>ppGpp inhibits the <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of purine nucleotides.</title><p id="P122">(a) Change in levels of GTP, GDP, and GMP (left) or ATP, ADP, and AMP (right) in the strains indicated harboring either pRelA’ or pRelA’(D275G). For each metabolite, the log<sub>2</sub> ratio of levels after induction relative to an uninduced control is shown. Bars indicate mean of two independent experiments with individual data points shown.</p><p id="P123">(b) Levels of ppGpp in the WT control or RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strains, carrying the plasmid indicated and grown in M9GAV, either with or without inducer as indicated in the legend. Asterisks indicate undetectable levels. Bars indicate mean of two independent experiments with individual data points shown.</p><p id="P124">(c) Time course of <sup>13</sup>C<sub>2</sub><sup>15</sup>N-glycine incorporation into adenosine and guanosine 5’-nucleotides in WT cells grown in M9GAV after pulse addition of the heavy amino acid. Cells were treated either during exponential growth (-ppGpp) or after 5 minutes of 40 μM IPTG treatment (+ ppGpp) to induce RelA’ expression. Data points represent mean values from three independent cell cultures, with bars indicating S.D.</p><p id="P125">(d) Summary of <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis and salvage pathways for purine nucleotides. Enzymes shown in red were identified as direct targets of ppGpp.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1511130-f0003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>ppGpp directly inhibits <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> synthesis of purine nucleotides by binding PurF.</title><p id="P126">(a) Summary of reactions catalyzed by PurF.</p><p id="P127">(b) ITC traces (top) and fitted isotherms (bottom) for the titration of 25 μM PurF tetramer with 1 mM ppGpp. For the right panel, PurF and ppGpp were pre-incubated with 0.5 mM pRpp. Representative traces from two independent replicates are shown.</p><p id="P128">(c) Change in precursor and intermediate metabolites of IMP biosynthesis following induction of RelA’ or RelA’(D275G) for 10 min, in either the WT control or RNAP 1<sup>-</sup>2<sup>-</sup> strain. Bars indicate mean of two independent experiments with individual data points shown.</p><p id="P129">(d) Overview of PurF tetramer in complex with ppGpp. One PurF subunit is colored based on the domain architecture (top), with other three subunits in pale blue. ppGpp-Mg is shown as yellow space-filling spheres. Two-fold rotational axes parallel to the plane of paper are highlighted.</p><p id="P130">(e) 2Fo–Fc electron density of ppGpp (blue mesh) contoured at 0.4σ overlaid with a stick model of two overlapping ppGpp-Mg<sup>2+</sup> molecules related by a two-fold non-crystallographic symmetry axis, one colored by element and the other in yellow. For Fo-Fc maps, see <xref rid="SD3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 4b</xref>.</p><p id="P131">(f) Comparison of the inactive conformation of PurF bound to ppGpp (left) to the active conformation of PurF bound to carboxylic pRpp (cpRpp, right), with an overlay of the two in the middle. α-helical elements involved in key rearrangements are highlighted. The PurF-ppGpp structure was colored based on domains, as in (e) with ppGpp in yellow sticks, while the PurF-cpRpp structure is in light gray with cpRpp in cyan sticks.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1511130-f0004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Preventing the regulation of PurF by ppGpp leads to a dysregulation of purine nucleotides.</title><p id="P132">(a) Zoom-in showing coordination of ppGpp by a network of basic residues. Hydrogen bonds accommodating the guanine base are shown by red dashes.</p><p id="P133">(b) Graph showing the activity of WT and mutant PurF variants following addition of 0, 0.1, or 1.0 mM ppGpp. Initial velocities of each reaction were normalized to that of WT PurF without ppGpp. For each PurF variant, the <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> for ppGpp determined by ITC is indicated below; ‘-’ indicates binding was not detectable. Bars indicate mean of two independent experiments with individual data points shown.</p><p id="P134">(c-e) Changes in metabolite levels following induction of RelA’ by 40 μM IPTG in either a WT or <italic toggle="yes">purF(R45A)</italic> strain. Time courses of fold changes in IMP-synthesis precursor and intermediates (c), in IMP and and guanosine 5’-nucleotides (e), and net change in summed abundance of adenosine and guanosine ribonucleotides, including (p)ppGpp at t=15 min (d) are shown. Data points represent mean, n=3, with error bars indicating S.D. Asterisks indicate p&lt;0.05 (Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, two-tailed).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="nihms-1511130-f0005.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p id="P135">Putative ppGpp-binding proteins identified</p></caption><table frame="below" rules="none"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">accession</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">function / annotation</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">log<sub>2</sub> (heavy / light)<xref rid="TFN2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr><tr><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A9M5">P0A9M5</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">Gpt</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">xanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">5.24</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A9M2">P0A9M2</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">Hpt</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">hypoxanthine phosphoribosyltransferase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">4.58</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P21169">P21169</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SpeC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ornithine decarboxylase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P39286">P39286</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RsgA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ribosome biogenesis GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A9X1">P0A9X1</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnuC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">zinc import ATP-binding protein</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A6M8">P0A6M8</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF-G</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">elongation factor G, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A6P7">P0A6P7</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EngB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTP-binding protein; putative GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AGD7">P0AGD7</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ffh</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal recognition particle protein, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P32664">P32664</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NudC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH pyrophosphatase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P00370">P00370</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GdhA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glutamate dehydrogenase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P25522">P25522</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MnmE</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA modification GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A705">P0A705</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IF-2 / InfB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translation initiation factor 2, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A8F0">P0A8F0</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">Upp</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">uracil phosphoribosyltransferase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">3.43</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P32132">P32132</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BipA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ribosome biogenesis GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A6P5">P0A6P5</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Der / EngA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ribosome-associated GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P10121">P10121</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FtsY</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal recognition particle receptor, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0CE47">P0CE47</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF-Tu</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translation elongation factor Tu, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P60785">P60785</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF-4 / LepA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translation elongation factor 4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P06616">P06616</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Era</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ribosome biogenesis GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P24203">P24203</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YjiA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative metal-binding GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P08192">P08192</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FolC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dihydrofolate synthase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A9J0">P0A9J0</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RnG</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ribonuclease G</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A7E9">P0A7E9</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">PyrH</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">uridylate kinase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">2.96</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P37759">P37759</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RfbB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTDP-glucose 4,6-dehydratase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AG24">P0AG24</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SpoT</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">bifunctional ppGpp synthase/hydrolase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P46853">P46853</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YhhX</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">uncharacterized oxidoreductase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P00350">P00350</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gnd</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A7D4">P0A7D4</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">PurA</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">adenylosuccinate synthetase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">2.75</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P17117">P17117</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NfsA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oxygen-insensitive NADPH nitroreductase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AEW6">P0AEW6</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">Gsk</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">inosine-guanosine kinase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">2.59</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0ABS1">P0ABS1</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DksA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA polymerase-binding transcription factor</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P37773">P37773</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mpl</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-MurNAc--L-Ala-γ-D-Glu-meso-DAP ligase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A7F3">P0A7F3</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">Pyrl</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">aspartate carbamoyltransferase, regulatory subunit</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">2.28</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A799">P0A799</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pgk</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoglycerate kinase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P14081">P14081</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SelB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">selenocysteyl-tRNA-specific translation elongation factor, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A7I4">P0A7I4</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RF-3 / PrfC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peptide chain release factor 3, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P62707">P62707</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GpmA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoglycerate mutase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P06999">P06999</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PfkB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-phosphofructokinase isozyme 2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A7D7">P0A7D7</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">PurC</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">phosphoribosylaminoimidazole-succinocarboxamide synthase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">2.07</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A6P1">P0A6P1</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF-Ts / Tsf</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">elongation factor Ts</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A9W3">P0A9W3</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EttA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">energy-dependent translational throttle protein</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AFL6">P0AFL6</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ppx</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">exopolyphosphatase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P27859">P27859</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TatD</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3'-5' ssDNA/RNA exonuclease</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AG16">P0AG16</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">PurF</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">glutamine amidophosphoribosyltransferase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">1.92</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0ADG7">P0ADG7</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">GuaB</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">inosine-5'-monophosphate dehydrogenase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">1.90</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A6I0">P0A6I0</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cmk</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytidylate kinase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AB89">P0AB89</ext-link></styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">PurB</styled-content></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">adenylosuccinate lyase</styled-content></td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><styled-content style="color:#FF0000;">1.86</styled-content></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AD61">P0AD61</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PykF</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pyruvate kinase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P00393">P00393</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ndh</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH:quinone oxidoreductase II</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0AEJ2">P0AEJ2</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EntC</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">isochorismate synthase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P04036">P04036</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DapB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-hydroxy-tetrahydrodipicolinate reductase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P08200">P08200</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Icd</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">isocitrate dehydrogenase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P31120">P31120</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GlmM</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoglucosamine mutase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0A796">P0A796</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PfkA</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-phosphofructokinase isozyme 2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P0ABF1">P0ABF1</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PcnB</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">poly(A) polymerase I</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="P42641">P42641</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ObgE</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative ribosome disassembly factor, GTPase</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p id="P136">red = nucleotide synthesis; grey = protein translation</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>*</label><p id="P137">: mean of two or three biological replicates.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>