
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Technol Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Technol. Cancer Res. Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3299</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tct</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101140941</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1533-0346</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1533-0338</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6997845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6997845.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6997845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6997845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31888413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1533033819893667</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1533033819893667</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of Apatinib on Serum CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK Cells, and T Cells Subgroup
in Malignant Tumor</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7550-3719</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="HQ">Hui-Qin</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="YF">Yi-Fu</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1533033819893667"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="WJ">Wen-Ju</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ying</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="SS">Shu-Sheng</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names initials="XX">Xiao-Xiu</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names initials="LH">Li-Hong</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names initials="JY">Jia-Yu</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hui-Min</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="HJ">Hui-jun</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1533033819893667">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1533033819893667">
<label>1</label>Department of Medical Oncology, The First Affiliated Hospital of USTC,
Division of Life Science and Medicine, University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei,
Anhui, People’s Republic of China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1533033819893667">Yi-Fu He, Department of Medical Oncology, The First
Affiliated Hospital of USTC, Division of Life Science and Medicine, University of Science
and Technology of China, Hefei, Anhui 230001, People’s Republic of China. Email:
<email>yifuhe@fsyy.ustc.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">326555</issue-id><elocation-id>1533033819893667</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>02</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-22 01:25:18.443"><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits
non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission
provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p>The immune makers including CD4+CD25+ T cells, natural killer cells, and T cells
subgroup were retrospectively analyzed to find the relationship between apatinib and the
immune system in the patients treated with apatinib.</p></sec><sec><title>Method:</title><p>Forty-two patients with advanced malignant tumors orally took apatinib as treatment and
16 patients with the same situation did not take apatinib as a control group. These
patients were all included in the study, and they orally received apatinib 500 mg daily
as monotherapy or combination. The treatment was continued until disease progression or
intolerable toxicity. CD4+CD25+ T cells, natural killer cells, and T cells subgroup were
detected before and 1 month after therapy for all the patients. The relationship between
the changing number of immune cells and progression-free survival was analyzed in this
study.</p></sec><sec><title>Result:</title><p>For the apatinib group, the rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells significantly increased
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .048). The median progression-free survival was 3.25 months for
the 42 patients. The median progression-free survival in the patients with the rate of
CD4+CD25+ T cells increased and decreased was 5.8 months and 2.9 months, respectively
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .012). Multivariate analysis found the increased rate of
CD4+CD25+ T cells was an independent prognostic factor for a longer progression-free
survival. The rate of natural killer cells and T cells subgroup did not change much
after apatinib therapy, and they were not independent prognostic factors for
progression-free survival.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells is very important in patients with apatinib treatment.
The changing number of CD4+CD25+ T cells may be a good indicator for apatinib prognosis.
Natural killer cells and T cells subgroup did not change much after apatinib, and they
were not independent prognostic factors for progression-free survival.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>CD4+CD25+ T cells</kwd><kwd>NK cells</kwd><kwd>T cells subgroup</kwd><kwd>apatinib</kwd><kwd>malignant tumor</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1-1533033819893667"><funding-source id="funding1-1533033819893667"><institution-wrap><institution>Medical Scientific Research Foundation of Anhui Province,
China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2019</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts3</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-1533033819893667"><title>Background</title><p>Apatinib is a kind of small-molecule inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth factor
receptor 2 (VEGFR-2), the evidences coming from clinical study had demonstrated its
encouraging anticancer activity in many malignant tumors, such as gastric cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> colorectal cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr2-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> esophagus cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr3-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> ovarian cancer,<sup><xref rid="bibr4-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and sarcoma.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> In clinic, we found the effect of apatinib varied widely in the different patients.
Some patients obtained satisfied effect, and the others did not get any benefit from the
drug in the same pathological type tumour. According to the mechanism of the drug, the
difference of the clinical effects may be caused by the different expression of VEGFR-2.
However, some unknown indicators may influent this different clinical efficacy. Apatinib
have an extensive antitumor activity, and the oncologists did not need to check any markers
to use it, so it is widely used in a variety of tumors now. So, this status quo cause the
drug abuse to some extent, and some patients did not get benefit from the drug. As a result,
for the oncologist there is an urgent need to identify some markers, which can help
screening patients and predicting the prognosis.</p><p>Traditionally, some chemotherapy drugs can cause temporarily impaired blood cell production
in the marrow and depressed immune system functions. However, in recent years, many studies
have found some chemotherapy drugs can enhance the immunogenicity of the patients with tumor.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Up to now, the influence of apatinib in the immune system has not reported. So, we
create the hypothesis that there is some relationship between apatinib and the immune
system, and we may try to find some immunity indicators which can be used to select the
right patient. And then we may find some immune prognostic indicators for the use of
apatinib.</p><p>In this study, we retrospectively analyzed the relationship between apatinib and the immune
system. We attempt to analyze the immune markers, which included CD4+CD25+ T cells, natural
killer (NK) cells, and T cells subgroup, in patients who take apatinib as treatment. And we
try to find some immunity indicators which may be used for selecting the right patient or to
find some immune prognostic indicators for the use of apatinib.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-1533033819893667"><title>Methods</title><sec id="section3-1533033819893667" sec-type="subjects"><title>Patients</title><p>Between February 2017 and March 2018, 69 patients who took apatinib in Anhui Provincial
Cancer Hospital (The First Affiliated Hospital of University of Science and Technology of
China) were included in the study. Progression-free survival (PFS) time could be followed
up of the patients. All the patients were diagnosed with advanced malignant tumor, and
previously took more than one regime of treatment at least. Consents were obtained from
all patients before the therapy of apatinib. In our department, the blood test of immune
cells is a conventional checking for all patients. We got the rate of serum CD4+CD25+ T
cells, NK cells, and T cells subgroup data from our hospital information system (HIS)
system. The patients were treated with apatinib alone or combination. CD4+CD25+ T cells,
NK cells, and T cells subgroup were detected in 3 days before receiving the apatinib
treatment, and 1 month after treatment for all the patients. Forty-two of 69 patients who
finished the immune cells detection before therapy and 1 month after therapy were included
in the study. Of the 42 patients, 12 patients were gastric cancer. The other 30 patients
were consisted of 9 patients with esophageal squamous cell carcinoma, 13 patients with
colorectal cancer, 3 patients with ovarian cancer, 3 patients with sarcoma, 1 patient with
malignant melanoma, and 1 patient with invasive thymoma. The median age was 57 years, the
range from 24 to 76 years. The ratio of males and females in the study was 1.5:1 (25 males
and 17 females). Seventeen patients had received regimens of apatinib in combination with
one chemotherapy drug, the other 25 patients took apatinib as monotherapy. Fourteen
patients had taken one regime of chemotherapy treatment previously and the other 28
patients had taken multiline chemotherapies before apatinib. Thirty-four of 42 patients
had more than 1 organ metastasis. The primary analysis data consisted of age, gender, the
rate of serum CD4+CD25+ T cells, the rate of serum NK cells and the rate of serum T cells
subgroup, diagnosis, the therapy line of apatinib, chemotherapy regimens, and the number
of metastatic organ. We also choose 16 patients who did not take apatinib as a control
group (nonapatinib group). All of the 16 patients were diagnosed with advanced malignant
tumor and did not take any therapy before the first time immune cells checking.</p></sec><sec id="section4-1533033819893667"><title>Immune Cell Detection Method</title><p>The rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, and T cells subgroup were all measured by flow
cytometry. The following antibodies were used in our study: anti-CD4 antibody (Abcam,
Cambridge, UK), anti-CD25 antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), anti-CD127 antibody (Abcam,
Cambridge, UK), anti-CD3 antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), anti-CD16 antibody (Abcam,
Cambridge, UK), anti-CD56 antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), anti-CD8 antibody (Abcam,
Cambridge, UK), and anti-CD45 antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK). Flow cytometry analysis was
performed on a FACScan (BD Biosciences, Mountain View, California) using CellQuest
software.</p></sec><sec id="section5-1533033819893667"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was conducted with SPSS version 16.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois).
The difference of immune cells was analyzed by <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test. The χ<sup>2</sup>
test was used as appropriate for the comparison of variables. The PFS was calculated by
the Kaplan-Meier method, and compared by log-rank test. Cox proportional hazards
regression model was performed to evaluate the prognostic factors for PFS. All statistical
tests were 2 sided, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt;.05 was considered statistically
significant in all tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section6-1533033819893667"><title>Results</title><p>In this study, 42 patients had finished the blood test of CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, and
T cells subgroup before and 1 month after apatinib therapy. The other 16 patients had also
finished the above examination before and 1 month after chemotherapy (nonapatinib group).
The results of immune cells were recorded in percentage form. For the apatinib group, the
median age was 57 years, PFS was 3.25 months. There are 32 patients still alive at the end
of the follow-up period (April 27, 2018), so the overall survival was not analyzed in this
article. The median value of CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, and T cells subgroup before the
treatment was 12.06%, 16.75%, and 74.45%, respectively. The relationship between immune
cells and patients’ characteristics is shown in <xref rid="table1-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The number of patients having gastric cancer
with elevated rate of T cells subgroup was larger than that of the other patients with
malignant tumor (χ<sup>2</sup> = 4.200, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .040). The patients with more
than 1 metastatic sites had a higher rate of NK cells than those with the single metastatic
patients (χ<sup>2</sup> = 5.559, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .018). Kaplan-Meier method was used to
analyze the relationship between PFS and the following factors. The factors were CD4+CD25+ T
cells, NK cells, and T cells before therapy, gender, age, diagnosis, the therapy line of
apatinib, monotherapy or combination, the number of metastatic sites. The results showing
the above factors did not display a substantial correlation with PFS (<xref rid="table2-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="table3-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In the control group, the characteristics of 16
patients and the relationship between immune cells was in <xref rid="table4-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The median PFS in the control group was 5.95
months, we did not find the relationship of CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, and T cells
subgroup in different ages, genders, diagnosis, and the number of tumor metastasis.</p><table-wrap id="table1-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of 42 Patients and Relationship Between Immune Cells.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinicopathologic Data</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">n</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">CD4+CD25+</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NK</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">T</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥12.06</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;12.06</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥16.75</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;16.75</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥74.45</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;74.45</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.757</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.757</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.753</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.190</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Single drug</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.889</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.753</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.753</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Combined chemotherapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.471</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.116</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: GC, gastric cancer; NK, natural killer</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table2-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier Analysis of the Relationship Between PFS and Clinical Characteristics
(Apatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table2.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Characteristics</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mPFS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.122-6.278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.272</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.675-4.525</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.999-6.400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.839</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.116-7.084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Diagnosis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gastric cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934-8.266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.360</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> The other cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.020-5.980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">The therapy line of apatinib</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Second line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.934-4.866</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.983</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> More than second line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.947-7.453</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">The number of metastases organ</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000-9.792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.464</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> More than one</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.281-6.519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn2-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; mPFS, median progression-free survival.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table3-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Influence of Serum CD4+CD25+ T Cells, NK Cells, and T Cells Subgroup in PFS (Apatinib
Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table3.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune Cells</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mPFS (Months)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+ cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥12.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.104-6.296</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.620</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;12.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.778-7.622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+CD127low/−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥5.255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.726-6.674</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.444</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5.255</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.112-4.888</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥16.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.855-5.345</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.673</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;16.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681-5.345</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥74.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.972-7.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.519</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;74.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.120-6.680</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥41.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.962-6.438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.224</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;41.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.845-7.955</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ts cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥29.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.917-6.483</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;29.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.794-6.606</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th/Ts</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥1.495</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.794-6.606</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.197</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;1.495</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.913-6.487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; mPFS, median progression-free survival; NK,
natural killer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table4-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>The Characteristics of 16 Patients and the Relationship Between Immune
Cells(Nonapatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table4.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Clinicopathologic data</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">n</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">CD4+CD25+</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">NK</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">T</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">χ<sup>2</sup>
</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 12.06</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;12.06</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥16.75</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;16.75</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">≥ 74.45</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 74.45</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.633</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.618</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.282</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> GC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metastasis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.883</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.798</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.245</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn4-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: GC, gastric cancer; NK, natural killer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After 1 month therapy of apatinib, the rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells elevated significantly (T
= −2.042, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .048). Further analysis found the rate of CD4+CD25+CD127-/low
cells, a subtype of CD4+CD25+ T cells, was increased significantly after 1 month therapy of
apatinib (T = −2.996, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .005). This phenomenon was not found in the rate
of NK cells and T cells (<xref rid="table5-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table
5</xref>). T cells are divided into Th cells and Ts cells. In this study, we did not find
that the 2 subtypes have a distinct change after the therapy. Further analysis found that
the patients with CD4+CD25+ T cells increased had a long PFS than those with CD4+CD25+ T
cells decreased (5.8 months vs 2.9 months, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .012; <xref rid="table6-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1533033819893667">Figure 1</xref>). In multivariable analyses, the rate of
CD4+CD25+ T cells increased after therapy was an independent influential factor of PFS, and
it was the only prognostic factor for PFS in the patients who receiving apatinib as
treatment in this study (<xref rid="table7-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table
7</xref>). We also used multivariable analysis method to analyze the role of the rate of
CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, T cells before and after 1 month therapy in PFS, but we did not
find any of the above factors was an independent prognostic factor. In the nonapatinib
group, we also found the rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells elevated significantly (T = −2.223,
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .026), but we did not find this phenomenon had correlation with PFS.
In multivariable analysis, none of the change of the CD4+CD25+ T cells, NK cells, and T
cells was an independent prognostic factor for PFS (<xref rid="table8-1533033819893667" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table5-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>The Difference of Immune Cells Before and After Therapy (Apatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table5.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune Cells</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+CD127low/-</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th/Ts</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.50±5.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37±2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.25±8.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.21±11.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.32±10.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.68±10.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50±0.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.36±6.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.34±2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.36±9.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.21±11.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.74±11.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.97±10.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56±0.86</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.996</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.906</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.416</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.452</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.671</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.680</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.387</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn5-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviation: NK, natural killer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table6-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><p>The Influence of Serum CD4+CD25+ T Cells, NK Cells, and T Cells Subgroup Before and
After Therapy in PFS (Apatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table6.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune Cells</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mPFS (months)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+ cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Increased</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.635-7.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Decrease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.804-3.999</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Increased</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.233-5.367</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.697</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Decrease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.438-5.762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Increased</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.588-6.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.880</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Decrease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.258-7.742</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn6-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; NK, natural killer; PFS, progression-free
survival.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The median progression-free survival of regulatory T cells increased and decreased
group (apatinib group).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-fig1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="table7-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><p>Multivariate Analysis of PFS in 42 Patients (Apatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table7.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Prognostic Factor</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Disease-Free Survival (PFS)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.524-3.473</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.534</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740-6.459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.157</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+ T cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124-0.947</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.039</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285-2.329</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.701</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374-2.480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.937</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The therapy regime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.277</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.440-3.709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.653</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869-7.758</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metastatic organ number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509-8.882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.301</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The line of therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.347-2.930</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.998</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn7-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; NK, natural killer; PFS, progression-free
survival.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table8-1533033819893667" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 8.</label><caption><p>Multivariate Analysis of PFS in 16 Patients (Nonapatinib Group).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-table8.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Prognostic Factor</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Disease-Free Survival (PFS)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odds Ratio</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.656</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790-16.913</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.097</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185-272.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.292</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+CD25+ T cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.832</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288-11.652</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.521</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.322</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037-149.726</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.690</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T cells change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138-10.815</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.858</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076-4.583</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.615</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metastatic organ number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158-5.185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.911</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn8-1533033819893667"><p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; NK, natural killer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section7-1533033819893667"><title>Discussion</title><p>For many malignant tumors there were always no effective medicines available in the late
stage. Apatinib is a small molecule which could inhibit VEGF-stimulated endothelial cell
migration and proliferation and decrease tumor microvascular density.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> It was approved and launched in People’s Republic of China in 2014 as a
subsequent-line treatment for patients with advanced gastric cancer. And the clinical trials
of this drug in other tumors are currently undergoing in clinic. In our clinical work, we
find apatinib is a new strategy for the treatment of a variety of solid tumors, such as
non-small cell lung cancer, breast cancer, and hepatocellular carcinoma, esophageal cancer,
sarcoma, and so on. During the apatinib medication, we have noticed an interesting
phenomenon. Some patients have obtained good results, and these patients always have a very
long PFS after the apatinib treatment. However, the others have the disease progression
rapidly and die very soon. As apatinib was approved in advanced gastric cancer, it was also
chosen for the other types of tumors because there was no effective medicines available, as
well as intolerable chemotherapy. This status quo may be related to the poor prognosis. But
in our work, we also find some patients with a good eastern cooperative oncology group
(ECOG) cannot get a good result from apatinib. What’s more, up to now there is no effective
prognostic indicator for the use of apatinib. This phenomenon makes us think apatinib may
have an influence on immune system, and the immune system may be an important factor for the
therapeutic effect.</p><p>CD4+CD25+ T cells is a subpopulation of suppressor T cells defined based on expression of
CD4 and CD25. CD4+CD25+ T cell is an important subtype of T lymphocytes. It’s a group of
regulatory T cells and is differ from Th1 and Th2 cells. CD4+CD25+ T cells, 5% to 10% of
peripheral CD4+T cells, resemble anergic cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, playing an
important role in peripheral immune tolerance, and playing a key role in the development of tumors.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="bibr10-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr11-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr12-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr13-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> The immunosuppressive function of CD4+CD25+ T cells had gained widespread attention.
Numerous studies have shown that CD4+CD25+ T cells play critical roles in maintaining
homeostasis, mediating tolerance to allografts and surveillance of tumor. Previous studies
showed elevated level of CD4+CD25+ T cells in tumor draining lymph nodes, including
cervical, endometrial, gastric cancers, and melanoma.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="bibr15-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr16-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>
</p><p>The depletion of CD4+CD25+ T cells can disrupt immunological unresponsiveness to autologous
tumors, thus mediated effective immune responses to tumor cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr18-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> The CD4+CD25+ T cells can suppress all subsets of Vα24+NKT cells, which including
Vα24+CD4-CD8- cells, Vα24+CD4+ and Vα24+CD8+, in both proliferation and cytokine production,
such as interferon γ, interleukin-4 (IL-4), IL-13, and IL-10.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> So the elevated rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells suppressed the cytotoxic activity of
Vα24+NKT cells and weakened the action of antitumor. Study had found CD4+CD25+ T cells was
an important contributor to the development of tumors immune tolerance and they play a
critical role in the induction of tolerance to tumor associated antigens and suppression of
antitumor immunity.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> CD4+CD25+ T cells consist of natural Tregs (nTregs) and peripherally induced Tregs (iTregs).<sup><xref rid="bibr21-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Natural Treg, with Foxp3 expression, are thymus derived, constitutively express CD25,
and their mechanism of suppression is cell contact dependent.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Induced Treg, adaptive Treg, is developing in the periphery, which Foxp3 is
considered unstable. Induced Treg cells variably express CD25, and they work by cells
contact and cytokine dependent mechanism.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Researchers found CD4+CD25+ T cells limited beneficial responses by suppressing
sterilizing immunity and compromising anti-tumor immunity.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Many studies showed high rate of CD4+CD25+ Treg cells was closely related with poor prognosis.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="bibr27-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> The levels of these cells in malignant tumor patients were higher than in
non-neoplastic patients.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Up to now, the inhibitory cytokines of IL-10, IL-35, and transforming growth factor β
are known as the 3 key mediators of Tregs function.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr30-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>
</p><p>Given the above, increased levels of CD4+CD25+ T cells in the peripheral blood of patients
with cancer were detected as compared to normal healthy control. And the previous research
suggested the higher rate of CD4+CD25+ T cells should be connected with poor outcome. But in
our study, we found the patients with CD4+CD25+ T cells increased after apatinib treatment
had a better outcome. This means the elevated Treg cells were closely associated with longer
PFS. But the rate of NK cells and T cells subgroup did not change much after apatinib, and
they were not an independent prognostic factor for PFS. The result is contrary to
conventional wisdom. This is an interesting phenomenon, and the mechanisms are worthy of
further investigation.</p><p>Apatinib is a small molecule which could inhibit VEGF-stimulated endothelial cell
migration. Vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 1 has been implicated in macrophage
chemotaxis and tumor cell survival and invasion. Vascular endothelial growth factor receptor
2 is the primary angiogenic receptor, and apatinib is working on VEGFR2, hence inhibiting
the formation of new blood vessels in the tumor tissues and the growth of tumor cells. Marek
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> found the CD4+ T cells produce significantly a high amount of VEGF in patients with
type 1 diabetes. These VEGF maybe induce VEGFR overexpression, so that it can increase the
efficiency of apatinib. A study found anti-VEGF(R) drug axitinib can increase the number of
naïve CD8(+) T cells and central memory CD4+ and CD8+T.<sup><xref rid="bibr32-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> The phenomenon in our study may demonstrate that immunogenicity is activated by
apatinib. A study found<sup><xref rid="bibr33-1533033819893667" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> low dose chemotherapeutic drugs can be used clinically to reduce Treg-mediated
immunosuppression. Apatinib may reduce inhibitory effect of Treg-mediated immunosuppression,
and then the patients obtain a good therapeutic effect.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section8-1533033819893667"><title>Conclusion</title><p>CD4+CD25+ T cells are very important for patients with apatinib treatment. The changing
number of CD4+CD25+ T cells may be a good indicator for apatinib, even for anti-VEGF(R) drug
prognosis.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1533033819893667"><p><bold>Authors’ Note:</bold> Our study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Anhui Provincial Hospital (The First
Affiliated Hospital of University of Science and Technology of China West District;
approval no. 2018-17). All patients provided written informed consents prior to enrollment
in the study.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2-1533033819893667"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research,
authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-1533033819893667"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research,
authorship, and/or publication of this article: Medical Scientific Research Foundation of
Anhui Province, China (1808085MH234) (1408085MH179).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1533033819893667"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Hui-Qin Luo <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_1533033819893667-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7550-3719">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7550-3719</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><glossary content-type="abbr"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1-1533033819893667">IL</term><def><p>interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2-1533033819893667">NK</term><def><p>natural killer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3-1533033819893667">mPFS</term><def><p>median progression-free survival</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4-1533033819893667">PFS</term><def><p>progression-free survival</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5-1533033819893667">VEGFR</term><def><p>vascular endothelial growth factor receptor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1533033819893667"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Apatinib for chemotherapy-refractory advanced metastatic gastric cancer:
results from a randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel-arm, phase II
trial</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>26</issue>):<fpage>3219</fpage>–<lpage>3225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23918952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2013.48.8585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1533033819893667"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Pilot study of apatinib as third-line treatment in patients with heavily
treated metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Colorec Can</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>30519</fpage>–<lpage>30594</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clcc.2018.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29576426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1533033819893667"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of apatinib treatment for advanced
esophageal squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Onco Targ Ther</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3965</fpage>–<lpage>3969</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/OTT.S132756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5558584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28860804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1533033819893667"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>A phase II study of apatinib in patients with recurrent epithelial ovarian
cancer</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>148</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29248198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2017.12.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1533033819893667"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Apatinib for advanced sarcoma: results from multiple
institutions’ off-label use in China</article-title>. <source>BMC Can</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>396</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-018-4303-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5889565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29625604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1533033819893667"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalgleish</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pre-treatment with chemotherapy can enhance the
antigenicity and immunogenicity of tumours by promoting adaptive immune
responses</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19997099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bjc.6605465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2813751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1533033819893667"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>YN968D1 is a novel and selective inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth
factor receptor-2 tyrosine kinase with potent activity in vitro and in
vivo</article-title>. <source>Cancer Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>;
<volume>102</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1374</fpage>–<lpage>1380</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21443688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2011.01939.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11158267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1533033819893667"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Safety and pharmacokinetics of novel selective vascular endothelial growth
factor receptor-2 inhibitor YN968D1 in patients with advanced
malignancies</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20923544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2407-10-529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2984425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1533033819893667"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonuleit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stassen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuettenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knop</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enk</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Identification and functional characterization of human
CD4(+)CD25(+) T cells with regulatory properties isolated from peripheral
blood</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1285</fpage>–<lpage>1294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.193.11.1285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2193380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1533033819893667"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levings</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangregorio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncarolo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human cd25(+)cd4(+) t regulatory cells suppress naive and
memory T cell proliferation and can be expanded in vitro without loss of
function</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1295</fpage>–<lpage>1302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.193.11.1295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2193376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1533033819893667"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dieckmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plottner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berchtold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Ex vivo isolation and characterization of CD4(+)CD25(+) T cells with
regulatory properties from human blood</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>1310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.193.11.1303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2193384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1533033819893667"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baecher-Allan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafler</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>CD4+CD25high regulatory cells in human peripheral
blood</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1245</fpage>–<lpage>1253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11466340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.167.3.1245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1533033819893667"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponchel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Human CD4(+)CD25(+) cells: a naturally occurring population of regulatory T
cells</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2736</fpage>–<lpage>2744</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood.v98.9.2736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1533033819893667"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Distribution of CD4+CD25high regulatory T-cells in tumor-draining lymph
nodes in patients with gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>J Surg Res</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>124</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jss.2004.10.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1533033819893667"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arihiro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Maturation of dendritic cells and T-cell responses in
sentinel lymph nodes from patients with breast carcinoma</article-title>.
<source>Cancer</source>.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1227</fpage>–<lpage>1236</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16475148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.21729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1533033819893667"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viguier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaître</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verola</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Foxp3 expressing CD4+CD25(high) regulatory T cells are overrepresented in
human metastatic melanoma lymph nodes and inhibit the function of infiltrating T
cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1444</fpage>–<lpage>1453</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.173.2.1444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1533033819893667"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onizuka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tawara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Tumor rejection by in vivo administration of anti-CD25 (interleukin-2
receptor alpha) monoclonal antibody</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>.
<year>1999</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3128</fpage>–<lpage>3133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10397255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1533033819893667"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Induction of tumor immunity by removing CD25+CD4+ T cells:
a common basis between tumor immunity and autoimmunity</article-title>. <source>J
Immunol</source>.
<year>1999</year>;<volume>163</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>5211</fpage>–<lpage>5218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1533033819893667"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunisato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells suppress NKT cell
functions</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>.
<year>2003</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>4516</fpage>–<lpage>4520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12907625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-1533033819893667"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>CD4+CD25+ regulatory T cells in tumor immunity</article-title>. <source>Int
Immunopharmacol</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26994448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2016.03.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-1533033819893667"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>T cell receptor stimulation-induced epigenetic changes and Foxp3 expression
are independent and complementary events required for Treg cell
development</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>799</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23123060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.immuni.2012.09.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-1533033819893667"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Naturally arising CD4+ regulatory t cells for immunologic
self-tolerance and negative control of immune responses</article-title>. <source>Annu
Rev Immunol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.21.120601.141122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-1533033819893667"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zelenay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes-Carvalho</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caramalho</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Foxp3+ CD25−CD4 T cells constitute a reservoir of committed regulatory
cells that regain CD25 expression upon homeostatic expansion</article-title>.
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4091</fpage>–<lpage>4096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.0408679102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC554795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-1533033819893667"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aiello</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Natural versus adaptive regulatory T
cells</article-title>. <source>Contrib Nephrol</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000082072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-1533033819893667"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Josefowicz</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudensky</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulatory T cells: mechanisms of differentiation and
function</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22224781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.25.022106.141623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6066374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-1533033819893667"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Increased prevalence of regulatory T cells in the tumor
microenvironment and its correlation with TNM stage of hepatocellular
carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1754</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20221638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00432-010-0833-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11827820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-1533033819893667"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Increased regulatory T cells correlate with CD8 T-cell impairment and poor
survival in hepatocellular carcinoma patients</article-title>.
<source>Gastroenterology</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2328</fpage>–<lpage>2339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17570208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.03.102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-1533033819893667"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hontsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Visualization of naturally occurring Foxp3+ regulatory T cells in normal
and tumor-bearing mice</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1793</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.intimp.2004.07.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-1533033819893667"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of suppression by suppressor T
cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15785759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni1180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-1533033819893667"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple Treg suppressive modules and their
adaptability</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22754556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2012.00178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-1533033819893667"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myśliwiec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raczyńska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zorena</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myśliwska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trzonkowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Increased spontaneous production of VEGF by CD4+ T cells
in type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Clin Immunol</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>137</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20705519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clim.2010.07.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-1533033819893667"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du Four</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maenhout</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benteyn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Disease progression in recurrent glioblastoma patients treated with the
VEGFR inhibitor axitinib is associated with increased regulatory T cell numbers and T
cell exhaustion</article-title>. <source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27098427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00262-016-1836-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11029796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-1533033819893667"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuirk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antigen-specific regulatory T cells—their induction and
role in infection</article-title>. <source>Semin Immunol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15036234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.smim.2003.12.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>