
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2057</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101603425</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ, Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6062821</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6062821.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6062821</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6062821</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30057857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3581</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Animal Behavior</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Body and skull morphometric variations between two shovel-headed species of Amphisbaenia (Reptilia: Squamata) with morphofunctional inferences on burrowing</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos Lima Hohl</surname><given-names initials="L">Leandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loguercio</surname><given-names initials="MFDC">Mariana Fiuza de Castro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicuro</surname><given-names initials="FL">Fernando Lencastre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte de Barros-Filho</surname><given-names initials="J">José</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha-Barbosa</surname><given-names initials="O">Oscar</given-names></name><email>obarbosa@uerj.br</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Departamento de Zoologia, Instituto de Biologia Roberto Alcantara Gomes, Laboratório de Zoologia de Vertebrados Tetrapoda—LAZOVERTE, Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro</institution>, <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Instituto de Biologia Roberto Alcantara Gomes, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ecologia e Evolução, Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro</institution>, <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Coordenação de Biologia, Centro Federal de Educação Tecnológica Celso Suckow da Fonseca—CEFET/RJ - Unidade Maracanã</institution>, <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label><institution>Departamento de Ciências Fisiológicas, Instituto de Biologia Roberto Alcantara Gomes, BIOVASC, Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro</institution>, <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>, <country>Brazil</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names initials="P">Philip</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2017-07-18"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">283301</issue-id><elocation-id>e3581</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2017-05-08"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2017-06-24"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>07</month><year>2017</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-07-31 23:11:34.650"><day>31</day><month>07</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>©2017 dos Santos Lima Hohl et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>dos Santos Lima Hohl et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/3581"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Morphological descriptions comparing <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> have been made previously. However, these taxa lack a formal quantitative morphological characterization, and comparative studies suggest that morphology and burrowing performance are be related. The excavatory movements of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> have been described in detail. However, there is a lack of studies comparing locomotor patterns and/or performance among different amphisbaenids sharing the same skull shape. This paper presents the first study of comparative morphometric variations between two closely related amphisbaenid species, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum,</italic> with functional inferences on fossorial locomotion efficiency.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Inter-specific morphometric variations were verified through statistical analyses of body and cranial measures of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> specimens. Their burrowing activity was assessed through X-ray videofluoroscopy and then compared. The influence of morphological variation on the speed of digging was tested among <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> individuals.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> are morphometrically distinct species. The first is shorter and robust with a wider head while the other is more elongated and slim with a narrower head. They share the same excavatory movements. The animals analyzed reached relatively high speeds, but individuals with narrower skulls dug faster. A negative correlation between the speed and the width of skull was determined, but not with total length or diameter of the body.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The morphometric differences between <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> are in accord with morphological variations previously described. Since these species performed the same excavation pattern, we may infer that closely related amphisbaenids with the same skull type would exhibit the same excavatory pattern. The negative correlation between head width and excavation speed is also observed in others fossorial squamates. The robustness of the skull is also related to compression force in <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. Individuals with wider heads are stronger. Thus, we suggest trade-offs between excavation speed and compression force during burrowing in this species.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Amphisbaenidae</kwd><kwd>Fossorial locomotion</kwd><kwd>Leposternon species</kwd><kwd>Locomotor performance</kwd><kwd>Morphological variation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>The Prociência Fellowship Program/UERJ, FAPERJ</funding-source><award-id>E-26/101.070/2013</award-id><award-id>E-26/111.279/2014</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>CAPES/DS and CNPq</funding-source><award-id>302162/2012-7</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The Prociência Fellowship Program/UERJ, FAPERJ (LSL Hohl: E-26/101.070/2013; O Rocha-Barbosa: E-26/111.279/2014), CAPES/DS and CNPq (O Rocha-Barbosa: 302162/2012-7) financially supported this work. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Amphisbaenians are fossorial reptiles with an elongated and cylindrical body shape (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1969</xref>) and, except the three <italic toggle="yes">Bipes</italic> species, all (nearly 200 species, <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Uetz, Freed &amp; Hosek, 2016</xref>) are limbless. They are a monophyletic group within Squamata (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1969</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kearney, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Kearney &amp; Stuart, 2004</xref>).</p><p>A strongly ossified and compact skull is common to all amphisbaenids. However, their heads may show four different morphological patterns: spade-head, keel-head, round-head, and shovel-head (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kearney, 2003</xref>). The “shovel” type, shared by the genera <italic toggle="yes">Rhineura</italic> (Rhineuridae, North America), <italic toggle="yes">Dalophia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Monopeltis</italic> (Amphisbaenidae, Africa), and <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> (Amphisbaenidae, South America), is considered the most specialized for digging (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Kearney, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al., 2014</xref>). This means that these animals are able to penetrate more easily into highly compacted soils reaching greater depths.</p><p>Currently, there are ten recognized <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> species (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Ribeiro et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Ribeiro, Santos-Jr &amp; Zaher, 2015</xref>). The species <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> has a widespread distribution, occurring in different regions of Brazil, as well as in Bolivia, Paraguay, Argentina, and Uruguay (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Perez &amp; Ribeiro, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Ribeiro et al., 2011</xref>). The widespread distribution of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> throughout South America is associated with recognized geographic morphological variation (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Gans &amp; Montero, 2008</xref>), including Paraguayan individuals that were suggested as being a different species by <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho (2000)</xref>. In the State of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> may occupy different soil types with different degrees of compaction and depth (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves-Dias &amp; Barros-Filho, 1992</xref>). On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> has a more restricted distribution, endemic to the State of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (<xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Rocha et al., 2009</xref>), and occupies a specific soil type, less compacted and shallower than those occupied by <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves-Dias &amp; Barros-Filho, 1992</xref>). Also, it is included as Endangered (status EN) on the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Colli et al., 2016</xref>), and on Brazil’s National Red List (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmbio.gov.br/portal/images/stories/biodiversidade/fauna-brasileira/avaliacao-do-risco/PORTARIA_N%C2%BA_444_DE_17_DE_DEZEMBRO_DE_2014.pdf">Portaria MMA no 444, 17 December, 2014</ext-link>).</p><p>Morphological differences between individuals of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> from the State of Rio de Janeiro include the number of annuli and vertebrae, snout-vent length, cephalic and pectoral shields configuration (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1971</xref>), and skull descriptive morphology (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Gans &amp; Montero, 2008</xref>). Among the osteological differences, the vertebrae numbers are 93–103 for <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and 119–123 for <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1971</xref>). <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho (2000)</xref> described the general anatomy of the skull of these species including features that we consider related to the excavation process. The skull of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> can be distinguished from <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> by the diamond-shaped outline of the anterior view of the facial region; angulations between facial and medial skull regions tending to less than 120°(mean value  = 118.8°); the largest width of the facial region being conspicuously shorter than the width of the occipital region; the prefrontal bones not having any conspicuous lateral expansions; and the facial region not being especially expanded laterally at the transverse crest line (between facial and medial regions) (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>). On the other hand, in <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, the anterior view of the facial region has a triangular-shaped outline; the average angulation between facial and medial skull regions is 121.6°; the largest width of the facial region is very close to the width of the occipital region; the prefrontal bones present characteristic lateral expansions; and there is a characteristic lateral expansion at the transverse crest line (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Despite the good qualitative description of morphological variations present in the literature, there are no body and/or skull morphometric differences supported by statistical approaches for these species. Furthermore, the morphofunctional consequences of the morphological variations in <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> remain unknown.</p><p>Fossorial animals have to be able to travel along an existing tunnel, burrow or extend existing tunnel systems, and leave the surface by penetrating the soil (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1978</xref>). The high degree of specialization of the amphisbaenians is well expressed in the speed and effectiveness with which they burrow tunnel systems and penetrate the substrate, even in fairly hard soils (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1978</xref>).</p><p>The excavation patterns of the Amphisbaenia range from random movements of the head and lateral movements to “shovel” and “screw” movements, which vary according to the four head types (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1974</xref>). Shovel-headed amphisbaenians excavate through “shovel” movements of the head, which is considered the most specialized digging pattern (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1974</xref>). In fact, morphological features and underground locomotor performance seem to be related. For instance, body and head size and strength directly affect the ability of fossorial squamates to penetrate the substrate and move inside their galleries (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al., 2004</xref>). <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref> postulated that <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> individuals with narrower heads dig faster than those with a wider head or more robust body. <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Gans (1978)</xref> suggested that the osteological reinforcement of the transverse crest, together with the discrete lateral projection of the otic capsules may be important for improving excavation efficiency. Furthermore, <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Vanzolini (1951)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho (1994)</xref> associated the fusion of cephalic and pectoral shields with the reduction of friction with the substrate, facilitating the underground displacement of the animal.</p><p>In the last 60 years, the locomotor behavior of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> has been incidentally studied through visual observations (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Kaiser, 1955</xref>), motion pictures of the external body (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al., 2004</xref>), and the videofluoroscopy technique (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al., 2014</xref>). The most recent description of the excavatory cycle of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> is presented as: (1) initial static position with the gular and anterior body regions lying over the tunnel floor; (2) retreating and downward bending of the head, with tip of snout touching the floor substrate; (3) a continuous upward and forward head movement, which compacts the substrate granules against the tunnel roof, while the pectoral region compresses the tunnel floor. This is followed by the dropping of the head, returning to the initial static position (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Not only there are few studies of the underground locomotion of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum,</italic> but all of them faced the problem of limited samples (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Kaiser, 1955</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al., 2014</xref>). In fact, there are no studies of other species of <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic>. Furthermore, there is a lack of studies comparing locomotor patterns and/or performance among different amphisbaenid species. Similarly, the review of literature shows that quantitative studies inferring the influence of morphological variation on the fossorial locomotor performance of amphisbaenids are scarce (e.g., <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">López, Martín &amp; Barbosa, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Given that there are notable morphological variations between <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, we hypothesized that body and skull morphometric variation is also evident. Therefore, such variation could impact locomotor performance. Considering that <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> share the same general shovel-headed pattern, they should have similar excavatory movements. Furthermore, based on the observations of <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref> that individuals of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> with narrower heads exert less force but dig faster than those with a wider head or more robust body, we believe that <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> individuals with narrower skulls and bodies may dig faster.</p><p>The main objective of the present study is to characterize the morphometric variations in body and skull between <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, providing morphofunctional inferences on burrowing. We also describe the excavatory pattern and performance of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, comparing its locomotor traits with <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>; and we verify the relation between the length and robustness of the body and skull with the burrowing speed among <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> individuals.</p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><sec><title>Morphometric analysis</title><p>A total of 26 adult <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> specimens were measured (<italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> Wagler, 1824 <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 14; <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (Hemprich, 1820) <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12). The sample included eight live individuals used in the locomotion analyses and 18 specimens from scientific collections deposited at National Museum and Zoology Department of the Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ). The specimens from scientific collections were prepared, after we took the body measures, through exposure to <italic toggle="yes">Dermestes</italic> sp (Coleoptera, Insecta) larvae or maceration in hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) (see <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>). Individuals with a length of more than 150 mm were considered adults (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1971</xref>), and no sexual dimorphism was found for the variables analyzed. <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> has some morphological variation along its geographic distribution in South America. Our analysis included only specimens from Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, therefore, we expected minor differences could exist considering particular ecotypes of this species. Identification of all specimens can be found in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Morphometric data of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 14) and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12) specimens.</title><p>All measures are in millimeters.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g004.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimens</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MWR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">294</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ285</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">466</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">326</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1321</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">489</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4458</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4490</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNRJ4791</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">443</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">375</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1399</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1401</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">462</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZUFRJ1511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">514</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><term-head>Body measures</term-head><def-item><term> TL</term><def><p>total length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> D</term><def><p>diameter</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn2" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl2"><term-head>Skull measures</term-head><def-item><term> CBL</term><def><p>condylo-basal length</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MW</term><def><p>maximum width</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> TCW</term><def><p>tranversal crest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MWR</term><def><p>maximum width of the rostral region</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn3" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl3"><term-head>Scientific Collections</term-head><def-item><term> MNRJ</term><def><p>Museu Nacional da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> ZUFRJ</term><def><p>Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn4" fn-type="other"><p>The first nine animals were recorded and released back into the wild and are identified by the number of specimen/year of recording.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Body measurements were taken using a measuring tape (in mm scale) whereas skull measurements were recorded with a digital caliper (model Pro-Max, Fowler-NSK scale 0.01 mm). The skull measurements were: condylo-basal length (CBL); maximum width (MW), situated at the occipital region covering the optical capsules; the transverse crest width (TCW); and maximum width of the rostral region (MWR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). The body measurements included: the total body length (TL) and diameter (D) in the middle of the body. The terminology of cranial structures follows <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Gans &amp; Montero (2008)</xref>. The skull measurements of the live individuals were taken using X-ray records through the software Tracker v. 4.96. The distance between lead pieces in the wall of the terrarium was used as scale (5 cm). For this sample, it was not possible to measure the TCW and MWR.</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Photography of the dorsal view of a <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> skull showing the measures taken.</title><p>CBL = condylo-basal length; MW = maximum width; TCW = transverse crest width; MWR = maximum width of the rostral region.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The frequency distributions of the morphometric variables were tested for normality (Shapiro–Wilk’s T) and homoscedasticity (Levene), as well as, skewness and kurtosis. The Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-Tests were used to test intra- and inter-specific morphometric variations among <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> specimens by comparing body and skull measurements. Comparisons between groups were performed through Principal Component Analysis (PCA) as a data exploratory method, over the standardized values of the original variables considered (TL, D, CBL and MW), to verify their trends of variation and the group distribution in their multivariate morphological space. Statistical analyses were performed with Statistica v.8.0 (StatSoft, Inc., Tulsa, OK, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Locomotion analysis</title><p>Eight adult individuals of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> from Rio de Janeiro City were analyzed (<italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum n</italic> = 7; <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum n</italic> = 1). <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon scutigerum</italic> is an elusive species. The individuals of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> were collected, recorded and analyzed by <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>. Field collections were approved by the Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio), environmental agency of the Brazilian government, with a permanent license number for collecting zoological material (15337), since May 28th, 2008. This locomotor behavior study was approved by the Ethics Committee for the Care and Use of Experimental Animals of the Instituto de Biologia Roberto Alcantara Gomes (CEUA/IBRAG/015/2017). The individuals are identified by number of specimen/year of recording in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Locomotion was recorded using videofluoroscopy. This technique, based on X-ray recording, has been used in behavioral studies of fossorial species of amphisbaenians (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al., 2014</xref>) and caecilians (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Summers &amp; O’Reilly, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Measey &amp; Herrel, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Herrel &amp; Measey, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Herrel &amp; Measey, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Before recording, <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> was maintained in the laboratory at the Laboratório de Zoologia de Vertebrados-Tetrapoda (LAZOVERTE), Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro (UERJ) under the same conditions presented by <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>, i.e., kept in a plastic box containing humid humus-rich soil, and feed with earthworms once a week. The X-rays were performed at the Hospital Universitário Pedro Ernesto (HUPE/UERJ), Rio de Janeiro, with a Toshiba videofluoroscopy machine (Toshiba Ultimax from Toshiba Medical Systems) that films at 30 frames per second with calibration of 200 mA and 40 kV. In addition, following the same procedures used by <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref> to film individuals of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> was kept in a glass terrarium filled with dry/loose semolina, and with lead markers placed on the outer face of the wall terrarium. More details about the recording procedure can be found in <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>. After filming, the animal was released back into the wild.</p><p>A total recording time of 7 min and 40 s containing 32 motion sequences of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> was analyzed frame by frame using the Toshiba Daicom Viewer software. The excavatory pattern was analyzed taking into account the details of the body postures and movements performed. The locomotor performance was evaluated through the distance covered, duration of the movement, speed and frequency of cycles performed, according to <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>.</p><p>Despite all <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> individuals sharing the same skull type, “shovel”, the sample contained two species. Thus, the excavatory pattern of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 37 cycles) was determined and compared inter-specifically with the three-step gait pattern exhibited by <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 132 cycles), according to <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>.</p><p>The small sample of individuals hindered more comprehensive inter-specific statistical comparisons. Therefore, we evaluated the degree of variation observed in the video footage among the individuals recorded as a starting point to estimate possible differences between locomotor performance in <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. The three fastest excavatory cycles (i.e., in which the animals reached highest speeds) performed by each individual (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7 <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 21 excavatory cycles; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1 <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 excavatory cycles) were quantified according to the locomotory parameters proposed.</p></sec><sec><title>Test of the relation between morphometric variables and burrowing speed</title><p>The influence of morphological variations on locomotor performance was assessed through Multiple Linear Regressions. The speed, expressing the degree of tunneling specialization (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1978</xref>), was used as the dependent variable to be regressed against body and skull measurements considered important for excavation ability according to <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans (1974)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref>: total body length and diameter, and the maximum width of skull (independent variables). The analyses were performed with Statistica v.8.0 (StatSoft, Inc., Tulsa, OK, USA) first adding only <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> individuals, and then inserting the one individual of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Morphological variation</title><p>Inter-specific differences between <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> were observed in total length (TL) (<italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 33.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), diameter of the body (D) (<italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 17.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), condylo-basal length (CBL) (<italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 34.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and maximum width of the skull (MW) (<italic toggle="yes">U</italic> = 27.0, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). However, there were no statistical differences in the transverse crest width (TCW) or maximum width of the rostral region of the skull (MWR). Statistics are given in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Comparative analyses of body and skull morphometric data between <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g005.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C. V. (%) Lm/Ls</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-Test <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">371.1 ± 69.1 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">446.6 ± 44.1 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 / 9.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.45 ± 2.77 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.31 ± 1.65 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 / 13.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.67 ± 2.56 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.27 ± 1.55 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 / 9.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.67 ± 1.84 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 ± 1.16 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 / 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.61 ± 1.11 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06 ± 1.04 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 / 14.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05 ns</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MWR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11 ± 1.24 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 ± 1.07 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 / 14.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05 ns</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl4"><def-item><term> C. V.</term><def><p>Coefficient of Variation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Lm</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Ls</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon scutigerum</italic></p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn2" fn-type="other"><p>Values are presented by means and standard deviation, in millimeters.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The PCA analysis indicated two main axes of group differentiation: PC1 and PC2 explained, respectively, 60.63% and 25.03% of the variation. On PC1, the variables D, CBL, and MW loaded strongly and negatively. On PC2, the total length of the body loaded negatively and strongly (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). According to the PCA scatterplot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> specimens occupied higher positive scores on PC1 and negative scores on PC2, tending to exhibit a greater elongated and slim body shape with a narrower head. On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> specimens occupied greater negative scores on PC1 and positive scores on PC2, featuring a shorter and robust body shape with a wider head.</p><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>The PCA loadings of the variables for the two main axis of variation (PC1 and PC2).</title><p>Larger absolute values indicate more influential traits on the multivariate space. The higher loadings in each axis were highlighted in bold. Eigenvalues and cumulative percentage of variation explained are also indicated.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g006.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.06223</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.99702</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.88608</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03308</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.89178</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.04454</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−0.91613</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07889</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eigenvalue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.423571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000637</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.6638</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Principal Component Analysis scatterplot showing the distribution of <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> specimens on the multivariate space through the two main axis of variation (PC1 and PC2).</title><p>Arrows indicate the direction of the correlation of each variable with the different PCs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Locomotor variation</title><p>A detailed analysis of the movement, through visual observation of X-ray images, revealed that the three-step excavatory cycle of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> seemed to be the same as <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref> described this movement as: (1) initial static position with the gular and anterior body regions lying over the tunnel floor; (2) retreating and downward bending of the head, with tip of snout touching the floor substrate; (3) a continuous upward and forwardhead movement, which compacts the substrate granules against the tunnel roof, while the pectoral region compresses the tunnel floor. This is followed by the dropping of the head, returning to the initial static position.</p><p>According to the locomotor performance data, <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> constructed galleries with an average speed of 0.465 cm s<sup>−1</sup> (±0.2), travelling 0.58 cm (±0.15) in 1.26 s (±0.43) seconds, and performed almost a complete excavatory cycle each second (0.8 ± 0.3 Hz). The three fastest excavatory cycles of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> showed that it constructed galleries with an average speed of 0.757 cm s<sup>−1</sup> (±0.06), travelling 0.73 cm (±0.11) in 0.83 s (±0.23) seconds, and performed a complete excavatory cycle each second (1.06 ± 0.17 Hz). During the three fastest excavatory cycles, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> was able to reach an average speed of 0.350 cm s<sup>−1</sup> (±0.09), travelling 0.59 cm (±0.18) in 1.77 s (±0.59), and performed about a half complete excavatory cycle each second (0.61 ±0.15 Hz).</p><p>The mean values and SDs of the locomotor performance variables suggest that some inter-specific differences may exist between the species. <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon scutigerum</italic> presented higher averages for speed, travel distance and frequency of excavatory cycles, and lower values for cycle duration in relation to those found for <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. On the other hand, the values of the coefficients of variation of the locomotor variables indicated some constancy in the species’ performances along the intra-specific footages. Therefore, despite the sample size limitation, based on this functional approach to the excavatory performance of the species, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> could be a better excavator than <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum,</italic> in the sense of speed of soil penetration and gallery construction. Descriptive statistics values are presented in <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistical values of the fastest excavatory cycles performed by <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (three cycles of one individual) and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> (21 cycles of seven individuals).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g007.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C. V. (%) Lm/Ls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Speed (cm s<sup>−1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350 ± 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.757 ± 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8 / 8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distance (cm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 ± 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 ± 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6 / 15.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 ± 0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 ± 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3 / 28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (Hz)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 ± 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 ± 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 / 16.6</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-4fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl5"><def-item><term> C. V.</term><def><p>Coefficient of Variation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Lm</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term> Ls</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon scutigerum</italic></p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn><fn id="table-4fn2" fn-type="other"><p>Values are presented by means and standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Test of the relation between morphometric variables and burrowing speed</title><p>When the analysis was restricted to <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> individuals, linear regression demonstrated a negative correlation between the speed (dependent variable) and the width of skull (independent variable) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.613; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.037) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3A</xref>), but not with total length (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.001; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.944) or diameter of the body (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.08; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.54). When inserting the unique specimen of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum,</italic> the analysis revealed a stronger and significant negative correlation between speed and width of skull (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.798; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3B</xref>. Relations with total length (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.30; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.153) or diameter of the body (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.42; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.079) remained non-significant.</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.3581/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Excavatory cycle speed as a function of width of skull in <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> individuals.</title><p>(A) Analysis restricted to <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. (B) Analysis after insertion of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, represented by the star.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="peerj-05-3581-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Inter-specific morphometric variation</title><p>Anatomical differences between <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> from Rio de Janeiro State are well known (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1971</xref>; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Gans &amp; Montero, 2008</xref>). The initial hypothesis that body and skull morphometric differences exist was corroborated. Significant differences between these two species in total length and diameter of the body, and maximum width of skull exist.</p><p>As suggested by the great number of vertebrae, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> with 93–103 vertebrae and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> with 119–123 (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1971</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> presented a more elongated body. According to <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho (2000)</xref>, the largest width of the facial region also covering the transverse crest of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> is very close to the maximum width of the skull at the occipital region. This configuration is different for <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>, in which the largest width of the facial region is shorter than the width of the occipital region. Based on this difference, that author concluded that <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> “has a very characteristic skull, specially the lateral expansion of the facial region, at the transverse crest line”. However, our results indicated statistical differences between these species for maximum width of skull (occipital region), but not for transverse crest width or maximum width of the rostralregion (facial region). Thus, the allometric relation between facial and occipital regions of these species proposed by <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho (2000)</xref> is more related to occipital differences than facial ones.</p></sec><sec><title>Inter-specific comparisons of excavatory behavior</title><p><xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> discussed the efficiency of videofluoroscopy as a methodology for analyzing locomotor behavior in fossorial squamates. They concluded that among the methodologies previously used (e.g., visual observations and motion pictures of the external body), videofluoroscopy was the most efficient in analyzing excavatory cycles. Considering that the present study also used videofluoroscopy as the methodology to access the fossorial locomotion of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, and replicated the movie set used by <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref> (i.e., the same glass terrarium marked with lead pieces and filled with dry/loose semolina), we conclude that the comparison results of locomotor pattern and performance between <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> were not influenced by methodological factors.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Leposternon scutigerum</italic> performed, in horizontal and vertical directions, the same three-step excavatory cycle first described by <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> for <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>, reinforced by <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>, as a retreating and downward bending of the head from an initial static position followed by an upward and forward head movement. This result suggests some partial support for the initial hypothesis that morphologically similar amphisbaenids would exhibit the same excavatory pattern. The results also suggests some support for the assumption of <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</xref> that, in spite of specific differences among the shovel-headed amphisbaenid species, the excavatory pattern was the same for all of those species, based on the fact that the shovel-head is, apparently, a convergence among the group (cf. <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans, 1974</xref>).</p><p>However, despite sharing the same skull type and performing three-step excavatory pattern, our quantitative approach of locomotor performance of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> suggested differences in all parameters analyzed (travel distance, excavatory cycle duration, speed, and frequency). According to <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Hohl et al. (2014)</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> was able to build a gallery of 12 cm in length in 1 min. Our results showed that this species was able to build a gallery of 21.6 cm in length in 1 min (mean values based on the three fastest cycles), whereas the single individual of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> studied was able to build a gallery of 46.4 cm in length in 1 min, i.e., more than twice, on average. Despite the lack of a formal statistical significance test, these values suggest that <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> may be a faster digger than <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Morphological features and locomotor performance</title><p><xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Gans (1974)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref> postulated that body, head size and strength directly affect the speed of fossorial squamates to penetrate the substrate and move inside their galleries. However, they only reported it qualitatively. <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref>, although relating the robustness of the head with the compression force, did not obtain the speed with which the animals excavated to associate with head width. According to our quantitative approach these previous statements seem partially true. Body dimensions (total length or diameter) seem to be not related to the increased speed of excavation. Despite the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value above the alpha = 0.05, it seems to be a trend of correlation between body diameter and speed. We are positive that a larger sample could bring more assurance to this hypothesis. However, regression analysis showed that the width of skull is related to the speed of excavation (individuals with slender skulls seem to be faster). The finding, that head width is negatively correlated with excavation speed, is in agreement with previous studies. <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">López, Martín &amp; Barbosa (1997)</xref> showed that individuals of <italic toggle="yes">Blanus cinereus</italic> with narrower, longer heads burrow faster. <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Vanhooydonck et al. (2011)</xref> showed that in burrowing skinks <italic toggle="yes">Acontias percivali</italic>, individuals with narrow heads were able to dig faster than broader-headed ones. Similar to our results, <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Vanhooydonck et al. (2011)</xref> also concluded that the speed in soil penetration is only predicted by the head width, curiouslly getting similar statistical values (<italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum - r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.613, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.037; <italic toggle="yes">Acontias percivali</italic> - <italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03).</p><p>The robustness of the skull has been demonstrated to be an important characteristic to improve soil penetration. Beyond being associated with excavation speed, as here presented, <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref> also demonstrated that the robustness of the skull is also related to compression force among <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>. Individuals with wider heads produced greater compression forces (about 25 N). Likewise, <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Vanhooydonck et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Baeckens et al. (2016)</xref> showed a strong positive relation between head size and bite force in <italic toggle="yes">A. percivali</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trogonophis wiemanni</italic>, respectively. According to these authors, bite performance also increased with head size in these species.</p><p>Besides individuals of the <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> species, our sample contained a unique <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> specimen that presented the narrowest skull (6.5 mm), and, according to our results, it showed the highest mean speed. Comparing inter-specifically, the morphological features of <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> supported the results of the locomotor performance analysis, and the differences in relation to <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic>.</p><p><xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Gans (1978)</xref> highlighted that the slight lateral protrusion of the otic capsules is important for improving the excavation efficiency, here corroborated by the negative correlation between the width of skull and speed through regression analysis. According to our morphological results based on a larger sample, the species <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> presented a narrower skull (maximum width situated at the occipital region covering the otic capsules) when compared to <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> which possesses a wider skull.</p><p>Future studies on compression force and bite performance are needed for these species. Although <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> exhibited low speed during digging in relation to <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic>, according to <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref>, <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Vanhooydonck et al. (2011)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Baeckens et al. (2016)</xref>, it might be able to exert greater compression and bite forces. Even small variations in head width may present a large impact on burrowing compression force (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al., 2004</xref>) and speed (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Vanhooydonck et al., 2011</xref>). Thus, our present data on speed, associated with the data from <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Navas et al. (2004)</xref> on compression forces suggest a performance trade-off between compression forces and burrowing speeds in the shovel-headed <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> (i.e., individuals with narrow heads excavate rapidly but exert less push force, while individuals with robust heads excavate slowly but exert more push force). This relation may be associated with the ecology and geographic distribution differences among <italic toggle="yes">L. microcephalum</italic> (larger geographic distribution occupying different soil types) and <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> (limited distribution occupying a restricted soil type).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Marcos José de Mello Pinheiro from Fundação Técnico Educacional Souza Marques, for lending the live <italic toggle="yes">L. scutigerum</italic> specimen; Marcos Paulo Silva de Almeida from Hospital Universitário Pedro Ernesto, for managing the X-ray machine and acquiring the images and footages; and Dr. Concepción Azorit Casas from Universidad de Jaén, Nicolas Snow from Academia English International Jaén, and Dr. Jeanine Salles dos Santos from UERJ for reviewing the manuscript. We also thank Dr. Timothy Moulton from UERJ for English reviewing the manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Leandro dos Santos Lima Hohl</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Mariana Fiuza de Castro Loguercio</xref> performed the experiments, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Fernando Lencastre Sicuro</xref> analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">José Duarte de Barros-Filho</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-5" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">Oscar Rocha-Barbosa</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Animal Ethics</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>This locomotor behavior study was approved by the Ethics Committee for the Care and Use of Experimental Animals of the Instituto de Biologia Roberto Alcantara Gomes.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Field Study Permissions</title><fn id="addinfo-2"><p>The following information was supplied relating to field study approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>Field experiments were approved by the Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio), environmental agency of the Brazilian government.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-3"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data is included in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Baeckens et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baeckens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Roa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huyghe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Fossorial and durophagous: implications of molluscivory for head size and bite capacity in a burrowing worm lizard</article-title><source>Journal of Zoology</source><volume>301</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jzo.12412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Barros-Filho (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Filho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Distribuição e análise morfológica do gênero Leposternon Wagler, 1824 no Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil (Reptilia, Amphisbaenia)</article-title><source>MSc dissertation</source><institution>Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro at Rio de Janeiro</institution></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Barros-Filho (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Filho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Osteologia Craniana Comparada de Espécies do Gênero Leposternon Wagler, 1824 (Reptilia, Amphisbaenia)</article-title><source>DSc thesis</source><institution>Universidade de São Paulo at São Paulo</institution><comment>vol. I, 138 pp. vol. II, 107 pp</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Barros-Filho, Hohl &amp; Rocha-Barbosa (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Filho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>LSL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha-Barbosa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Excavatory cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalum</italic> Wagler, 1824 (Reptilia, Amphisbaenia)</article-title><source>International Journal of Morphology</source><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0717-95022008000200027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Colli et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colli</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tedeschi</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreto-Lima</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>In the depths of obscurity: knowledge gaps and extinction risk of Brazilian worm lizards (Squamata, Amphisbaenidae)</article-title><source>Biological Conservation</source><volume>204</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2016.07.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Gans (1969)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1969</year><article-title>Amphisbaenians, reptiles specialized for a burrowing existence</article-title><source>Endeavour</source><volume>28</volume><issue>105</issue><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Gans (1971)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>Studies on amphisbaenians (Amphisbaenia, Reptilia). 4, A review of the amphisbaenid genus <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic></article-title><source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source><volume>144</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>464</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Gans (1974)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><source>Biomechanics—an approach to vertebrate biology</source><publisher-name>J B Lippincott</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Gans (1978)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>The characteristics and affinities of the Amphisbaenia</article-title><source>The Transactions of the Zoological Society of London</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1978.tb00376.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Gans (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Checklist and bibliography of the Amphisbaenia of the world</article-title><source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source><volume>289</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/0003-0090(2005)289&lt;0001:CABOTA&gt;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Gans &amp; Montero (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>An atlas of amphisbaenian skull anatomy</article-title><source>Biology of reptilia</source><publisher-name>Society for the Study of Amphibians and Reptiles</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>738</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Gonçalves-Dias &amp; Barros-Filho (1992)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonçalves-Dias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Filho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><volume>Vol. 19</volume><article-title>Correlação entre <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> (Reptilia: Amphisbaenia) e os solos do Estado do Rio de Janeiro</article-title><source>Congresso Latino-Americano de Zoologia, 12 Congresso Brasileiro de Zoologia</source><fpage>189</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Herrel &amp; Measey (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Measey</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>The kinematics of locomotion in caecilians: effects of substrate and body shape</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Zoology Part A</source><volume>313</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20301183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Herrel &amp; Measey (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Measey</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Feeding underground: kinematics of feeding in caecilians</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Zoology Part A</source><volume>317</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jez.1745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22927194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Hohl et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>LSL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loguercio</surname><given-names>MFC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buendía</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida-Santos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viana</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros-Filho</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha-Barbosa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Fossorial gait pattern and performance of a shovel-headed amphisbaenian</article-title><source>Journal of Zoology</source><volume>294</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jzo.12173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Kaiser (1955)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1955</year><article-title>Über die Fortbewegungsweise der Doppelschleichen—beobachtungen an <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon microcephalus</italic> (Wagl.)</article-title><source>Zoologischer Anzeiger</source><volume>154</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Kearney (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Systematics of the Amphisbaenia (Lepidosauria: Squamata) based on morphological evidence from recent and fossil forms</article-title><source>Herpetological Monographs</source><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1655/0733-1347(2003)017[0001:SOTALB]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Kearney &amp; Stuart (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Repeated evolution of limblessness and digging heads in worm lizards revealed by DNA from old bones</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source><volume>271</volume><fpage>1677</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2004.2771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1691774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>López, Martín &amp; Barbosa (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martín</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>State and morphological dependent escape decisions in a fossorial lizard </article-title><named-content content-type="abstract-details">Abstract 289</named-content><source>Journal of Morphology</source><volume>232</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Measey &amp; Herrel (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Measey</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Rotational feeding in caecilians: putting a spin on the evolution of cranial design</article-title><source>Biology Letters</source><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2006.0516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1833987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Navas et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Navas</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoniazzi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaui-Berlink</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jared</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohlsdorf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pai-Silva</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Morphological and physiological specialization for digging in amphisbaenians, an ancient lineage of fossorial vertebrates</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source><volume>207</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2433</fpage><lpage>2441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.01041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15184515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Perez &amp; Ribeiro (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SLB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Reptilia, Squamata, Amphisbaenidae, <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> spp.: distribution extension, new state record, and geographic distribution map</article-title><source>Check List</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15560/4.3.291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Ribeiro et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cintra</surname><given-names>CED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva-Jr</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Description of a new pored <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> (Squamata, Amphisbaenidae) from the Brazilian Cerrado</article-title><source>South American Journal of Herpetology</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2994/057.006.0303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Ribeiro, Santos-Jr &amp; Zaher (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-Jr</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>A new species of <italic toggle="yes">Leposternon</italic> Wagler, 1824 (Squamata, Amphisbaenia) from northeastern Argentina</article-title><source>Zootaxa</source><volume>4034</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.4034.2.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26624443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Rocha et al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>CFD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergallo</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fidalgo</surname><given-names>ECC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uzêda</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>MAS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sluys</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>TCC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cozzolino</surname><given-names>ACR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><source>Estratégias e ações para a conservação da biodiversidade no Estado do Rio de Janeiro</source><publisher-name>Instituto Biomas</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Summers &amp; O’Reilly (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Reilly</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>A comparative study of locomotion in the caecilians <italic toggle="yes">Dermophis mexicanus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Typhlonectes natans</italic> (Amphibia: Gymnophiona)</article-title><source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source><volume>121</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1997.tb00147.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Uetz, Freed &amp; Hosek (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uetz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The reptile database</article-title><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.reptile-database.org">http://www.reptile-database.org</uri><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2016-10-05">5 October 2016</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Vanhooydonck et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhooydonck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boistel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Push and bite: trade-offs between burrowing and biting in a burrowing skink (<italic toggle="yes">Acontias percivali</italic>)</article-title><source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source><volume>101</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2010.01563.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Vanzolini (1951)</label><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanzolini</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1951</year><article-title>Evolution, adaptations and distribution of the Amphisbaenian Lizards (Sauria: Amphisbaenidae)</article-title><source>DSc thesis</source><institution>Harvard University at Cambridge</institution></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>