
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Metab Syndr Relat Disord</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Metab Syndr Relat Disord</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1164</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">met</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101150318</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">met</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Metabolic Syndrome and Related Disorders</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1540-4196</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1557-8518</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7929914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7929914.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7929914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7929914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33170086</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/met.2020.0092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1089/met.2020.0092</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Triglyceride-Glucose Index and Related Parameters Predicted Metabolic Syndrome in Nigerians</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Raimi et al.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">TyG Index and Metabolic Syndrome in Nigeria</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raimi</surname><given-names initials="TH">Taiwo H.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, FMCP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dele-Ojo</surname><given-names initials="BF">Bolade F.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, FMCP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dada</surname><given-names initials="SA">Samuel A.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, FWACP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fadare</surname><given-names initials="JO">Joseph O.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FMCP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajayi</surname><given-names initials="DD">David D.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajayi</surname><given-names initials="EA">Ebenezer A.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, FWACP, FACP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajayi</surname><given-names initials="OA">Oladimeji A.</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS, FWACP, FRCP</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label>Department of Medicine, Ekiti State University/Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital, Ado-Ekiti, Nigeria.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Ekiti State University, Ado-Ekiti, Nigeria.</aff><aff id="aff3"><label><sup>3</sup></label>Department Chemical Pathology, Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital, Ado-Ekiti, Nigeria.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">Address correspondence to: Taiwo H. Raimi, MBBS, FMCP, Department of Medicine, Ekiti State University Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital, Ado-Ekiti 360001, Nigeria <email>taiwo.raimi@eksu.edu.ng</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year><string-date>March 2021</string-date></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">376583</issue-id><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-03-05 00:16:25.467"><day>05</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Taiwo H. Raimi et al. 2021; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Taiwo H. Raimi et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="met.2020.0092.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pdf" xlink:href="met.2020.0092.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">Background:</italic></bold> Triglyceride-glucose (TyG) index, a product of triglyceride and fasting plasma glucose, is a novel tool that can identify people with metabolic syndrome (MS). It is unknown if TyG index can identify MS among Nigerians.</p><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">Methods:</italic></bold> Cross-sectional health screening conducted between August and December 2018, among staff and students of Ekiti State University/Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital, Nigeria, Ado-Ekiti. The analysis included 473 participants, aged ≥18 years. Anthropometric indices and blood pressure were measured by standard protocol. Fasting lipid profile and blood glucose were determined. TyG index and product of TyG and anthropometric indices were calculated, and MS defined according to the harmonized criteria. The diagnostic ability of TyG index and related parameters to identify people with MS was determined with the area under curve (AUC) of receiver operating characteristic curves. Stepwise logistic regression analyses were used to generate odd ratios (ORs) for prediction of MS.</p><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">Results:</italic></bold> The mean age of the participants was 39.2 (11.4) years and there were 173 (36.6%) men. In all participants, TyG-waist to height ratio (TyG-WHtR) shows the largest AUC for MS detection (0.863, 95% confidence interval, CI: 0.828–0.892) followed by TyG-waist circumference (TyG-WC) (0.858, 95% CI: 0.823–0.888), TyG-body mass index (TyG-BMI) (0.838, 95% CI: 0.802–0.870), TyG index (0.796, 95% CI: 0.757–0.831), WHtR (0.791, 95% CI: 0.752–0.827), and TyG-waist-to-hip ratio (TyG-WHpR) (0.771, 95% CI: 0.730–0.808) in that order. Gender analysis revealed that TyG-WC and TyG-WHtR have largest AUC in both genders. Before and after adjustment, TyG-WHtR (OR: 6.86, 95% CI: 3.94–11.93) and TyG index (OR: 5.91, 95% CI: 3.01–11.59) presented the highest OR in all participants, respectively.</p><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">Conclusions:</italic></bold> TyG index is effective in identifying MS in this cross-sectional study, and the product of TyG index and anthropometric indices improved identification and prediction of MS.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>TyG index</kwd><kwd>cardiovascular risk factors</kwd><kwd>metabolic syndrome</kwd><kwd>obesity</kwd><kwd>anthropometry</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><ref-count count="28"/><page-count count="7"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Metabolic syndrome (MS) is characterized by co-occurrence of cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk factors such as arterial hypertension, android obesity, hyperglycemia, and dyslipidemia.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Abnormal lipid metabolism of MS is characterized by elevated triglyceride (TG) and low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C). Detection of MS enables identification of those who are at risk of type 2 diabetes mellitus and CVD.<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> MS is also associated with excess mortality.<sup><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref></sup></p><p>Insulin resistance (IR), characterized by impaired tissue sensitivity or responsiveness to circulating insulin, is thought to be the pathogenic disorder underlying MS.<sup><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The gold standard for measuring IR is the euglycemic clamp method, but due to the technicalities involved, it is unsuitable for large-scale epidemiological survey. Therefore, surrogates that correlate with direct (clamp) method, such as Homeostasis Model Assessment for Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR) and Quantitative Insulin Sensitivity Check Index (QUICKI) were developed.<sup><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Determination of IR with HOMA-IR involves insulin assay that lacked standardization, coupled with the fact that it is a labile hormone. Thus, it is necessary to develop a simple tool to identify IR, and by extension, MS.</p><p>Triglyceride-glucose (TyG) index, a product of triglyceride and fasting plasma glucose (FPG) is a novel tool that has been found to correlate with surrogate and direct measures of IR.<sup><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> In a study that compared the predictive ability of TyG index and HOMA-IR in identifying IR determined with glucose clamp, the former outperformed the latter.<sup><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Furthermore, TyG index is strongly associated with, and performed better than HOMA-IR in identifying MS.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Finally, TyG-related parameters such as product of TyG and waist circumference (TyG-WC), TyG and waist-to height ratio (TyG-WHtR), TyG and waist-to-hip ratio (TyG-WHpR), and TyG and body mass index (TyG-BMI) improved identification of people with IR.<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p>Previous studies that evaluated the usefulness of TyG index were conducted among Americans, Caucasians, and Asians. Blacks have low TG despite the high rates of CVDs, the so-called metabolic paradox.<sup><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> In sub-Sahara Africans with MS, elevated TG has been documented as the least common lipid abnormality.<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Thus, it is unknown if TyG index can identify MS among blacks. Can TyG index and related parameters identify MS in Nigerians? Is TyG index as effective in identifying MS in Nigerians as it is in other races? This study was aimed at answering these questions. We hypothesize that TyG index may be less effective in identifying MS in Nigerians. Furthermore, we hypothesize that product of TyG index and anthropometric indices will improve prediction of MS.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s002"><title>Methods</title><p>To test our hypothesis, we analyzed the data of cross-sectional health screening conducted between August and December 2018, among staff and students of Ekiti State University/Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital (EKSU/EKSUTH), Ado-Ekiti, Nigeria.</p><p>Four hundred seventy-three participants, aged ≥18 years were included in this analysis. Participants were recruited using convenient sampling method. Exclusion criteria included pregnant women, those with history of memory or neurological impairments, or both, which would limit reading, talking, or walking. The Research and Ethics Committee of Ekiti State University Teaching Hospital, Ado-Ekiti approved the study protocol (EKSUTH/A67/2018/08/004). Written informed consent was obtained from the participants.</p><p>Demographic data of age, gender, marital status, educational attainments, and occupation were obtained from the participants. History of smoking was also obtained.</p><sec id="s003"><title>Anthropometric and blood pressure measurements</title><p>Weight (in kilograms) and height (in meters) of participants were determined with bathroom scales and stadiometer, respectively. Waist (at the level of umbilicus) and hip (widest diameter) circumferences (in centimeters) were determined with nonstretchable tape. The body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight/height<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, waist-to-hip ratio (WHpR) was calculated as waist circumference/hip circumference, and waist-to-height ratio (WHtR) was calculated as waist circumference/height in centimeters. The blood pressure was determined (while participants were seated), twice with mercury sphygmomanometer, and average taken. The first and fifth Korotkoff sounds were taken as the systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s004"><title>Laboratory analysis</title><p>After an overnight fast, venous sample were obtained through aseptic techniques for plasma glucose and lipids measurements. Plasma glucose was determined by glucose oxidase method. Total cholesterol and TG were determined by enzymatic method. HDL-C was estimated by oxidase/peroxidase method after precipitation of other cholesterol fractions. Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol was calculated by Friedwald equation. All analyses were done with kits by Randox (Randox Laboratories Ltd., UK)</p></sec><sec id="s005"><title>Definition of terms</title><p>TyG index and related parameters were calculated as follows:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(1)</label><p>TyG index = Ln[TG (mg/dL) × fasting glucose (mg/dL)/2].<sup><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><label>(2)</label><p>TyG-BMI = TyG index × BMI</p></list-item><list-item><label>(3)</label><p>TyG-WC = TyG index × WC</p></list-item><list-item><label>(4)</label><p>TyG-WHpR = TyG index × WHpR</p></list-item><list-item><label>(5)</label><p>TyG-WHtR = TyG index × WHtR.</p></list-item></list></p><p>MS was defined according to the harmonized criteria.<sup><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> These criteria have good concordance with the International Diabetes Federation definition, thus making comparisons among studies possible.<sup><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s006"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Data analysis was done with Statistical Package for Social Sciences (IBM SPSS) version 25 for Windows (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY) and MedCalc Statistical Software version 19.1.5 (MedCalc Software bv, Ostend, Belgium; <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.medcalc.org;">https://www.medcalc.org;</uri> 2020). Continuous variables were presented as means (standard deviation), whereas categorical variables were presented as (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>) percentages. Kolmogorov–Smirnov test of normality was used to determine the distribution of continuous variables. Variables that are normally distributed were compared with independent sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test, whereas variables that are not normally distributed were compared with the Mann–Whitney test. The diagnostic ability of TyG index and related parameters to identify people with MS (as per the harmonized criteria) was determined with the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves. These were compared with diagnostic ability of WHtR, which was earlier shown to have the best predictive ability in Nigeria.<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Pairwise comparison of the area under curve (AUC) on the ROC curve was done by DeLong method.<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Stepwise logistic regression analyses were used to generate odd ratios (ORs) for prediction of MS, and adjusted for age, smoking, gender, SBP, and DBP. A probability (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>) value of &lt;0.05 was taken as significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s007"><title>Results</title><p>Four hundred seventy-three participants comprising 173 (36.6%) men were analyzed for this study, giving a male to female ratio of 1:1.7. The mean age of the participants was 39.2 years. The age, systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP), fasting plasma glucose (FPG), TG, HDL-C, TyG index, and TyG-WC of men and women were not significantly different. In comparison with men, women had significantly higher anthropometric and TyG parameters of BMI, WC, and WHtR, TyG-BMI, and TyG-WHtR, but lower WHpR and TyG-WHpR (<xref rid="tb1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tb1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Clinical Characteristics of the Study Participants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALL participants (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 473)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 173)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 300)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.2 (11.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.0 (11.5)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4 (11.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.485</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.1 (14.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.5 (13.1)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.3 (15.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Height (m)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6 (0.09)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70 (0.07)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61 (0.07)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.492</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Waist circumference (cm)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.3 (13.1)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.8 (12.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.1 (13.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hip circumference (cm)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.9 (12.9)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.5 (11.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102.9 (13.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.5 (5.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.1 (4.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3 (5.8)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87 (0.14)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.88 (0.09)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 (0.16)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53 (0.08)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51 (0.08)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55 (0.08)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SBP (mmHg)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119.3 (18.9)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119.6 (16.2)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119.1 (20.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.276</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DBP (mmHg)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.4 (13.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.4 (11.9)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.4 (13.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.875</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fasting glucose (mg%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.4 (27.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.1 (26.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.1 (28.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.267</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Triglyceride (mg%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">123.6 (80.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">127.7 (84.1)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.2 (78.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.413</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High-density lipoprotein (mg%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.7 (29.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.7 (26.2)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.6 (30.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.715</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4 (0.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4 (0.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3 (0.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.342</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TyG-BMI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">221.7 (51.1)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210.7 (40.5)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">228.1 (55.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TyG-WC</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">730.5 (134.7)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">722.1 (131.3)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">735.3 (136.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.311</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TyG-WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3 (1.4)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4 (1.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.2 (1.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5 (0.8)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3 (0.8)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.6 (0.9)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MS <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86 (18.2)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (11.6)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (22.0)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1"><p>Data were expressed as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (SD), except for smoking history and MS that were expressed as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%).</p></fn><fn id="tf2"><p>BMI, body mass index; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; MS, metabolic syndrome; SBP, systolic blood pressure; SD, standard deviation; TyG, triglyceride-glucose; TyG-BMI, product of TyG and body mass index; TyG-WC, product of TyG and waist circumference; TyG-WHpR, product of TyG and waist-to-hip ratio; TyG-WHtR, product of TyG and waist-to-height ratio; WHpR, waist-to-hip ratio; WHtR, waist-to height ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The ROC curve analyses are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1A–C</xref>, and the corresponding AUCs (95% confidence interval, CI) in <xref rid="tb2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. <xref rid="tb3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the pairwise comparison of the AUCs of WHtR, TyG index, TyG-BMI, TyG-WC, TyG-WHpR, and TyG-WHtR for the detection of MS. All the parameters significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) identified MS in all participants and both genders. In all participants, TyG-WHtR shows the largest AUC for MS detection (0.863, 95% CI: 0.828–0.892) followed by TyG-WC (0.858, 95% CI: 0.823–0.888), TyG-BMI (0.838, 95% CI: 0.802–0.870), TyGindex (0.796, 95% CI: 0.757–0.831), WHtR (0.791, 95% CI: 0.752–0.827), and TyG-WHpR (0.771, 95% CI: 0.730–0.808) in that order. Gender analysis revealed that TyG-WC and TyG-WHtR have largest AUC in both genders, suggesting that they have the best discriminating power to identify MS in comparison with other parameters.</p><fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG. 1.</label><caption><p>ROC curves for the parameters for identifying MS. <bold>(A)</bold> ROC curve for each parameter for identifying MS in all participants. <bold>(B)</bold> ROC curve for each parameter for identifying MS in men. <bold>(C)</bold> ROC curve for each parameter for identifying MS in women. MS, metabolic syndrome; ROC, receiver operating characteristic; TyG, triglyceride-glucose; TyG-BMI, product of TyG and body mass index; TyG-WC, product of TyG and waist circumference; TyG-WHtR, product of TyG and waist-to-height ratio; TyG-WHpR, product of TyG and waist-to-hip ratio; WHtR, waist-to height ratio. Color images are available online.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="met.2020.0092_figure1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="tb2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The Areas Under the Receiver Operating Characteristic Curve for Each Parameter for Identifying Metabolic Syndrome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUC</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">All participants</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.752–0.827</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.796</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.757–0.831</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-BMI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.838</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.802–0.870</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WC</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.858</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.823–0.888</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.771</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.730–0.808</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.863</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.828–0.892</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Men</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.810</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.743–0.866</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.892</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.836–0.934</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-BMI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.897</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.841–0.938</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WC</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.919</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.867–0.955</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.859</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.798–0.907</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.909</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.856–0.947</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Women</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.766</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.714–0.812</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.775</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.724–0.821</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-BMI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.810</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.761–0.853</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WC</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.838</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791–0.877</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.781</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.730–0.826</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.836</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.789–0.876</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3"><p>AUC, area under curve; CI, confidence interval; WHtR, waist-to height ratio; TyG-BMI, product of TyG and body mass index; TyG-WC, product of TyG and waist circumference; TyG-WHpR, product of TyG and waist-to-hip ratio; TyG-WHtR, product of TyG and waist-to height ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tb3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Pairwise Comparison of Area Under Curve of the Different Parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Men</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Women</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">WHtR∼TyGindex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00445</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0822</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00936</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0653 to 0.0742</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0317 to 0.196</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0739 to 0.0926</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.125</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.414</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.220</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.9006</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.1572</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.8256</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">WHtR∼TyG_BMI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0467</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0868</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0445</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00495 to 0.0885</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0167 to 0.157</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.00551 to 0.0946</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.192</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.426</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.744</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0284</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0153</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0811</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">WHtR∼TyG_WC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0665</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.109</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0719</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0314 to 0.102</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0602 to 0.157</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0319 to 0.112</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.708</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.396</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.525</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">WHtR∼TyGWHpR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0204</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0330</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0152</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0392 to 0.0799</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0726 to 0.139</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0474 to 0.0777</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.670</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.612</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.474</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.5029</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.5403</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.6352</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">WHtR∼TyG_WHtR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0712</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0989</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0703</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0423 to 0.100</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0552 to 0.143</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0337 to 0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.834</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.434</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.763</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">TyGindex∼TyG_BMI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0423</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00458</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0352</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0129 to 0.0974</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0718 to 0.0810</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0324 to 0.103</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.501</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.117</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.020</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.1334</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.9065</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.3078</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">TyGindex∼TyG_WC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0621</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0626</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0626</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0153 to 0.109</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00588 to 0.119</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00588 to 0.119</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.601</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.163</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.163</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0093</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0305</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0305</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">TyGindex∼TyGWHpR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0248</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0330</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00580</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0186 to 0.0682</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0726 to 0.139</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0424 to 0.0540</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.120</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.612</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.236</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.2627</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.5403</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.8137</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">TyGindex∼TyG_WHtR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Difference between areas</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0667</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0167</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0610</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 95% CI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0201 to 0.113</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0610 to 0.0943</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00673 to 0.115</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> z statistic</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.803</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.421</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.203</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Significance level</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0051</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.6740</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0276</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Pairwise comparison of the AUCs showed that compared with WHtR (the reference or standard), TyG index and TyG-WHpR equally (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) identified MS in all the participants and both genders. In contrast, TyG-BMI, TyG-WC, and TyG-WHtR were better than WHtR in detecting MS in all the participants (TyG-BMI vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0284; TyG-WC vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002; TyG-WHtR vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and both men (TyG-BMI vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0153; TyG-WC vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001; TyG-WHtR vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and women (TyG-WC vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0004; TyG-WHtR vs. WHtR, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002). In women TyG-BMI was as good as WHtR in identifying MS. Both TyG-WC and TyG-WHtR equally identified MS in all the participants, but were better than TyG index in all participants and women. In men TyG index and all the TyG parameters perform equally in detecting MS.</p><p>The result of ORs and 95% CIs for MS before and after adjustment for gender (for all participants), age, smoking, SBP, and DBP is shown in <xref rid="tb4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Nonsignificant parameters were automatically removed by the software from the model. In a model that included TyG index and TyG parameters, only TyG index and TyG-WHtR significantly predicted MS in all participants and women, before and after adjustment. In men, only TyG index and TyG-BMI significantly predicted MS. Before adjustment, TyG-WHtR presented the highest OR in all participants (6.86, 95% CI: 3.94–11.93) and women (4.11, 95% CI: 2.43–6.95), whereas TyG index presented the highest OR in men (9.12, 95% CI: 2.50–33.33). After adjustment, TyG index presented the highest OR in all participants (5.91, 95% CI: 3.01–11.59) and men (28.36, 95% CI: 4.69–171.63). In all the models, the percentage variation (<italic toggle="yes">R<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></italic>) for MS increased after adjustment.</p><table-wrap id="tb4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>The Odd Ratios for Metabolic Syndrome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unadjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adjusted OR (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup></th><th align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All participants</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.3–44.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.3–60.8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.67 (1.93–6.96)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.91 (3.01–11.59)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.86 (3.94–11.93)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.10 (2.40–7.03)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHpR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56 (0.33–0.94)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0294</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Men</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.8–56.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3–71.1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.12 (2.50–33.33)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0008</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.36 (4.69–171.63)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-BMI</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (1.02–1.06)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0344 (1.01–1.06)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Women</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.4–39.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4–57.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG index</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.14 (1.17–3.93)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0140</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.88 (1.86–8.08)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> TyG-WHtR</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.11 (2.43–6.95)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.93 (2.12–7.30)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> </td><td align="center" valign="bottom" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf4"><p>OR, odd ratio; TyG-BMI, product of TyG and body mass index; TyG-WC, product of TyG and waist circumference; TyG-WHpR, product of TyG and waist-to-hip ratio; TyG-WHtR, product of TyG and waist-to height ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s008"><title>Discussion</title><p>Identification and prompt management of MS are important to prevent future diabetes and CVD.<sup><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Because direct measurement of IR, the underlying disorder in MS is difficult to determine in large-scale studies, surrogates are necessary. In this study, we assessed and compared the predictive ability of TyG index, TyG-BMI, TyG-WC, TyG-WHpR, and TyG-WHtR in identifying MS as per the criteria. Furthermore, these were compared with WHtR.</p><p>TyG index and all the TyG-related parameters identified MS. Overall, TyG index and TyG-WHpR were as good as WHtR in identifying MS. Furthermore, TyG-WHtR with AUC of 0.863, and TyG-WC with AUC of 0.858 were superior to TyG index and WHtR in all the participants. A combination of TyG index and obesity indices is better than TyG index alone in women but not in men.</p><p>Consistent with our finding, previous study by Khan et al.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> showed that TyG index predicted MS. In their study, TyG index with AUC of 0.764 was superior to other CVD risk factors and IR in identifying MS. However, they neither compared TyG index with any anthropometric index nor with TyG-anthropometric indices. In another Korean study that examined the usefulness of TyG index in identifying metabolically obese but normal weight individuals, Lee et al.<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> found that the index highly predicted MS with a large AUC of between 0.855 and 0.868. A similar study among Chinese also confirmed the predictive ability of TyG index with AUC of 0.863–0.867 depending on the gender.<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></p><p>The overall AUC for TyG index (0.796) in our study is similar to that of Pakistan study,<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> but lower than Korean<sup><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and Chinese<sup><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> studies, suggesting that TyG index may be less predictive in our cohort when compared with the latter populations (Koreans and Chinese). It has been suggested that TG levels may determine the cutoff of TyG index for identifying MS,<sup><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> but whether this is applicable to AUC is doubtful. The mean TG, FPG, and TyG index in our study were lower, despite similar AUC compared with that of the Pakistani study.<sup><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> In comparison with Korean study,<sup><xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> our cohort had a higher TG, lower FPG, similar TyG index, but a lower overall AUC. These may imply that the interaction among these parameters in identifying MS is complex and ethnic specific.</p><p>In contrast, Lim et al.<sup><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> compared the ability TyG index and related parameters to predict IR. Similar to our findings, they reported that a combination of TyG index and anthropometric indices predicted IR (the underlying disorder in MS) better than TyG alone. Cardiovascular risk factors interact synergistically. Therefore, it is expected that addition or combination of three CVD risk factors should predict MS than only one or two risk factors. Apart from the fact that MS was less prevalent among men, the reason why TyG-related parameters were not better than TyG index alone in men is unclear, since both genders had similar mean TG and FPG. It may, however, be due to variable gender-dependent interaction of CVD risk factors, which has been reported by some workers.<sup><xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></p><p>Our ROC analysis showed that TyG-WHtR and TyG-WC outperformed other indices in all participants and women. Further, TyG-WHtR showed the highest OR in all participants and women before adjustment. TyG-WHtR appear to be the best of all the parameters studied. Thus, combining TyG and WHtR may be valuable in identifying MS in our cohort. Both WC and WHtR are markers of visceral fat that has been found to correlate more with CVD than BMI, a measure of general obesity.<sup><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Because WHtR corrected for height, it may be better than WC. Indeed, it was reported that WHtR identified people with early health risks better than a matrix that combined BMI and WC.<sup><xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> In a study that compared the predictive ability of multiple anthropometric indices and other parameters, TyG-WC was reported to be the best.<sup><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> But TyG-WHtR was not included for comparison in their study.</p><p>Similar studies for comparison are lacking in our environment. But WHtR was earlier reported to be superior to WC in identifying CVD risk factors.<sup><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Reports of a multicountry study on performance of anthropometric indices for identification of cardiometabolic disorders in sub-Sahara Africa also confirmed our finding.<sup><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> In the aforementioned study involving &gt;19,000 participants, WHtR was as good as WC but better than BMI and WHpR in all the cohort and men. It was, however, the best index in women. It is, therefore, not surprising that TyG-WHtR was the best predictor of MS in this study.</p><sec id="s009"><title>Strength and limitations</title><p>Our study has strength and limitations. First, this is the first study in our environment to evaluate the usefulness of TyG index and TyG-related parameters (involving commonly used anthropometric indices) to detect MS. Because definition of MS is ethnic specific, our findings is not generalizable. Furthermore, the cutoff of TyG index for identifying MS was not determined.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s010"><title>Conclusions</title><p>TyG index is effective in identifying MS in this cross-sectional study. Furthermore, the product of TyG index and anthropometric indices improved identification and prediction of MS.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s011" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Author Disclosure Statement</title><p>No conflicting financial interests exist.</p></sec><sec id="s012"><title>Funding Information</title><p>No funding was received for this work.</p></sec><ref-list content-type="parsed"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alberti</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eckel</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Grundy</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Harmonizing the metabolic syndrome: A joint interim statement of the International Diabetes Federation Task Force on Epidemiology and Prevention; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; American Heart Association; World Heart Federation; International Atherosclerosis Society; and International Association for the Study of Obesity</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>1640</fpage>–<lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.192644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic syndrome as a predictor of type 2 diabetes, and its clinical interpretations and usefulness</article-title>. <source>J Diabetes Investig</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jdi.12075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4020225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiyoshi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of metabolic syndrome on the risk of cardiovascular disease mortality in the United States and in Japan</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24169008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amjcard.2013.08.042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karajamaki</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hukkanen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kauma</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic syndrome but not genetic polymorphisms known to induce NAFLD predicts increased total mortality in subjects with NAFLD (OPERA study)</article-title>. <source>Scand J Clin Lab Invest</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31851849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/00365513.2019.1700428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tracy</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Staley</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic syndrome: Major risk factor for morbidity and mortality in severely injured trauma patients</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>230</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31672670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2019.09.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alberti</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmet</surname>
<given-names>PZ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Definition, diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus and its complications. Part 1: Diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus provisional report of a WHO consultation</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9686693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9136(199807)15:7&lt;539::AID-DIA668&gt;3.0.CO;2-S</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leroith</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karnieli</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Insulin resistance in obesity as the underlying cause for the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Mt Sinai J Med</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20960553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/msj.20212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahan</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reaven</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Relationship between surrogate estimates and direct measurement of insulin resistance in women with polycystic ovary syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Endocrinol Invest</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30701438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40618-019-01014-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6639126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reaven</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of two methods using plasma triglyceride concentration as a surrogate estimate of insulin action in nondiabetic subjects: Triglycerides x glucose versus triglyceride/high-density lipoprotein cholesterol</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1673</fpage>–<lpage>1676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.metabol.2011.04.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical usefulness of lipid ratios, visceral adiposity indicators, and the triglycerides and glucose index as risk markers of insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25326814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12933-014-0146-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4209231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vasques</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Novaes</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Mda</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>TyG index performs better than HOMA in a Brazilian population: A hyperglycemic clamp validated study</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>e98</fpage>–<lpage>e100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21665314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.diabres.2011.05.030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sobia</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niazi</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic clustering of risk factors: Evaluation of Triglyceride-glucose index (TyG index) for evaluation of insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Diabetol Metab Syndr</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13098-018-0376-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6173832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of triglyceride glucose index, and related parameters to predict insulin resistance in Korean adults: An analysis of the 2007–2010 Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0212963</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30845237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0212963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6405083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaillard</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Osei</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic syndrome in Black people of the African diaspora: The paradox of current classification, definition and criteria</article-title>. <source>Ethn Dis</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2 Suppl 2</issue>):S2-1-7<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19537240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ekoru</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>GAV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Deriving an optimal threshold of waist circumference for detecting cardiometabolic risk in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ijo.2017.240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5880575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero-Romero</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Simental-Mendia</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Ortiz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The product of triglycerides and glucose, a simple measure of insulin sensitivity. Comparison with the euglycemic-hyperinsulinemic clamp</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>3347</fpage>–<lpage>3351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20484475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/jc.2010-0288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raimi</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Odusan</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fasanmade</surname>
<given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Metabolic syndrome among apparently healthy Nigerians with the harmonized criteria: Prevalence and concordance with the International Diabetes Federation (IDF) and Third Report of the National Cholesterol Education Programme—Adult Treatment Panel III (NCEP-ATP III) Criteria</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Dis Rev</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oguoma</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nwose</surname>
<given-names>EU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Anthropometric indices: How they compare in screening of cardio-metabolic risks in a Nigerian sub-population</article-title>. <source>Afr J Med Med Sci</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28686832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: A nonparametric approach</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>837</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A novel criterion for identifying metabolically obese but normal weight individuals using the product of triglycerides and glucose</article-title>. <source>Nutr Diabetes</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e149</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25915739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nutd.2014.46</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4423196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Fasting triglycerides and glucose index is more suitable for the identification of metabolically unhealthy individuals in the Chinese adult population: A nationwide study</article-title>. <source>J Diabetes Investig</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1050</fpage>–<lpage>1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jdi.12975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6626942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30417578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The cut-off values of triglycerides and glucose index for metabolic syndrome in American and Korean Adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Korean Med Sci</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>–<lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28145645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3346/jkms.2017.32.3.427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5290101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Masoudkabir</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Poorhosseini</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vasheghani-Farahani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Synergistic effect of hypertension with diabetes mellitus and gender on severity of coronary atherosclerosis: Findings from Tehran Heart Center registry</article-title>. <source>ARYA Atheroscler</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26862339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4738041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>Y-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>H-C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Gender difference in the interaction effects of diabetes and hypertension on stroke among the elderly in the Shih-Pai Study, Taiwan</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0136634</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26322779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0136634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4554728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nalini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharafkhah</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Poustchi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparing anthropometric indicators of visceral and general adiposity as determinants of overall and cardiovascular mortality</article-title>. <source>Arch Iran Med</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31356096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8843234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashwell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Waist-to-height ratio as an indicator of “early health risk”: Simpler and more predictive than using a “matrix” based on BMI and waist circumference</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e010159</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4800150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26975935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashwell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A simple cut-off for waist-to-height ratio (0.5) can act as an indicator for cardiometabolic risk: Recent data from adults in the Health Survey for England</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>
<year>2019</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31840619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S0007114519003301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Triglyceride glucose-waist circumference, a novel and effective predictor of diabetes in first-degree relatives of type 2 diabetes patients: Cross-sectional and prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Transl Med</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27604550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12967-016-1020-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5015232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>