
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3390</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijip</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8911335</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7691946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7691946.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7691946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7691946</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2058738420974900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2058738420974900</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Candesartan modulates microglia activation and polarization via NF-κB
signaling pathway</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qie</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738420974900">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-2058738420974900">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuanyuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738420974900">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-2058738420974900">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaosheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-2058738420974900">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-2058738420974900">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738420974900">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-2058738420974900">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names initials="W">Weijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-2058738420974900">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4685-1057</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zongjian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738420974900">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2058738420974900"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-2058738420974900"><label>1</label>Department of Rehabilitation, Beijing
Rehabilitation Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff2-2058738420974900"><label>2</label>Department of Research, Beijing
Rehabilitation Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff3-2058738420974900"><label>3</label>Department of Plastic Surgery,
Affiliated Hospital of Weifang Medical University, Weifang, Shandong, China</aff><aff id="aff4-2058738420974900"><label>4</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Beijing
Tsinghua Chang Gung Hospital, School of Clinical Medicine, Tsinghua University,
Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff5-2058738420974900"><label>5</label>Department of Neurological
Rehabilitation, Beijing Rehabilitation Hospital, Capital Medical University,
Beijing, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2058738420974900">Zongjian Liu, Department of Research,
Beijing Rehabilitation Hospital, Capital Medical University, Xixiazhuang,
Badachu Road, Shijingshan District, Beijing 100144, China. Email:
<email>liuzj888@ccmu.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="corresp2-2058738420974900">Weijun Gong, Department of Neurological
Rehabilitation, Beijing Rehabilitation Hospital, Capital Medical University,
Xixiazhuang, Badachu Road, Shijingshan District, Beijing 100144, China. Email:
<email>gwj197104@ccmu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1-2058738420974900"><label>*</label><p>Shuyan Qie and Yuanyuan Ran contributed equally to this paper</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">351103</issue-id><elocation-id>2058738420974900</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-29 22:25:11.880"><day>29</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900.pdf"/><abstract><p>Microglia are diverse cells that acquire different functional phenotypes in
response to microenvironment in which they reside. Several transcriptional
regulators have been identified that regulate different microglia phenotypes.
They are mainly stimulated into two opposing phenotypes, classically (M1) and
alternatively (M2) phenotype. Regulating microglia polarization from M1 to M2
state has been suggested as a potential therapeutic approach in treatment of CNS
disorders. Candesartan, an angiotensin II type I receptors antagonist, exerts
beneficial effects for antioxidant, anti-inflammation, neurotrophic, and
anti-apoptotic function. However, the effect of candesartan on microglia
polarization and underlying mechanisms remain unknown. In this study, the
resting microglia were stimulated to M1 microglia with lipopolysaccharide (LPS)
and interferon-γ (IFN-γ), and then treated with vehicle or candesartan for 24 h.
RT-PCR was utilized to detect the mRNA expression of microglia phenotype markers
and inflammatory cytokines. Microglia phenotype markers and toll-like receptor 4
(TLR4)/nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) pathway were determined by western blot. A
neuron-microglia co-culture system was used to determine whether candesartan
could ameliorate the neurotoxic effect of M1 microglia to oxygen-glucose
deprivation (OGD) neuron. Candesartan treatment reduced the expression of M1
markers, and increased M2 markers. Meanwhile, candesartan reduced fluorescence
intensity and protein level of M1 marker and enhanced M2 marker. Candesartan
also regulated the neuroinflammatory response via reducing the release of
pro-inflammatory cytokines and increasing anti-inflammatory cytokines in LPS +
IFN-γ stimulated BV2 cells. Candesartan markedly inhibited the protein level of
TLR4, the phosphorylation of IKBα and p65, and suppressed nuclear translocation
of NF-κB p65. BAY 11-7085, a NF-κB inhibitor, remarkably enlarged the inhibitory
effect of candesartan on NF-κB pathway. In addition, M1 phenotype microglia
exacerbated post-OGD N2a cells death and LDH release, whereas candesartan
reversed such neurotoxic effect. Candesartan treatment may ameliorate
stroke-induced neuronal damage through shifting microglia to M2 phenotype in a
TLR4/NF-κB-dependent manner.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>BV2 cells</kwd><kwd>candesartan</kwd><kwd>microglia polarization</kwd><kwd>neuroinflammation</kwd><kwd>NF-κB</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-2058738420974900"><title>Introduction</title><p>Microglia are specialized innate immune macrophages in the central nervous system
(CNS) and perform numerous functions required for CNS development, homeostasis, and
repair.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>
Clinical and experimental studies support that microglia play important roles in
regulating immune and inflammatory responses for pathogenesis and repairment in CNS
injuries, including Alzheimer’s disease, Parkinson’s disease, and stroke.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Many lines of evidence indicate
that microglia can exhibit a diverse range of phenotypes with beneficial or
deleterious functions in response to their surroundings.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Microglia phenotypes have the characteristics of spatial, temporal and
functional diversity during the progression of CNS disease.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> For instance, the classically activated M1 microglia are stimulated by
lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and interferon-γ (IFN-γ), which lead to inflammatory
amplification through the secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines including tumor
necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleukin-1β (IL-1β), and IFN-γ.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> In contrast, alternatively activated M2 microglia are induced by
interleukin-4 (IL-4) or interleukin-13 (IL-13), which exert neuroprotective effects
by removing cell debris and producing anti-inflammatory cytokines such as
transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β) and interleukin-10 (IL-10).<sup><xref rid="bibr8-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Several transcriptional regulators have been identified that regulate
different microglia phenotypes, including nuclear factor kappa-B (NF-κB), signal
transducer and activator of transcription (STATs), interferon regulatory factors
(IRFs), and so on.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Excessive inflammation responses during the course of CNS injury are
detrimental for the recovery of neurological function.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Not surprisingly, balancing between M1 and M2 microglia polarization play a
key role during the CNS disease progression.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>Candesartan is an antagonist blocking angiotensin II type I receptors (AT1R, encoded
by Atgr1) stimulation by angiotensin II when administered systemically.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> More observations strongly suggest that angiotensin II signaling may
participate in multiple functions for cerebral circulation, stress responses and
inflammation through the AT1Rs activation.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> But decreasing AT1R activity
with the AT1R antagonist candesartan is therapeutic function on hypertension,<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> heart failure,<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> cerebrovascular accident, or stroke.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) can be stimulated by LPS, and further activates
downstream NF-κB, which eventually induces the transcription of pro-inflammatory
mediators and promotes the polarization of M1 phenotypic microglia.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In LPS model rats, candesartan was also found to reduce gene expression of
pro-inflammatory cytokines, and microglia activation in the brain.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> The anti-inflammatory effects of candesartan may result from the inhibition
of Angiotensin II and LPS common signaling cascades. In LPS-stimulated human renal
tubular epithelial model, candesartan inhibited inflammatory factors likely via
reducing TLR4, but independent on AT1R.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> These studies indicated that candesartan treatment could ameliorate different
pathological effect, yet candesartan has not been assessed for regulation on
microglia polarization.</p><p>The present study was designed to test the underlying mechanism of candesartan in
modulating microglia polarization. Firstly, candesartan was demonstrated to inhibit
microglia M1 polarization and promote M2 polarization. Furthermore, candesartan
treatment also significantly modulated neuroinflammatory response via attenuating
pro-inflammatory cytokines and increasing anti-inflammatory factors. The cellular
mechanisms of this process may be associated with the inhibition of TLR4/NF-κB
signaling pathway. In addition, candesartan inhibited the neurotoxic effect of M1
microglia on OGD neurons in neuron-microglia co-culture system. Therefore, these
findings support the view that candesartan alleviates neuronal damage at least
partially by modulating the balance between M1 and M2 microglia polarization in a
TLR4/NF-κB-dependent manner.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-2058738420974900"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="section3-2058738420974900"><title>Microglia cell model and candesartan treatment</title><p>Both mouse microglia (BV2 cells) and neuron (N2a cells) were purchased from Cell
Center, Institute of Basic Medical Sciences, CAMS and PUMC, Beijing, China. BV2
cells were cultured in DMEM medium (Gibco), which was supplemented with 10%
fetal bovine serum (Gibco), and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco). The cells
were then incubated at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. For
M1 microglia, microglial cells were stimulated with 100 ng/mL LPS + 20 ng/mL
IFN-γ (PeproTech),<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="bibr20-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and then treated with vehicle or candesartan (Sigma). For
M2 microglia, microglial cells were induced with 20 ng/mL IL-4 (PeproTech).<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> After 24 h treatment, cells were harvested for testing the changes of
mRNA and protein level, and the supernatant was collected for measuring the
level of inflammatory cytokines.</p></sec><sec id="section4-2058738420974900"><title>Cell viability and LDH assay</title><p>BV2 cells (3 × 10<sup>4</sup>/well) were seeded into 96-well plates (Gibco), and
treated with vehicle or different concentrations of candesartan (0.5, 1, 5, 10,
20, 30, 40, and 50 µM) for 24 h. The cell viability of BV2 microglial cells was
evaluated by the cell counting kit-8 assay (CCK-8 assay, Beyotime). Each well
was exposed to 10 μL of CCK-8 reagent (Beyotime). During the last 1 h incubation
at 37°C, all wells were measured for the absorbance at 450 nm in a microplate
reader (Biotek). The cytotoxicity of candesartan on BV2 cells was analyzed by a
lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) assay kit (Beyotime) according to the manufacturer’s
protocol. The concentrations of LDH were measured for the absorbance at 490 nm
using a microplate reader (Biotek). The data were expressed as percentages of
the value of vehicle cells.</p></sec><sec id="section5-2058738420974900"><title>Nitric oxide assay</title><p>BV2 cells (1.5 × 10<sup>6</sup>/well) were cultured in 60 cm culture dish, and
treated with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL) followed by vehicle or optimal
dose of candesartan for 24 h. The concentration of nitric oxide (NO) in
supernatant was performed using the Griess reaction kit according to the
manufacturer’s instruction (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute). The 490
nm absorbance was measured by a microplate reader (Biotek). The NO concentration
was calculated using the standard curve of sodium nitrate.</p></sec><sec id="section6-2058738420974900"><title>ELISA measurements</title><p>BV2 cells (1.5 × 10<sup>6</sup> cells/well) were cultured in 60 cm culture dish,
and treated with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), together with vehicle or
optimal dose of candesartan for 24 h. The supernatant was collected for
detecting the protein level of pro-inflammatory (TNF-α, IL-12p70, and IL-6) and
anti-inflammatory (TGF-β and IL-10) according to the instructions of ELISA kits
(Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute).</p></sec><sec id="section7-2058738420974900"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>BV2 microglial cells (1.5 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well) were seeded in a 24-well
plate containing the coverslip. The cells were treated with LPS (100 ng/mL) +
IFN-γ (20 ng/mL) followed by vehicle or selected dose of candesartan. After 24
h, cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde followed by blocking with 5% donkey
serum. The cells were incubated with primary antibodies, rabbit anti-iNOS (1:100
dilution, Abcam) or rabbit anti-CD206 (1:200 dilution, Abcam) at 4°C overnight.
Cells were washed with PBS, followed by incubation with the secondary antibody
for 2 h at room temperature, Alexa Fluor 488 donkey anti-rabbit IgG (1:400
dilution, Invitrogen). After being washed, the nucleus was stained with DAPI.
All samples were observed with a laser confocal microscope (Nikon).</p></sec><sec id="section8-2058738420974900"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA in BV2 cells was extracted using RNA prep Pure cell kit (TIANGEN)
according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The cDNA was prepared by using
Quantscript RT Kit (TIANGEN). Quantitative PCR was performed on quantitative PCR
systems (Applied Biosystems 7500 Real-Time PCR Systems, Thermo Fisher
Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) using the synthetic primers and the SuperReal
PreMix Plus (SYBR Green) kit (TIANGEN). Gene specific primers used for cDNA
amplification were as listed in <xref rid="table1-2058738420974900" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The data were analyzed by the
2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> method.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></p><table-wrap id="table1-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Gene specific primers used for cDNA amplification.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primers(5′-3′)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">CD11b</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAAGACGATCTCAGCATCA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTCTGGCTTGCTGAATCCTT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">iNOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAAGCACCTTGGAAGAGGAG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAGGCCAAACACAGCATACC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">YM1/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGGGTAATGAGTGGGTTGG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACGGCACCTCCTAAATTGT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">CCL22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGATGCAGGTCCCTATGGT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAGGATTTTGAGGTCCAGA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">IL-6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGGATACCCCCAACAGACC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAGTGCATCATCGTTGTTCATACA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">TNF-α</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATCTCAAAGACAACCAACTAGTG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCCAGCTGGAAGACTCCTCCCAG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">IL-10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAAGCCTTATCGGAAATGA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTTCACAGGGGAGAAATCG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">GAPDH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGGTCGGTGTGAACGGATTTG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGGTCGTTGATGGCAACA</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section9-2058738420974900"><title>Western blot</title><p>Proteins extracted from BV2 cells by RIPA buffer containing the protease and
phosphatase inhibitors (Roche) were used for western blotting. In brief, protein
samples (30 µg/lane) were separated on 12% SDS-PAGE and transferred to PVDF
membrane (Millipore). Membranes were blocked with fat-free milk (5%) in TBST for
2 h at room temperature. Membranes were then respectively incubated with the
primary antibodies overnight at 4°C, including iNOS (1:500, Abcam), CD206
(1:1000, Abcam), TLR4 (1:500, Abcam), NF-κB p65 (1:2000, Abcam), phospho-NF-κB
p65 (p-p65, 1:2000, Abcam), IKBα (1:1000, Abcam), phospho-IKBα (p- IKBα, 1:2000,
Abcam), GAPDH (1:2000, Abcam), LaminB1 (1:2000, Abcam). After washing 3 times
with TBST, membranes were respectively incubated with HRP-conjugated secondary
antibodies (1:4000) for 2 h at room temperature. GAPDH and LaminB1 were used as
the internal control. Membranes were detected by the ECL chemiluminescence
detection system (Millipore). The band intensity was measured using Image J.</p></sec><sec id="section10-2058738420974900"><title>Neuron-microglia co-culture</title><p>BV2 microglia and N2a cells were co-cultured in transwell-24 system (Corning) as
our previous study.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The cell density ratio is 1:10 (BV2 microglia: N2a cells). BV2 cells were
seeded on removable culture inserts, and then treated with LPS (100 ng/mL) +
IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), together with vehicle or selected dose of candesartan for 24
h. Remove the medium and wash microglia with fresh medium for 3 times. N2a cells
growing in 24-well plate were subjected to oxygen glucose deprivation (OGD) for
3 h. Microglia-neuron co-cultures were executed by placing microglia inserts on
the top of no-OGD or post-OGD N2a cells. After 24 h co-culture, microglia
inserts were removed. Neuronal survival was measured by MTT assay (Roche).
Neuronal cytotoxicity was detected by LDH assay (Beyotime). MTT and LDH assay
were carried out according to the manufacturer’s protocol.</p></sec><sec id="section11-2058738420974900"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The results are expressed as the means ± SEM. Statistical significance among
multiple experimental groups was determined by one-way ANOVA of variance with
prism software version 5.0 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA).
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically
significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section12-2058738420974900"><title>Results</title><sec id="section13-2058738420974900"><title>Effects of candesartan on cellular viability and cytotoxicity in BV2
cells</title><p>To assess the effects of candesartan on cellular viability and LDH release in BV2
cells, the cells were cultured with vehicle or different concentration of
candesartan (0.5, 1, 5, 10, 20, 30, 40, and 50 µM) for 24 h. Compared to vehicle
group, the cell viability was markedly reduced by 20, 30, 40, and 50 µM
candesartan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974900">Figure 1a</xref>).
However, 0.5, 1, 5, and 10 µM candesartan did not significantly affect the cell
viability. In LDH assay, no cytotoxic effects were observed following culture of
BV2 with 0.5, 1 µM candesartan for 24 h. But candesartan (5, 10, 20, 30, 40, and
50 µM) resulted in the significant release of LDH in BV2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974900">Figure 1b</xref>). According to
two experimental results, the 1 µM concentration was selected for further
experiments. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974900">Figure
1c</xref>, BV2 microglia were subjected to LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20
ng/mL), or IL-4 (20 ng/mL), and then treated with vehicle or candesartan (1 µM)
for 24 h. Compared with the vehicle, LPS + IFN-γ induced microglia polarization
toward M1 phenotype, which showed cell swelling, irregular boundary, and less
cell number. But candesartan treatment improved morphology and numbers,
including smaller cell body and more clear boundaries. IL-4-treated microglia,
M2 phenotype, represented as the similar morphology and cell number with the
vehicle group.</p><fig id="fig1-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Effects of candesartan on cell viability and LDH release of BV2
microglial cells. BV2 cells were treated with vehicle or candesartan
(0.5, 1, 5, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50 μM) for 24 h. (a) The cell viability was
revealed by CCK-8 assay. (b) The cytotoxicity of candesartan on BV2
cells was detected by LDH assay. (c) Images of BV2 cells were taken
after treatment with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), or IL-4
(20 ng/mL), together with vehicle, candesartan (1 μM) for 24 h.</p><p>Scale bars represent 50 μm (lower). Data is expressed as mean ± SEM.
Samples were collected from three independent experiments, each
performed in duplicate.</p><p>***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni
post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section14-2058738420974900"><title>Candesartan treatment inhibits the mRNA level of M1 markers and enhances M2
markers</title><p>To determine the effect of candesartan on microglia polarization, we measured the
mRNA expression of microglia phenotype markers in BV2 cells using RT-PCR at 24 h
after LPS + IFN-γ stimulation. The mRNA expression of M1 markers (CD11b and
iNOS) were markedly increased under the stimulation of LPS + IFN-γ, but
significantly reduced after treatment with candesartan (1 μM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974900">Figure 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974900">b</xref>). However, the mRNA
expression of M2 marker YM1/2 was obviously reduced by LPS + IFN-γ. The
candesartan treatment reversed the reduction in the mRNA level of YM1/2 and
CCL22 in LPS + IFN-γ induced BV2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974900">Figure 2c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974900">d</xref>). The results reveal that candesartan
modulates microglia polarization toward M2 phenotype.</p><fig id="fig2-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Candesartan suppresses the mRNA expression of M1 markers and promotes M2
markers in LPS + IFN-γ stimulated BV2 microglia cells. BV2 cells were
stimulated with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), and then treated
with vehicle or candesartan (1 μM) for 24 h. The mRNA expression for M1
markers CD11b (a) and iNOS (b), and M2 markers YM1/2 (c) and CCL22 (d)
were examined by RT-PCR.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>**<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way
ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-2058738420974900"><title>Candesartan treatment inhibits the protein level of M1 marker and enhances M2
marker</title><p>To further investigate the effect of candesartan on microglia polarization, we
measured the protein expression of microglia phenotypic markers in LPS + IFN-γ
stimulated BV2 cells using immunofluorescence staining and western blot at 24 h.
As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738420974900">Figure 3</xref>,
LPS + IFN-γ markedly increased the fluorescence intensity of iNOS (M1 marker),
and significantly decreased CD206 (M2 marker). However, candesartan treatment
greatly inhibited the fluorescence intensity of iNOS while significantly
enhanced CD206 in LPS + IFN-γ treated BV2 cells.</p><fig id="fig3-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Candesartan treatment reduces fluorescence intensity of M1 marker and
enhances M2 marker in BV2 microglia cells. BV2 cells were stimulated
with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), and then treated with vehicle
or candesartan (1 μM) for 24 h. Representative fluorescence images show
M1 marker iNOS (green, a) and M2 marker CD206 (green, c) staining. The
nuclei were stained with DAPI (blue) solution. Scale bars = 20 μm.
Quantification of the fluorescence intensity of iNOS (b) and CD206 (d)
in BV2 cells.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way
ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig3.jpg"/></fig><p>Western blot results showed that the protein level of iNOS was significantly
higher, and CD206 was greatly lower in LPS + IFN-γ treated BV2 cells compared to
the vehicle group. But candesartan treatment remarkably inhibited the protein
level of iNOS and enhanced CD206 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738420974900">Figure 4</xref>). Here, these results
demonstrate that candesartan promotes M2 polarization and inhibits M1
polarization, indicating that candesartan shifts microglia from M1 to M2
phenotype.</p><fig id="fig4-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Candesartan treatment decreases the protein expression of M1 marker and
increases M2 marker in BV2 cells. BV2 microglia cells were stimulated
with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL), and then treated with vehicle
or candesartan (1 μM) for 24 h. Representative Western blot (a) and
quantitative analysis of M1 marker iNOS (b) and M2 marker CD206 (c).
GAPDH was used as a loading control.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way
ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section16-2058738420974900"><title>Candesartan alleviates the pro-inflammatory responses in LPS + IFN-γ
stimulated BV2 cells</title><p>To further determine the effects of candesartan on inflammatory responses, the
level of inflammatory factor was detected by RT-PCR and ELISA. RT-PCR results
showed that LPS + IFN-γ treatment significantly up-regulated the mRNA level of
pro-inflammatory cytokine (IL-6, TNF-α) in BV2 cells compared to the vehicle
group. Candesartan significantly reduced the mRNA expression of IL-6 and TNF-α),
and increased anti-inflammatory factor IL-10 in LPS + IFN-γ stimulated BV2 cells
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974900">Figure 5a–c</xref>). Next,
the release of inflammatory cytokines in culture supernatant after inflammatory
stimulation was measured by ELISA. LPS + IFN-γ significantly enhanced the
release of pro-inflammatory (IL-6, TNF-α, IL-12p70) and suppressed
anti-inflammatory (IL-10). Candesartan markedly inhibited the release of
pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-6, TNF-α, IL-12p70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974900">Figure 5d–f</xref>), and promoted
anti-inflammatory factors (TGF-β, IL-10) in LPS + IFN-γ induced BV2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974900">Figure 5g</xref> and h). In
addition, LPS + IFN-γ markedly up-regulated the level of NO in culture
supernatant compared to the vehicle group. But candesartan obviously
down-regulated the NO level in LPS+IFN-γ treated BV2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974900">Figure 5i</xref>). Taken together, the data show
that candesartan inhibits pro-inflammatory responses after inflammatory
stimulation.</p><fig id="fig5-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Candesartan inhibits pro-inflammatory cytokines and enhances
anti-inflammatory cytokines in LPS + IFN-γ activated BV2 microglial
cells. BV2 cells were cultured with LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL),
together with vehicle or candesartan (1 μM) for 24 h. (a–c) The mRNA
expressions for pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-6 and TNF-α) and
anti-inflammatory cytokine (IL-10) were examined by RT-PCR. (d–h) The
concentration of pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-6, TNF-α, and IL-12p70)
and anti-inflammatory cytokines (TGF-β and IL-10) were examined by ELISA
assay. (i) NO assay.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01,
***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way ANOVA followed by
Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section17-2058738420974900"><title>Candesartan regulates microglia polarization toward M2 phenotype through
TLR4/NF-кB pathway</title><p>TLR4/NF-кB pathway participates in regulation of microglia phenotype polarization.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In order to reveal the underlying mechanism of candesartan on modulation
of microglia polarization, we examined the protein level of TLR4, p-IKBα, IKBα,
p-p65, p65 in BV2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">Figure
6a</xref>). LPS + IFN-γ increased the protein level of TLR4, the ratio of
p-IKBα/IKBα and p-p65/p65 compared to vehicle, whereas candesartan dramatically
reduced the expression of TLR4, the ratio of p-IKBα/IKBα and p-p65/p65 (Figure
6b–d) in LPS + IFN-γ stimulated BV2 cells. To further clarify the underlying
role of NF-кB pathway, BAY 11-7085 was used to inhibit activation of NF-кB. We
found that the decrease of p-IKBα/IKBα and p-p65/p65 ratio were further
aggravated when BAY 11-7085 was added to LPS + IFN-γ stimulated BV2 cells in the
presence of candesartan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">Figure
6c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">d</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Candesartan shifts microglia polarization via the inhibition of
TLR4/NF-κB signaling pathway. BV2 was treated for 30 min with an NF-κB
inhibitor (BAY 11-7085, 1 μg/mL), followed by stimulation with LPS
(100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL) in the presence of vehicle or candesartan
(1 μM) for 24 h. Representative western blot (a) and quantification
analysis of TLR4 (b), p-IKBα/IKBα (c), and p-p65/p65 (d). (e–g) The
protein expressions of p65 in nuclear and cytoplasm were measured by
western blot, respectively.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01,
***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way ANOVA followed by
Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig6.jpg"/></fig><p>To determine the effect of candesartan on nuclear translocation of NF-κB, we
examined the protein level of p65 in nuclear and cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">Figure 6e</xref>). LPS + IFN-γ decreased p65
protein level in cytoplasm, but increased in nucleus. Candesartan markedly
reversed the nuclear translocation of p65 through increasing the protein level
of p65 in cytoplasm and decreasing p65 in nucleus after LPS + IFN-γ stimulation.
What’s more, the nuclear translocation of p65 was obviously decreased when BAY
11-7085 was added to LPS + IFN-γ-stimulated BV2 cells in the presence of
candesartan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">Figure 6f</xref>
and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-2058738420974900">g</xref>). These results
indicate that candesartan shifts microglia phenotype polarization at least
partially in dependent on TLR4/NF-кB pathway.</p></sec><sec id="section18-2058738420974900"><title>Candesartan reduces the neurotoxic effect of M1 microglia on post-OGD
neurons</title><p>We have demonstrated that candesartan promoted microgli toward M2 polarization
and enhanced the expression of anti-inflammatory cytokine in BV2 cells at 24 h
after LPS + IFN-γ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974900">Figures
2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738420974900"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738420974900"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974900">5</xref>). To further confirm whether
candesartan may protect against neuronal death through the regulation of
microglial polarization, the neuron-microglia co-culture system was performed as
we showed previously.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> LPS + IFN-γ could stimulate microglia toward M1 polarization. When M1
microglia co-cultured with post-OGD neurons, they significantly exacerbated
neuronal death and enhanced LDH release. However, candesartan increased neuronal
viability and inhibited LDH release in neuron-microglia co-culture system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-2058738420974900">Figure 7</xref>). These findings
suggest that candesartan inhibits the neurotoxic effect of M1 microglia to OGD
neurons via suppressing M1 but enhancing M2 microglial polarization.</p><fig id="fig7-2058738420974900" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Candesartan reduces the neurotoxic effect of M1 microglia in co-cultured
neurons. BV2 cells in transwell were exposed to regular microglia media
(resting phenotype), or LPS (100 ng/mL) + IFN-γ (20 ng/mL) (M1
phenotype) for 24 h in the absence or presence of candesartan (1 μM).
Neuronal N2a cells were subjected to OGD for 3 h. BV2 cells in transwell
was applied over the non-OGD or post-OGD N2a cultures for 24 h. (a) N2a
viability was quantified by MTT assay. (b) Cytotoxicity was quantified
by LDH release.</p><p>Data is expressed as mean ± SEM. Samples were collected from three
independent experiments, each performed in duplicate.</p><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01,
***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, one-way ANOVA followed by
Bonferroni post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-fig7.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section19-2058738420974900"><title>Discussion</title><p>Candesartan (C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>20</sub>N<sub>6</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) is an oral
angiotensin II receptor type I receptors antagonist, which may act against
vasoconstriction and reduce peripheral vascular resistance.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Angiotensin II also binds to AT2R, which is thought to be activated by
candesartan as it blocks the actions of AT1R.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> The therapeutic potential of candesartan has been reported in some diseases,
such as hypertension,<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> renal damage,<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Alzheimer disease.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> More emerging evidence revealed that candesartan could effectively inhibit
glial activation,<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> reduce inflammatory response,<sup><xref rid="bibr28-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> and block NF-κB activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> However, in the present study, we showed that candesartan inhibited
inflammatory response and induced the shift of microglia from pro-inflammatory M1 to
anti-inflammatory M2 phenotype, which may be associated with TLR4-mediated NF-κB
pathway.</p><p>Microglia are the brain-resident macrophages in the central nervous system (CNS),
which are the target of inflammatory mediators in the CNS injuries and play a
foremost role in the neuroinflammatory response.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> In different environmental stimuli, microglia/macrophage could differentiate
into M1 or M2 phenotype. M1-polarized microglia release high level of
pro-inflammatory cytokines and upregulate the expression of M1 markers. However,
M2-polarized microglia enhance the level of anti-inflammatory factors and
up-regulate M2 markers.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> According to the plasticity of microglia/macrophages, the balance of between
M1 and M2 microglia polarization is a key player in neuroinflammatory response in
CNS injuries.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Candesartan not only blocks the activation of AT1R, but also promotes
angiotensin II-mediated AT2R stimulation.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Telmisartan, an antagonist blocking AT1R, was shown to prevent the
LPS-induced microglia activation by promoting M2 polarization via
CaMKKbeta-dependent AMPK activation.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> In this study, our results showed that candesartan can shift microglia
polarization from M1 to M2 phenotype. AT1R blockade by candesartan inhibits glial
activation and neuroinflammation response induced by LPS.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Consistent with the previous report, candesartan inhibited the release of
pro-inflammatory cytokine (IL-6, TNF-α, and IL-12p70), promoted the level of
anti-inflammatory cytokine (IL-10, TGF-β) in LPS + IFN-γ induced BV2 cells. The data
suggest that candesartan treatment inhibits inflammation response via regulating the
balance of M1/M2 microglia polarization.</p><p>Our studies demonstrated that candesartan regulated microglia polarization, which was
accompanied by the regulation of inflammatory response. But the mechanisms whereby
candesartan promotes microglial polarization to M2 subtype are not yet clear.
Several transcriptional regulators have been identified to participate in regulating
microglia polarization toward M1 phenotype such as activator protein-1 family
(AP-1), NF-κB family, STAT1.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> TLR4/NF-κB signaling pathway is one of the most widely recognized
intracellular signaling pathways in inflammatory responses, which is demonstrated to
participate in shifting microglial polarization toward M1.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Curcumin was reported to alleviate neuroinflammation responses through
promoting microglia phenotype shift toward M2, which may be associated with the
suppression of the TLR4-mediated NF-κB signaling pathway.<sup><xref rid="bibr32-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> Pinocembrin reduced hemorrhagic brain injury and suppressed M1 phenotype
microglia through inhibiting TLR4.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> In agreement with the above observation, candesartan markedly inhibited the
protein expression of TLR4 and the phosphorylation of IKBα and p65 in LPS + IFN-γ
treated BV-2 cells. Besides, candesartan markedly reversed the nuclear translocation
of p65 in LPS + IFN-γ stimulated BV2 cells. The inhibitory effect of candesartan on
NF-кB pathway was further aggravated by the NF-кB inhibitor, BAY 11-7085. These
results further illustrate that candesartan regulates microglia polarization at
least partially through TLR4-mediated NF-κB pathways. Meisoindigo protected against
focal cerebral ischemia-reperfusion injury by regulating microglia/macrophage
polarization via NF-κB signaling pathway.<sup><xref rid="bibr34-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Candesartan was reported to reduce infarct volume and improve behavior after
stroke via reducing of the TLR signaling cascade.<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2058738420974900" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> In our co-culture system, candesartan ameliorated the neurotoxic effect of M1
microglia to OGD neurons via regulating microglia polarization toward M2 phenotype.
The data indicate that candesartan may alleviate stoke-induced neuronal damage
through suppressing inflammatory response and modulating microglia polarization
through inhibiting TLR4/NF-κB signaling pathway. However, both the in vivo and
primary cell experiments are still required to confirm the underlying mechanism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section20-2058738420974900"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This present study demonstrates that candesartan inhibited LPS + IFN-γ induced
pro-inflammatory response and increased anti-inflammatory response. Candesartan has
a significant regulatory effect on the balance of microglia polarization, shifting
microglia to M2 phenotype and inhibiting the polarization of M1 microglia phenotype.
The inhibitory effects of candesartan on the neurotoxic effect of M1 microglia to
OGD neurons may be associated with modulating inflammatory response and microglia
polarization in a TLR4-mediated NF-κB dependent manner. Our findings suggest that
candesartan can indirectly reduce neuronal damage via modulating microglial
polarization, providing new evidence that candesartan might be a promising
therapeutic strategy for stoke.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This study was funded
by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81671161) to Z Liu.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Zongjian Liu <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974900-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4685-1057">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4685-1057</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2058738420974900"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holtman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional control of
microglia phenotypes in health and disease</article-title>. <source>The
Journal of Clinical Investigation</source>
<volume>127</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):
<fpage>3220</fpage>–<lpage>3229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28758903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI90604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5669536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2058738420974900"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>)
<article-title>Microglial and macrophage polarization—new prospects for
brain repair</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews. Neurology</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25385337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrneurol.2014.207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4395497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2058738420974900"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keren-Shaul</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spinrad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>A unique
microglia type associated with restricting development of Alzheimer’s
disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>169</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>1276</fpage>–<lpage>1290</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28602351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2017.05.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2058738420974900"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>AKF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>)
<article-title>Neurobiology of microglial action in CNS injuries:
Receptor-mediated signaling mechanisms and functional roles</article-title>.
<source>Progress in Neurobiology</source> 119–120:
<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24923657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2014.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4121732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2058738420974900"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prinz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>How microbiota shape
microglial phenotypes and epigenetics</article-title>. <source>Glia</source>
<volume>68</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):
<fpage>1655</fpage>–<lpage>1672</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32181523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/glia.23822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2058738420974900"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staszewski</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Microglia heterogeneity in the single-cell
era</article-title>. <source>Cell Reports</source>
<volume>30</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>1281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32023447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.01.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2058738420974900"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orihuela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harry</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Microglial M1/M2 polarization
and metabolic states</article-title>. <source>British Journal of
Pharmacology</source>
<volume>173</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25800044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/bph.13139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4742299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2058738420974900"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Federoff</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Targeting microglial
activation states as a therapeutic avenue in Parkinson’s
disease</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28642697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnagi.2017.00176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5463358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-2058738420974900"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Acute
hypoxia induced an imbalanced M1/M2 activation of microglia through NF-κB
signaling in Alzheimer’s disease mice and wild-type
littermates</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Aging
Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28890695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnagi.2017.00282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5574879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-2058738420974900"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bregonzio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armando</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Oral
administration of an AT1 receptor antagonist prevents the central effects of
angiotensin II in spontaneously hypertensive rats</article-title>.
<source>Brain Research</source>
<volume>1028</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15518636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.06.079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-2058738420974900"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohshima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Therapeutic approach for
neuronal disease by regulating renin-angiotensin system</article-title>.
<source>Current Hypertension Reviews</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23971691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/15734021113099990004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-2058738420974900"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villapol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotective effects of
angiotensin receptor blockers</article-title>. <source>American Journal of
Hypertension</source>
<volume>28</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25362113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajh/hpu197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-2058738420974900"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gohlke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jürgensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Kügelgen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>)
<article-title>Candesartan cilexetil: development and preclinical
studies</article-title>. <source>Drugs of Today</source>
<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12973413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1358/dot.1999.35.2.527966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-2058738420974900"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claggett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Heart
failure with mid-range ejection fraction in CHARM: characteristics, outcomes
and effect of candesartan across the entire ejection fraction
spectrum</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Heart Failure</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):
<fpage>1230</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29431256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ejhf.1149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-2058738420974900"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosomi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelisch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>)
<article-title>Therapeutic effects of postischemic treatment with
hypotensive doses of an angiotensin II receptor blocker on transient focal
cerebral ischemia</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hypertension</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):
<fpage>2210</fpage>–<lpage>2219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21934531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/HJH.0b013e32834bbb30</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-2058738420974900"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saijo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Microglial cell origin and
phenotypes in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews.
Immunology</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):
<fpage>775</fpage>–<lpage>787</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nri3086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-2058738420974900"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benicky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Lemus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>)
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of angiotensin receptor blockers in
the brain and the periphery</article-title>. <source>Cellular and Molecular
Neurobiology</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6–7</issue>):
<fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19259805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10571-009-9368-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2718067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-2058738420974900"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>)
<article-title>Candesartan inhibits LPS-induced expression increase of
toll-like receptor 4 and downstream inflammatory factors likely via
angiotensin II type 1 receptor independent pathway in human renal tubular
epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Sheng Li Xue Bao : [Acta
physiologica Sinica]</source>
<volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24343720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-2058738420974900"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Curcumin
protects against ischemic stroke by titrating microglia/macrophage
polarization</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Aging
Neuroscience</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28785217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnagi.2017.00233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5519528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-2058738420974900"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>HDAC
inhibition prevents white matter injury by modulating microglia/macrophage
polarization through the GSK3β/PTEN/Akt axis</article-title>.
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States
of America</source>
<volume>112</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):
<fpage>2853</fpage>–<lpage>2858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25691750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1501441112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4352818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-2058738420974900"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>)
<article-title>Comparison of the long‑term effects of candesartan and
olmesartan on plasma angiotensin II and left ventricular mass index in
patients with hypertension</article-title>. <source>Hypertension Research:
Official Journal of the Japanese Society of Hypertension</source>
<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19927151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/hr.2009.192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-2058738420974900"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qie</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Melatonin protects against ischemic stroke by modulating
microglia/macrophage polarization toward anti-inflammatory phenotype through
STAT3 pathway</article-title>. <source>CNS Neuroscience &amp;
Therapeutics</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):
<fpage>1353</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31793209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/cns.13261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6887673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-2058738420974900"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessaguet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danigo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>)
<article-title>Candesartan prevents resiniferatoxin-induced sensory
small-fiber neuropathy in mice by promoting angiotensin ii-mediated AT2
receptor stimulation</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2017.08.039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-2058738420974900"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Candesartan targeting of
angiotensin II type 1 receptor demonstrates benefits for hypertension in
pregnancy via the NF-κB signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Molecular
Medicine Reports</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29845261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2018.9070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6059699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-2058738420974900"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Candesartan and
epigallocatechin-3-gallate ameliorate gentamicin-induced renal damage in
rats through p38-MAPK and NF-κB pathways</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Biochemical and Molecular Toxicology</source>
<volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>e22254</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jbt.22254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-2058738420974900"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trigiani</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Royea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacalle-Aurioles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>Pleiotropic benefits of the angiotensin receptor blocker
candesartan in a mouse model of Alzheimer disease</article-title>.
<source>Hypertension</source>
<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30354809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.118.11775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-2058738420974900"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>Angiotensin receptor blockade modulates NFκB and STAT3
signaling and inhibits glial activation and neuroinflammation better than
angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibition</article-title>. <source>Molecular
Neurobiology</source>
<volume>53</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):
<fpage>6950</fpage>–<lpage>6967</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26666666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12035-015-9584-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-2058738420974900"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larrayoz</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benicky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>)
<article-title>Candesartan reduces the innate immune response to
lipopolysaccharide in human monocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Hypertension</source>
<volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):
<fpage>2365</fpage>–<lpage>2376</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19730394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/HJH.0b013e3283314bc7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2928995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-2058738420974900"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skaper</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Facci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Microglia and mast cells: Two
tracks on the road to neuroinflammation</article-title>. <source>FASEB
Journal: Official Publication of the Federation of American Societies for
Experimental Biology</source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):
<fpage>3103</fpage>–<lpage>3117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22516295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1096/fj.11-197194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-2058738420974900"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Macrophage plasticity and
polarization: in vivo veritas</article-title>. <source>The Journal of
Clinical Investigation</source>
<volume>122</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>795</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22378047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI59643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3287223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-2058738420974900"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>)
<article-title>Telmisartan prevention of LPS-induced microglia activation
involves M2 microglia polarization via CaMKKβ-dependent AMPK
activation</article-title>. <source>Brain, Behavior, and Immunity</source>
<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2015.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26188187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-2058738420974900"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Curcumin
mitigates neuro-inflammation by modulating microglia polarization through
inhibiting TLR4 axis signaling pathway following experimental subarachnoid
hemorrhage</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Neuroscience</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <year>1223</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnins.2019.01223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6872970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31803007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-2058738420974900"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>)
<article-title>Pinocembrin protects hemorrhagic brain primarily by
inhibiting toll-like receptor 4 and reducing M1 phenotype
microglia</article-title>. <source>Brain, Behavior, and Immunity</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.12.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5453178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28007523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-2058738420974900"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Meisoindigo protects against focal cerebral
ischemia-reperfusion injury by inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome activation and
regulating microglia/macrophage polarization via TLR4/NF-κB signaling
pathway</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Cellular Neuroscience</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31920554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fncel.2019.00553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6930809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-2058738420974900"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Safwet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Maraghy</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Candesartan and glycyrrhizin ameliorate ischemic brain damage
through downregulation of the TLR signaling cascade</article-title>.
<source>European Journal of Pharmacology</source>
<volume>724</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejphar.2013.12.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24378346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>