
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7693198</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7693198.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7693198</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7693198</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33205807</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20203092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BSR20203092</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology &amp; Inflammation</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Bases of Health &amp; Disease</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Translational Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Aging</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Metabolism</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="toc-heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Investigation of CD26, a potential SARS-CoV-2 receptor, as a biomarker of age and pathology</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha</surname><given-names initials="A">Animesh Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names initials="S">Subhojit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names initials="J">James</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaetova-Ladinska</surname><given-names initials="E">Elizabeta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names initials="S">Shahid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trowsdale</surname><given-names initials="J">John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6660-1659</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha-Chowdhury</surname><given-names initials="R">Ruma</given-names></name><email>rr224@cam.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label>John van Geest Centre for Brain Repair, Department of Clinical Neuroscience, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, U.K.</aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label>CamKolInv, Cambridge Kolkata Innovation and Therapeutic Limited, Cambridge, U.K.</aff><aff id="AFF3"><label>3</label>Department of Neuroscience, Psychology and Behaviour, University of Leicester, Leicester, U.K.</aff><aff id="AFF4"><label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry, Cambridge Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities Research Group, Cambridge, U.K.</aff><aff id="AFF5"><label>5</label>Division of Immunology, Department of Pathology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, U.K.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Ruma Raha-Chowdhury (<email>rr224@cam.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-11-26"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">369643</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20203092</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted-manuscript"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-10 12:25:15.173"><day>10</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the . Open access for this article was enabled by the participation of University of Cambridge in an all-inclusive <italic toggle="yes">Read &amp; Publish</italic> pilot with Portland Press and the Biochemical Society under a transformative agreement with JISC.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20203092.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20203092.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Objective:</bold> In some individuals, coronavirus severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection leads to a variety of serious inflammatory symptoms, including blood clotting and acute respiratory distress. Death due to COVID-19 shows a steep rise in relation to age. Comorbidities such as type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), hypertension, and cardiovascular disease also increase susceptibility. It has been reported that T-cell regulatory dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4; cluster of differentiation 26 (CD26)) binds to the external spike (S) glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2 as a receptor, for the viral entry into the host cell. CD26 is expressed on many cells, including T and natural killer (NK) cells of the immune system, as a membrane-anchored form. A soluble form (sCD26) is also found in the blood plasma and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF).</p><p><bold>Approach and results:</bold> To investigate a possible relationship between sCD26 levels, age and pathology, serum samples were collected from control, T2DM and age-related dementia (ARD) subjects. A significant reduction in serum sCD26 levels was seen in relation to age. ARD and T2DM were also associated with lower levels of sCD26. The analysis of blood smears revealed different cellular morphologies: in controls, CD26 was expressed around the neutrophil membrane, whereas in T2DM, excessive sCD26 was found around the mononucleated cells (MNCs). ARD subjects had abnormal fragmented platelets and haemolysis due to low levels of sCD26.</p><p><bold>Conclusions:</bold> These findings may help to explain the heterogeneity of SARS-CoV-2 infection. High serum sCD26 levels could protect from viral infection by competively inhibiting the virus binding to cellular CD26, whereas low sCD26 levels could increase the risk of infection. If so measuring serum sCD26 level may help to identify individuals at high risk for the COVID-19 infection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>age-related dementia</kwd><kwd>Corona virus COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Covid-19 biomarker</kwd><kwd>dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4)</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2 infection</kwd><kwd>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>A novel coronavirus, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus2 (SARS-CoV-2) is the cause of the latest pandemic, characterised with severe acute respiratory syndrome (ARS) and high mortality due to both a direct cytotoxic viral effect and a severe systemic inflammation [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1–3</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 is a member of the Coronaviridae family, β-coronavirus genus of the B lineage, and is closely related to the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV), Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), and several bat coronaviruses (CoVs) [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. COVID-19 disease, caused by SARS-CoV-2, has a considerably worse prognosis in older and obese people, some ethnic populations and with comorbidities such as diabetes mellitus, hypertension, cardiovascular disease and chronic lung disease [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6–9</xref>].</p><p>All coronaviruses (CoVs) utilise a portion of the spike protein called the receptor-binding domain (RBD) to recognise and attach to the surface of human cells, allowing the viral particle to gain entry through the plasma membrane [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 uses angiotensin-converting enzyme-2 (ACE2), the same receptor as SARS-CoV, to infect humans [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, there is recent evidence that the outer membrane spike glycoprotein S1 of SARSviruses binds to dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4)/cluster of differentiation 26 (CD26) when entering into the cells of the respiratory tract [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Differential expression of ACE2 and DPP4/CD26 as receptors of spike glycoproteins may help to explain the heterogeneity of clinical features in people infected with different CoVs [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For cell entry, SARS-CoV-2 S protein also requires a protease, such as Furin, Trypsin, human airway trypsin-like protease, cathepsin-L or the transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2) [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16–19</xref>]. ACE2 or CD26 may be activated by proteolytic cleavage by TMPRSS2 or cathepsin-L in late endosomes in a pH-dependent manner but the virus can also be activated by trypsin-like proteases at the cell surface in a pH-independent manner [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>DPP4, also known as CD26, is a serine exopeptidase, a multifunctional type-II transmembrane glycoprotein that presents in a dimeric form on the cell surface. CD26 is multifunctional, highly conserved among mammals and plays a major role in glucose metabolism [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It preferentially cleaves dipeptides from hormones and chemokines after a proline amino acid residue, thereby regulating their bioactivity [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. CD26, being a proteolytic enzyme that is expressed in most cell types (particularly in the immune cells, T cells and natural killer (NK) cells), exists in both membrane-anchored (mCD26) and soluble form (sCD26) [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. sCD26 is thought to be shed from the membrane into plasma, and still maintains its enzymatic activity. sCD26 is also found in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), exerting its multifunctional effects through various signalling pathways that induce and regulate inflammatory and immunological processes [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In humans, mCD26 is primarily expressed on lung epithelial cells, endothelial membranes of the pancreas, small intestine, liver, kidney, prostate, placenta and on activated leucocytes [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Variations in sCD26 levels in serum have been reported as clinically relevant in several pathophysiological conditions including in type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and virus infections [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. sCD26 has the capacity to degrade incretins, GLP-1 and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) (both involved in stimulating insulin secretion in a glucose-dependent manner), as well as the brain natriuretic peptide (BNP), and the chemokine stromal-derived factor-1α (SDF-1α), involved in cardiovascular function [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p>The emergent global spread of SARS‐CoV‐2 and its grave impact on public health demands an immediate, coordinated effort in biomedical research to increase understanding of the pathogenesis of the virus and its entry into host cells. The high fatality rate imposes an urgent need for rapid identification of effective treatments including novel therapeutics, antivirals and vaccines. We screened mCD26 and sCD26 expression to investigate its role in innate immunity and inflammation [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. To achieve this, we included samples from T2DM [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and age-related dementia (ARD) subjects who are considered at high risk for COVID-19 and share some pathological features [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Via analysis of CD26 involvement in various clinical and pathological conditions that are also characteristic of COVID-19, we provide circumstantial evidence for sCD26 implication in viral infections, such as SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Ethics and participants</title><p>Ethics and Research and Development (R&amp;D) approvals were granted by the National Research Ethics Committee of the East of England. Cambridge Health Authorities Joint Ethics Committee granted ethical approval for use of human brain tissue and serum samples (project reference number: REC:15/WM/0379). Written consents were obtained from controls, adults with diabetes participants and subjects with ARD with the capacity to consent. Verbal assent was obtained from participants with ARD lacking capacity to provide written assent, and this was provided instead by an appointed consultee, in accordance with the Mental Capacity Act of the U.K. (2005). Information on older controls (OCs; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50) and ARDs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50) has already been disclosed in a previous publication [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Paraffin-embedded sections of human brain</title><p>Human brain sections of young and aged postmortem CNS-diseased, were provided by the Cambridge Brain Bank under the project reference number REC:15/WM/0379.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Blood and serum/plasma collection</title><p>Whole blood, serum and plasma samples from human younger controls (YCs: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, aged between 30 and 55 years), and OCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, aged between 56 and 85 years), middle-aged type II diabetes (T2DM, non-demented, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, aged between 30 and 55 years) (please note that none of the control subjects had a clinical diagnosis of dementia) and ARD (OD, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, aged between 56 and 85 years) were collected for DNA and protein analyses. All blood samples were collected for serum in BD vacutainer SST advance tubes (containing inert gel barrier and clot activator coating). Serum and plasma were separated immediately by centrifugation at 2465×<bold><underline><italic toggle="yes">g</italic></underline></bold> for 6 min at 4°C, aliquoted and stored at −80°C until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Blood slide preparation</title><p>A drop of blood placed on a slide was spread as described previously [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The slide was air-dried and fixed in 100% methanol and stored at 4°C. Further investigations, including immunohistochemistry (IHC), were performed on stored fixed slides as described later.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Animals</title><p>Three months old C57/Bl6 mice were purchased from Charles River and bred for the experiments at University of Cambridge Bioscience Facility (UBSS, at John van Geest Centre for Brain Repair Animal Facility). All experiments were performed according to the ‘Animal (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986’ and the ‘Guidance of the Operation of ASPA 2014’, and were approved by the Ethical Committee of the U.K. Home Office (PPL number 70/7920).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Mice tissue preparation</title><p>All animals were housed under standard conditions (12-h light–dark cycle, 20°C ambient temperature) with free access to food and water. Animals undergoing perfusion were anaesthetised with raising concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> followed by terminal injection of Euthatal (0.3 ml per 100 g of body weight). Collection of fresh tissues was performed after raising the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> followed by cervical dislocation. For histochemical analyses, animals were anaesthetised with pento-barbitone and flash-perfused transcardially with 0.9% saline followed with 4% (v/v) paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 0.1 M phosphate buffer saline (PBS; pH 7.4). Brains were removed, post-fixed for 4 h in the same fixative, and then cryoprotected with 30% sucrose in 0.1 M PBS. Brains and other tissues (spleen and duodenum) were sectioned by microtome as described previously [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. For <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridisation (ISH), unfixed tissues were carefully dissected from C57/Bl6 mice from various brain regions and different organs including spleen, lung, duodenum and embryos (embryonic day 18, ED 18) and snap-frozen in dry ice until analysed by ISH.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>ISH</title><p>Brain tissues and other organs were prepared for ISH and probed as described previously [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. To synthesise DIG-labelled RNA probes, the target CD26 cDNA was amplified by PCR using primers designed on the basis of the mouse CD26 cDNA sequence used in RT-PCR. The primers used for DIG labelling were:</p><p>CD26-insF: TAATACGACTCACTATACAAGAAATATCCTCTACTATTAG CD26-insR: ATTTAGGTGACACTATAGAGAAATCCACTTCCAACATCGAC sequenced and homology checked by BLAST search (NCBI database). <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> transcription reactions were performed using dig-UTP RNA labeling mix and SP6 or T7 RNA polymerase (Roche, Mannheim, Germany).</p><p>ISH with DIG-labelled probe was carried out on spleen, brain and other embryonic tissues’ sections fixed in 4% PFA for 10 min, permeabilised for 10 min in (0.1 M PBS with 0.5% Triton X-100), and acetylated by 10-min incubation in triethanolamine solution. Pre-hybridisation was performed in hybridisation buffer for 3 h at 62°C and then hybridised with DIG-labelled probes (100 ng/ml) in the same buffer overnight at 62°C. Stringent washing was performed in 0.2× SSC for 1 h at 62°C. For the detection of DIG-labelled hybrids, the slides were equilibrated in maleic acid buffer (MAB, 0.1 M maleic acid and 0.15 M NaCl, pH 7.5), incubated for 1 h at room temperature (RT) with 1% blocking reagent made in MAB (blocking buffer), and then for 1 h with alkaline phosphatase-conjugated anti-DIG antibodies (Roche, Mannheim, Germany) diluted 1:5000 in blocking buffer. The slides were washed twice for 30 min in MAB and incubated overnight in colour development buffer [2.4 mg levamisole (Sigma), 45 μl 4-nitroblue tetrazolium (Sigma), and 35 μl 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-phosphate (Sigma) in 10 ml of a buffer made of 0.1 M Trizma base, 0.1 M NaCl and 0.005 M MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 9.5]. The reaction was stopped in neutralising buffer (0.01 M Trizma base and 0.001 M EDTA, pH 8) and sections were mounted in PBS/glycerol and a coverslip applied over the section on the slide. Non-specific binding was analysed using sense probes.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Solid-phase enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</title><p>The sCD26 plasma concentration was measured with the human DPPIV/CD26 DuoSet ELISA development System kit (R&amp;D Systems, Catalogue number DY1180) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, for the detection of sCD26, in 96-well culture plates were incubated overnight with monoclonal antibody (mAb) anti-CD26 capture antibody (1 μg/ml) (R&amp;D systems, catalogue number 842127). The following day the plates were washed three times with washing buffer (0.05% Tween 20 in 0.1 M PBS pH 7.4) and blocked in blocking solution (1% BSA and 0.05% Tween 20 in 0.1 M PBS) for 2 h at RT. After blocking, the plates were washed three times with washing buffer and loaded with 10 μl plasma into 90 μl blocking solution and incubated 4 h at RT. All experiments were performed in quadruplicate unless otherwise specified. A recombinant human protein (R&amp;D, Catalogue number 842129) was diluted in assay buffer in a two-fold serial dilution and used for the standard curve with a concentration range of 1000, 500, 250, 125, 62, 31, 15, and 0 pg/ml. After 4 h of incubation, the samples were removed and the plates were washed three times for 5 min with washing buffer before incubation for 2 h at RT for detection with a biotinylated rabbit monoclonal anti-human CD26 (catalogue number 842128, R&amp;D) antibody (1 μg/ml) diluted in blocking buffer. After three further washing steps, the plates were incubated with anti-rabbit HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (1:4000) for 1 h followed by three washes. A total of 100 μl of 1-Step ULTRA tetramethylbenzidine (TMB-ELISA, Thermo Scientific) was added for ∼30 min at RT. Finally, 100 μl of 2 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> was added to quench the reaction. Colorimetric quantification was performed with an Infinite m200 plate reader (Tecan) at 450/540 nm.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Antibodies</title><p>The following primary antibodies were used: mouse monoclonal anti-CD26 (mAb M-A261, Invitrogen) and rabbit polyclonal (pAb) anti-CD26 antibody (Abcam, Ab28340). Other antibodies used in the present study were rabbit pAb anti-apolipoprotein-E (ApoE; Abcam, Ab85311), anti-CD3 (PA5-32318) Thermo Fisher Scientific, anti-cluster of differentiation 42b (CD42b; Abcam, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="Ab104704">Ab104704</ext-link>), anti-rabbit polyclonal glycophorin (Abcam, 196568), anti-divalent metal protein 1 (DMT1; Abcam, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="Ab123085">Ab123085</ext-link>), anti-ferroportin (FPN; Abcam Ab85370), anti-GFAP (Abcam Ab48050), anti-CD68 (Sigma–Aldrich, AMAB98073), and anti-CD11b (Thermo Fisher, mAbM1/70). The following secondary antibodies were used: biotinylated goat anti-rabbit-Ig and biotinylated horse anti-mouse (both from Vector Laboratories, 1:250 for IHC); Alexa Fluor 568-labelled donkey anti-mouse-Ig, Alexa Fluor 488-labelled donkey anti-rabbit-Ig, and Alexa Fluor 568-labelled donkey anti-goat-Ig (all from Invitrogen, 1:1000 for immunofluoresence).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>Brain and other sections were blocked using blocking buffer (0.1 M PBS, 0.3% Triton X-100, 10% normal donkey serum) for 1 h at RT, then incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibody diluted in blocking buffer. Alexa Fluor-conjugated secondary antibodies were used for detection and samples counterstained with 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, Sigma). Sections were then mounted on glass slides with coverslips using Fluoro Save (Calbiochem).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Microscopy</title><p>Bright-field images were taken and quantified using Lucia imaging software and a Leica FW 4000 upright microscope equipped with a SPOT digital camera. Fluorescence images were obtained using a Leica DM6000 wide-field fluorescence microscope equipped with a Leica FX350 camera with ×20 and ×40 objectives. Images were taken through several z-sections and de-convolved using Leica software. A Leica TCS SP2 confocal laser-scanning microscope was used with ×40 and ×63 objectives to acquire high-resolution images.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Image and statistics analyses</title><p>Data were analysed by the paired Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test (two-tailed) for two-group comparison, or by ANOVA test for multiple comparison testing. Values in the figures are expressed as mean ± SEM. A one-way ANOVA was used for comparison of data among control, T2DM and ARD and conducted with IBM-SPSS statistic 19 software. Significance was analysed using GraphPad and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values ≤0.001 were considered significant and are indicated in the corresponding figures and figure legends.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>sCD26 serum protein levels are reduced in dementia, diabetes and in older people</title><p>To explore the level of sCD26, serum samples from young and old controls [age-matched T2DM: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, 30–55 years; non-demented) and ARD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=50, aged between 56 and 85 years) subjects were analysed by sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) using Human DPP4/CD26 (R&amp;D system, catalogue number: DY1180). All samples were analysed on the same day, using same standard to reduce the day-to-day variation.</p><p>Levels of sCD26 were lower in older subjects as well as in patients with comorbidities such as T2DM and ARD. The serum protein analysis by ELISA showed that the mean level of sCD26 in control subjects was higher than seen in their older counterparts (901.3 vs 664.2 pg/ml, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.6, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value ≤0.0001) in YC and OC respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In younger T2DM, the mean level was (402.9 pg/ml, compared with the mean level in ARD of 216.8 pg/ml, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.7, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value ≤0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). A significant reduction in serum sCD26 levels was seen in ARD and in T2DM subjects compared with age-matched controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>sCD26 serum protein levels are reduced in dementia, diabetes and in older people</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The ELISA analysis performed with human serum showed that CD26 levels were highest in the YCs, followed by OCs, significantly decreased in young diabetics (T2DM) and lowest in the ARD (OD). (YC vs T2DM, and OC vs OD, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.0001; YC vs OC, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.001 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.001*** and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.0001 showed with ****). All serum samples were analysed at the same time to reduce the day-to-day variation. CD26 mRNA expression was detected by ISH using sense and antisense DIG-labelled CD26 probe. A sense probe was used to investigate non-specific binding in tonsil section, no non-specific binding was observed (<bold>B</bold>). Localisation of CD26 enzyme activity in tonsils, a predominant staining of CD26 mRNA was observed in the outer darker extra-follicular T cells region of tonsil with much less staining in the inner germinal centres (<bold>C</bold>), in the endothelium of heart of ED 18 (<bold>D</bold>), endothelial layer of pancreas (<bold>E</bold>), embryonic spleen (<bold>F</bold>), in adult spleen (<bold>G</bold>). In adult mouse duodenum, CD26 expressed in the epithelial brush border (<bold>H</bold>), around the hepatocytes in the liver (<bold>I</bold>), in the lung epithelial cells (<bold>J</bold>) and in the placental trophoblast cells (<bold>K</bold>), (cellular localisation of mRNA indicated by arrow in all panels). There was no mRNA visible in the mouse brain cells (<bold>L</bold>), whereas present in the brain parenchymal blood vessels (<bold>M</bold>), in sub-ventricular zone (SVZ) (<bold>N</bold>) and in the choroid plexus (CP) (<bold>O</bold>). Together, these findings indicated that CD26 mRNA is expressed in T cells, epithelial and endothelial cells of many different organs. Scale bar: (B–F,H–J = 50 μm, K–O = 100 μm).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20203092-g1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Soluble Serum CD26 levels in young vs old controls, diabetics and old demented subjects measured by ELISA</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum CD26 (pg/ml)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YC</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young diabetic</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OC</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old demented</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">901.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">664.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two-way ANOVA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ordinary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Source of variation</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>% of total variation</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value summary</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Significant</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Row factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.504</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANOVA table</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F (DFn, DFd)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Row factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">970863</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19814</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F (49, 147) = 0.9051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.6493</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13450000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4483000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F (3, 147) = 204.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residual</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3218000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21890</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of missing values</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tukey’s multiple comparisons test</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Diff.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI of diff.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YC vs. Young diabetic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498.4 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">421.5–575.3 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YC vs. OC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.2–313.9 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">YC vs. Old demented</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">684.4 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">607.5–761.3 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young diabetic vs. OC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–261.3 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−338.2 to −184.4 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young diabetic vs. Old demented</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.1–262.9 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old control vs. Old demented</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447.3 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370.4–524.2 (pg/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">****</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>CD26 mRNA expression pattern identified in immune cells</title><p>Using ISH with a DIG-labelled sense and antisense CD26 probes, we visualised the cellular location of CD26 mRNA in freshly frozen human tonsil, mouse heart, pancreas, embryonic and adult spleen, duodenum, liver, lung and placenta, as shown previously (see ‘Materials and methods’ section) [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. There was no non-specific binding with sense probe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B), whereas with the antisense probe, a predominant staining in the outer darker T cells region of the lymphoid follicle was observed with much less staining in the inner area of the germinal centre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). Higher mRNA expression was seen in the embryonic tissues (in the endothelial layer of the heart, pancreas and spleen) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>D–F). The highest levels were seen in the placenta, in trophoblast cells, in the spleen, in the duodenum, particularly in the intestinal epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>G–I,K). The membrane-bound mRNA levels was also visible in the lung epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>J). However, very limited mRNA was seen in the mouse brain tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>L), except in blood vessels, sub-ventricular zone (SVZ) and choroid plexus (CP) epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>M–O). Together, these findings indicate that CD26 mRNA is expressed in T cells, epithelial and endothelial cells of many different organs.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>CD26 protein is expressed in the CP epithelial cells and meningeal blood vessels</title><p>COVID-19 infection affects epithelial and endothelial lining of the lung and meningeal macrophages as well as other cells of the immune system [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. For validation of CD26 protein levels in the brain and other immune cells, tissue sections were stained by immunofluorescence (IF) using anti-CD26 mouse mAb (M-A261, Invitrogen) and analysed using confocal microscopy. A clear signal was seen in the human spleen white pulp, very close to the central canal and the T-cell area surrounding the lymphoid follicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A–C). CD26 and CD3 (a marker expressed in T cells) colocalised in the outer darker region of the germinal centre containing large- and medium-sized T lymphocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>CD26 protein is expressed in the CP epithelial cells, meningeal blood vessels and bind with divalent metal proteins in the duodenum</title><p>Double IFC staining was performed in the human spleen using mouse mAb anti-CD26 (Green) and rabbit polyclonal (pAb) anti-CD3 (red), and DAPI for nuclei (blue) (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>). CD26 immunoreactivity was seen in the human spleen in white pulp, very close to the central canal and in T-cell area surrounding the lymphoid follicles (A,B). CD26 and CD3 (a marker expressed in T cells) colocalised in the outer darker region of the germinal centre containing large- and medium-sized T lymphocytes and both proteins colocalised (C). Embryonic mouse CP was stained with CD26 (green) and DAPI (blue) and imaged using confocal microscopy. Very high CD26 expression was present in the mouse embryonic CP epithelium (<bold>D</bold>). Human normal brain section particularly CP was stained with CD26 (green) and ApoE (red), both proteins were present in the CP epithelial membrane and colocalised in the macrophages (<bold>E</bold>). A mouse brain section from lateral ventricle stained with CD26 (red) and a macrophages marker CD68 (green), CD26-positive macrophages were visible at the wall of ventricle and in the CP, both proteins colocalised (<bold>F</bold>). An ARD brain section from cortex, close to a blood vessel was stained with CD26 (green) and astrocyte marker (GFAP, red), showed that CD26 protein carried by RBCs and macrophages entering through damaged blood vessels (BVs), surrounded by GFAP-positive astrocytes (<bold>G</bold>). Another blood vessel in the brain stained with CD26 (green) visible in the epithelium (<bold>H</bold>). A human brain section from frontal cortex stained with CD26 (red) and a microglial marker CD11b (green) colocalised in the meningeal macrophages in the Pial surface of cortex (<bold>I</bold>). Cellular localisation of CD26 protein indicated with white arrow in all panels). Duodenum sections from adult mouse was stained with CD26 (green) and DAPI (blue), visible in the columnar cells within the crypts (<bold>J</bold>), and colocalised with metal-binding protein DMT1 at the apical surface (<bold>K</bold>). Large populations of T lymphocytes positive for CD26 colocalised with another metal-binding protein FPN at the basolateral site and in the central core of lamina propria containing blood vessels (<bold>L</bold>). Scale bar in (A–F) = 40 μm, (G–L) = 25 μm. Abbreviation: RBC, red blood cell.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20203092-g2.jpg"/></fig><p>There was no visible mRNA expression of CD26 in the adult human or mouse brain, but unexpectedly high levels of proteins were observed in the human CP epithelial cells and meningeal blood vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>M,O). CD26 protein expression was present in the mouse embryonic CP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D), human CP epithelial cells and macrophages that colocalised with ApoE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>E). CD26 protein was seen in the perivascular macrophages and colocalised with CD68 (a known peripheral macrophage marker) in lateral ventricle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>F). It was visible in the epithelial layer of blood vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>H). When human brain sections (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=6) from ARD subjects were stained with CD26 and an astrocyte marker with GFAP antibody, sCD26 protein was detected in the wall of blood vessels: presumably sCD26 which entered the brain parenchyma from blood vessels via astrocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>G,H). CD26 was detected in the meningeal macrophages colocalised with CD11b, a monocyte/microglial marker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>I).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Membrane-bound CD26 protein binds with divalent metal proteins in the duodenum</title><p>Although SARS-CoV-2 may primarily enter through the lung’s epithelial cells, the small bowel may also be an important entry point or an interaction site [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Our <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>H) revealed prominent CD26 expression in the small intestine (duodenum and jejunum). We immunostained mouse gut tissues with CD26 antibody and other known duodenal membrane-binding protein markers, DMT1 and FPN to assess the expression further [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The most distinct feature of the small intestine is the mucosal lining, with brush border villi and crypts, lined with columnar cells. CD26 staining was seen in the columnar cells within the crypts, particularly in the apical surface and colocalised with metal-binding protein, DMT1, at the apical surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>J,K). Large populations of T lymphocytes positive for CD26 colocalised with another metal-binding protein (FPN) at the basolateral site and in the central core of lamina propria containing blood vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>L). Throughout the small intestine, confluent lymphoid tissues known as Peyer’s patches were visible and CD26 positive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>L).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>CD26 and coagulopathy</title><p>One of the emerging hallmarks of COVID-19 is a coagulopathy, termed as ‘sepsis-induced coagulopathy’ (SIC) with elevated D-dimer and fibrinogen levels [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is related to an infection-induced systemic inflammatory response with endothelial dysfunction and microthrombosis often leading to organ failure [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36–38</xref>]. Several observational studies have characterised monocytes during SARS-CoV-2 infection [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. We investigated cellular expression of CD26 in blood smears from different age groups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=20, age between 30 and 85 years) and imaged using confocal microscopy. The blood smears from young and old subjects were co-labelled with CD26 monoclonal antibody and either with an erythrocyte plasma membrane marker (glycophorin) or a platelet marker (CD42b). Glycophorin was expressed on the surface of red blood cells (RBCs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A–C) with CD26 seen around the RBCs (could be on erythrocytes spikes) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A,B). There was stronger CD26 expression around the RBCs membranes in the controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A,G) and in T2DM compared with ARD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B,C). CD26 was expressed on the surface of mononucleated cells (MNCs) around the outer membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D,E), and a web-like appearance that colocalised with integrin CD42b protein was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>F). The control subjects had stronger CD26 expression around the neutrophil membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D,G,J), whereas in T2DM there was excessive sCD26 around the MNCs and haemolysis in RBCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>H,K). The young and old control subjects expressed much more CD26 in MNC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D,G,J,L), whereas younger T2DM and older ARD subjects carried abnormal fragmented platelets stained with CD42b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>H,I). Additionally, scattered sCD26 was observed extracorporally of RBCs and within MNCs in the T2DM samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>H–K). A classic dysmorphology (bilobed neutrophils) was frequently seen in blood of T2DM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>H,K) whereas normal neutrophils positive for CD26 were found in controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D–G).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>CD26 is expressed on the surface of MNCs around the outer membrane, and a web-like appearance that colocalised with integrin observed</title><p>The blood smears from normal, T2DM and ARD were stained with CD26 (green) and either glycophorin (red) or CD42b (red) and imaged using confocal microscopy. In normal blood smears, glycophorin was expressed on the surface of RBCs (<bold>A</bold>) and CD26 seen around the RBCs in T2DM and ARD (<bold>B,C</bold>). Blood smear showed normal MNCs surrounded by CD26 (green) and CD42b (red) in normal platelets (red) (<bold>D</bold>), in T2DM (<bold>E</bold>) and in ARD (<bold>F</bold>). In T2DM, there was excessive sCD26 around the MNCs and some clumped platelets (red) in the periphery (<bold>H</bold>–<bold>K</bold>). Demented (ARD) subjects showed a web-like expression of CD26 proteins (green) present surrounding the neutrophil and granulocytes (<bold>F</bold>), and fractured platelets (red) around the MNCs with visible nets of integrin (<bold>I</bold>). One old control blood smear stained either with CD26 (green) and either with glycophoryn or CD42b (red). CD26 was present around the MNCs (<bold>G</bold>) and some platelets colocalised with CD26 and CD42b (<bold>J</bold>). Cellular localisation of CD26 protein indicated with white arrow in all panels). CD26 level was highest in the controls, lower in T2DM and lowest in the ARD (<bold>L</bold>). Scale bar in A–K = 10 μm. ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.001, ****<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>≤0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20203092-g3.jpg"/></fig><p>In ARD subjects (with dementia), RBCs appeared abnormally shaped (macrocytic with damaged erythrocytes spikes) and platelets found were fragmented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>F–I). These findings suggest that further investigation of CD26 involvement in lymphocyte regulation is warranted, especially in relation to the coagulation cascade.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>COVID-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2 is now a pandemic [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 pathology is similar to that of SARS-CoV- and MERS-CoV-induced viral pneumonia [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. CoV has specific immune response and immune escape characteristics and can cause severe pathogenic mechanisms through inflammation leading to a variety of symptoms like acute respiratory distress syndrome, gastrointestinal disorder, renal failure, vascular bleeds, stroke, T cell-specific immune responses and cytokine storm [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Cytokine storm is hypercytokinemia that increases the volume of pro-inflammatory cytokines in the serum (e.g. IL-1β, IL-6, IL-12, INF-γ) and chemokines (CXCL10 and CCL2), and is correlated with pulmonary inflammation and extensive lung involvement as seen in COVID-19 patients [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. MERS-CoV infection was also described to provoke increased concentration of cytokines (IL-15, IL-17, TNFα and INF-γ) [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. It is reported that victims infected with SARS-CoV-2 also demonstrate high levels of IL-1β, TNFα, INF-γ, CXCL10 and CCL2 which may be attributed to the activated response of T helper 1 (Th1) cells [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. CXCL10 binds to CXCR3, a G-protein-coupled receptor, which is known to be expressed on activated T lymphocytes, NK cells and some epithelial and endothelial cells. CXCL10–CXCR3 acts in an autocrine fashion on the oxidative burst and chemotaxis in the inflamed neutrophils, leading to fulminant pulmonary inflammation [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p><p>Recently, sequence and modelling analyses of S glycoproteins of MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2 and further co-purification with the MERS-CoV S1 domain, identified that CD26 functions as a cellular receptor for MERS-CoV and possibly SARS-CoV-2 [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Another recent study reported a correlation between CD26 and ACE2, suggesting that both membrane proteins could be relevant in the pathogenesis of virus entry [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The co-expression of ACE2 and CD26 as receptors of spike glycoproteins suggests that different human CoVs may target similar cell types across different human tissues, and this may also explain the presence of similar clinical features in patients infected with different CoVs. In addition, it was shown that CD26 acted as a CoV co-receptor, thus suggesting a potential similar mechanism of entry for SARS-CoV-2. There is a connection between the SARS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2, ACE2 and the rationale for soluble ACE2 as a potential therapy by using ACE2<sup>+</sup>-small extracellular vesicles (sEVs) [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. We suggest that soluble CD26 circulates via platelets and T cells carrying vesicles as shown in the normal blood smear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).T herapeutic approaches may be envisaged using sCD26 as a decoy receptor which could inhibit the entry of the virus through cell surface [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In this study, we analysed the expression pattern in healthy subjects and subjects who are at high risk for COVID-19. Our findings now need to be validated with COVID-19 patients.</p><p>The role of CD26 in immune regulation has been extensively characterised, with findings elucidating its linkage with signalling pathways and structures involved in T-lymphocyte activation as well as antigen presenting dendritic T-cell interaction [<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In this study, we show that CD26 is expressed in T cells, the extrafollicular area of tonsil and at T-cell areas in the germinal centre of the spleen and is also colocalised with CD3 [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The outer darker region of the germinal centre of tonsil, showed that it contained large- and medium-sized lymphocytes as described before [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Spleen may be one of the organs directly attacked by the virus in some patients who died from COVID-19. T and B lymphocytes in the spleen decreased in varying degrees, lymphoid follicles are atrophied, decreased or absent [<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. T cells secrete cytokines and chemokines in immune cells as reported in some genes present in MHC region [<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. These findings suggest that the binding of sCD26 to the spike (S) glycoprotein may also depend on T-cell population.</p><p>Although SARS-CoV-2 may primarily enter the cells of the lungs, the small bowel may also be an important site of entry or interaction site, as the enterocytes are rich in ACE2 receptors [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Duodenal mucosa expresses mCD26 particularly on the apical site of the brush border epithelial cells where T cells present and bind with many divalent metals including Fe<sup>+</sup>, Ca<sup>+</sup>, Co<sup>+</sup>, Zn<sup>+</sup> and Hg<sup>+</sup> [<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Particularly, iron (Fe<sup>+</sup>) plays an important role in inflammation and causes disbalance and hyperferritinaemia in COVID-19 [<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Most iron absorption occurs in the duodenum via the DMT1-mediated uptake and FPN1-mediated export across the apical and basolateral membranes respectively [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. CD26 is a cysteine-rich protein, that can bind with divalent metal-binding proteins (DMT1) and FPN [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Much of this research focus has centred on the ectodomain of the spike protein. The ectodomain is anchored to a transmembrane region, followed by a cytoplasmic tail. Recently, it was reported that a sequence similarity exists between the cysteine-rich cytoplasmic tail of the CoV spike protein with the cysteine-rich domain in hepcidin protein, which is a key regulator of iron homoeostasis in humans and other vertebrates has been reported [<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59–61</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) glycoprotein can bind DMT1 on the apical site of brush border epithelial cells in the gut mucosa, and could mediate membrane fusion and virus entry into the cells. High levels of sCD26 can therefore potentially compete and prevent viral entry through gut mucosa and exert beneficial immunoprotective effects via elevation of GIP, a peptide that is produced in gastrointestinal K cells and further proteolysed by CD26 [<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. As a consequence, the small bowel may serve as a viral entry site or as a potentiating organ, magnifying the systemic inflammatory response, small bowel being the largest lymphoid organ of the body. A significant proportion of COVID-19 patients with gastrointestinal symptoms clearly support the involvement of the small bowel in SARS-CoV-2 [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>One of the emerging hallmarks of COVID-19 is a coagulopathy, termed as ‘SIC’ with elevated D-dimer and fibrinogen levels [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It was shown that platelet activation and platelet–leucocyte interactions participate in the pathophysiology of viral infections, including dengue, HIV and influenza [<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Recently, a hypercoagulability state has been reported as a major pathologic event in COVID-19, and thromboembolic complications are listed among life-threatening complications of the disease [<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Platelets are chief effector cells of haemostasis and pathological thrombosis [<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In this paper, we demonstrated that increased platelet activation and platelet–monocyte aggregate formation are observed in diabetic subjects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E,H), and much more prominent in ARD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>F,I) but not in controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D,G).</p><p>Recent clinical evidence has revealed T2DM and cardiovascular risk factors increase susceptibility to COVID-19 infection [<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The elderly, and those with underlying medical conditions particularly obesity, diabetes, ARD are the pre-existing diseases associated with the greatest risk and death in COVID-19 pandemic [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. We therefore chose T2DM, ARD and age-matched young and old controls who are at high risk for COVID-19 infection. They all could thus have common risk factors that affect different organs, particularly the epithelial membrane responsible for the viral entry. We found that CD26 is expressed in the epithelial membrane of the CP and in the endothelium of blood vessels in the brain. The CP is a secretory tissue responsible for producing both the CSF in the vertebrate brain and many innate immune molecules to protect the brain from infection by surveying the blood–brain barrier (BBB) [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. CD26 protein is present in the CP epithelial membrane and in the outer layer of brain pia mater particularly in the meningeal macrophages, where it is colocalised with other brain spectrins, known as fordin and ankyrin [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Similarly, CD26 is expressed in erythrocyte membranes (also having erythrocyte spikes) and is colocalised with membrane proteins, glycophorin and integrin α2β3 [<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Since SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) glycoprotein binds to erythrocytes, causing clotting defects in the small blood vessels [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], we analysed blood smears from young, diabetic (T2DM) and older subjects (ARD). In young controls, the higher levels of sCD26 around neutrophils, and in platelets was seen, whereas in immunocompromised T2DM subjects many fractured platelets and clumped RBCs with haemolysis were visible, alongside a web-like expression of integrin proteins was present surrounding the neutrophil and granulocytes (also visible in ARD subjects). Furthermore, in ARD subjects macrocytic, broken RBCs and fragmented platelets were present. These findings demonstrated the impaired coagulopathy in older subjects and those with T2DM and dementia, and complement our previous findings of another immunoprotective molecules such as TREM2, suggesting that CD26 may also be required for the haemopoietic cellular growth and protection [<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].</p><p>Levels of serum CD26 are approximately three-times higher in pregnant women at ∼3 μg/ml (R.R.-C., unpublished data). CD26 mRNA expression is elevated in placental trophoblasts, where it may induce regulatory T cell (Treg) differentiation and protect the foetus from external infections [<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. These findings suggest that newborn babies and young children may be protected from COVID-19 due to high levels of sCD26. Another study reported female HIV positive but disease-free sex-workers in Nairobi also showed higher levels of serum sCD26 and thereby presumably protecting them from all other viral infections [<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Our findings suggest that T-cell regulatory CD26 is expressed in different organs from tonsil, spleen, gut mucosa to brain (particularly in CP and in BBB) and sCD26 may play a crucial role as a decoy receptor which could inhibit the entry of the virus through cell surface, allowing more time for neutralising antibodies to be raised against the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have shown sCD26 expressed in serum, and mCD26 in T cells (in tonsil and spleen), in CP, duodenum and erythrocytes. We observed a significant reduction in serum sCD26 levels with age and in T2DM subjects compared with age-matched controls. Thus, we suggest that measuring sCD26 level in the serum of young and old control subjects and comparing them with SARS-CoV-2 virus carrying subjects could be explored as a possible test for inflammatory stages in COVID-19: high serum sCD26 level could protect from viral infection by blocking the receptor from virus entry, whereas low sCD26 level may be associated with a higher risk of infection. If correct,a therapeutic approach may be to use sCD26 as a decoy receptor which could competitively inhibit the entry of the virus through cell surface.</p></sec><sec sec-type="perspectives" id="sec6"><title>Perspectives</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The rapid global spread of SARS‐CoV‐2 and its grave impact on public health immediately demands prompt and efficient coordinated effort in biomedical research to increase the understanding of the pathogenesis of the virus and its impact upon the host cells. T2DM and cardiovascular risk factors increase the susceptibility to COVID-19 infection. Variations in sCD26 levels in serum have been reported as clinically relevant in several pathophysiological conditions including T2DM and virus infections, where CD26 may plays a critical role in the innate immunity and T-cell regulation.</p></list-item><list-item><p>We investigated the mCD26 and sCD26 expression to uncover CD26 role in the innate immunity and inflammation. For this, we analysed samples from T2DM and ARD subjects who are considered at high risk for COVID-19. We show sCD26 is expressed in serum, T cells (in tonsil and spleen) whereas mCD26 in CP, duodenum and erythrocytes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>We suggest that measuring sCD26 level in the serum should be explored as a possible test for inflammatory stages in COVID-19: high serum sCD26 level could protect from viral infection by blocking the receptor from virus entry, whereas low sCD26 level may be associated with a higher risk of infection. It could be theraputic approches to use sCD26 as a decoy receptor which could competitively inhibit the entry of the virus through cell surface.</p></list-item></list></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Professor Robert Friedland for serum samples from aged cohort, Professor Antony Holland for the encouragement and advice, Dr Chiwen Chang involved in the antibody development, Dr Vinod Divalia for his critical observation and suggestion of blood smear slides, and Cambridge Brain Bank (supported by NIHR, Biomedical Research, Cambridge) for human brain sections. Our sincere gratitude goes towards the participants and support from their family members.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec7"><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data analysed in the present paper are already included in the manuscript, including a table.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript. CamKolInv is a non-profitable organisation.</p></sec><sec id="sec9" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Medical Research Council (MRC) [grant number RNAG/254]; the National Institute of Health Research (NIHR) [grant number; The John van Geest Foundation, Cambridge, U.K.; and the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Program [grant number 695551 (work in J.T.’s laboratory)].</p></sec><sec id="sec10" sec-type="Open-access"><title>Open Access</title><p>Open access for this article was enabled by the participation of University of Cambridge in an all-inclusive <italic toggle="yes">Read &amp; Publish</italic> pilot with Portland Press and the Biochemical Society under a transformative agreement with JISC.</p></sec><sec id="sec11" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>A.A.R., J.H. and S.C. performed biochemical analysis, critically evaluated the results. A.A.R. performed tissue analysis and confocal microscopy. S.Z. evaluated clinical findings, and E.M.-L. evaluated clinical samples and edited the manuscript. R.R.-C. and J.T. contributed to the hypothesis development and edited the manuscript. R.R.-C. performed study design, supervised the project, critically evaluated the results and wrote the manuscript. All authors carefully read, edited and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>Ethics Approval</title><p>All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki Declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="G1">ACE2</term><def><p>angiotensin-converting enzyme-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">ApoE</term><def><p>apolipoprotein-E</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">ARD</term><def><p>age-related dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">ARS</term><def><p>acute respiratory syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">BBB</term><def><p>blood–brain barrier</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">CCL2</term><def><p>C-C Motif Chemokine Ligand 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">CD26</term><def><p>cluster of differentiation 26</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">CD42b</term><def><p>cluster of differentiation 42b</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">CNS</term><def><p>Central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">CoV</term><def><p>Coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">COVID-19</term><def><p>Coronavirus-19</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12">CP</term><def><p>choroid plexus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">CSF</term><def><p>cerebrospinal fluid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G14">CXCL10</term><def><p>C-X-C motif chemokine ligand 10</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G15">DMT1</term><def><p>divalent metal protein 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G16">DPP4</term><def><p>dipeptidyl peptidase 4</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G17">ELISA</term><def><p>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G18">FPN</term><def><p>ferroportin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G19">GFAP</term><def><p>Glial fibrillary protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G20">GIP</term><def><p>glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G21">IF</term><def><p>immunofluorescence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G22">IHC</term><def><p>immunohistochemistry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G23">INF</term><def><p>Interferon</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G24">ISH</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridisation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G25">MAB</term><def><p>maleic acid buffer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G26">mAb</term><def><p>mouse monoclonal antibody</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G27">mCD26</term><def><p>membrane-anchored CD26</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G28">MERS-CoV</term><def><p>Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G29">MNC</term><def><p>mononucleated cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G30">NK</term><def><p>natural killer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G31">OC</term><def><p>older control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G32">PBS</term><def><p>phosphate buffer saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G33">PFA</term><def><p>paraformaldehyde</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G34">RBC</term><def><p>red blood cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G35">RT</term><def><p>room temperature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G36">SARS-CoV</term><def><p>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G37">SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G38">sCD26</term><def><p>soluble CD26</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G39">SIC</term><def><p>sepsis-induced coagulopathy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G40">T2DM</term><def><p>type 2 diabetes mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G41">TMPRSS2</term><def><p>transmembrane protease serine 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G42">TREM2</term><def><p>Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G43">Treg</term><def><p>regulatory T cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G44">YC</term><def><p>younger control</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>579</volume>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>382</volume>, <fpage>1708</fpage>–<lpage>1720</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7092819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>395</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30183-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7159299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rota</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a novel coronavirus associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>300</volume>, <fpage>1394</fpage>–<lpage>1399</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1085952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>579</volume>, <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7095418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Heymsfield</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>COVID 19 and the patient with obesity - the editors speak out</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/oby.22808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32237212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Cardiovascular comorbidity and its impact on patients with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Eur. Respir. J.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01227-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7236831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32341104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Diabetes is a risk factor for the progression and prognosis of COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Metab. Res. Rev.</source><fpage>e3319</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dmrr.3319</pub-id>, <comment>Online ahead of print</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32233013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grasselli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Baseline characteristics and outcomes of 1591 patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 admitted to ICUs of the Lombardy Region, Italy</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>1574</fpage>–<lpage>1581</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.5394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32250385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Structure of SARS coronavirus spike receptor-binding domain complexed with receptor</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>309</volume>, <fpage>1864</fpage>–<lpage>1868</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structure of MERS-CoV spike receptor-binding domain complexed with human receptor DPP4</article-title>. <source>Cell Res.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>986</fpage>–<lpage>993</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2013.92</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23835475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3731569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 is a functional receptor for the SARS coronavirus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>426</volume>, <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>454</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14647384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7095016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vankadari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilce</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Emerging WuHan (COVID-19) coronavirus: glycan shield and structure prediction of spike glycoprotein and its interaction with human CD26</article-title>. <source>Emerg. Microbes Infect.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1739565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7103712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radzikowska</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Distribution of ACE2, CD147, CD26, and other SARS-CoV-2 associated molecules in tissues and immune cells in health and in asthma, COPD, obesity, hypertension, and COVID-19 risk factors</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>2829</fpage>–<lpage>2845</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.14429</pub-id><comment>Epub 2020 Aug 24</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32496587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7300910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>181</volume>, <fpage>271.e8</fpage>–<lpage>280.e8</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32142651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Dipeptidyl peptidase 4 is a functional receptor for the emerging human coronavirus-EMC</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>495</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23486063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7095326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durinx</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of dipeptidyl peptidase activity in serum: soluble CD26/dipeptidyl peptidase IV is responsible for the release of X-Pro dipeptides</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>5608</fpage>–<lpage>5613</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-1327.2000.01634.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10951221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Meester</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Natural substrates of dipeptidyl peptidase IV</article-title>. <source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>477</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/0-306-46826-3_7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10849732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambeir</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Dipeptidyl-peptidase IV from bench to bedside: an update on structural properties, functions, and clinical aspects of the enzyme DPP IV</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Clin. Lab. Sci.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/713609354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorrell</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gysbers</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>McCaughan</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>CD26: a multifunctional integral membrane and secreted protein of activated lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Scand. J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3083.2001.00984.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11555388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A recombinant receptor-binding domain of MERS-CoV in trimeric form protects human dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (hDPP4) transgenic mice from MERS-CoV infection</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>
<volume>499</volume>, <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>382</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2016.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27750111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5167628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Cloning and functional expression of the T cell activation antigen CD26</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>149</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1352530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosaraju</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Saxagliptin: a dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitor ameliorates streptozotocin induced Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2013.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Physiology and pharmacology of DPP-4 in glucose homeostasis and the treatment of Type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne)</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2019.00080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30828317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6384237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>CD26/dipeptidylpeptidase IV-chemokine interactions: double-edged regulation of inflammation and tumor biology</article-title>. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>955</fpage>–<lpage>969</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.3MR0915-401R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26744452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Anticipating and mitigating the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on Alzheimer’s disease and related dementias</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jagp.2020.04.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32331845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7165101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azarpazhooh</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Correlations between COVID-19 and burden of dementia: an ecological study and review of literature</article-title>. <source>J. Neurol. Sci.</source>
<volume>416</volume>, <fpage>117013</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2020.117013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32659508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7334961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The systemic iron-regulatory proteins hepcidin and ferroportin are reduced in the brain in Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Neuropathol. Commun.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2051-5960-1-55</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24252754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3893417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha-Chowdhury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Erythromyeloid-derived TREM2: a major determinant of Alzheimer’s disease pathology in Down syndrome</article-title>. <source>J. Alzheimers Dis.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>1143</fpage>–<lpage>1162</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-170814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29278889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5817909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha-Chowdhury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Expression and cellular localization of hepcidin mRNA and protein in normal rat brain</article-title>. <source>BMC Neurosci.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12868-015-0161-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25896789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4409766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Postmortem examination of patients with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<volume>323</volume>, <fpage>2518</fpage>–<lpage>2520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.8907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32437497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7243161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Pathological inflammation in patients with COVID-19: a key role for monocytes and macrophages</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-020-0331-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32376901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7201395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monkemuller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rickes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>COVID-19, coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 and the small bowel</article-title>. <source>Rev. Esp. Enferm. Dig.</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32343593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17235/reed.2020.7137/2020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKie</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A novel duodenal iron-regulated transporter, IREG1, implicated in the basolateral transfer of iron to the circulation</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(00)80425-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of iron mediated regulation of the duodenal iron transporters divalent metal transporter 1 and ferroportin 1</article-title>. <source>Blood Cells Mol. Dis.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>488</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcmd.2002.0587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iba</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Diagnosis and management of sepsis-induced coagulopathy and disseminated intravascular coagulation</article-title>. <source>J. Thromb. Haemost.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1989</fpage>–<lpage>1994</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jth.14578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31410983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Anticoagulant treatment is associated with decreased mortality in severe coronavirus disease 2019 patients with coagulopathy</article-title>. <source>J. Thromb. Haemost.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1094</fpage>–<lpage>1099</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jth.14817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9906401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Abnormal coagulation parameters are associated with poor prognosis in patients with novel coronavirus pneumonia</article-title>. <source>J. Thromb. Haemost.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>847</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jth.14768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32073213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pence</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Severe COVID-19 and aging: are monocytes the key?</article-title>
<source>Geroscience</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1051</fpage>–<lpage>1061</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11357-020-00213-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32556942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7299454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Outbreak of pneumonia of unknown etiology in Wuhan, China: the mystery and the miracle</article-title>. <source>J. Med. Virol.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31950516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Isolation of a novel coronavirus from a man with pneumonia in Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>367</volume>, <fpage>1814</fpage>–<lpage>1820</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1211721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23075143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>T cell responses to whole SARS coronavirus in humans</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>181</volume>, <fpage>5490</fpage>–<lpage>5500</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.181.8.5490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18832706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2683413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Channappanavar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Pathogenic human coronavirus infections: causes and consequences of cytokine storm and immunopathology</article-title>. <source>Semin. Immunopathol.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00281-017-0629-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28466096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7079893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Interferon-mediated immunopathological events are associated with atypical innate and adaptive immune responses in patients with severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>8692</fpage>–<lpage>8706</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00527-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17537853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1951379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melchjorsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Paludan</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Expression and function of chemokines during viral infections: from molecular mechanisms to in vivo function</article-title>. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.1102577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12949236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7166880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grifoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Targets of T cell responses to SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus in humans with COVID-19 disease and unexposed individuals</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>181</volume>, <fpage>1489</fpage>–<lpage>1501</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.015</pub-id><comment>Epub 2020 May 20</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32473127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7237901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>CXCL10-CXCR3 enhances the development of neutrophil-mediated fulminant lung injury of viral and nonviral origin</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med.</source>
<volume>187</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.201203-0508OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3927876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Putative conformations of the receptor-binding domain in S protein of hCoV-EMC in complex with its receptor dipeptidyl peptidase-4</article-title>. <source>J. Infect.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2013.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4355062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Single cell RNA sequencing of 13 human tissues identify cell types and receptors of human coronaviruses</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>526</volume>, <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2020.03.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32199615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7156119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wysocki</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Satchell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Soluble angiotensin-converting enzyme 2: a potential approach for coronavirus infection therapy?</article-title>
<source>Clin. Sci. (Lond.)</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>543</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/CS20200163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32167153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) as a SARS-CoV-2 receptor: molecular mechanisms and potential therapeutic target</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-020-05985-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32125455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7079879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection by anti-CD26 monoclonal antibody</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>13892</fpage>–<lpage>13899</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02448-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24067970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3838260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casrouge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Lymphocytes are a major source of circulating soluble dipeptidyl peptidase 4</article-title>. <source>Clin. Exp. Immunol.</source>
<volume>194</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cei.13163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30251416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6194339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stankovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distribution of dipeptidyl peptidase IV in patients with chronic tonsillitis</article-title>. <source>Clin. Vaccine Immunol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>794</fpage>–<lpage>798</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CVI.00054-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18385458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2394850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Pathological changes of the spleen in ten patients with coronavirus disease 2019(COVID-19) by postmortem needle autopsy</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Bing Li Xue Za Zhi</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>582</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32340089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.cn112151-20200401-00278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivakamasundari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression and cellular localization of the protein encoded by the 1C7 gene: a recently described component of the MHC</article-title>. <source>Immunogenetics</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>732</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002510000192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10941844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effect of divalent cations on the porcine kidney cortex membrane-bound form of dipeptidyl peptidase IV</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>371</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2010.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21093607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Pastora</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Hyperferritinemia in critically ill COVID-19 patients - Is ferritin the product of inflammation or a pathogenic mediator?</article-title>
<source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source>
<volume>509</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2020.06.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32579952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7306200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehsani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>COVID-19 and iron dysregulation: distant sequence similarity between hepcidin and the novel coronavirus spike glycoprotein</article-title>. <source>Biol. Direct</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13062-020-00275-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33066821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7563913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavezzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Troiani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Corrao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>COVID-19: hemoglobin, iron, and hypoxia beyond inflammation. A narrative review</article-title>. <source>Clin. Pract.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32509258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4081/cp.2020.1271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7267810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>The Hepcidin/Ferroportin axis modulates proliferation of pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>12972</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-31095-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30154413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6113242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salcedo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotective and neurotrophic actions of glucagon-like peptide-1: an emerging opportunity to treat neurodegenerative and cerebrovascular disorders</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>166</volume>, <fpage>1586</fpage>–<lpage>1599</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.2012.01971.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22519295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3419902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>Z.G.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Platelet-leukocyte interactions link inflammatory and thromboembolic events in ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source>Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>1207</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05733.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20955420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3245960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hottz</surname><given-names>E.D.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Platelet activation and platelet-monocyte aggregate formation trigger tissue factor expression in patients with severe COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>1330</fpage>–<lpage>1341</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2020007252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32678428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7483437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Protective vascular coagulation in response to bacterial infection of the kidney is regulated by bacterial lipid A and host CD147</article-title>. <source>Pathog. Dis.</source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>fty087</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femspd/fty087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30476069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7297223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muniyappa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gubbi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic, coronaviruses, and diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab.</source>
<volume>318</volume>, <fpage>E736</fpage>–<lpage>E741</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpendo.00124.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7191633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isik</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>The effects of sitagliptin, a DPP-4 inhibitor, on cognitive functions in elderly diabetic patients with or without Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract.</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2016.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28056430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha-Chowdhury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Choroid plexus acts as gatekeeper for TREM2, abnormal accumulation of ApoE, and fibrillary tau in Alzheimer’s disease and in Down syndrome dementia</article-title>. <source>J. Alzheimers Dis.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-181179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30909239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6598012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wenegieme</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Babitch</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Characterization of calcium binding to brain spectrin</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>4333</fpage>–<lpage>4337</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1537825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glenney</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glenney</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Erythroid spectrin, brain fodrin, and intestinal brush border proteins (TW-260/240) are related molecules containing a common calmodulin-binding subunit bound to a variant cell type-specific subunit</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>4002</fpage>–<lpage>4005</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.79.13.4002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6955786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC346564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iba</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Diagnosis of sepsis-induced disseminated intravascular coagulation and coagulopathy</article-title>. <source>Acute Med. Surg.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31304023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ams2.411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6603393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raha</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Neuroprotective effect of TREM-2 in aging and Alzheimer’s disease model</article-title>. <source>J. Alzheimers Dis.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/JAD-160663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27662313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Immunobiology of trophoblast cells</article-title>. <source>Indian J. Clin. Biochem.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02867545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23105269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3454069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Songok</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>CD26/dipeptidyl peptidase IV (CD26/DPPIV) is highly expressed in peripheral blood of HIV-1 exposed uninfected female sex workers</article-title>. <source>Virol. J.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-7-343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21108831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3009705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>