
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Sci Monit</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Med Sci Monit</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1959</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">medscimon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">9609063</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Medical Science Monitor</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medical Science Monitor : International Medical Journal of Experimental and Clinical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1234-1010</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1643-3750</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Scientific Information, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7781046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7781046.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7781046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7781046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33377476</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/MSM.927029</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">927029</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy in Evaluation of Cerebral Metabolic Status Before and After Carotid Endarterectomy/Thromboendarterectomy and Carotid Artery Stenting in Patients with Asymptomatic Critical Internal Carotid Artery Stenosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sklinda</surname><given-names initials="K">Katarzyna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-medscimonit-26-e927029">A</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-medscimonit-26-e927029">B</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn3-medscimonit-26-e927029">C</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-medscimonit-26-e927029">D</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-medscimonit-26-e927029">E</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-medscimonit-26-e927029">F</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn7-medscimonit-26-e927029">G</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mruk</surname><given-names initials="B">Bartosz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-medscimonit-26-e927029">B</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-medscimonit-26-e927029">E</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surowiecka</surname><given-names initials="A">Agnieszka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-medscimonit-26-e927029">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn3-medscimonit-26-e927029">C</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-medscimonit-26-e927029">D</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciaś</surname><given-names initials="M">Marek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-medscimonit-26-e927029">B</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paluch</surname><given-names initials="Ł">Łukasz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-medscimonit-26-e927029">F</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andziak</surname><given-names initials="P">Piotr</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-medscimonit-26-e927029">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-medscimonit-26-e927029">4</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-medscimonit-26-e927029">A</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walecki</surname><given-names initials="J">Jerzy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-medscimonit-26-e927029">A</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-medscimonit-26-e927029">
<label>1</label>Department of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, Centre of Postgraduate Medical Education, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af2-medscimonit-26-e927029">
<label>2</label>Department of Surgical Research and Transplantology, Mossakowski Medical Research Centre, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af3-medscimonit-26-e927029">
<label>3</label>Department of General and Vascular Surgery, Central Clinical Hospital of the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Administration, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af4-medscimonit-26-e927029">
<label>4</label>Centre of Postgraduate Medical Education, Warsaw, Poland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-medscimonit-26-e927029">Corresponding Author: Katarzyna Sklinda, e-mail: <email>katarzyna.sklinda@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>A</label><p>Study Design</p></fn><fn id="fn2-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>B</label><p>Data Collection</p></fn><fn id="fn3-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>C</label><p>Statistical Analysis</p></fn><fn id="fn4-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>D</label><p>Data Interpretation</p></fn><fn id="fn5-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>E</label><p>Manuscript Preparation</p></fn><fn id="fn6-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>F</label><p>Literature Search</p></fn><fn id="fn7-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>G</label><p>Funds Collection</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">350698</issue-id><fpage>e927029-1</fpage><lpage>e927029-7</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-01-08 00:16:28.027"><day>08</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Med Sci Monit, 2020</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under Creative Common Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The relative efficacy of carotid endarterectomy (CEA)/thromboendarterectomy (TEA) and carotid artery stenting (CAS) already has been compared in randomized controlled trials and a meta-analysis, but only limited data exist describing the status of cerebral metabolism before and after these interventions.</p><p>The aim of the present study was to compare metabolic changes before and after treatment of carotid stenosis and assess their potential clinical implications.</p></sec><sec><title>Material/Methods</title><p>Patients with asymptomatic unilateral critical internal CAS were imaged with proton 3T magnetic resonance spectroscopy (H-MRS) because the technique is more sensitive than regular magnetic resonance imaging for detection of the early signs of ischemic events. Abnormal metabolite ratios detected with H-MRS may precede actual morphological changes associated with hypoperfusion as well as reperfusion changes. Ipsilateral and contralateral middle cerebral artery vascular territories were both evaluated before and after vascular intervention. H-MRS was performed within 24 h before and after surgery. Correlations in the metabolic data from H-MRS for N-acetylaspartic acid (NAA)+N-acetylaspartylglutamate, creatinine (Cr)+phosphocreatinine, and phosphocholine+glycerophosphocholine (Cho) were sought.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>H-MRS voxels from 11 subjects were analyzed. Values for dCho/CrI, dCho/CrC and Cho/Naal (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) were significantly higher ipsilaterally than contralaterally. Ratios for dNaa/ChoC and Cho/NaaC were significantly higher on the non-operated side (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>H-MRS may be helpful for assessment of patients with CAS, particularly because unlike other modalities, it reveals postoperative changes in metabolic brain status. Initial results indicate the important role of perioperative neuroprotective treatment.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>MeSH Keywords</title><kwd>Brain</kwd><kwd>Carotid Stenosis</kwd><kwd>Hypoxia-Ischemia, Brain</kwd><kwd>Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have found that both carotid endarterectomy (CEA) and carotid artery stenting (CAS) are effective for preventing subsequent stroke or death in patients with critical internal carotid artery (ICA) stenosis that is symptomatic (e.g., the North American Symptomatic Carotid Endarterectomy Trial [NASCET], the European Carotid Surgery Trial, and the International Carotid Stenting Study) or asymptomatic (e.g., the Asymptomatic Carotid Atherosclerosis Study and the Asymptomatic Carotid Surgery Trial [ACT]). The relative effectiveness of CEA and CAS already has been compared in RCTs such as ACT 1 and the Carotid Revascularization Endarterectomy versus Stenting Trial and a meta-analysis. However, only limited data exist describing and/or comparing cerebral metabolism prior to and after use of the 2 methods. The aim of this study was to compare CEA and CAS using data from localized <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> proton 3T magnetic resonance spectroscopy (H-MRS).</p><p>Many studies have shown that CEA and CAS are effective for the management of patients with ICA stenosis. A recent meta-analysis showed that the risk of stroke during long-term follow-up was significantly higher with CAS, buts mostly attributable to minor subclinical periprocedural strokes [<xref rid="b1-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b2-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>Localized <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> H-MRS is a method used to measure the metabolic status of brain tissue [<xref rid="b3-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Because it is noninvasive and more sensitive than regular magnetic resonance imaging for detection of the early signs of ischemic events, H-MRS may be a source of valuable clinical information about vascular interventions. Different metabolite ratios detected by this method may precede actual morphological changes associated with hypoperfusion and reperfusion changes.</p><p>The aim of this study was to compare metabolic changes before and after treatment of ICA stenosis and assess their potential clinical implications. Concentrations of the following metabolites were assessed: NAA (N-acetylaspartic acid+N-acetylaspartylglutamate), Cr (creatinine+phosphocreatine), and Cho (primarily phosphocholine+glycerophosphocholine).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>We designed a prospective study to using H-MRS to compare metabolic changes in vasculature in the territory of the middle cerebral artery (MCA) in 11 patients with critical ICA stenosis undergoing either CEA/TEA or CAS. Patients were evaluated using MRI prior to and 1 to 3 days after the procedure. Both the contralateral and ipsilateral sides were evaluated. The comparison involved initial structural recognition of brain structures based on fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (FLAIR) axial scans. If no exclusion criteria were met, FLAIR images were followed by single-voxel spectroscopy-magnetic resonance spectroscopy (SV-MRS) Point RESolve Spectroscopy (PRESS) with a long echo time (TE) point of 144 ms. All protocols were approved by the Internal Review Board of Central Clinical Hospital of the Ministry of the Interior and Administration and written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p><p>The analyzed parameters included index values on the ipsilateral (I) side (the operated side) for NAA/Cr, Cho/Cr, NAA/Cho, and Cho/NAA before and after surgery (I2), as well as on the contralateral (C) side and in controls (C2). The differences in values before and after the surgery were calculated as delta.</p><p>Of 18 consecutive patients (mean age 77 years) with critical ICA stenosis (&gt;70% reduction in diameter), 9 were eligible for CEA and 2 for CAS, based on CT NASCET criteria [<xref rid="b4-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. According to European Society for Vascular Surgery (ESVS) criteria [<xref rid="b5-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], CEA is the method of choice in patients with ICA stenosis &gt;70%. CAS is considered an option for patients with multiple contraindications to conventional surgical intervention, such as clinically significant cardiac disease, severe pulmonary disease, contralateral carotid occlusion, recurrent stenosis after CEA, previous radical neck surgery, or cervical radiation therapy. Therefore, the number of patients in the study arms differed.</p><p>After surgical qualification, a short MR protocol was followed. In 5 patients, post-ischemic changes were diagnosed within the MCA territory. One patient had severe brain atrophy that caused dilatation of intracranial fluid-filled spaces. One patient refused to undergo control imaging after surgery without providing a reason. The remaining 11 patients were evaluated with H-MRS prior to and 1 to 14 days after the designated procedure. Eleven patients met the final inclusion criteria for the study, namely asymptomatic unilateral critical ICA stenosis (&gt;70% reduction in diameter, based on CT NASCET criteria) with neither clinical nor imaging symptoms of stroke and no contraindications to MRI. Patients included in the study had only low-grade ICA stenosis affecting the contralateral side (&lt;50%). The characteristics of the study group are shown in <xref rid="t1-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p><p>Vascular interventions were carried out by experienced surgeons using heparin, antiplatelet therapy, and appropriate regional anesthesia. All CAS procedures were performed under distal embolic protection. Localized H-MRS was performed on a 3T MR scanner (Ingenia, Philips Healthcare, Best, The Netherlands) and using an Ingenia 3T Scanner Receiver Head Coil.</p><p>After routine scout scans of the head, FLAIR images were acquired in the axial plane. The technician was instructed to pay special attention to symmetric positioning of patient’s head to facilitate further positioning of the voxel. Based on the FLAIR images, patients were qualified for or disqualified from further imaging. Patients were excluded if they had focal lesions within the MCA territory and brain atrophy that caused significant dilatation of brain sulci or ventricles that made subsequent proper voxel placement in the area of interest, such as the basal ganglia, less reliable.</p><p>The spectroscopy protocol was based on 1H-SV (single-voxel) PRESS, with a long TE of 144 ms, a repetition time of 2000 ms, and a flip angle of 90 degrees. Both the ipsilateral and contralateral MCA vascular territories were evaluated. The proposed voxel size in the standard protocol was large (2×2×2 cm) to gain as much signal as possible. The basal ganglia are one of the brain regions most prone to ischemic injury and this voxel position increased the chance of detecting subtle changes. The voxels were carefully placed on the ipsilateral and contralateral side, with attention to symmetry and avoidance of fluid-filled spaces.</p><p>Results were expressed in raw data and also processed using Philips Spectral Analysis software. Because total Cr concentration is the most constant value in H-MR spectroscopy, it was used as an internal reference marker. The relative metabolite ratios (NAA/Cr, Cho/Cr, NAA/Cho, NAA/Cho, Cho/NAA) were subsequently calculated. Patient data, expressed as means±standard deviation [SD], were compared using a <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, which was repeated twice. Any potential correlation was evaluated with a Pearson coefficient. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The patients who underwent TEA were significantly older than those who underwent CAS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001). In the TEA group, the mean preoperative and postoperative values were as follows: NAA/Cr I, 1.68 (range 1.28–2.75) and 1.66 (range 1.09–2.19); NAA/Cr C, 1.95 (range 1.05–4.65) and 1.68 (range 0.89–1.98); Cho/Cr I 1.19 (range 0.76–1.6) and 1.58 (range 0.98–5.58); Ch/Cr C, 1.19 (range 0.82–2.22) and 1.9 (range 0.68–2.25); NAA/Cho I 1.47 (range 1.12–1.96) and 1.87 (range 0.99–4.79); NAA/Cho C, 1.72 (range 1.01–2.99) and 1.78 (range 0.49–4.2); Cho/NAA I, 0.72 (range 0.53–0.96) and 0.63 (range 0.21–1.01); and Cho/NAA C, 0.65 (range 0.33–0.99) and 0.702 (range 0.21–1.12).</p><p>In the CAS group, the mean preoperative and postoperative values were as follows: NAA/Cr I, 2.78 (range 2.22–3.34) and 1.55 (range 1.37–1.64); NAA/Cr C, 1.46 (range 1.38–1.55) and 2.18 (range 1.38–1.81); Cho/Cr, I 1.51 (range 1.22–1.8) and 0.9 (range 0.85–1.02); Ch/Cr C, 0.85 (range 0.67–1.02) and 0.9 (range 0.85–1.02); NAA/Cho I, 1.83 (range 1.82–1.83) and 1.37 (range 1.13–1.61); NAA/Cho C, 1.8 (range 1.55–2.05) and 2.02 (range 1.87–2.17); Cho/NAA I, 0.55 and 0.62; and Cho/NAA C, 0.57 (rage 0.49–0.65) and 0.49 (range 0.46–0.53).</p><p>There was a statistically significant difference between dCho/CrI, dCho/CrC, and dCho/NaaI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) values, all of which were higher on the operated side. The dNaa/Cho value was significantly lower on the operated side (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001).</p><p>The postoperative Cho/Cr index for the ipsilateral site was lower in the older patients.</p><p>Levels of dNaa/ChoC for the ipsilateral side were significantly higher than on the operated side (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001) as were levels of Cho/NaaC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-medscimonit-26-e927029">Figures 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-medscimonit-26-e927029"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-medscimonit-26-e927029"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-medscimonit-26-e927029"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-medscimonit-26-e927029">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>As a clinical neuroimaging modality, H-MRS can provide information about metabolic changes in the brains of patients with CAS that may aid preoperative evaluation of their condition and be helpful for monitoring their postoperative state. The spectra in the present study were obtained from single voxels placed in the region of the basal ganglia, which is an area with known sensitivity to oxygen deficiency. We assessed metabolites that are routinely depicted in the 1 to 5 ppm range of the chemical shift scale, namely NAA+N-acetylaspartylglutamate (neuronal integrity), Cr+phosphocreatine (energy metabolism), Cho (membrane stability), and lactate (anaerobic glycolysis). These metabolites may serve as biomarkers for physiologic and pathologic conditions in the brain. An increase in the Cho/Cr ratio combined with a reduced NAA/Cho ratio could serve as a marker for brain damage in a situation in which the sensitivity and specificity of conventional MRI is insufficient. <italic toggle="yes">Ex vivo</italic> [<xref rid="b6-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and histologic studies [<xref rid="b7-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] have shown that in the mature brain, NAA is present only in neurons, axons, and dendrites – not in glial cells. Therefore, it has been univocally defined as a biomarker for neuronal integrity. tNAA (mainly NAA, with a little from N-acetylaspartylglutamate) is meant to be an <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> biomarker for the presence of viable or damaged neurons [<xref rid="b8-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>The decrease in NAA in the group of patients we studied was unilateral; therefore, we reject neurodegenerative disorders as a possible explanation [<xref rid="b9-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. None of the patients manifested clinical symptoms associated with other known causes of unilateral NAA decrease, such as epilepsy [<xref rid="b10-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and stroke [<xref rid="b11-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Ischemic stroke was excluded based on clinical symptoms as well as the FLAIR images. However, all of the patients had chronic hypoxia followed by rapid blood reperfusion, the biochemical characteristics of which can be seen on MRS. The influence of critical CAS on the human brain has yet to be established. The role of metabolism in reperfusion syndrome also is unclear and the usefulness of MR techniques in assessing it has not been described.</p><p>Patients with these conditions have a chronic reduction in energy substrates, which results in impairment of cell metabolism. Subsequently, a rapid inflow of oxygen and glucose-rich blood occurs and normal cell metabolism is again possible. In some cases, this scenario changes after approximately 24 h and cell death is observed due to a cascade of intracellular factors that leads to mitochondrial dysfunction. In stroke patients, this process has been described based on its gross manifestations on diffusion coefficient maps and MRI. In patients with CAS, it can only be depicted on MRS because blood flow still exists but is slowly deteriorating [<xref rid="b11-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>As the ischemia-reperfusion sequence takes place, the membrane breakdown due to cellular necrosis has pathophysiologic effects. Similar changes have been described in neurodegenerative diseases [<xref rid="b12-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], stroke [<xref rid="b13-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], traumatic injury, and diffuse white matter injury in premature infants [<xref rid="b14-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Routinely used imaging modalities and clinical examination are not sensitive enough to provide evidence of this process. H-MRS, however, shows an increase in the cerebral Cho/Cr ratio on the ipsilateral side.</p><p>The increase in the Cho/Cr ratio seen in the present study was due to increased Cho rather than reduced Cr, as an increase in Cho/NAA coexisted on the same side. An increase in the Cho/Cr ratio has been described in astrogliosis in primates [<xref rid="b15-medscimonit-26-e927029" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>The present study has a number of limitations. First, because it involved single-voxel MRS, regions that experienced chronic hypoperfusion and that may have had a different metabolic signature, such as the cerebral cortex, may have been missed. In that case, a different imaging modality, such as single-photon emission computed tomography, might be worth using because it covers the whole cerebral volume and is sensitive to changes in brain perfusion. Second, we used the contralesional hemisphere as a reference because all of the patients had unilateral critical CAS and underwent unilateral recanalization. It must be stressed, though, that if the integrity of the circle of Willis has not been compromised, the cerebral blood supply from it may be sufficient for the whole cerebrum even if the patency of 1 of the carotids is impaired. A comparison of results in our patients with normal controls (mean age 76 years) could have resulted in errors due to presence of common neurodegenerative disorders and brain atrophy in this age group as well as less severe CAS.</p><p>We did not include in the description of our results changes in lactate level because of errors in assessment of the concentration of that metabolite. The reasons for lack of lactate detection within voxels could include inadequate water suppression, too small voxel size, and limited spectral quality due to head movement.</p><p>Our results should be confirmed in a larger data set and further investigations should follow, using other imaging modalities as well as psychological evaluation, which would be worth evaluating to confirm the relationship between changes in cerebral metabolism and in cognitive function after surgery. Incorporation of diffusion tensor imaging as well as late-delayed comparative imaging might be useful to investigate further development of postoperative cerebral changes, such as asymmetric white matter damage. Volumetric image analysis with segmentation also could enable temporal evaluation of gray and white matter atrophy. To summarize, metabolic changes revealed in patients with asymptomatic unilateral steno-occlusive carotid artery disease may indicate which of them will benefit from endarterectomy through improvement in neurological status. Initial results indicate that perioperative neuroprotective treatment could play an essential role.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although MRS may be difficult to include in a routine preoperative MR protocol, it may provide important information about cerebral metabolic status.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn8-medscimonit-26-e927029"><p><bold>Ethical statement</bold></p><p>The present study was approved by the local Bioethics Committee (Approval no. 54/2016 issued on January 6, 2016 by the Ethics and Surveillance Committee for Research in Human and Animal Sciences at the Central Clinical Hospital of the Ministry of Internal Affairs).</p></fn><fn id="fn9-medscimonit-26-e927029"><p><bold>Source of support:</bold> Departmental sources</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can carotid endarterectomy improve metabolic status in patients with asymptomatic internal carotid artery flow lesion? Studies with localized <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12218960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1067/mva.2002.126555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sardar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aronow</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Carotid artery stenting versus endarterectomy for stroke prevention: A meta-analysis of clinical trials</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>69</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>2266</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28473130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacc.2017.02.053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical applications of magnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>Magn Reson Q</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7873353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasziw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The North American Symptomatic Carotid Endarterectomy Trial: Surgical results in 1415 patients</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>1999</year><volume>30</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1751</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/01.str.30.9.1751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricco</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Borst</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Editor’s Choice – Management of Atherosclerotic Carotid and Vertebral Artery Disease: 2017 Clinical Practice Guidelines of the European Society for Vascular Surgery (ESVS)</article-title><source>Europ J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ejvs.2017.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28851594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tallan</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the distribution of N-acetyl-L-aspartic acid in brain</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1957</year><volume>224</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13398385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moffett</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namboodiri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cangro</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical localization of N-acetylaspartate in rat brain</article-title><source>Neuroreport</source><year>1991</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1768855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00001756-199103000-00005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>N-acetylaspartate decrease in acute stage of ischemic stroke: A perspective from experimental and clinical studies</article-title><source>Magn Reson Med Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25500779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2463/mrms.2014-0039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inglese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-brain N-acetylaspartate as a surrogate marker of neuronal damage in diffuse neurologic disorders</article-title><source>Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1843</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17921226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3174/ajnr.A0774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8134227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wennberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of 1H magnetic resonance spectroscopy in pre-operative evaluation for epilepsy surgery. A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Epilepsy Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>71</volume><issue>2–3</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16890408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2006.06.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Combined (1)H MR spectroscopy and diffusion-weighted MRI improves the prediction of stroke outcome</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2000</year><volume>55</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10953180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/wnl.55.4.498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturrock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laule</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decolongon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy biomarkers in premanifest and early Huntington disease [published correction appears in Neurology, 2011; 76(3): 309]</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2010</year><volume>75</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>1702</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21060093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181fc27e4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3033605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparovic</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy in traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>J Head Trauma Rehabil</source><year>2001</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11275576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00001199-200104000-00005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melbourne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>White matter NAA/Cho and Cho/Cr ratios at MR spectroscopy are predictive of motor outcome in preterm infants</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2014</year><volume>271</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24475798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/radiol.13122679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-medscimonit-26-e927029"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lentz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westmoreland</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationships between astrogliosis and 1H MR spectroscopic measures of brain choline/creatine and myo-inositol/creatine in a primate model</article-title><source>Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15814917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7977133</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Preoperative single-voxel, 144-ms proton 3T brain magnetic resonance spectroscopy in a patient with asymptomatic unilateral right-sided carotid stenosis. (<bold>A</bold>) Ipsilateral side. (<bold>B</bold>) Contralateral side.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f2-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Postoperative single-voxel, 144-ms proton 3T brain magnetic resonance spectroscopy in a patient with asymptomatic unilateral right-sided carotid stenosis. (<bold>A</bold>) Ipsilateral side. (<bold>B</bold>) Contralateral side.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f3-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of delta values for choline/creatine in ipsilateral and contralateral sites. (Subtraction of values before and after surgery.) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f4-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of delta values for choline/N-acetylaspartic acid in the ipsilateral and contralateral sites. (Subtraction of values before and after surgery.) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029-g004.jpg"/></fig><fig id="f5-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of delta values for choline/N-acetylaspartic acid in the ipsilateral and contralateral sites. (Subtraction of values before and after surgery.) <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="medscimonit-26-e927029-g005.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="t1-medscimonit-26-e927029" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the group.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study group</th><th colspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1">N=11</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Gender</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (73%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (27%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Types of surgery</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEA/TEA</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (82%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAS</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (18%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Site of the surgery</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LICA</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (64%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RICA</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (36%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 yrs</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>