
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Clin Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">618</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jeccr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8308647</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research : CR</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0392-9078</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-9966</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7745499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7745499.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7745499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7745499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33334367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-020-01795-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1795</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants regulate proliferation and migration: prognostic implications for muscle invasive bladder cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="S">Sheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitschke</surname><given-names initials="K">Katja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Worst</surname><given-names initials="TS">Thomas Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fierek</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weis</surname><given-names initials="CA">Cleo-Aron</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names initials="M">Markus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porubsky</surname><given-names initials="S">Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kriegmair</surname><given-names initials="M">Maximilian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erben</surname><given-names initials="P">Philipp</given-names></name><address><email>philipp.erben@medma.uni-heidelberg.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7700.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2190 4373</institution-id><institution>Department of Urology and Urosurgery, Medical Faculty Mannheim, </institution><institution>University of Heidelberg, </institution></institution-wrap>68167 Mannheim, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412679.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1771 3402</institution-id><institution>Department of Oncology, </institution><institution>The First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Hefei, 230032 Anhui China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7700.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2190 4373</institution-id><institution>Institute of Pathology, Medical Faculty Mannheim, </institution><institution>University of Heidelberg, </institution></institution-wrap>68167 Mannheim, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5330.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2107 3311</institution-id><institution>Institute of Pathology, University Hospital Erlangen, </institution><institution>Friedrich-Alexander-University Erlangen-Nürnberg, </institution></institution-wrap>91052 Erlangen, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">348838</issue-id><elocation-id>288</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-02 16:25:13.347"><day>02</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13046_2020_Article_1795.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Growing evidence supports the pivotal role of long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) in the regulation of cancer development and progression. Their expression patterns and biological function in muscle invasive bladder cancer (MIBC) remain elusive.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Transcript levels of lncRNA miR-31 host gene (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>) and its splice variants were measured in our MIBC cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 102) by qRT-PCR, and validated in silico by the TCGA cohort (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 370). Kaplan-Meier and multiple Cox regression analysis were conducted to evaluate the survival significance of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants. Functional experiments were performed to examine the proliferation and migration abilities of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants by knockdown approaches.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In this study, a decreased expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was found in bladder cancer cells and tissues, except in the basal subtype. Survival analysis showed that high expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was associated with poor overall survival (OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) in patients with MIBC of basal subtype. Two splice variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> lacking exon 1 (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic>) and exon 3 (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>) were identified to have specific expression patterns in different molecular subtypes of our MIBC cohort. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> was highly expressed in basal subtype tumors. A high expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> was associated with worse OS and DFS in our cohort. In vitro experiments revealed that knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> inhibits cell proliferation, colony formation, and migration in bladder cancer. Cell proliferation and migration assays after knockdown of splice variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> showed corresponding roles for the full-length transcript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Our study demonstrates that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants could serve as biomarkers for the classification and prognosis prediction of patients with MIBC.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13046-020-01795-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>LncRNA</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic></kwd><kwd>Muscle invasive bladder cancer</kwd><kwd>Biomarker</kwd><kwd>Molecular subtype</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par16">Bladder urothelial carcinoma (BLCA) is the tenth most common cancer worldwide with an estimated 550,000 new cases and 200,000 deaths in 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It is widely accepted that BLCA is a heterogeneous disease, which is classified into two distinct subtypes: non-muscle invasive bladder cancer (NMIBC) and muscle invasive bladder cancer (MIBC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. MIBC is responsible for most cases involving metastases leading to death, which arise from 10 to 20% of advanced NMIBC cases, and its clinical management remains limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Currently, several classifications have proposed sets of molecular classes, including basal and luminal subtypes, which are partially characterized by <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In addition, epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) is expressed at high level in basal tumors, involved in controlling the basal gene signature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Although a number of groups have reported molecular classifications of BLCA to evaluate the severity and prognosis of this disease, reliable and effective biomarkers for early diagnosis and prognostic prediction are still lacking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Thus, in-depth understanding of molecular events and underlying mechanisms involved in the carcinogenesis of MIBC may provide effective therapeutic targets and predictive biomarkers, which are urgently needed.</p><p id="Par17">Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) are a class of RNA transcripts, which are longer than 200 nucleotides and do not have protein-coding capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Recent studies have demonstrated that lncRNAs play essential roles in a wide range of biological processes, such as proliferation, apoptosis, cell cycle arrest, cell migration, and invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Furthermore, it has been shown that several lncRNAs are deregulated in many tumors and may be involved in both carcinogenesis and cancer metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Recently, the miR-31 host gene (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, also known as <italic toggle="yes">LOC554202</italic>) has been identified in several cancers, such as breast, colorectal, gastric cancer, and pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. It is also reported that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was down-regulated in BLCA cell lines and tumor tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, the functional role of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its association with molecular classifications in BLCA are as yet unknown.</p><p id="Par18">Despite the continuously growing knowledge on lncRNAs and cancer, a reliable clinical molecular marker has not yet been found. Considering that dysregulation of mRNA splicing can trigger cancer signaling pathways and contribute to almost all hallmarks of cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], the alternative splicing of lncRNAs may also impact cellular processes, which could open new possibilities for biomarker discovery. Previously, it was reported that splice variants of osteopontin have prognostic value in breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In BLCA, CD44 splice variants have been demonstrated to be involved in tumor progression and chemosensitivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In addition, the lncRNA <italic toggle="yes">PVT1</italic> and its splice variant are highly expressed in clear cell renal cell carcinoma, and function as oncogenic transcripts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. These findings advocate for the use of lncRNAs and their splice variants as tissue-specific transcripts and promising prognostic biomarkers in certain cancers. However, the precise function of most lncRNAs and the mechanisms of their molecular regulation remains to be elucidated.</p><p id="Par19">In this study, the expression level and clinicopathologic significance of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> were first evaluated by in silico database analysis and then by qRT-PCR in a cohort from our institution. Upon knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, a series of in vitro experiments was performed to investigate the effects of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> on proliferation, colony formation, and migration of BLCA cells. Transcript-specific knockdown with consecutive cell functional assays were performed to determine the role of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> splice variants and to investigate their association with molecular subtypes of MIBC. Further survival analyses were carried out to determine if <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants could be used as prognostic biomarkers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patients and tissue samples</title><p id="Par20">This study retrospectively enrolled 102 patients who received radical cystectomy (RC) at the Department of Urology and Urosurgery of the University Medical Centre Mannheim, between 2008 and 2012, and who had a histological diagnosis of MIBC (males: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 74, 73%, median age: 71 years, range: 41–88 years; females: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28, 27%, median age: 73 years, range: 47–86 years; Mannheim cohort). All patients were treated with RC and bilateral lymphadenectomy without preoperative chemotherapy or radiotherapy. With the help of the clinic’s internal documentation program, the following parameters were collected after examination of the pathology findings: sex, age, T-stage, N-stage, M-stage, grading, lymphovascular invasion (LVI), blood vessel invasion (VI), simultaneous carcinoma in situ (CIS), multifocality, and soft tissue positive surgical margin.</p><p id="Par21">Formalin fixed paraffin embedded (FFPE) tumor tissue samples were evaluated for pathological stage according to the 2017 TNM classification from the Union for International Cancer Control (UICC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Tumors were graded using the 2017 WHO/ISUP classification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Studies involving human participants were approved by the ethical board of the University of Heidelberg (2015-549 N-MA) and performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. The Cancer Genome Atlas cohort (TCGA, Provisional) contained RNA sequencing data of 407 patients with MIBC and complete clinicopathological and follow-up data (males: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 300, 73.7%, median age: 68 years, range: 34–90 years; females: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 107, 26.3%, median age: 72 years, range: 43–90 years; TCGA cohort). Thirty-seven patients with tumor stage T1 or not defined T stage were excluded from the survival analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 370).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Database</title><p id="Par22">Expression data in transcripts per million (TPM) of 25 human bladder cancer cell lines were collected from the Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was analyzed by Expression Atlas (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/home">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/gxa/home</ext-link>) and normalized by TPM. Transcript expression data of 370 BLCA samples and 21 normal samples were collected from TCGA (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tcga-data.nci.nih.gov/tcga/">https://tcga-data.nci.nih.gov/tcga/</ext-link>) and analyzed by cBioPortal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbioportal.org/">http://www.cbioportal.org/</ext-link>), which normalized the samples by reads per kilobase million (RPKM) and log2 transformation. Expression of transcripts, exons and junctions was collected and analyzed using the Xena online exploration tool (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://xena.ucsc.edu/">https://xena.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>) and TSVdb (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tsvdb.com">http://www.tsvdb.com</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The lncRNA-protein interactions were analyzed by lncPro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. lncPro yields a score using amino acid and nucleotide sequences. This score can be used to measure the interaction between a pair of lncRNA and protein. The sequence of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and protein sequences were obtained from the NCBI database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par23">In this study six different cell lines were used, including a normal human urothelium cell line (UROtsa), a basal-like urothelial carcinoma cell line (SCaBER), two luminal-like urothelial carcinoma cell lines (RT112 and RT4), and two mixed-type urothelial carcinoma cell lines (UMUC3 and T24). UROtsa cells were cultured in Roswell Park Memorial Institute medium (RPMI) supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum (FBS). RT112, RT4, SCaBER, and UMUC3 cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) containing 10% FBS. T24 cells were cultured in McCoy’s 5A medium containing 10% FBS. UMUC3, SCaBER, RT112, and T24 cells were obtained from the European Collection of Authenticated Cell Cultures (ECACC), RT4 from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC), and UROtsa cells from a collaborator. Before starting the experiments, all cell lines were authenticated by Multiplexion (Heidelberg, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>siRNA transfection</title><p id="Par24">A pool of four different small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) against <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> (designated si-<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, set of 4), and transcript-specific siRNAs against <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> were transfected into urothelial cells using the DharmaFECT1 siRNA transfection reagent (GE Healthcare Dharmacon, Inc., CO, USA). Scrambled siRNA was used as negative control. All sequences of the siRNAs are listed in Table S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p id="Par25">Cell viability was analyzed using the 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium (MTS) assay (Promega, Wis, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions with six replicates. MTS solution was added at 0, 24, 48, and 72 h after different siRNA transfections and the absorbance was measured using a microplate reader at 492 nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Colony formation assay</title><p id="Par26">For colony formation assays, urothelial cells were seeded in six-well plates at a concentration of 5000 cells per well in triplicates, and cultured for 7 days before staining viable colonies with crystal violet (Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany). The staining intensity of the colonies was quantitated using ImageJ software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Migration assay</title><p id="Par27">Cell migration was evaluated by a wound-healing assay. Cells were seeded in cell culture inserts (ibidi GmbH, Munich, Germany) and the open wound area was measured after 12 h. The proportion of the wound area was quantitated using TScratch software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>RNA extraction and qRT-PCR</title><p id="Par28">Total RNA of cells was isolated using RNeasy Mini kits (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. For FFPE tissues, RNA was extracted and enriched using the magnetic-bead-based XTRAKT FFPE Kit (Stratifyer, Cologne, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Next, reverse transcription was performed for cell samples using the M-MLV Reverse Transcriptase kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), and for FFPE samples using the Superscript III reverse transcriptase kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) with sequence-specific primers. qPCR was used to measure relative mRNA expression with TaqMan Fast Advanced Master Mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). β-Glucuronidase (GUS) and calmodulin2 (Calm2) were measured as reference genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The relative mRNA expression level was normalized to reference genes and determined using the 40-∆CT or 2<sup>-∆∆CT</sup> method for cell culture samples and FFPE samples, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. All primers and probes used in this study are shown in Table S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par29">Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 20.0 software (IBM, Chicago, IL, USA) and GraphPad Prism 6.0 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, USA). A Kolmogorov–Smirnov (K-S) test was used to determine whether the data were normally distributed. Student’s t-tests were used to compare groups of normally distributed numerical data, while the Mann–Whitney U and Kruskal–Wallis tests were used to compare non-normally distributed numerical data. Linear regression was used to determine the efficiency of amplification. Spearman tests were used to test the correlation between different gene expressions. The cut-off values of the high and low <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression groups were determined by receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis in the Mannheim cohort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Similarly, in the TCGA cohort, the cut-off value (log2 value) of high and low <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression groups were determined by ROC curve analysis. The Cox regression model was used for univariable and multivariable analysis to calculate hazard ratio (HR). For multivariable analysis, parameters with a cut-off value of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.2 inform the univariable analysis were included. The expression of <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> was used as a marker for basal phenotype. High <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> and low <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> were defined as expression above and below median. Survival rates of patients were calculated using the Kaplan–Meier method, and comparisons were made with the log-rank test. In all cases, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>MIR31HG expression was subtype-specific in bladder cancer tissues and cell lines</title><p id="Par30">First, in silico analyses of expression of MIR31HG were performed. In the TCGA dataset, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was down-regulated in MIBC (median expression 0.2435, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 370) compared to normal tissues (median expression 0.3549, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0002, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Patients with BLCA in the TCGA cohort were classified into basal/squamous, luminal, luminal-infiltrated, luminal-papillary and neuronal subtypes according to mRNA clustering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Among all subtypes, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in basal/squamous (median expression 7.10 with range of 0 to 9.96) subtype was the most abundant, which was higher than in luminal (median expression 3.16 with range of 0.13 to 6.8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), luminal-infiltrated (median expression 4.99 with range of 0 to 9.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), luminal-papillary (median expression 5.53 with range of 0 to 9.92, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0002), and neuronal (median expression 4.92 with range of 0 to 8.7, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0215) subtypes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). By clustering according to a trichotomous molecular classifications based on an alternative mRNA clustering of the TCGA cohort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], it is also determined that the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was higher in the basal subtype (median expression 7.10 with range of 0 to 9.96) compared to the luminal (median expression 5.21 with range of 0 to 10.16) and infiltrated (median expression 4.99 with range of 0 to 9.16) subtypes (Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>A). Furthermore, due to the significance of lymph node metastasis in MIBC cohort, the expression of MIR31HG in different lymph node status was analyzed. No significant difference was found between lymph node metastasis negative and positive groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.2650, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>B).
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in BLCA tissue samples and cell lines. <bold>a</bold> In the TCGA cohort data, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was down-regulated (median expression 0.2435) in tumors compared with normal tissues (median expression 0.3549). <bold>b</bold> In the TCGA cohort, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was higher in basal/squamous (median expression 7.10 with range of 0 to 9.96) subtype compared to luminal (median expression 3.16 with range of 0.13 to 6.8), luminal-infiltrated (median expression 4.99 with range of 0 to 9.16), luminal-papillary (median expression 5.53 with range of 0 to 9.92), and neuronal (median expression 4.92 with range of 0 to 8.7) subtypes. <bold>c</bold> In a normal urothelial cell line (UROtsa) and five BLCA cell lines (SCaBER, UMUC3, T24, RT112 and RT4), expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was detected by qPCR. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was significantly lower in UMUC3 and T24 cells, and higher in SCaBER cells compared to UROtsa cells. The lowest <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was observed in RT112 and RT4 cells</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was also detected in a normal urothelial cell line (UROtsa) and three BLCA cell lines (SCaBER, UMUC3 and T24) by qRT-PCR. Significantly lower expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was observed in UMUC3 (mean expression 33.59, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0003) and T24 cells (mean expression 32.34, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared with UROtsa cells (mean expression 34.01). In contrast, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was higher in SCaBER cells (mean expression 35.53, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0200) compared to UROtsa cells. The lowest level of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was observed in RT112 (mean expression 21.03, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and RT4 cells (mean expression 23.64, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was analyzed in RNA-seq data from the Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia containing 25 BLCA cell lines, including 20 bladder urothelial cell carcinomas, a bladder squamous cell carcinoma, and four bladder carcinoma cell lines from unknown primaries. The data showed that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression levels in SCaBER cells (expression level: 10 TPM) were higher than in RT112 (expression level: 0 TPM), RT4 (expression level: 0 TPM), and UMUC3 cells (expression level: 3 TPM, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>C).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Identification and expression of two splice variants of MIR31HG</title><p id="Par32">Demographic and clinical-pathological data of the 102 patients with MIBC included in the Mannheim cohort are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Median follow-up of the entire cohort was 21 months (range 3–121 months) and the median follow-up of surviving patients was 50 months (range 9–121 months). In total, 52 patients (50.98%) suffered a relapse (local relapse <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, lymph nodes and/or distant metastases <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 36, unclear metastasis pattern <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10). Of the 56 (54.90%) patients who died during the follow-up, 38 (37.25%) of them died because of BLCA.
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinicopathological characteristics of patients and specimens of the Mannheim cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinicopathological Features</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt; 70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> ≥70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stage</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> T2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> T3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> T4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lymph node metastasis</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Negative</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Undefined</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par33">Four transcript variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> were retrieved from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) nucleotide database. Transcript variant 1 (RefSeq ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NR_027054.2">NR_027054.2</ext-link>) is the full transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, containing four exons and three junctions. For simplification, transcript variant 2 (RefSeq ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NR_152877.1">NR_152877.1</ext-link>) lacking exon 1 was named <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic>, and transcript variant 4 (RefSeq ID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NR_152879.1">NR_152879.1</ext-link>) lacking exon 3 was named <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>. Transcript-specific primers for each splice variant were designed and are listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>. A model of the gene sequence of the <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> transcript (ENST00000304425.3) and its two splice variants, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>, is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a. In the Mannheim cohort, a significantly higher expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> (median expression 34.7) was found compared to the transcripts, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (median expression 35.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0187) and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> (median expression 36.7, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0001, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> junction 3, which reflects <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression, was significant higher in the basal (median expression 0.6267) compared to the luminal (median expression 0.3478) subtype in the TCGA cohort (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0081, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). As the expression of <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> can be used as a marker for basal and luminal phenotypes, respectively, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was analyzed in terms of <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> dependent expression. High <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> (Ct value &gt; 36.55) and high <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> (Ct value &gt; 34.12) were defined as expression above median. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> expression was higher in the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0395, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d), and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression was higher in the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1514, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e).
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and two splice variants in the BLCA cohort. <bold>a</bold> Gene model of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> transcript and splice variants <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>. <bold>b</bold> In the Mannheim cohort, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> (median expression 34.7) was significantly higher than in the splice variants, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (median expression 35.5) and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> (median expression 36.7). <bold>c</bold> In the TCGA cohort, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> was significantly higher in basal (median expression 0.6267) compared to luminal (median expression 0.3478) subtype. <bold>d</bold> In the Mannheim cohort, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> was higher in the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> group compared to the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> group. <bold>e</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression was higher in the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> group compared to the high <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> group in the Mannheim cohort</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO2" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>MIR31HG expression was associated with copy-number alterations</title><p id="Par34">The in silico analysis of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> copy-number alterations revealed a genetic alteration rate of 25% (92/370). Putative copy-number alterations including deep/shallow deletion, diploid, gain, and amplification were acquired from the GISTIC (Genomic Identification of Significant Targets in Cancer) algorithm. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> showed 56.76% of shallow/deep deletion (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 210), 31.62% of diploid (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 117), and 11.62% of gain/amplification (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 43, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was significantly higher in the subgroup with gain (median expression 7.46, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and diploid (median expression 7.12, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) compared to those with a deletion alteration (median expression 4.77, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). High expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was found in the subgroup with deletion and diploid alteration than in gain (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 47, 20.44% in gain; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 99, 43.04% in diploid; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 84, 36.52% in deletion), while low expression was observed in the subgroup with deletion alteration, compared to diploid and gain (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 15, 8.67% with gain; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 28, 16.18% with diploid; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 130, 75.15% with deletion, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression in association with copy-number alterations. <bold>a</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> showed 56.76% of shallow/deep deletion, 31.62% of diploid and 11.62% of gain/amplification. <bold>b</bold> Significantly higher expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was observed in the subgroup with gain (median expression 7.46) and diploid (median expression 7.12) compared to deletion (median expression 4.77). <bold>c</bold> High expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was observed in the subgroup with deletion and diploid than in gain (n = 47, 20.44% in gain; n = 99, 43.04% in diploid; n = 84, 36.52% in deletion), while low expression was observed in the subgroup with deletion compared to diploid and gain (n = 15, 8.67% in gain; n = 28, 16.18% in diploid; n = 130, 75.15% in deletion)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO3" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>MIR31HG as prognostic marker for patients with basal subtype</title><p id="Par35">After the analysis of gene expression and copy-number alterations of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, the association with clinical outcome and parameters was analyzed in the TCGA and the Mannheim cohort. The expression of MIR31HG showed no significant correlation with overall survival (OS) and disease free survival (DFS) in the full TCGA cohort (Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Interestingly, survival analysis showed that patients of the TCGA cohort with basal subtype were significantly associated with OS and DFS based on <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> risk stratification. The group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression showed a worse OS compared to the group with low expression (median survival, 28 vs. 16 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0073, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Furthermore, the group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression showed a worse DFS compared to the group with low expression (median survival, 27 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1379, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier plot of overall survival (OS) and disease free survival (DFS) were associated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> risk stratification. <bold>a</bold> In the TCGA cohort with basal subtype, the group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression showed a worse OS compared to the group with low expression (median survival, 28 vs. 16 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0073). <bold>b</bold> In the TCGA cohort with basal subtype, the group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression showed a worse DFS compared to the group with low expression (median survival, 27 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1379). The numbers below the figures showed the number of patients at risk in each group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO4" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Splice variants of MIR31HG as prognostic markers for patients</title><p id="Par36">In the Mannheim cohort, Kaplan-Meier analysis and the log-rank test were used to evaluate the association of the expression of two <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> splice variants with OS and DFS. For the full-length transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, no significant difference in OS (median survival 18 vs. 21 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.2032, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) and DFS (median survival 11 vs. 9 months for <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.7365, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b) was found between high and low expression levels. Tumors with both high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (median survival 15 vs. 38 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0315, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c) and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression (median survival 12 vs. 30 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0024, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e) showed a worse OS. The groups with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (median survival 7 vs. 25 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0134, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d) and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> (median survival 9 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.1008, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f) expression also showed a worse DFS. Tumors with high expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> Exon1–2 (Junction 3), which could partially present as <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>, showed a worse OS than the group with low expression, in the TCGA cohort with basal subtype (median survival 15 vs. 17 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0298, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>A). No significant difference was found for DFS (median survival 12 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.5670, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>B).
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier plot of the Mannheim cohort of OS and DFS associated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants risk stratification. No significant correlation was found with OS (<bold>a</bold>, median survival 18 vs. 21 months) and DFS (<bold>b</bold>, median survival 11 vs. 9 months for <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>) in the group with full-length transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. The group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> expression showed a worse OS (<bold>c</bold>, median survival 15 vs. 38 months) and DFS (<bold>d</bold>, median survival 7 vs. 25 months) compared to the group with low expression. The group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression showed a worse OS (<bold>e</bold>, median survival 12 vs. 30 months) and DFS (F, median survival 9 vs. 15 months) compared to the group with low expression. The numbers below the figures showed the number of patients at risk in each group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO5" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">Similar to the analysis of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in the TCGA cohort, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants were also analyzed regarding to OS and DFS in patients from Mannheim with basal subtype (high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> expression). No significant differences were found in OS (median survival 18 vs. 20 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.6664, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>A) and DFS (median survival 17 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.8690, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>B) between high and low expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, also in high and low expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (median survival 15 vs. 18 months for OS, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.2338, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>C; median survival 29 vs. 17 months for DFS, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.5984, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>D). Significant difference with OS was found between high and low expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> in the basal subtype cohort (median survival 13 vs. 22 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0194, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>E). Yet, no significant correlation was found with DFS (median survival 15 vs. 36 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.3427, Fig. S<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>F).</p><p id="Par38">In the univariable Cox regression analysis, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0063) and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0114) expression as well as the stage of cancer (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0092) were found to be predictive for patient outcome. In the multivariable Cox regression analysis, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> was identified as an independent prognostic factor (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0090), similar as stage (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0243). No significant differences of OS were found between basal (high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic>) and non-basal (low <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic>) group in the univariable analysis. However, no significant correlation was observed between the full-length transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> regarding to OS of the patients in the univariable analysis, nor with patient age, patient gender, lymph node status, and LVI (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Univariable and multivariable cox regression analysis of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants with clinicopathological features in the Mannheim cohort (<italic toggle="yes">HR</italic> hazard ratio, <italic toggle="yes">CI</italic> confidence interval, <italic toggle="yes">LVI</italic> lymphovascular invasion, <italic toggle="yes">Basal</italic> high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> expression, <italic toggle="yes">Non-basal</italic> low <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> expression, significant <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values are bold)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Factor</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Univariable</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariable</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">HR (95%CI)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis Age</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &lt;70 vs. ≥70</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.701(0.406–1.212)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2041</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male vs. Female</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.980(0.535–1.795)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9485</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Stage</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> T2 vs. T3/4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.401(0.202–0.797)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0092</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.445(0.220–0.900)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0243</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>LVI</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Negative vs. Positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.550(0.075–4.050)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5570</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Lymphnode Status</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Negative vs. Positive</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.547(0.245–1.221)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1418</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.694(0.243–1.987)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4961</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold>Molecular Subtype</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Basal vs. Non-basal</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.202(0.596–2.422)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6073</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low vs. High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.720(0.681–4.347)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2522</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low vs. High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.753(1.457–9.664)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0063</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.896(0.831–4.329)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1294</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Low vs. High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.522(1.235–5.149)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0114</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.805(1.293–6.083)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0090</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>MIR31HG is required for BLCA tumorigenesis</title><p id="Par39">To evaluate the possible role of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in BLCA, a pool of four siRNAs against <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> (designated si-<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, set of 4) were transfected in T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells. Each transfection resulted in a sufficient knocked down of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression. Cell viability was determined using the MTS assay based on absorbance at 490 nm after 0, 24, 48, and 72 h. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown by siRNA showed lower cellular viability at three time points compared to the control group transfected with scramble siRNA (si-NC, Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a-c). Moreover, colony formation was detected by culturing cells in a 6-well plate and stained with crystal violet after 7 days. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed fewer cell colonies compared to the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d). The staining intensity of the colony formation assay was quantified by calculating the colony intensity percentage. BLCA cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed a reduced formation of colonies compared to the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>e). Migration was detected by a wound-healing assay. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed a larger open wound area compared with the control group after 12 h (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>f). The difference in open wound area after 12 h was quantified by calculating the percentage of change in the open wound area (open wound area at 12 h - open wound area at 0 h). BLCA cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed fewer changes in open wound area compared with the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>g).
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> is required for BLCA tumorigenesis. <bold>a</bold>-<bold>c</bold> Cell viability was quantified using the MTS assay. T24 (A), UMUC3 (<bold>b</bold>) and SCaBER (<bold>c</bold>) cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown by siRNA showed lower cellular viability compared with control group with scramble siRNA (si-NC). <bold>d</bold> Colony formation was detected by measuring the stained cells after 7 days. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed fewer cell colonies compared to control group. <bold>e</bold> Staining intensity percentage of colony formation assay was analyzed by ImageJ software. BLCA cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed decreased staining intensity compared with control group. <bold>f</bold> Wound healing assay was measured using cell culture inserts. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed more open wound area compared with control group after 12 h. <bold>g</bold> Open wound area was quantified by calculating the percentage of change in open wound area after 12 h. BLCA cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown showed fewer changes in open wound area compared to the control group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO6" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Two splice variants of MIR31HG regulate BLCA growth with cell specificity</title><p id="Par40">To further evaluate the possible role of the transcripts <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> in BLCA, transcript-specific siRNAs were transfected into BLCA cells. Cell viability was quantified by MTS assay based on absorbance at 490 nm after 0, 24, 48, and 72 h. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown by specific siRNA showed decreased cellular viability with cell specificity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a-c). <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> knockdown showed significantly decreased absorbance in T24 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0018, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a) and UMUC3 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0029, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b) cells after 72 h, and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown resulted in a significant decrease in absorbance in SCaBER (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0346, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c) cells exclusively after 72 h. Colony formation was detected by culturing cells in 6-well plates and staining with crystal violet after 7 days. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown by specific siRNA showed fewer cell colonies with cell specificity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d). T24 and UMUC3 cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> knockdown showed a significantly reduced staining intensity compared with control transfected cells. SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown showed significantly decreased staining intensity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>e). Migration was detected with a wound healing assay using cell culture inserts. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown by specific siRNA showed a larger open wound area compared with cell specificity after 12 h (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>f). The difference in open wound area after 12 h was quantified by calculating the percentage of change in open wound area (open wound area 12 h - open wound area 0 h). T24 and UMUC3 cells showed fewer changes in open wound area, both in the <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown groups. SCaBER cells showed fewer changes in the open wound area upon <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>g).
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Two splice variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> are required for BLCA tumorigenesis with cell specificity. (A-C) Cell viability was quantified using the MTS assay. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> knockdown showed a significant decrease in absorbance in T24 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0018, <bold>a</bold> and UMUC3 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0029, <bold>b</bold> cells, and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown showed a significant decrease in absorbance in SCaBER (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0346, <bold>c</bold> cells after 72 h. <bold>d</bold> Colony formation was detected by measuring cell staining after 7 days. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown by specific siRNA showed fewer cell colonies with cell specificity. <bold>e</bold> Staining intensity percentage of colony formation assay was analyzed by ImageJ sofware. T24 and UMUC3 cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> knockdown and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown showed a significant decrease in staining intensity compared to the control group. <bold>f</bold> Wound healing assay was measured using cell culture inserts. T24, UMUC3, and SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown by specific siRNA showed a larger open wound area compared with cell specificity after 12 h. <bold>g</bold> Difference in open wound area was quantified by calculating the percentage of change in open wound area after 12 h. T24 and UMUC3 cells showed fewer changes in the open wound area, in both <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown groups. SCaBER cells showed fewer changes in the open wound area in the <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> knockdown group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO7" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> is associated with EGFR pathway</title><p id="Par41">To discover the potential mechanisms underlying the functions of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, the related proteins were focused on EGFR, which was reported as a molecular signature of basal or squamous-like bladder cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The lncRNA-protein interactions of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and EGFR were analyzed by lncPro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and predicted 9 Isoforms of EGFR interacting. Besides EGFR and its isoforms, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was predicted as interactive with phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K) and receptor tyrosine-protein kinase erbB-2 (HER2) protein (score above 50, Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Interaction scores of EGFR, PI3K HER2 protein and MIR31HG</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protein</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.4935</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform a</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0794</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform b</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.4501</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform c</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.9972</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform d</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.8757</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform e</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.5006</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform f</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.7342</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform g</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.3893</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform h</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.7141</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR isoform i</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.5429</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PI3K</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.5458</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 isoform a</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.9194</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 isoform b</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.7639</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 isoform c</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.0902</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 isoform d</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.6083</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 isoform e</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.4699</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par42">To further reveal the interaction with the coded gene, gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> was detected in <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown cells. Significantly higher expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> was observed in SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0367, Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). No significant difference of expression was observed between T24 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.4086) and UMUC3 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.4734) cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown and control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> in BLCA cell lines with MIR31HG knockdown. To narrow the differences in <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> expression between cell lines, the 2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup> values of expression data in T24, UMUC3 and SCaBER cells were normalized by the expression data in UROtsa. <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> expression was significantly higher in SCaBER cells with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> knockdown compared to negative siRNA group. Expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> showed no significant difference between T24 and UMUC3 cells with MIR31HG knockdown and negative siRNA group</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="MO8" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par43">This study aimed to investigate the expression pattern and biological function of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in MIBC, as well as its clinical significance and prognostic value in patients. In order to evaluate its role in tumorigenesis and progression, functional in vitro assays were combined with lncRNA expression analysis based on molecular subtypes and relevant clinicopathologic parameters.</p><p id="Par44">In previous studies on multifarious tumors, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> showed a tissue-specific expression pattern. In breast cancer and non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cells, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was upregulated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In gastric cancer tissues and cell lines, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was poorly expressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Another study showed that MIR31HG level is substantially upregulated in oral carcinoma, significantly associated with poor clinical outcomes and representing an independent prognostic predictor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In our study, lower <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> transcript levels were found in luminal-like and mixed-type BLCA cell lines compared with a normal urothelium cell line. Accordingly, down-regulated <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression was found in cancer tissues compared to normal tissues, which supports expression results measured by qPCR from a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, the previous results were measured in stage- and type-mixed BLCA tissues, and in this study, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was measured in MIBC and associated with multiple molecular subtype respectively. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was found to be highly expressed in cells lines and clinical tumor samples with the basal subtype compared to luminal and other subtypes, indicating that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> not only shows tissue specific, but also subtype-specific overexpression in MIBC.</p><p id="Par45">In contrast to a previous study, which reported that <italic toggle="yes">miR-31</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> are down-regulated in triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) cell lines of basal subtype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], the present study shows that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> is highly expressed in the BLCA cell line of basal subtype and markedly correlates with the survival of patients with MIBC basal subtype. This might be due to tissue specific expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. In this study, two MIBC cohorts with multiple molecular subtypes were involved rather than single cell line, which may also lead to the dissimilar results. Further studies of BLCA preclinical models are needed for validation. It is noteworthy that two transcript variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>) were identified and their expression was analyzed in BLCA cells and MIBC tissues. Besides the different expression levels in MIBC patient tissues, the two splice variants showed distinguished expression patterns in basal and luminal subtypes, respectively. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> showed high expression in the basal subtype, both in the TCGA cohort and the Mannheim cohort, which is also observed for the group with high <italic toggle="yes">KRT5</italic> expression. In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> showed high expression in luminal subtype tumors in the Mannheim cohort, corresponding to tumors with a high <italic toggle="yes">KRT20</italic> expression.</p><p id="Par46">Additionally, higher <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> transcript levels were found to be associated with worse OS and DFS in the basal subtype cohort, but not in the whole TCGA cohort. It is the first time to discover the prognostic value of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in BLCA, or associated with subtypes of tumors. Furthermore, expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> was significantly associated with OS and DFS in the Mannheim cohort, rather than the full-length transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. In the TCGA cohort, it was demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression was significantly associated with OS of the basal subtype group. These results, together with univariable and multivariable Cox regression analysis suggested that the alternative splice variants of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> may serve as potential biomarkers for certain molecular subtypes of MIBC, which could contribute to an individualized bladder cancer subclassification and therapy decision making. It is worth noting that lymph node status is not associated with OS based on survival analysis, which is controversial to other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The possible reasons could be limited number of patients, diverse distribution of lymph node status and T stages as well as different scale of lymph node examination. Therefore, validation in larger patient cohorts with long-term follow-up is needed. In the Mannheim cohort, few patients were treated with neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy. For further validation, the number of positive lymph nodes and chemotherapy status should be also taken into consideration.</p><p id="Par47">Two groups independently recognized the significance of a distinct basal MIBC subtype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. According to classification of the TCGA, basal tumors were divided into two subsets that were largely distinguished by differential expression of biomarkers associated with EMT, which is a reversible developmental process by promoting invasion, metastasis, “stemness”, and drug resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The potential significance of the mesenchymal basal BLCA was identified using a “claudin-low” gene expression signature in breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. A previous study reported that tumor suppressor microRNA-361 was de-repressed by <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in osteosarcoma cells, leading to cell growth and mesenchymal phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. These results may indicate that high expression <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> could be served as a surrogate marker of poor outcome defined by relative activation of EMT and sponge of tumor suppressor. The discovery that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> is highly expressed and significantly outcome-correlated in MIBC with basal subtype, has complemented the selection of MIBC markers.</p><p id="Par48">Due to its potential clinical relevance as a marker, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its underlying biological functions could be vital to the tumor. In this study, by knocking down <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> expression using siRNA, diminished cell proliferation, colony formation, and migration were assessed in BLCA cell lines. This study is the first to highlight the function of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in BLCA cells, which indicates that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> might serve as an oncogene in certain types of BLCA. With the in-depth study of MIR31HG, several downstream targets were found in present researches. For example, it is reported that overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> significantly decreased the expression of miR-575, enhanced the suppression of tumorigenicity 7 like (ST7L) in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). Thus, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> regulated <italic toggle="yes">ST7L</italic> expression through sponging miR-575, and acted as tumor suppressor in HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Another published research showed that the level of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) tissues was positively correlated with the expression of furin and matrix metalloproteinase 1 (MMP1). When <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was silenced, the expressions of furin and <italic toggle="yes">MMP1</italic> in ESCC cells were significantly inhibited. These results suggest that the involvement of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in invasion and migration of ESCC cell may be partly achieved through the furin / <italic toggle="yes">MMP1</italic> pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In a study in oral cancer, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was identified as a hypoxia-inducible lncRNA and forms a complex with hypoxia-inducible factor-1 α (HIF-1α), thus as an adverse prognostic predictor for the cancer progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In addition, it was reported that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> could function as an oncogene that promotes pancreatic cancer progression, by acting as an endogenous sponge competing for miR-193b [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Similarly, it was shown that silencing of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> significantly inhibited NSCLC cell migration, invasion, and metastasis by attenuated sponging of miR-214 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The various mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> suggest that downstream pathways could be involved with other non-coding RNAs, which requires further verification. In this study, similar to the full-length transcript, a series of functional experiments validated the corresponding roles in certain types of BLCA cells. The knock-down of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> resulted in reduced colony formation ability and cell viability solely in SCaBER cells, suggesting that exon-specific or transcript-specific mechanisms could be a new direction in studying basal-like BLCA. Recently, emerging data have demonstrated that RNA splice variants are associated with drug resistance in cancer. The expression of androgen receptor (AR) splicing variants in castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) samples increased significantly. The most common AR splicing variants are AR-V7 and ARv567es [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. These variants are important factors for insensitive to AR antagonists of CRPC patients. Furthermore, splice variants in V600E BRAF-mutant-positive malignant melanoma patients were shown to be associated with vemurafenib resistance, indicating that aberrant splicing could be a novel mechanism of acquired resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Furthermore, interference of the pre-mRNA splicing modulators sufficiently inhibited formation of these splice variants, suggesting that splice variant-specific siRNAs may be proposed as a therapeutic strategy to overcome drug resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">For basal or squamous-like bladder cancer, molecular signatures were found based on clustering RNA-seq data, including <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> is overexpressed in up to 74% of bladder cancer tissue specimens, and is amplified in squamous cell carcinomas (SCC) of the bladder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. To further investigate the potential relationship between <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic>, a computational method called lncPro was applied to predict the associations within. All the nine isoforms of EGFR, as well as PI3K and HER2 protein, were predicted as interactive with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. The positive interaction score suggested that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> might be involved in the EGFR/PI3K/AKT signaling pathway. Furthermore, expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> was detected in three <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>-knockdown BLCA cell lines. In SCaBER cells, which shows the basal / squamous signature, expression of <italic toggle="yes">EGFR</italic> was reversely correlated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. According to another study on lung cancer, by knocking down <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>, reversal of gefitinib resistance was found by regulation of the EGFR/PI3K/AKT signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Taken together, these findings suggested that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> might potentially correlate with the EGFR pathway.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par50">In summary, our data show that <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was highly expressed in basal subtype cells and tissues of MIBC. <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants (<italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic>) could regulate proliferation and migration of corresponding BLCA cells. Furthermore, in different MIBC cohorts, <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants were associated with survival of different subgroups of patients. Our research provides new insights into studies for the molecular classification of MIBC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13046_2020_1795_MOESM1_ESM.zip" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Fig. S1.</bold> Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in BLCA tissue samples and cell lines based on in silico data. (A) Expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> was higher in basal (median expression 7.10 with range of 0 to 9.96) subtype than in luminal (median expression 5.21 with range of 0 to 10.16) and infiltrated (median expression 4.99 with range of 0 to 9.16) subtypes in patients of the TCGA cohort. (B) No significant difference of MIR31HG expression was found between lymph node metastasis negative and positive groups. (C) RNA-seq data from the Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia showed expression levels in TPM (transcripts per million) for <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> in 25 BLCA cell lines. <bold>Fig. S2.</bold> Kaplan-Meier plot of the TCGA cohort of OS and DFS associated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> risk stratification. The group with high or low expression of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> showed no significant correlation with OS (A, median survival, 16 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.9638) and DFS (B, median survival, 15 vs. 17 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.4175) in the whole TCGA cohort. The numbers below the figures showed the number of patients at risk in each group. <bold>Fig. S3.</bold> Kaplan-Meier plot of the TCGA cohort with basal subtype of overall survival associated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> Exon1–2 (Junction 3) risk stratification. (A) The group with high Junction 3 expression showed worse OS than the group with low expression (median survival, 17 vs. 14 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0298). (B) No significant difference was observed in DFS between the group with high and low Junction 3 expression (median survival, 17 vs. 15 months, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.5670). The numbers below the figures showed the number of patients at risk in each group. <bold>Fig. S4.</bold> Kaplan-Meier plot of the Mannheim cohort with basal subtype of OS and DFS associated with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic> and its splice variants risk stratification. No significant correlation was found with OS (A, median survival 18 vs. 20 months) and DFS (B, median survival 17 vs. 15 months) in the group with full-length transcript of <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HG</italic>. No significant correlation was found with OS (C, median survival 15 vs. 18 months) and DFS (D, median survival 29 vs. 17 months) in the group with <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE1</italic>. The group with high <italic toggle="yes">MIR31HGΔE3</italic> expression showed a worse OS (E, median survival 13 vs. 22 months) compared to the group with low expression, no significant correlation was found with DFS (F, median survival 15 vs. 36 months). The numbers below the figures showed the number of patients at risk in each group. <bold>Table S1.</bold> siRNAs used in this study. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Primers and probes used in this study.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BLCA</term><def><p id="Par5">Bladder urothelial carcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DFS</term><def><p id="Par6">Disease-free survival</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EGFR</term><def><p id="Par7">Epidermal growth factor receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FFPE</term><def><p id="Par8">Formalin fixed paraffin embedded</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>lncRNA</term><def><p id="Par9">Long non-coding RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIR31HG</term><def><p id="Par10">miR-31 host gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIBC</term><def><p id="Par11">Muscle invasive bladder cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OS</term><def><p id="Par12">Overall survival</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>siRNA</term><def><p id="Par13">small interfering RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCGA</term><def><p id="Par14">The Cancer Genome Atlas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPM</term><def><p id="Par15">Transcripts per million</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Annette Steidler and Lena Hoffmann for excellent technical support. We would like to thank Blerta Thaqi for the technical work.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>SW: Conceptualization, Methodology, Investigation, Writing - original draft. KN: Methodology, Investigation, Writing - review&amp; editing. TSW: Investigation, Writing - review&amp; editing. AF: Formal analysis, Investigation. C-AW: Writing - review &amp; editing. ME: Writing - review &amp; editing. SP: Writing - review &amp; editing. MK: Writing - review &amp; editing. PE: Conceptualization, Methodology, Funding acquisition, Supervision, Writing - review &amp; editing. The author(s) read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The study was funded by the common scientific pool of participating institutions. Sheng Wu was supported by a scholarship from the China Scholarship Council. Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data and materials of this study are available from the corresponding author for reasonable requests.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par51">Studies involving human participants were approved by the ethical board of the University of Heidelberg (2015-549 N-MA) and performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par52">All authors agree to submit the article for publication.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par53">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Babjuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capoun</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comperat</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EAU guidelines on non-muscle-invasive Urothelial carcinoma of the bladder: update 2016</article-title><source>Eur Urol</source><year>2017</year><volume>71</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2016.05.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27324428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aragon-Ching</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werntz</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zietman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidisciplinary Management of Muscle-Invasive Bladder Cancer: current challenges and future directions</article-title><source>Am Soc Clin Oncol Educ Book</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/EDBK_201227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30231340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plimack</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman-Censits</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of distinct basal and luminal subtypes of muscle-invasive bladder cancer with different sensitivities to frontline chemotherapy</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2014.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24525232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4011497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical and molecular characteristics of bladder urothelial carcinoma subtypes</article-title><source>J Cell Biochem</source><year>2019</year><volume>120</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>9956</fpage><lpage>9963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.28278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30548659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkmer</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Three differentiation states risk-stratify bladder cancer into distinct subtypes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1120605109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3277552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of long noncoding RNAs</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2011.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21925379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3199020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functional role of long non-coding RNA in human carcinomas</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>38</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-10-38</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21489289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3098824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNAs in urologic malignancies: functional roles and clinical translation</article-title><source>J Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1842</fpage><lpage>1855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/jca.15876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27698924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5039368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prensner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinnaiyan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence of lncRNAs in cancer biology</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-11-0209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3215093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA Loc554202 regulates proliferation and migration in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>446</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2014.02.144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24631686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA Loc554202 induces apoptosis in colorectal cancer cells via the caspase cleavage cascades</article-title><source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-015-0217-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26362196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4567799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>F-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased long noncoding RNA MIR31HG is correlated with poor prognosis and contributes to cell proliferation in gastric cancer</article-title><source>Tumour Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>7693</fpage><lpage>7701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13277-015-4644-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26692098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA MIR31HG exhibits oncogenic property in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma and is negatively regulated by miR-193b</article-title><source>Oncogene.</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>3647</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2015.430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26549028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4947634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased expression of LncRNA MIR31HG in human bladder cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Biomark</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/CBM-160635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27434291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13020480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative splicing in cancer: implications for biology and therapy</article-title><source>Oncogene.</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2013.570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24441040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walaszek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lower</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziolkowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer risk in premalignant lesions: osteopontin splice variants indicate prognosis</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2018</year><volume>119</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1259</fpage><lpage>1266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41416-018-0228-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30353046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6251032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khandelwal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appunni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD44 splice variant (CD44v3) promotes progression of urothelial carcinoma of bladder through Akt/ERK/STAT3 pathways: novel therapeutic approach</article-title><source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>145</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2649</fpage><lpage>2661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00432-019-03024-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31529191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11810428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>lncRNA PVT1 and its splicing variant function as competing endogenous RNA to regulate clear cell renal cell carcinoma progression</article-title><source>Oncotarget.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>49</issue><fpage>85353</fpage><lpage>85367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.19743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29156724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5689614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montironi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updates in the eighth edition of the tumor-node-metastasis staging classification for urologic cancers</article-title><source>Eur Urol</source><year>2018</year><volume>73</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2017.12.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29325693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woldu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagrodia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guideline of guidelines: non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>119</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bju.13760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28058776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5315602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barretina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caponigro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stransky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Margolin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Cancer cell line encyclopedia enables predictive modelling of anticancer drug sensitivity</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2012</year><volume>483</volume><issue>7391</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22460905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3320027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TSVdb: a web-tool for TCGA splicing variants analysis</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>405</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4775-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29843604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5975414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational prediction of associations between long non-coding RNAs and proteins</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-14-651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24063787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3827931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasband</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliceiri</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NIH image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5554542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebäck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>MMP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koumoutsakos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Detmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TScratch: a novel and simple software tool for automated analysis of monolayer wound healing assays</article-title><source>Biotechniques.</source><year>2009</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2144/000113083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19450233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinkele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wezel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictive value of lymphangiogenesis and proliferation markers on mRNA level in urothelial carcinoma of the bladder after radical cystectomy</article-title><source>Urol Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>36</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>530.e19</fpage><lpage>530.e27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.urolonc.2018.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30446441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tramm</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sørensen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimal reference genes for normalization of qRT-PCR data from archival formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded breast tumors controlling for tumor cell content and decay of mRNA</article-title><source>Diagn Mol Pathol</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PDM.0b013e318285651e</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23846446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2− ΔΔCT method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improvement of the 2ˆ(−delta delta CT) method for quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction data analysis</article-title><source>Biostat Bioinforma Biomath</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4280562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanetti</surname><given-names>MRD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petricelli</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paschoal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araujo Júnior</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of a cutoff value for pelvic floor distensibility using the Epi-no balloon to predict perineal integrity in vaginal delivery: ROC curve analysis. Prospective observational single cohort study</article-title><source>Sao Paulo Med J</source><year>2016</year><volume>134</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1516-3180.2014.8581009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25789777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10496538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Ahmadie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellmunt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherniack</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive molecular characterization of muscle-invasive bladder cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>171</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>56. e25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28988769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5687509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rempel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worst</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steidler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subclassification, survival prediction and drug target analyses of chemotherapy-naïve muscle-invasive bladder cancer with a molecular screening</article-title><source>Oncotarget.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><issue>40</issue><fpage>25935</fpage><lpage>25945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.25407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29899832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5995241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Network</surname><given-names>CGAR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive molecular characterization of urothelial bladder carcinoma</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2014</year><volume>507</volume><issue>7492</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24476821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3962515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dandan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jianliang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haiyan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuedong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA MIR31HG is activated by SP1 and promotes cell migration and invasion by sponging miR-214 in NSCLC</article-title><source>Gene.</source><year>2019</year><volume>692</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2018.12.077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ATH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA LncHIFCAR/MIR31HG is a HIF-1α co-activator driving oral cancer progression</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15874</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28639619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5489688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Augoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plow</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sossey-Alaoui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-31 and its host gene lncRNA LOC554202 are regulated by promoter hypermethylation in triple-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-11-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22289355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3298503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieskovsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groshen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Radical cystectomy in the treatment of invasive bladder cancer: long-term results in 1,054 patients</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2001.19.3.666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebouissou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard-Pierrot</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Reyniès</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krucker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapeaublanc</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EGFR as a potential therapeutic target for a subset of muscle-invasive bladder cancers presenting a basal-like phenotype</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><issue>244</issue><fpage>244ra91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3008970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal and neoplastic urothelial stem cells: getting to the root of the problem</article-title><source>Nat Rev Urol</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrurol.2012.142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22890301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3468664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McConkey</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinney</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into subtypes of invasive bladder cancer: considerations of the clinician</article-title><source>Eur Urol</source><year>2014</year><volume>66</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2014.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24877661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kardos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mose</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selitsky</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Claudin-low bladder tumors are immune infiltrated and actively immune suppressed</article-title><source>JCI insight</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e85902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.85902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27699256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5033914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA MIR31HG abrogates the availability of tumor suppressor microRNA-361 for the growth of osteosarcoma</article-title><source>Cancer Manag Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>8055</fpage><lpage>8064</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S214569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6722458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA MIR31HG inhibits hepatocellular carcinoma proliferation and metastasis by sponging microRNA-575 to modulate ST7L expression</article-title><source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-018-0853-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30176933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6122648</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC11852547"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The diagnostic value of long non-coding RNA MIR31HG and its role in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2018.03.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29605445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostaghel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yegnasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannahill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct transcriptional programs mediated by the ligand-dependent full-length androgen receptor and its splice variants in castration-resistant prostate cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>3457</fpage><lpage>3462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-11-3892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22710436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3415705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprenger</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vessella</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostaghel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Castration resistance in human prostate cancer is conferred by a frequently occurring androgen receptor splice variant</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2715</fpage><lpage>2730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI41824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2912187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulikakos</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Persaud</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janakiraman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moriceau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RAF inhibitor resistance is mediated by dimerization of aberrantly spliced BRAF(V600E)</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2011</year><volume>480</volume><issue>7377</issue><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3266695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasprzak</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulikakos</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misteli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of vemurafenib-resistant melanoma by interference with pre-mRNA splicing</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25971842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4435825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albadine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadallah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High epidermal growth factor receptor immunohistochemical expression in urothelial carcinoma of the bladder is not associated with EGFR mutations in exons 19 and 21: a study using formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded archival tissues</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>43</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1590</fpage><lpage>1595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2011.11.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22406363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3505673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased MIR31HG lncRNA expression increases gefitinib resistance in non-small cell lung cancer cell lines through the EGFR/PI3K/AKT signaling pathway</article-title><source>Oncol Lett</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>3494</fpage><lpage>3500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2017.5878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28529576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5431660</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>