
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Nanomedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Nanomedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">616</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">intjnano</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101263847</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijn</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Nanomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9114</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2013</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7783201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7783201.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7783201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7783201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33414637</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S276336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">276336</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tuftsin-Bearing Liposomes Co-Encapsulated with Doxorubicin and Curcumin Efficiently Inhibit EAC Tumor Growth in Mice</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Murugesan et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Murugesan et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murugesan</surname><given-names initials="K">Kalaimathi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names initials="P">Padmapriya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5865-6430</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadeva</surname><given-names initials="R">Raghunandan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names initials="CM">Chhitar M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8001-0115</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Haq</surname><given-names initials="W">Wahajul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Bioinformatics and Applied Biotechnology (IBAB)</institution>, <addr-line>Bangalore</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI), Medicinal and Process Chemistry Division</institution>, <addr-line>Lucknow</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Kalaimathi Murugesan <institution>Institute of Bioinformatics and Applied Biotechnology (IBAB)</institution>, <addr-line>Biotech Park, Electronic City Phase I</addr-line>, <addr-line>Bangalore</addr-line><addr-line>560100</addr-line>, <country>India</country><phone>Tel +919585986415</phone> Email mathi.biotech@gmail.com</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">349619</issue-id><fpage>10547</fpage><lpage>10559</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-01-08 15:16:20.567"><day>08</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 Murugesan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Murugesan et al.</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="ijn-15-10547.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Background</title><p>Targeted multidrug-loaded delivery systems have emerged as an advanced strategy for cancer treatment. In this context, antibodies, hormones, and small peptides have been coupled to the surface of drug carriers, such as liposomes, polymeric and metallic nanoparticles loaded with drugs, as tumor-specific ligands. In the present study, we have grafted a natural macrophage stimulating peptide, tuftsin, on the surface of the liposomes (LPs) that were loaded with doxorubicin (DOX) and/or curcumin (CUR), by attaching to its C-terminus a palmitoyl residue (Thr-Lys-Pro-Arg-CO-NH-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>-NH-COC<sub>15</sub>H<sub>31</sub>, P.Tuft) to enable its grafting within the liposome’s bilayer.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>The prepared drug-loaded liposomes (DOX LPs, CUR LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) were thoroughly characterised in terms of particle size, drug content, encapsulation efficiency and structural properties using UV–visible spectroscopy, dynamic light scattering (DLS) and Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR). The anti-cancer activity and drug toxicity of the liposomal formulations were examined on Ehrlich ascites carcinoma (EAC) tumor-induced mice model.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>A significant reduction in the tumor weight and volume was observed upon treating the tumor-bearing mice with palmitoyl tuftsin-grafted dual drug-loaded liposomes (P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs), as compared to the single drug/peptide-loaded formulation (DOX LPs, CUR LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft- LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs). Western blot analysis revealed that the tumor inhibition was associated with p53-mediated apoptotic pathway. Further, the biochemical and histological analysis revealed that the various liposomal preparation used in this study were non-toxic to the animals at the specified dose (10mg/kg).</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, we have developed a targeted liposomal formulation of P.Tuftsin-bearing liposomes co-encapsulated with effective anti-cancer drugs such as doxorubicin and curcumin. In experimental animals, tumor inhibition by P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs indicates the synergistic therapeutic effect of the peptide and the dual drug.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>palmitoyl-tuftsin</kwd><kwd>antitumor</kwd><kwd>doxorubicin</kwd><kwd>curcumin</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="11"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>In recent years, combination drug therapy and multidrug-loaded delivery systems have emerged as an advanced approach to cancer treatment.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Besides, combination of chemotherapeutic drugs along with the targeted peptide-based nanoformulations has shown great potential in cancer treatment.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> For instance, treatment with RGDK-peptide (arginine-glycine-aspartate)-bearing liposomes loaded with curcumin and doxorubicin have shown to exhibit a better effect on the tumor vasculature.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Further, Sengupta et al<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> developed an effective delivery system called “nanocell” for sequential release of multi-drugs within solid tumors. This means that an ideal drug delivery system must have a target-specific component and an effective release strategy at the specific site. Keeping this in view, we have employed in this study the target peptide, tuftsin-bearing liposomes, co-encapsulated with hydrophobic (CUR) and hydrophilic (DOX) drugs.</p><p>Tuftsin is an immunomodulatory tetrapeptide (Thr-Lys-Pro-Arg) derived from immunoglobulin IgG.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Modification of tuftsin at the C-terminus with the addition of a fatty acyl chain (Thr-Lys-Pro-Arg-CO-NH-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>-NH-COC<sub>15</sub>H<sub>31;</sub> palmitoyl Tuftsin; P.Tuft) has been shown to facilitate easy grafting of this peptide on to the surface of the liposomes.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> It has been demonstrated that palmitoyl Tuftsin-bearing liposomes specifically bind to polymorphonuclear (PMN) cells, macrophages and monocytes and consequently induce the natural killer activity of these cells against tumors and pathogens.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Furthermore, tuftsin-bearing liposomised etoposide have shown to significantly inhibit the growth of fibrocarcinoma<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> and administration of antigenic polypeptide along with tuftsin effectively inhibited the tumor growth in colorectal cancer.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Despite the use of tuftsin for over forty years, the pathway through which tuftsin signals have not been fully elucidated, lately it was identified that tuftsin signals by binding to neuropilin-1 receptor which plays an important role in blood vessel formation and microvascular permeability of tumor cells.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In this study, we have used palmitoyl tuftsin to enable its efficient grafting on to the liposome surface, and also to further complement the anti-tumorigenic potential of the drugs encapsulated in the liposomes.</p><p>Doxorubicin (DOX) is an antitumor antibiotic widely used to treat several types of cancers.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> However, its clinical use is restricted vowing to its drug resistance and side effects.<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Therefore, various attempts have been made to find new chemosensitizers, to improve the efficacy of doxorubicin against multi drug-resistant (MDR) cancer cells.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Curcumin is one such compound that acts as a chemosensitizer to reverse doxorubicin resistance against solid tumors by down regulation of NF-kB transcription factor.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In addition to its strong anti-cancer activity, curcumin is now being explored for its unique ability to enhance the effects of chemotherapeutics when administered along with several anticancer drugs, such as doxorubicin, cisplatin, etc.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> For instance, treatment with poly (butyl cyanoacrylate) nanoparticles (PBCA-NPs) loaded with DOX and CUR efficiently reversed MDR resistance in MCF-7 breast cancer cell line.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> We, therefore, considered it appropriate to co-encapsulate curcumin with doxorubicin as a chemosensitizer in tuftsin-bearing liposomes<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> to enhance the efficacy of doxorubicin against EAC induced solid tumors. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref> is a schematic representation of the tuftsin-bearing liposomes encapsulated with the dual drug.<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The schematic representation of the assembly of tuftsin-bearing liposomes encapsulated with DOX and CUR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0001.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> DSPE-PEG, distearoyl-L-A-phosphatidylethanolamine; DOX, doxorubicin; CUR, curcumin; LPs, liposomes.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Preparation of Liposomes</title><p>Palmitoyl Tuftsin (P.Tuft) was prepared as reported earlier.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The solvent evaporation method was used for the preparation of various liposomal formulations (LPs) used in this study.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Briefly, in 10mL of chloroform, curcumin (CUR; 3mg), cholesterol (15mg), DSPE-PEG 2000 (12.5mg) and egg lecithin (120mg) were dissolved. In a rotary evaporator, the mixture was evaporated at 45° C, and the thin layer formed was dried overnight for complete removal of the solvent. The thin film was then suspended in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing 50 mg of P.Tuft for 30 mins. The mixture was then sonicated at 500W for 2 min using probe-type ultrasonicator. Curcumin-loaded liposomes (CUR-LPs) with and without P.Tuft was prepared using the same method. The unencapsulated curcumin was removed by centrifugation at 5000 rpm for 45 min. Doxorubicin (DOX) loaded liposomes were prepared by preheating the liposomes at 37°C in a water bath. Followed by the addition of 5mg/mL of DOX to the preheated liposomes with gentle stirring for 15min at 37°C.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Characterisation of Liposomes</title><p>The particle size distribution of the liposomes was analysed using DLS (Malvern zetasizer nano ZS90, Malvern, UK) with the following parameters; refractive index 1.59, scattering angle of 90° and viscosity of 0.89. FT-IR analysis was carried out as described by Murugesan et al.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Amounts of curcumin entrapped inside the liposomes was determined by measuring absorption at 450 nm after lysis of the liposomes with 1% triton-X. The amount of encapsulated DOX in the liposomes was determined by measuring absorption at 483 nm using UV-visible spectrophotometer X (Tecan Infinite M 200 pro, Tecan Austria GmbH, Austria) after lysis of liposomes with 10% SDS (w/v). P.Tuftsin was quantified by using HPLC with fluorescence detector. Briefly, the synthesised P.Tuftsin-bearing liposomes were dissolved in methanol and then diluted with a mixture of acetonitrile and water (20:80, v/v), 2ul of the resultant solution was then injected into the HPLC system (Agilent 1100 series). C18 column was used for chromatographic separation, the mobile phase consisted of acetonitrile and 0.2% formic acid with a flow rate of 1 mL/min.
<disp-formula-group id="UM0001"><disp-formula><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-e0001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{Entrapment\,efficiency\,}}\left({{\rm{EE\%\,}}} \right){\rm{ = }}{{{\rm{Concentration\,of\,entrapped\,drug}}} \over {{\rm{Total\,drug\,concentration}}}}{\rm{ \times 100}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>In vitro Release Studies</title><p>The liposomal formulations (CUR LPs, DOX LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) equivalent to 1mL were filled in the dialysis bag with a cut off of 12–14KDa. Each dialysis bag was immersed in a solution containing 0.01M PBS (pH 7.4) with 1% tween 80 and 20% ethanol placed on a shaker at 100rpm. One milliliter of the sample was then withdrawn at 1 hr, 2 hr, 4 hr, 8hr, 12hr, 24hr, 36hr and 48hr and replaced with 1mL of PBS. The amount of DOX and CUR released at each time point was then analysed. The experiment was carried out in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Preparation of Rhodamine B-Labelled Liposomes</title><p>Rhodamine B isothiocyanate (5mg) was solubilised in 1mL of DMSO. From this solution, 200µL was added to 1 mL of various preparations of liposomes (Blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) followed by addition of 1 mL of 2 M NaHCO<sub>3</sub> buffer. The mixture was then incubated in dark for 12 hr at 4°C. Free rhodamine B was removed by dialysis against distilled water.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>In vitro Cellular Uptake of Liposomes</title><p>Human cervical cancer cell line (HeLa) was procured from NCCS (National Center for Cell Sciences), Pune, India. The cells were grown in 50 mL flask in MEM media and about 80% confluency the cells were detached by trypsinization, pelleted, and suspended in fresh media. 2mL of 5×10<sup>7</sup> cells were coated on the coverslips and kept for 12hr to adhere. To it was added 200ul of rhodamine B-labelled preparations of various types of liposomes (Blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) and the mixture was incubated further for 12 hr. After incubation, the cells were fixed for 10 mins with 4% paraformaldehyde. The nuclei of the cell were stained with DAPI (4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole), and the fluorescence images were captured and analysed by confocal laser-scanning microscope (FV1000, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>In vivo Efficacy in EAC Tumor-Induced Mice</title><p>The animal study was approved by CPCSEA (“committee for the purpose of control and supervision of experiments on animals”, Government of India, Animal welfare division, Reg. No. 1994/GO/ReBi/S/17/CPCSEA) and all the experiments were conducted according to the guidelines and regulation of CPCSEA. The in vivo efficacy of different types of liposomes was evaluated in Ehrlich ascites carcinoma (EAC) tumor-bearing mouse model. The tumor was induced in swiss albino mice by injection of 1×10<sup>6</sup> EAC cells on either of the hind limb of mice. When tumor volume reached ≃ 200 mm<sup>3</sup>, the animals were segregated into eight experimental groups (5 animals per group). The formulations (Blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs and untreated control) were given intraperitoneally at a dose of 10 mg/kg every alternate day for 30 days. The tumor volume and body weight were monitored for 30 days. The tumor volume was calculated with a digital caliper using the formula V = (LxWxW)/2, where V is tumor volume, W is tumor width, L is tumor length.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Western Blotting</title><p>Protein samples were isolated from 100mg tumor tissues from each treatment groups (CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs and untreated control). The protein concentration was determined by Bradford method. The protein samples were then resolved on sodium dodecyl sulphate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE). The resolved protein samples were blotted onto PVDF membrane using semi-dry transfer method (Transblot-Turbo blotting system, Biorad, USA). The membranes were treated with 5% non-fat milk for 1 hour at room temperature. The membranes were then incubated with primary antibody (Bcl-2, BAX and p53) for 2 hours followed by incubation with streptavidin–horseradish peroxidase conjugate for 1 hour. The immunoblots were developed using chemiluminescence detection reagent (Clarity Western ECL blotting substrate, Biorad, USA). The intensity of the bands was captured using Syngene G: Box gel doc system and the bands were quantified using GelQuant.Net, BiochemLab solutions.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Assessment of Drug Toxicity</title><p>The drug toxicity was evaluated after treatment of the mice with various preparations of liposomes (Blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) for 30 days. At the end of the experiment, blood samples were collected from mice in each treatment groups and serum was separated. The drug toxicity assessment was made as per the protocol described in ALT/AST activity assay kit (Abcam, India).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Histological Analysis</title><p>The H &amp; E staining was performed as described by Murugesan et al.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Briefly, the tumor tissues and the organs were fixed in formalin and then embedded in paraffin. The tissues were sectioned into 5 µm thickness. The protocol followed dewaxing of the tissue slides with xylene for 5 mins followed by dehydration in ethanol gradient (100–30%). The slides were then washed with distilled water and then incubated with hematoxylin for 5 min. The slides were washed with 1% acid-alcohol and then counter stained with eosin for 1 min. The tissue slides were dehydrated in ethanol gradient followed by incubation with xylene for 5 min. The slides were then fixed using DPX mounting medium and observed under the microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2010"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All experiments were performed in triplicates and reported as mean ± SD. One-way analysis of variance was used to determine the statistical significance of the drug release assay and tumor size. Significant change is considered at p-value ≤0.05. The statistical data was evaluated on SPSS v20.0 software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Particle Size and Entrapment Efficiencies</title><p>The hydrodynamic diameters of the various formulations containing DOX LPs, CUR LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs were measured by DLS (dynamic light scattering) and the size was within the range of 100–140nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>, <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The drug entrapment efficiencies of doxorubicin and curcumin loaded liposomes were determined spectrophotometrically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). Curcumin entrapment efficiency in liposomes was found to be (70–78%) and the entrapment efficiency of doxorubicin was about (96–98%). The amount of Tuftsin in liposomes ranged from 50–60% of the total amount.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Size, Polydispersity Index and Entrapment Efficiency of Liposomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Liposomes</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Average Size (nm)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Polydispersity Index (PDI)</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Entrapment Efficiency (%)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CUR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DOX</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tuftsin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DOX LPS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.4±0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CUR LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9±4.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DOX-CUR LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2±1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.1±0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P.Tuft LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P.Tuft-CUR LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.8±4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P.Tuft-DOX LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.4±1.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2±4.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.5±2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Size determination of LPs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0002.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Particle size distribution of Liposomes including, DOX LPs, CUR LPs, CUR-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs as measured by DLS.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> DLS, dynamic light scattering; P.Tuft, palmitoyl tuftsin; DOX, doxorubicin; CUR, curcumin.</attrib></fig><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Characterisation of LPs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0003.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> UV-spectrophotometric detection and quantification of entrapped DOX and CUR in different kinds of LPs. (<bold>A</bold>) Quantification of tuftsin by RP-HPLC method, tuftsin fraction eluting at 13.9 min at 227nm (<bold>B</bold>).</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> RP-HPLC, reverse phase liquid chromatography.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>FTIR Analysis</title><p>The encapsulation of DOX/CUR in the liposomes was confirmed by FTIR spectroscopy. The FTIR absorption spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>) ranged from 3365 cm<sup>−1</sup>to 713 cm<sup>−1</sup>. The characteristic peaks of curcumin were found at 3508 cm<sup>−1</sup> represents the –OH stretching, peak at 1271 cm<sup>−1</sup> represents C–O stretching, and 1023 cm<sup>−1</sup> represents C–O–C stretching. The main characteristic peaks of DOX corresponds to –NH<sub>2</sub> stretching at 3450 cm<sup>−1</sup>, C–C stretching corresponds to peak at 1410 cm<sup>−1</sup>, and 1073 cm<sup>−1</sup> corresponds to C=O stretching vibrations. The signature peaks of P.Tuft were found at 1300 cm<sup>−1</sup> (-RNH<sub>2</sub>), 1747 cm<sup>−1</sup> and 1033 cm<sup>−1</sup> (C-C stretching). Once encapsulated with DOX or CUR the characteristic peaks were shifted from 1747 to 1781, 1073 to 1082 and 1271 to 1267 cm<sup>−1</sup>, respectively. The occurrence of the characteristic peaks corresponding to DOX/CUR in each of the liposomes indicated that the drugs were successfully loaded in the liposomes.<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Characterization of structural properties by Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0004.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Note:</bold> FTIR analysis of different kinds of LPs including CUR LPs, DOX LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>In vitro Release Kinetics</title><p>A diphasic release pattern was observed for DOX and CUR, with an initial rapid release up to 4h and sustained release until 48 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">figure 5B</xref>). DOX release at 48 h was about 54–63% in DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs and P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs. Similarly, in case of Cur about 46–55% release was observed in CUR LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs and P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs. No significant difference was observed in release pattern of both DOX and CUR from P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs and P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs when compared with DOX/CUR LPs. The results indicate that presence of P.Tuftsin on the surface of the liposomes does not alter the release pattern of the drugs from liposomes. However, a slight decrease in release of DOX and CUR on addition of P.Tuftsin may be due to high encapsulation efficacy of the drugs within the liposomes which attributed to slower burst release compared to DOX/CUR LPs.<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>In vitro release profile of DOX and CUR.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0005.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Percent cumulative release of DOX (<bold>A</bold>); percent cumulative release of CUR (<bold>B</bold>). The experiment was carried out using dialysis membrane diffusion technique. The data are representative of three experiments. Each value represents mean ±SD of three experiments.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>In vitro Cellular Internalisation of Liposomes</title><p>The internalization of rhodamine B-labelled LPs in HeLa cells was visualised by confocal laser scanning microscopy. The red intensity indicated the level of internalization of rhodamine B-labelled LPs inside the cells. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>, all the liposomal formulations showed intracellular rhodamine B concentration after 12 hr. The red fluorescence intensity in the cytosol of the HeLa cells confirmed the uptake of Rhodamine-B labelled LPs by the cancer cells.<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>In vitro cellular uptake study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0006.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Confocal images of HeLa cells after 12 h of incubation with different kinds of LPs at the same concentration 0.1 mg/mL; the nuclei were stained by DAPI (blue), and all of the LPs are labeled by rhodamine B (red).</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>In vivo Efficacy of Different Kinds of Liposomes</title><p>The tumor-bearing mice were subjected to treatment with different liposomal formulations (Blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs and untreated control) for 15 doses at a dose of 10mg/kg. The tumor volume and body weight were measured every day for 30 days. The tumor volume in each group at the start of the experiment ranged from 0.2 to 0.26 cm<sup>3</sup>. At the end of treatment, the average tumor volume was 5.84 cm<sup>3</sup> for control group, 6 cm<sup>3</sup> for blank LPs, 3.64 cm<sup>3</sup> for P.Tuft LPs, 3 cm<sup>3</sup> for CUR LPs, 2.48 cm<sup>3</sup> for DOX LPs, 1.84 cm<sup>3</sup> for DOX-CUR LPs, 1.72 cm<sup>3</sup> for P.Tuft-CUR LPs, 1.75 cm<sup>3</sup> for P.Tuft-DOX LPs, 1.53 cm<sup>3</sup> for P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7A</xref>). At the end of treatment, the average tumor volume of CUR LPs, DOX LPs, P.Tuft LPs (*P&lt;0.05) and DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs decreased significantly (**P&lt;0.01) compared with the control groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7B</xref>). The results indicate that P.Tuft co-encapsulated with CUR and DOX suppressed the tumor growth more efficiently, compared to the single drug or the dual drug formulations. The initial body weight of mice ranged from 30–31g (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7C</xref>) and the weight changes towards the end of the experiments in all the groups were found to be similar. The average tumor weight after 30 days of treatment was 6.8 g for control, 6.2 g for blank, 4.9 g for P.Tuft LPs, 4.5 g for CUR LPs, 4 g for DOX LPs, 3.8 g for DOX-CUR LPs, 3.32 g for P.Tuft-DOX, 3.1 g for P.Tuft-CUR and 2 g for P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7D</xref>). The results indicate that all the formulations administered at a concentration of 10 mg/kg significantly reduced the tumor growth in mice, with insignificant changes in the body weight.<fig id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The in vivo effects different kinds of LPs in EAC tumor-bearing mice.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0007.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Growth curve of EAC tumors in each group (<bold>A</bold>) Images of tumors removed from mice in each group after treatment (<bold>B</bold>) Individual body weight of mice after treatment (<bold>C</bold>) Individual tumor weight of mice after 30 days of treatment (<bold>D</bold>). Each value represents mean ±SD from fifteen mice *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Expression of Apoptotic Proteins</title><p>The effect of various liposomal formulations on the expression of major apoptotic regulatory proteins (BCL-2, BAX, p53) was determined using Western blotting. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8</xref>, liposomal formulations with P.Tuftsin (P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) significantly increased the regulation of BAX about (2–2.5 fold, P&lt;0.01) and p53 about (2 fold, P&lt;0.05) when compared to untreated control. Whereas BCL-2 expression decreased by (0.3–0.5 fold, P&lt;0.05) in P.Tuftin treatment groups in relation to untreated control. The result indicates that the tumor suppression may be associated with p53-mediated apoptotic pathway .<fig id="f0008" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Apoptosis protein expression in tumor tissues.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0008.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Western blot analysis and quantification of Apoptosis-related proteins (<bold>A</bold>). The cell lysates were subjected to SDS-PAGE and blotted with Bax (<bold>B</bold>), p53 (<bold>C</bold>) and BCL-2 (<bold>D</bold>) antibodies. The data are representative of three experiments. Each value represents mean ±SD of three experiments.(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9</xref>) *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01.</attrib></fig><fig id="f0009" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of p53-mediated apoptotic pathway.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0009.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> Bax, Bcl-2 Associated X-protein; BCL-2, B-cell lymphoma 2; p53, tumor protein p53.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Assessment of Drug Toxicity</title><p>At the end of 30 days of treatment with blank LPs, CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs, blood samples were collected from all the treatment groups and the serum was separated. ALT/AST levels in the serum were analysed. The results indicated that the levels were within the normal range among all the treatment groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10</xref>; ALT &lt;60 U/L, AST&lt;100 U/L). However, DOX-LPs and P.Tuft-DOX LPS showed a mild elevation in ALT and AST levels.<fig id="f0010" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Assessment of liver toxicity in mice on treatment with different kinds of LPs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0010.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Quantification of plasma concentration of AST (<bold>A</bold>) and ALT (<bold>B</bold>) after 30 days of treatment with different kinds of LPs. Each value represents mean ±SD of three experiments. **P&lt;0.01, compared with the untreated control.</attrib><attrib><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2008"><title>Histopathology</title><p>The specimens of tumor tissues, kidney, liver and spleen were excised from the mice of experimental and control groups (P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs). The H and E stained sections of tumor tissue and organs were observed for changes such as steatoses, infiltrative cells, necrosis, enlargement of organs (hyperplasia), pigmentation; new blood vessel formation (angiogenesis) and changes in sinuses and lymphoid follicles. The histopathological changes in liver and tumor tissue of the treatment groups indicated a significant reduction in hyperplasia and angiogenesis in comparison with the controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0011">Figure 11</xref>). The results indicate that there was a significant improvement in the pathological condition of the tumor and organs after treatment with P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs compared to the controls.<fig id="f0011" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>The micrographs of H&amp;E-stained sections of the main organs and tumors after treatment with different kinds of LPs.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJN-15-10547-g0011.jpg"/><attrib><bold>Notes:</bold> Hematoxylin and eosin-stained tumor, liver, spleen and kidney tissue after treatment of mice (treatment every second day for 30 days). Angiogenesis (black arrow), hyperplasia (red arrow). The images were observed at 20× magnification.</attrib></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Doxorubicin is a widely used broad-spectrum anti-cancer agent for the treatment of various cancer types. Nevertheless, the use of doxorubicin is associated with several setbacks, primarily induction of multi drug resistant (MDR) gene expression owing to internalisation of the drug in cytoplasmic vesicles.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> The reasons for drug resistance may be due to the activation of drug-efflux pump which removes the drug from the cells leading to a low concentration of intracellular drug levels. Furthermore, MDR has been associated with ABC transporter proteins such as MRP-1 (multidrug resistance associated protein) and Pgp (P-glycoprotein).<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> To this end, curcumin has been found to downregulate ABC transporters including MRP-1, P-gp and ABCC1 that are linked to MDR.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Earlier studies have shown that nanoformulations of curcumin in combination with doxorubicin could overcome MDR in tumor cells. For instance, Duan et al<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> demonstrated that loading of both DOX and CUR in chitosan/poly(butylcyanoacrylate) nanoparticles reversed the multidrug resistance in MCF-7 breast cancer cell lines; NanoDOXCur (NDC) a composite polymer nanoformulation have shown to reduce DOX related cardiomyopathy;<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> co-encapsulation of DOX and CUR in poly(D,L-Lactide-Co-Glycolide) nanoparticles suppressed the progression of MDR in leukaemia cell line K562.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In order to take advantage of these pleiotropic properties of curcumin, our study aimed to develop curcumin doxorubicin co-loaded liposomal system. Furthermore, in this study liposomes were used as nanocarriers, owing to its enhanced stability, bioavailability, and shelf life for sensitive ingredients as they are assembled from phospholipid bilayers similar to cell membranes and their biphasic character making them suitable for being carriers for both hydrophilic (in the central aqueous compartment) and hydrophobic (in lipid bilayers) compound.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></p><p>Tuftsin a tetrapeptide (Thr-Lys-Pro-Arg) stimulates immunomodulatory effects by binding specifically to macrophages, monocytes, and polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMN).<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Many studies have reported the anti-tumor efficacy of tuftsin in animal models.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The intrinsic anticancer/antitumor property of tuftsin makes it an ideal candidate to be administered along with potent anticancer drugs in order to efficiently treat various types of cancers. In the present study, we evaluated the anti-tumor activity of palmitoyl tuftsin-grafted liposomes co-encapsulated with dual/single drug.</p><p>It has been demonstrated that the liposomes encapsulated with both CUR and DOX along with P.Tuft effectively inhibited the tumor growth (P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs, P&lt;0.01) in experimental animals, compared with the liposomes loaded with either drug alone/peptide alone (CUR LPs, DOX LPs, DOX-CUR LPs, P.Tuft LPs, P&lt;0.05), suggesting synergy between the anti-tumor efficacies of P.Tuft and combination of doxorubicin with curcumin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>). This may be attributed to efficient uptake of P.Tuft-bearing drug-loaded liposomes by the tumor tissue and then modulation of ABC drug transporters function by curcumin. This is in accordance with an earlier study which showed that tuftsin-bearing liposomized etoposide, significantly inhibited the tumor growth at a dosage of 10 mg/kg when administered for five days.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Based on these findings, we hypothesize that doxorubicin from the liposomes efficiently reaches the tumor vasculature with the help of curcumin and exerts its cytotoxicity. In addition, the anti-tumor activity of tuftsin perhaps is manifested through the stimulation of cytotoxic effector cells, such as PMN, macrophages, and natural killer cells, rather than by direct cytotoxicity. This finds support from studies of Florentin et al<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, which demonstrated that mice treated with tuftsin showed tumor-specific cytostatic activity through activated peritoneal macrophages, and also enhanced antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC).</p><p>Tumor cells are known to have dysregulated apoptotic machinery; therefore, several anti-tumor drugs/therapies aim at regulating the disturbed apoptotic machinery.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> BAX a pro-apoptotic regulator belonging to the BCL-2 protein family plays a key role in induction of apoptosis in tumor cells.<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> p53 a tumor suppressor protein can intervene at crucial steps of apoptosis by localisation to mitochondria.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Once translocated to nucleus p53 interacts with BCL-2 and neutralises it thereby altering the ratio of BAX to BCL-2.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Any drug/peptide that activates BAX signify anticancer treatment by regulation of apoptosis.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In the present study, we have found induction in the expression of p53 (P&lt;0.05) and BAX (P&lt;0.01) significantly in P.Tuftsin treatment groups in comparison to control groups. Whereas the expression of BCL-2 (P&lt;0.05) was significantly downregulated in P.Tuftsin treatment groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8</xref>). The mechanism involves upregulation of BAX via p53-mediated apoptosis. The results find support from the earlier studies, wherein omega-3 conjugate-bearing tuftsin tagged liposomes delayed progression of hepatocarcinoma by regulation of BAX/BCL2 expression in animal model.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Another study with tuftsin-bearing liposomized etoposide (Tuft-Lip-ETP) delayed tumor growth in Swiss albino mice with fibrosarcoma by upregulation of p53.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> It could be confirmed that the selective tumor suppression in the tuftsin treatment groups may be due to the induction of p53-mediated apoptosis.</p><p>The biochemical analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9</xref>) revealed that various liposomal formulations showed no significant toxicity at the administered dose (10mg/Kg). This is in accordance with earlier studies, wherein mice showed no visible toxicity upon injecting in them up to 400mg of tuftsin per kg of body weight.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Besides, DOX LPs and P.Tuft-DOX LPs showed slightly elevated levels of ALT/AST but the toxicity level of doxorubicin was suppressed in combination with curcumin. In agreement with this study, it has been shown that curcumin effectively reversed the toxicity of doxorubicin by down regulation of P-gp and blocking its transport function in breast cancer cell line.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Another study on leukemia cell line indicated that curcumin reduced the toxic side effect of doxorubicin by down regulation of MDR transporters and inhibition of nuclear factor kappa B (NFkB).<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p>In conclusion, the results of the study suggest that the synthesised liposomes (P.Tuft-CUR LPs, P.Tuft-DOX LPs, P.Tuft-DOX-CUR LPs) are potent anti-tumorigenic formulations against solid tumors. We believe that with further optimisation of the dosage and ratio of the drugs/peptide the combination therapy could be used for less toxic and more effective cancer treatments.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This research was funded by DBT BioCare women scientist scheme. The authors want to thank the Institute of Bioinformatics and Applied Biotechnology (IBAB) for providing the animal house facility.</p></ack><sec id="s0005" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest for this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Glasgow</surname>
<given-names>MDK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chougule.</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Recent developments in active tumor targeted multifunctional nanoparticles for combination chemotherapy in cancer treatment and imaging</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biomed Nanotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1859</fpage>–<lpage>1898</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1166/jbn.2015.2145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26554150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4816444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pastorino</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brignole</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Paolo</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Targeting liposomal chemotherapy via both tumor cell-specific and tumor vasculature-specific ligands potentiates therapeutic efficacy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>10073</fpage>–<lpage>10082</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-06-2117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17047071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Barui</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haseena</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhuri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Simultaneous Delivery of doxorubicin and curcumin encapsulated in liposomes of pegylated RGDK-lipopeptide to tumor vasculature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomaterials</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1643</fpage>–<lpage>1656</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2013.10.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sengupta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eavarone</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Capila</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Temporal targeting of tumour cells and neovasculature with a nanoscale delivery system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>436</volume>(<issue>7050</issue>):<fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16049491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kandpal</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin-bearing liposomes as rifampin vehicles in treatment of tuberculosis in mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8203859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/aac.38.3.588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC284502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owais</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnakumar</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>RK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bachhawat</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin-bearing liposomes as drug vehicles in the treatment of experimental aspergillosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEBS Lett</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>326</volume>(<issue>1–3</issue>):<fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(93)81760-W</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8325389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin-bearing liposomes in treatment of macrophage-based infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Drug Deliv Rev</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-409X(99)00061-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10699310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Varun Dwivedi</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owais</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin augments antitumor efficacy of liposomized etoposide against fibrosarcoma in Swiss Albino Mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Med</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>5–6</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2119/2007-00018.Khan</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17622310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1906688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiaohui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment effect of tuftsin and antigen peptide combined with immune cells on colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med Sci Monit</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>5465</fpage>–<lpage>5472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31333222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.915037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6668490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nissen</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Selwood</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tsirka</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin signals through its receptor neuropilin-1 via the transforming growth factor beta pathway</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurochem</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jnc.12404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24033337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3805743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siebert</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gensicka-Kowalewska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cholewinski</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dzierzbicka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin – properties and analogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Med Chem</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>34</issue>):<fpage>3711</fpage>–<lpage>3727</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867324666170725140826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28745220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammad</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Malvi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Strategy to enhance efficacy of doxorubicin in solid tumor cells by methyl-β-cyclodextrin: involvement of p53 and fas receptor ligand complex</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11853</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep11853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4493576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pugazhendhi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Edison</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Velmurugan</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppusamy</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toxicity of Doxorubicin (Dox) to different experimental organ systems</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>200</volume>(<issue>May</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2018.03.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29534993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>In vivo reversal of doxorubicin resistance by (-)-epigallocatechin gallate in a solid human carcinoma xenograft</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Lett</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>208</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15142676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2004.01.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname>
<given-names>JΜ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Curcumin reverses chemoresistance of human gastric cancer cells by downregulating the NF-κB transcription factor</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncol Rep</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1197</fpage>–<lpage>1203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21811763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2011.1410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ganta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amiji</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Coadministration of paclitaxel and curcumin in nanoemulsion formulations to overcome multidrug resistance in tumor cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>928</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/mp800240j</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19278222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Reversion of multidrug resistance by co-encapsulation of doxorubicin and curcumin in chitosan/poly(butyl cyanoacrylate) nanoparticles</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>426</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2012.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22274587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sercombe</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Veerati</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moheimani</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sood</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Advances and challenges of liposome assisted drug delivery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>December</issue>):<fpage>286</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2015.00286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4664963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haq</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin-bearing liposomes as antibiotic carriers in treatment of macrophage infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Methods Enzymol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>391</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15721387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0076-6879(05)91016-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dual-functional liposomes based on pH-responsive cell-penetrating peptide and hyaluronic acid for tumor-targeted anticancer drug delivery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomaterials</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>36</issue>):<fpage>9246</fpage>–<lpage>9258</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2012.09.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23031530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murugesan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koroth</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of green synthesised silver nanoparticles (ST06-AgNPs) using curcumin derivative (ST06) on human cervical cancer cells (HeLa) in vitro and EAC tumor bearing mice models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nanomed</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5257</fpage>–<lpage>5270</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S202404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6646051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31409988</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC9288184"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Coformulation of doxorubicin and curcumin in poly(D,L-lactide-co-glycolide) nanoparticles suppresses the development of multidrug resistance in K562 cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/mp100455h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21480667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Limtrakul</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chearwae</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phisalphong</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ambudkar</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Modulation of function of three ABC drug transporters, P-glycoprotein (ABCB1), mitoxantrone resistance protein (ABCG2) and multidrug resistance protein 1 (ABCC1) by tetrahydrocurcumin, a major metabolite of curcumin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-006-9302-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16960658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chearwae</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chung-Pu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>H-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Randall Lee</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ambudkar</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Limtrakul</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Curcuminoids purified from turmeric powder modulate the function of human multidrug resistance protein 1 (ABCC1)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16021489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00280-005-0052-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pramanik</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A composite polymer nanoparticle overcomes multidrug resistance and ameliorates doxorubicin-associated cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncotarget</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>640</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22791660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3442295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulboacă</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boarescu</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bolboacă</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparative effect of curcumin versus liposomal curcumin on systemic pro-inflammatory cytokines profile, MCP-1 and RANTES in experimental diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nano</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>8961</fpage>–<lpage>8972</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IJN.S226790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6873975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31819412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bulboaca</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boarescu</surname>
<given-names>P-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porfire</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of nano-epigallocatechin-gallate on oxidative stress and matrix metalloproteinases in experimental diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antioxidants (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox9020172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7070619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32093214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amoscato</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babcock</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Tuftsin: a hormone-like tetrapeptide with antimicrobial and antitumor activities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Life Sci</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1081</fpage>–<lpage>1090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0024-3205(81)90684-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6262587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babcock</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amoscato</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>In vivo and in vitro antitumor activities of tuftsin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann N Y Acad Sci</italic></source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>419</volume>(<issue>1 Antineoplasti</issue>):<fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1983.tb37109.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6324636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babcock</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Noyes</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antitumor effect of tuftsin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biochem</italic></source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>December</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00225293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6895773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Florentin</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bruley-Rosset</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kiger</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>In vivo immunostimulation by tuftsin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Immunol Immunother</italic></source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00199631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Orrenius</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Defects in the apoptotic machinery of cancer cells: role in drug resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Cancer Biol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1044-579X(02)00130-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Apoptosis-regulating proteins as targets for drug discovery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Mol Med</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4914(01)02026-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname>
<given-names>HJM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gil-Gómez</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecules in focus bax. The pro-apoptotic Bcl-2 family member, bax</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biochem Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1357-2725(98)00006-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9695020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vousden</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Regulation and function of the p53 tumor suppressor protein</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Opin Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(00)00216-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haldar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The relationship between BcI2, bax and p53: consequences for cell cycle progression and cell death</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Hum Reprod</italic></source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1109</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molehr/4.12.1099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9872359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="report"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schendel</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of BC1-2, BC1-XL, and bax pore formation and their role in apoptosis regulation</article-title>. <year>1999</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21236/ada383308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Targeted nano-delivery of novel omega-3 conjugate against hepatocellular carcinoma: regulating COX-2/bcl-2 expression in an animal model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Pharmacother</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>July</issue>):<fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2016.04.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27261618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Owais</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toxicity, stability and pharmacokinetics of amphotericin b in immunomodulator tuftsin-bearing liposomes in a murine model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Antimicrob Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkl177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16709592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>