
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3390</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijip</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8911335</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Immunopathology and Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0394-6320</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2058-7384</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7691899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7691899.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7691899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7691899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33233960</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2058738420974888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2058738420974888</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Aberrant miR-219-5p is correlated with TLR4 and serves as a novel
biomarker in patients with multiple organ dysfunction syndrome caused by acute
paraquat poisoning</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yunxiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738420974888">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2058738420974888">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7133-2238</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2058738420974888">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2058738420974888"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-2058738420974888"><label>1</label>Emergency Department, Qingdao Jiaozhou
Central Hospital, Qingdao, Shandong, China</aff><aff id="aff2-2058738420974888"><label>2</label>Radiology Department, Qingdao Jiaozhou
Central Hospital, Qingdao, Shandong, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2058738420974888">Yuming Gao, Emergency Department, Qingdao
Jiaozhou Central Hospital, No. 29, Xuzhou Road, Jiaozhou, Qingdao, Shandong
266300, China. Email: <email>neuron_yun@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">351103</issue-id><elocation-id>2058738420974888</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-31 20:25:13.803"><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Ltd unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888.pdf"/><abstract><p>This study aimed to investigate the clinical significance of serum
microRNA-219-5p (miR-219-5p) in patients with multiple organ dysfunction
syndrome (MODS) caused by acute paraquat (PQ) poisoning, and its correlation
with Toll-like Receptor 4 (TLR4). Luciferase reporter assay was used to
investigate in vitro the correlation of miR-219-5p with TLR4. Serum miR-219-5p
levels were evaluated by quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction. Serum
levels of TLR4, IL-1β, and TNF-α were measured by Enzyme-linked immune sorbent
assay (ELISA). ROC analysis was performed to assess the diagnostic significance,
Kaplan-Meier survival curves and Cox regression analysis were used to evaluate
the prognostic value of miR-219-5p in MODS patients. TLR4 was a target gene of
miR-219-5p and was increased in MODS patients. Serum miR-219-5p level was
decreased and negatively correlated with TLR4 level in MODS patients
(<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.660, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), which had
important diagnostic value and negatively correlated with APACHE II score in
MODS patients. The miR-219-5p expression was markedly associated with the WBC,
ALT, AST, PaCO<sub>2</sub>, Lac, and APACHE II score. Non-survivals had more
patients with low miR-219-5p expression. Patients with low miR-219-5p expression
had shorter survival time. MiR-219-5p and APACHE II score were two independently
prognostic factors for 28-day survival. MiR-219-5p was negatively correlated
with, while TLR4 was positively correlated with the levels of IL-1β and TNF-α.
The serum miR-219-5p level may be a potential biomarker for acute PQ-induced
MODS diagnosis and prognosis. Furthermore, miR-219-5p may be associated with the
progression of MODS by regulating TLR4-related inflammatory response.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>diagnosis</kwd><kwd>microRNA-219-5p</kwd><kwd>multiple organ dysfunction syndrome</kwd><kwd>paraquat poisoning</kwd><kwd>prognosis</kwd><kwd>TLR4</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-2058738420974888"><title>Introduction</title><p>Paraquat (N, N-dimethyl-4, 4-bipyridinium dichloride, PQ) is a herbicide which is
widely used in agriculture, because it has a faster effect and is cheaper compared
with other herbicides.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Besides, in the developing countries, self-poisoning by pesticides is an
important public health problem.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> PQ is high toxic to humans, has no antidotes and no effective treatment,
resulting in an individual mortality rate as high as 50−90%.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Although clinical comprehensive treatment, including gastric lavage,
international diarrhea, diuresis, and blood perfusion, has been adopted, the
therapeutic effect is poor and the fatality rate remains high.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Studies have found that the concentration of PQ in severely body from low to
high was stomach wall (&lt;limit of quantitation, LOQ), cardiac blood (0.11 µg/mL),
liver (0.2 µg/g), kidney (0.24 µg/g), brain (0.32 µg/g), and lung (0.49 µg/g).<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> PQ mainly accumulates in the lungs (pulmonary concentrations can be 6 to 10
times higher than those in plasma) and remains in the lungs even as blood levels
begin to drop.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> PQ poisoning can lead to multiple organ dysfunction syndrome
(MODS).<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>The development of MODS is wildly believed to be the result of uncontrolled immune
system dysfunction and the resulting systemic inflammatory response is characterized
by the release of large amounts of inflammatory mediators and extensive genomic
activation patterns.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> MODS is the leading reason of morbidity and mortality in the intensive care units.<sup><xref rid="bibr10-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The lost homeostasis between pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory reaction
is considered to play a vital role in the progression of MODS.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Generally, anti-inflammatory therapy is the major regimen in the early
therapy of PQ poisoning.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> And many genes, including microRNAs (miRNAs), have been found to be
differentially expressed in the occurrence and development of inflammation and
therefore can be used as candidate targets for gene treatment.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Recent study has reported that miR-27a might regulate the MODS process
induced by PQ poisoning via regulating the inflammatory response, and IL-10 is
involved in this process.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Additionally, miR-146a might be involved in the occurrence of lung injury
induced by PQ poisoning, which was achieved via IL-6.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p><p>Toll like receptor 4 (TLR4) is a pattern recognition receptor, which is a vital part
of the innate immune system and has the regulatory effects on the acute inflammatory response.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Liu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> found that the mRNA level of TLR4 markedly increased in lung tissue treated
by PQ, consequently TLR4 might play a vital role in PQ-induced acute lung injury. A
study by Dong et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> revealed that the TLR4 might function as a mediator, suggesting the vital
role of TLR4 in PQ-induced myocardial injury. Up to now, the key role of miRNAs
played in regulating TLR4 has been widely studied. In the study of the role of
miR-124 in regulating the TLR4 signaling pathway of microglia, miR-124 could inhibit
the TLR4 levels.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Additionally, the TLR4 was reported to be a direct target of miR-590, and
miR-590 promoted proliferation and blocked ox-LDL-induced apoptosis in HAECs by
inhibiting the TLR4/NF-KB pathway.<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Yu et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> found that long noncoding RNAs (lncRNA) PCAT1 negatively regulated
miR-145-5p, which promoted TLR4 expression and promoted osteogenic differentiation
by activating the TLR signaling pathway. MiR-219-5p has been known to be associated
with the regulation of inflammatory response.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bibr22-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> However, as far as we know,
miR-219-5p has not been previously studied in relation to PQ poisoning, nor its
relationship with TLR4. For exploring the regulatory mechanism of TLR4, the miRNA
molecules that may regulate TLR4 were predicted by bioinformatics prediction method.
The complementary binding sequence of miR-219-5p was found in the 3’-UTR of TLR4
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974888">Figure 1a</xref>), suggesting
that miR-219-5p may be a potential regulator of TLR4. Therefore, we suspected that
miR-219-5p might play a potential role in the MODS caused by PQ poisoning by
regulating TLR4-related inflammatory response.</p><fig id="fig1-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>TLR4 is a direct target gene of miR-219-5p. (a) Schematic illustration of the
miR-219-5p targeting site at the 3’-UTR of TLR4 gene. (b) The serum
miR-219-5p expression levels was upregulated by the miR-219-5p mimic
(***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). (c) Luciferase activity was
inhibited by overexpression of miR-219-5p in WT group
(*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-fig1.jpg"/></fig><p>In this study, serum miR-219-5p levels and TLR4 levels in MODS patients induced by PQ
poisoning were measured, the correlation between TLR4 and miR-219-5p as well as the
correlation of them with pro-inflammatory cytokines in MODS patients were discussed,
and the clinical value of miR-219-5p was further explored.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-2058738420974888"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="section3-2058738420974888"><title>Patients and sample collection</title><p>A total of 75 patients with MODS caused by acute PQ poisoning were
retrospectively analyzed in this study, who visited the emergency department of
Qingdao Jiaozhou Central Hospital from 2012 to 2017. The inclusion criteria: (1)
all patients arrived at the hospital within 24 h of poisoning; (2) the poisons
were all taken orally with the estimated amount of 10–80 mL; (3) all patients
were diagnosed following Fry reported diagnostic criteria.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> As soon as admission to hospital, 10–15 mL venous blood of all patients
were collected, serum was separated and stored at −80°C for further using.
Besides, 75 healthy subjects who had physical examinations in our hospital
during the same period were enrolled in the control group and their fasting
venous blood were collected. The exclusion criteria: patients suffered from
immune or immune-related diseases, such as diabetes, tumors, chronic liver
disease, chronic kidney disease, or connective tissue disease. All patients were
treated according to a standard comical therapy regimens, including gastric
lavage, catharsis, hemoperfusion, antioxidants, high-dose intravenous
methylprednisolone and cyclophosphamide, and other treatment methods. All
procedures of this study were approved by the Ethics Committee of Qingdao
Jiaozhou Central Hospital and the written informed consents of each participant
were obtained. Each patient was followed up for 28 days and survival data were
recorded. As for the selection of sample size, which was decided based on margin
of error (set at 10%) and confidence level (set at 90%). Therefore, the minimum
sample size should be 68. In addition, we have also referred to other similar
published studies for confirming that the sample size in our cohort study is
appropriated.</p></sec><sec id="section4-2058738420974888"><title>Data collection</title><p>All data were collected and recorded on a standard basis for each patient within
24 h after admission, including: (1) Demographic parameter, such as age and
gender; (2) Time interval between PQ intake and admission to the emergency
department; (3) Estimation of PQ intake; (4) Blood biochemical indexes included
white blood count (WBC), blood urea nitrogen (BUN), alanine transaminase (ALT)
and aspartate transaminase (AST); (5) Arterial partial pressure of carbon
dioxide (PaCO<sub>2</sub>) and blood lactic acid (Lac) were measured using
i-STAT blood gas analyzer (Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, USA).</p></sec><sec id="section5-2058738420974888"><title>Cell culture and transfection</title><p>Human kidney epithelial cells 239 cells were purchased from Shanghai Cell Bank of
Chinese Academy of Science (Shanghai, China) for luciferase reporting
experiment. The cells were cultured using Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium
(DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco, Grand Island, New
York), and sustained in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere at 37°C. MiR-219-5p mimic
and corresponding negative control (NC) were used for cell transfection to
regulate the miR-219-5p expression in 239 cells, which were purchased from
GenePharma (Shanghai, China). The cells were transfected with the miR-219-5p
mimic, mimic NC using Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent (Invitrogen,
Carlsbad, California) following the manufacturer’s protocols. Cells were
collected 24 h after transfection for subsequent analyzes.</p></sec><sec id="section6-2058738420974888"><title>Luciferase reporter assay</title><p>The putative binding site of miR-219-5p at the 3’-UTR of TLR4 was predicted using
miRanda (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microrna.org/microrna/home.do">http://www.microrna.org/microrna/home.do</ext-link>). To confirm whether
there was a direct interaction between miR-219-5p and TLR4, a luciferase
reporter assay was performed. The wild-type (WT) 3’-UTR containing the binding
site of miR-219-5p or mutant-type (MT) 3’-UTR were inserted in the pGL-control
vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The combined vectors were respectively
co-transfected into 239 cells with miR-219-5p mimic or mimic NC using
Lipofectamine 3000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) according to the
instruction of manufacturer. 48 h after transfection, the activity of firefly
luciferase was evaluated by a Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System
(Promega).</p></sec><sec id="section7-2058738420974888"><title>RNA extraction and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction
(qRT-PCR)</title><p>Trizol Reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) was used to extract total RNA from
serum samples following the protocol of manufacturer. MiScript Reverse
Transcription Kit (QIAGEN, Germany) was used to perform reverse transcriptions.
The miR-219-5p expression was estimated by qRT-PCR, which was carried out with
SYBR green I Master Mix kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). U6 was used as an
internal control. The final miR-219-5p expression was calculated using the
2<sup>-∆∆Ct</sup> method<sup><xref rid="bibr24-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> and normalized to U6.</p></sec><sec id="section8-2058738420974888"><title>Enzyme-linked immune sorbent assay</title><p>The concentration of serum TLR4 and the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines
(IL-1β and TNF-α) were all measured by ELISA method, which was carried out
according to the instructions of manufacturer (Germany, IBL Company). TLR4
concentration and the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines were calculated
according to the standard curves provided by the kits.</p></sec><sec id="section9-2058738420974888"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyzes were performed by using SPSS 21.0 software (SPSS, Inc.,
Chicago, USA) and GraphPad Prism 7.0 software (Inc., Chicago, USA). All data
were presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). The measurement data was
compared using student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, and the counting information
was compared using chi-square test. Correlation of miR-219-5p and TLR4 levels
with APACHE II score were assessed using Pearson’s correlation coefficient.
Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was applied to assess the
diagnostic value of miR-219-5p in MODS caused by PQ poisoning. Kaplan-Meier and
Cox regression analysis were used to evaluate the prognostic value of
miR-219-5p. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically
significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section10-2058738420974888"><title>Results</title><sec id="section11-2058738420974888"><title>TLR4 is a direct target gene of miR-219-5p</title><p>To confirm whether there was a direct interaction between miR-219-5p and TLR4, a
luciferase reporter assay was conducted. A binding site of miR-219-5p was
identified in the 3’-UTR of TLR4, indicating that miR-219-5p can directly bind
toTLR4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974888">Figure 1a</xref>). By
cell transfection, miR-219-5p expression in the 239 cells was significantly
upregulated by the miR-219-5p mimic (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974888">Figure 1b</xref>). Additionally,
the results luciferase reporter assay indicated that the miR-219-5p upregulation
significantly inhibited the relative luciferase activity in WT group
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), while there was no change in the MUT group
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2058738420974888">Figure 1c</xref>). These
data indicated that miR-219-5p could directly targeted TLR4.</p></sec><sec id="section12-2058738420974888"><title>Serum miR-219-5p expression in patients with MODS induced by PQ
poisoning</title><p>The serum miR-219-5p levels were measured using RT-qPCR in all MODS patients and
controls. The results indicated that serum miR-219-5p level was markedly reduced
in MODS patients compared with those in the controls (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;
0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2058738420974888">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Serum miR-219-5p level was markedly decreased in MODS patients induced by
PQ poisoning compared with those in controls
(***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-fig2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section13-2058738420974888"><title>Association of miR-219-5p expression with clinicopathological characteristics
of MODS patients induced by PQ poisoning</title><p>To explore the role of miR-219-5p in the development of MODS caused by PQ
poisoning, the association between miR-219-5p and the clinicopathological
features of all patients were examined. The MODS patients were classified into
low (n = 39) and high (n = 36) miR-219-5p expression groups based on the mean
value of the expression of miR-219-5p. As shown in <xref rid="table1-2058738420974888" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, miR-219-5p expression was
clearly associated with WBC (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018), ALT
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.012), AST (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), PaCO2
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), Lac (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), and APACHE
II score (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), whereas no significant association was
observed between miR-219-5p and other clinicopathological features, including
gender, age, time to hospital, estimated amount, BUN (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
&gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="table1-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Association of miR-219-5p expression with the clinicopathological
characteristics of MODS patients induced by paraquat poisoning.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low miR-219-5p expression
(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 39)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High miR-219-5p expression
(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 36)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.923 ± 9.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.194 ± 8.978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.551</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hospital (h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.256 ± 5.632</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.611 ± 4.842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated amount (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.414 ± 16.758</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.817 ± 15.308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.873</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.180 ± 2.424</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.985 ± 1.762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.928 ± 1.753</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.598 ± 1.527</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.389</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.703 ± 28.689</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142.206 ± 22.424</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.327 ± 28.456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.358 ± 13.836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaCO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.626 ± 2.264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.659 ± 3.260</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lac</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.733 ± 0.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.304 ± 0.570</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">APACHE II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.037 ± 2.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.255 ± 1.883</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-2058738420974888"><p>WBC: white blood count; BUN: blood urea nitrogen; ALT: alanine
transaminase; AST: aspartate transaminase; PaCO<sub>2</sub>: partial
pressure of carbon dioxide; Lac: arterial blood lactic acid; APACHE
II: the acute physiology and chronic health evaluation II score.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section14-2058738420974888"><title>Diagnostic value of miR-219-5p and its correlation with disease severity in
MODS patients</title><p>In view of the significant dysregulation of serum miR-219-5p expression in the
MODS patients. A ROC curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738420974888">Figure 3a</xref>) was plotted to assess the diagnostic value of serum
miR-219-5p in this study. The area under the curve (AUC) for miR-219-5p was
0.891 with a sensitivity of 89.33% and a specificity of 76% at the cutoff of
0.800, indicating the considerable diagnostic accuracy of the serum miR-219-5p
expression in MODS patients. Additionally, we observed a negative correlation
between miR-219-5p expression and APACHE II score in MODS patients
(<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.403, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-2058738420974888">Figure 3b</xref>), suggesting
that miR-219-5p was negatively correlated with the disease severity in patients
with MODS induced by PQ poisoning.</p><fig id="fig3-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Diagnostic value of miR-219-5p and its correlation with disease severity
in patients with MODS induced by PQ poisoning. (a) ROC curve for MODS
patients based on serum miR-219-5p, which had an AUC of 0.891 with the
sensitivity of 89.33% and specificity of 76%. (b) Correlation between
APACHE Ⅱ score and miR-219-5p expression in MODS patients induced by PQ
poisoning (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.403, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-fig3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-2058738420974888"><title>Prognostic value of miR-219-5p for the 28-day survival of MODS
patients</title><p>According to 28-day survival, all 75 MODS patients induced by PQ poisoning were
grouped into two groups: survival group (n = 26) and non-survival group (n =
49). Thus, the 28-day survival rate (%) was 34.67 in the 75 MODS patients. As
shown in <xref rid="table2-2058738420974888" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>,
non-survivors had markedly high levels of WBC, BUN, ALT, AST, Lac, and markedly
low levels of PaCO<sub>2</sub> compared with the survivals (all
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Besides, as for the traditional score
between survival and non-survival group, non-survivors had markedly higher
APACHE II score (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Moreover, the miR-219-5p
expression level was markedly different between survival and non-survival group
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), the expression of miR-219-5p was markedly
low in non-survival group.</p><table-wrap id="table2-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The comparisons between survivors and non-survivors of MODS patients
induced by paraquat poisoning.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-table2.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survivors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 26)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-survivors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 49)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MiR-219-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.683 ± 0.219</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.486 ± 0.214</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.115 ± 9.816</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.755 ± 8.857</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hospital (h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.115 ± 6.035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.653 ± 4.918</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated amount (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.853 ± 14.305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.926 ± 16.239</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.765 ± 1.323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.583 ± 1.937</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.362 ± 1.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.517 ± 1.375</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.097 ± 19.244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.557 ± 21.773</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.912 ± 13.060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.611 ± 22.356</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaCO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.257 ± 2.982</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.723 ± 2.553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lac</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.005 ± 0.434</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.804 ± 0.512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">APACHE II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.528 ± 1.546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.855 ± 2.337</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn2-2058738420974888"><p>WBC: white blood count; BUN: blood urea nitrogen; ALT: alanine
transaminase; AST: aspartate transaminase; PaCO<sub>2</sub>: partial
pressure of carbon dioxide; Lac: arterial blood lactic acid; APACHE
II: the acute physiology and chronic health evaluation Ⅱ score.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Moreover, the Kaplan-Meier survival curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-2058738420974888">Figure 4</xref>) was established to analyze the
correlation between miR-219-5p expression and the survival depending on the
28-day survival. From the Kaplan-Meier survival curves, we observed that the
patients with low miR-219-5p expression had markedly shorter survival time than
the patients with high miR-219-5p expression (log-rank <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;
0.001). The further multivariate Cox regression analyses indicated that
miR-219-5p expression and APACHE II score were two independent prognostic
factors for 28-day survival in patients with MODS (all <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;
0.05, <xref rid="table3-2058738420974888" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Kaplan-Meier survival curves in the MODS patients induced by PQ
poisoning. The survival time of patients with low miR-219-5p expression
was shorter than those patients with high miR-219-5p expression
(Log-Rank <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-fig4.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="table3-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Multivariate cox regression analysis for miR-219-5p in MODS patients
induced by paraquat poisoning.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-table3.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariate analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MiR-219-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.174–24.342</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.736–2.817</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700–2.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.373</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to hospital (h)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.798–3.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated amount (mL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.445</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755–2.766</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686–2.384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.438</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622–2.452</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.206</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630–2.310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.572</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.682</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.796–3.553</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaCO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.621–2.579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.517</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lac</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.391</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.622–3.111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.422</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">APACHE II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.090–4.724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-2058738420974888"><p>WBC: white blood count; BUN: blood urea nitrogen; ALT: alanine
transaminase; AST: aspartate transaminase; PaCO<sub>2</sub>: partial
pressure of carbon dioxide; Lac: arterial blood lactic acid; APACHE
II: the acute physiology and chronic health evaluation II score.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section16-2058738420974888"><title>Negative correlation between miR-219-5p and TLR4 in MODS patients</title><p>The serum TLR4 expression levels was measured using ELISA in MODS patients and
controls. The results indicated that the serum TLR4 level was markedly increased
in MODS patients compared with the TLR4 level in the controls
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974888">Figure 5a</xref>). Furthermore, we observed a
negative correlation between serum miR-219-5p and TLR4 in patients with MODS
induced by PQ poisoning (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = −0.660, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt;
0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-2058738420974888">Figure 5b</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The correlation between serum miR-219-5p level and TLR4 level in MODS
patients induced by PQ poisoning. (a) Serum TLR4 level was markedly
increased in MODS patients compared with those in controls. (b) Serum
miR-219-5p expression levels was negatively correlated with serum TLR4
levels in MODS patients induced by PQ poisoning
(<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = –0.660, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-fig5.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section17-2058738420974888"><title>Correlation of miR-219-5p and TLR4 with pro-inflammatory cytokines in MODS
patients</title><p>The inflammatory response in MODS patients were determined by measuring the serum
pro-inflammatory cytokines, including IL-1β and TNF-α. The results shown in
<xref rid="table4-2058738420974888" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
indicated the negative correlation of miR-219-5p levels with pro-inflammatory
cytokines and positive correlation of TLR4 with pro-inflammatory cytokines,
which implied the potential correlation of miR-219-5p and TLR4 with inflammation
in MODS progression.</p><table-wrap id="table4-2058738420974888" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Correlation of miR-219-5p and TLR4 with pro-inflammatory cytokines in
MODS patients induced by paraquat poisoning.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-table4.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">IL-1β</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">TNF-α</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">r</italic> value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MiR-219-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.482</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.501</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TLR4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section18-2058738420974888"><title>Discussion</title><p>PQ, an agent highly toxic to humans and animals, is a widely used herbicide.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>Acute PQ poisoning can cause a strong inflammatory reaction.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Activated TLR4 is a receptor of the innate immune system that has key effect
on the regulation of inflammation.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> A study indicated that the inflammation mediated by TLR4 played a key role in
the occurrence of kidney damage and fibrosis in cyclosporine nephrotoxicity.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> And Nrf2 could protect lung cells by regulating the TLR4 and Akt signaling
pathways, suggesting TLR4 mediated inflammatory-related lung injury.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> These studies suggested that TLR4 was important in inflammatory response. In
addition, some studies has suggested that TlR4 played an important role in PQ
poisoning.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr18-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></p><p>MiRNAs are widely involved in a variety of pathophysiological processes, including
cancer, cardiovascular and metabolic diseases.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="bibr31-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr32-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> According the results of
bioinformatics, miR-219-5p may be a potential regulator of TLR4, suggesting the
potential role of miR-219-5p in PQ poisoning. Thus, in this study, a total of 75
patients with PQ poisoning MODS and 75 healthy controls were collected, and serum
miR-219-5p levels were compared between control group and case group. The results
showed that the serum miR-219-5p level of PQ poisoning MODS patients was
significantly lower than the serum miR-219-3p level of health control group.
Clinical data analysis revealed that serum miR-219-5p was significantly associated
with WBC, ALT, AST, PaCO<sub>2</sub>, Lac and APACHE II score. We knew that patients
with PQ poisoning develop multiple organ dysfunction, including lung, kidney, liver
and heart. ALT and AST are indicators of liver function, while PaCO<sub>2</sub> and
Lac are important indicators of lung function and respiratory function,
respectively. Chen et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> found that miR-219-5p prevented cirrhosis through increasing keratinocyte
growth factor (KGF). The study by Gao et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr34-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> indicated that miR-219-5p was differentially expressed in liver cirrhosis,
suggesting that miR-219-5p might affect the process of liver cirrhosis. The above
evidence indicated the important role of miR-219-5p in liver injury. Thus, we
speculate that miR-219-5p may be involved in organ damage in MODS patients cause by
PQ poisoning, which supported our present results.</p><p>We further analyzed the diagnostic and prognostic significance of miR-219-5p in
patients with PQ poisoning MODS. In this study, serum miR-219-5p level was
downregulated in patients compared with the controls. According to the ROC curve,
miR-219-5p may be a diagnostic biomarker for MODS caused by PQ poisoning. Besides,
we observed a significantly negative correlation between APACHE II score and
miR-219-5p expression in MODS patients, suggesting that miR-219-5p was negatively
correlated with the severity in patients with MODS induced by PQ poisoning. All
patients were then divided into survival and non-survival groups based on 28-day
survival. Compared with the surviving patients, the levels of WBC, BUN, ALT, AST and
Lac were higher and levels of PaCO<sub>2</sub> was lower in non-surviving patients,
reflecting the loss of kidney, liver and lung injury. We also found that there were
more patients with low expression of miR-219-5p in the non-survival group,
suggesting that the expression of miR-219-5p was associated with 28-day survival in
patients with MODS caused by PQ poisoning. And the results of KM curves also showed
that the patients with low expression of miR-219-5p had shorter survival time. In
addition, multivariate Cox regression analysis suggested that miR-219-5p level and
APACHE II score were two independent prognostic factor for 28-day survival. However,
the APACHE II score has been shown to assess the prognosis of acute PQ poisoning.<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> This study indicated the significant correlation of serum miR-219-5p level
with APACHE II score, suggesting that miR-219-5p was significantly correlated with
PQ poisoning severity. Therefore, we believe that serum miR-219-5p may be a
valuablel clinical tool for MODS patients by PQ poisoning.</p><p>In this study, bioinformatics analysis showed that miR-219-5p may be a potential
regulator of TLR4. The results of this study indicated that serum TLR4 expression
was increased and serum miR-219-5p was decreased in MODS patients caused by PQ
poisoning, and was negatively correlated with TLR4. Finally, the double luciferase
reporter gene experiment proved that TLR4 was a direct target gene of miR-219-5p.
Therefore, we speculate that miR-219-5p may play a potential role in the MODS
patients caused by PQ poisoning by regulating TLR4. Furthermore, considering the
differentially expression of miR-219-5p in the progression of inflammation and the
regulatory effects of TLR4 on the inflammation, we explored the correlation of
miR-219-5p and TLR4 with pro-inflammatory cytokines in MODS patients. Negative
correlation of miR-219-5p levels with pro-inflammatory cytokines and positive
correlation of TLR4 with pro-inflammatory cytokines were found. Thus, we considered
that miR-219-5p might be involved in the MODS progression by regulating TLR4-related
inflammatory response.</p><p>There are still some limitations in this study. The clinicopathological parameters of
the included patients were not comprehensive enough and the data collection was
incomplete. Other clinicopathological parameters can be added to better examine the
association between miR-219-5p levels and different organ dysfunction, such as serum
cardiac troponin I (cTnI), serum creatinine (SCr), and so on. Moreover, the sample
size is relatively small, which needs to be further increased in the further
research. Furthermore, recent studies have found that activation of Sirtuin 1 plays
important role in protecting lung injury induced by PQ and Sirtuin 1 is now strongly
linked to MODS, thus, its activation is important to prevent lung injury and
MODS.<sup><xref rid="bibr36-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><xref rid="bibr37-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr38-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="bibr39-2058738420974888" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> Thus, plasma Sirtuin 1 levels
may be relevant to the diagnosis of PQ-induced MODS. We suspected that the relevance
of Sirtuin 1 and miR-219-5p may be relevant to PQ poisoning. However, it remains to
be determined if Sirtuin 1 analysis is more sensitive to PQ-induced MODS when
compared with miR-219-5p, which needs to be further study in the research.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section19-2058738420974888"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, the results of this study indicated that serum miR-219-5p expression
level was decreased, serum TLR4 expression level was increased, and a negative
correlation was observed between them in MODS patients induced by acute PQ
poisoning. Additionally, serum miR-219-5p level might be a new diagnostic and
prognostic factor for MODS patients induced by PQ poisoning. Moreover, TLR4 was
demonstrated as a direct target gene of miR-219-5p and significant correlation of
miR-219-5p and TLR4 with inflammatory cytokines was found, indicating that
miR-219-5p may be involved in the pathogenesis of MODS by regulating the
TLR4-related inflammatory response.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval and consent to participate:</bold> A signed written informed consent was obtained from each patient and the
experimental procedures were all in accordance with the guideline of the Ethics
Committee of Qingdao Jiaozhou Central Hospital (#JZCHh20111025).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Consent for publication:</bold> Written informed consent for publication was obtained from each participant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Yuming Gao <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_2058738420974888-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7133-2238">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7133-2238</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Availability of data and material:</bold> All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published
article.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2058738420974888"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Effects
of paraquat ban on herbicide poisoning-related mortality</article-title>.
<source>Yonsei Medical Journal</source>
<volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>859</fpage>–<lpage>866</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28541002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3349/ymj.2017.58.4.859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5447120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2058738420974888"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawarammana</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Medical management of
paraquat ingestion</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical
Pharmacology</source>
<volume>72</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>757</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21615775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2125.2011.04026.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3243009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2058738420974888"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>Metabolic profiling of amino acids associated with mortality
in patients with acute paraquat poisoning</article-title>. <source>Medical
Science Monitor: International Medical Journal of Experimental and Clinical
Research</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1397</fpage>–<lpage>1407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29513648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.905843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5854108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2058738420974888"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Paraquat poisoning mechanism
and its clinical treatment progress</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua wei
zhong bing ji jiu yi xue</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):
<fpage>1043</fpage>–<lpage>1046</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29151425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3760/cma.j.issn.2095-4352.2017.11.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2058738420974888"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Homicidal paraquat poisoning</article-title>. <source>Journal
of Forensic Sciences</source>
<volume>64</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>941</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1556-4029.13945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2058738420974888"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinis-Oliveira</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Navarro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Paraquat
poisonings: Mechanisms of lung toxicity, clinical features, and
treatment</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Toxicology</source>
<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18161502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10408440701669959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2058738420974888"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>)
<article-title>Correlation of plasma endothelin and multiple organ
dysfunction syndrome caused by acute paraquat poisoning</article-title>.
<source>Zhongguo wei zhong bing ji jiu yi xue = Chinese Critical Care
Medicine = Zhongguo weizhongbing jijiuyixue</source>
<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15877960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2058738420974888"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Clinical
analysis of multiple organ dysfunction syndrome caused by acute paraquat
poisoning</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua lao dong wei sheng zhi ye bing
za zhi = Zhonghua laodong weisheng zhiyebing zazhi = Chinese Journal of
Industrial Hygiene and Occupational Diseases</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>519</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22214158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-2058738420974888"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De’Ath</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Early
changes within the lymphocyte population are associated with the development
of multiple organ dysfunction syndrome in trauma patients</article-title>.
<source>Critical Care</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>176</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27268230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13054-016-1341-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4895987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-2058738420974888"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The cytokine storm and
factors determining the sequence and severity of organ dysfunction in
multiple organ dysfunction syndrome</article-title>. <source>The American
Journal of Emergency Medicine</source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajem.2007.10.031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-2058738420974888"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Multiple organ dysfunction
syndrome</article-title>. <source>Current Problems in Pediatric and
Adolescent Health Care</source>
<volume>43</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):
<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24295608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cppeds.2013.10.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-2058738420974888"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Pozo-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente-Pascual</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>Targeting corneal inflammation by gene therapy: Emerging
strategies for keratitis</article-title>. <source>Experimental Eye
Research</source>
<volume>176</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29981344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.exer.2018.07.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-2058738420974888"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Clinical
significance of serum levels of microRNA-27a and its correlation with
interleukin-10 in patients with multiple organ dysfunction syndrome caused
by acute paraquat poisoning</article-title>. <source>Experimental and
Therapeutic Medicine</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>1961</fpage>–<lpage>1968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32104255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/etm.2020.8409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7027156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-2058738420974888"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Lung injury caused by
paraquat poisoning results in increased interleukin-6 and decreased
microRNA-146a levels</article-title>. <source>Experimental and Therapeutic
Medicine</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29896267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/etm.2018.6153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5995050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-2058738420974888"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iotzova-Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freiberger</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>TLR4 as
a negative regulator of keratinocyte proliferation</article-title>.
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):
<fpage>e0185668</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28982115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0185668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5628845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-2058738420974888"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>)
<article-title>Toll-like receptor 4 implicated in acute lung injury induced
by paraquat poisoning in mice</article-title>. <source>International Journal
of Clinical and Experimental Medicine</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):
<fpage>3392</fpage>–<lpage>3397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25419373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4238491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-2058738420974888"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>)
<article-title>Toll-like receptor 4 is involved in myocardial damage
following paraquat poisoning in mice</article-title>.
<source>Toxicology</source>
<volume>312</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23969119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tox.2013.08.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-2058738420974888"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Periyasamy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>Cocaine-mediated downregulation of miR-124 activates
microglia by targeting KLF4 and TLR4 signaling</article-title>.
<source>Molecular Neurobiology</source>
<volume>55</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>3196</fpage>–<lpage>3210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28478506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12035-017-0584-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5673594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-2058738420974888"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>MiR-590 inhibits endothelial cell apoptosis by
inactivating the TLR4/NF-kappaB pathway in atherosclerosis</article-title>.
<source>Yonsei Medical Journal</source>
<volume>60</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30799593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3349/ymj.2019.60.3.298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6391523</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12673646"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-2058738420974888"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>)
<article-title>LncRNA-PCAT1 targeting miR-145-5p promotes TLR4-associated
osteogenic differentiation of adipose-derived stem cells</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</source>
<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):
<fpage>6134</fpage>–<lpage>6147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30338912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jcmm.13892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6237555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-2058738420974888"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fredman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>)
<article-title>Self-limited versus delayed resolution of acute inflammation:
Temporal regulation of pro-resolving mediators and microRNA</article-title>.
<source>Scientific Reports</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22957142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep00639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3434392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-2058738420974888"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2020</year>)
<article-title>Upregulation of microRNA-219-5p relieves ulcerative colitis
through balancing the differentiation of Treg/Th17 cells</article-title>.
<source>European Journal of Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology</source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):
<fpage>813</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32175983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MEG.0000000000001712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7269018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-2058738420974888"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Multiple system organ
failure</article-title>. <source>The Surgical Clinics of North
America</source>
<volume>68</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0039-6109(16)44435-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-2058738420974888"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene
expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta
C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-2058738420974888"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>A
survival case of intravenous paraquat intoxication: A case
report</article-title>. <source>Medicine</source>
<volume>97</volume>(<issue>30</issue>): <fpage>e11669</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30045322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MD.0000000000011669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6078682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-2058738420974888"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Effects of paraquat on IL-6
and TNF-alpha in macrophages</article-title>. <source>Experimental and
Therapeutic Medicine</source>
<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>1783</fpage>–<lpage>1789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30783450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/etm.2018.7099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6364147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-2058738420974888"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Role of the toll like
receptor (TLR) radical cycle in chronic inflammation: Possible treatments
targeting the TLR4 pathway</article-title>. <source>Molecular
Neurobiology</source>
<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23436141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12035-013-8425-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7091222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-2058738420974888"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Guerrero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannata-Ortiz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>)
<article-title>TLR4-mediated inflammation is a key pathogenic event leading
to kidney damage and fibrosis in cyclosporine
nephrotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Archives of Toxicology</source>
<volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>1925</fpage>–<lpage>1939</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27585667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00204-016-1830-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-2058738420974888"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Nrf2
protects against acute lung injury and inflammation by modulating TLR4 and
Akt signaling</article-title>. <source>Free Radical Biology &amp;
Medicine</source>
<volume>121</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29678610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2018.04.557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-2058738420974888"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Correia de Sousa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gjorgjieva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolicka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2019</year>)
<article-title>Deciphering miRNAs’ action through miRNA
editing</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Molecular
Sciences</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>24</issue>): <fpage>6249</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms20246249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31835747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-2058738420974888"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barwari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs in cardiovascular
disease</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American College of
Cardiology</source>
<volume>68</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):
<fpage>2577</fpage>–<lpage>2584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27931616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.09.945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-2058738420974888"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rupaimoole</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA therapeutics:
Towards a new era for the management of cancer and other
diseases</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Drug Discovery</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrd.2016.246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-2058738420974888"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>Suppression of microRNA-219-5p activates keratinocyte growth
factor to mitigate severity of experimental cirrhosis</article-title>.
<source>Cellular Physiology and Biochemistry: International Journal of
Experimental Cellular Physiology, Biochemistry, and Pharmacology</source>
<volume>40</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):
<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000452542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27855391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-2058738420974888"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Coding
and non-coding gene regulatory networks underlie the immune response in
liver cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>e0174142</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28355233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0174142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5371304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-2058738420974888"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Further
evidence of the usefulness of acute physiology and chronic health evaluation
II scoring system in acute paraquat poisoning</article-title>.
<source>Clinical Toxicology</source>
<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16615662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/15563650500514251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-2058738420974888"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Single gene inactivation with
implications to diabetes and multiple organ dysfunction
syndrome</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epigenetics</source>
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>24</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-2058738420974888"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Sirtuin 1, a diagnostic
protein marker and its relevance to chronic disease and therapeutic drug
interventions</article-title>. <source>EC Pharmacology and
Toxicology</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-2058738420974888"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>SIRT1
exerts protective effects against paraquat-induced injury in mouse type II
alveolar epithelial cells by deacetylating NRF2 in vitro</article-title>.
<source>International Journal of Molecular Medicine</source>
<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>1049</fpage>–<lpage>1058</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ijmm.2016.2503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-2058738420974888"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>)
<article-title>Resveratrol protects mice from paraquat-induced lung injury:
The important role of SIRT1 and NRF2 antioxidant pathways</article-title>.
<source>Molecular Medicine Reports</source>
<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>1833</fpage>–<lpage>1838</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2015.4710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>