
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1915</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bsr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">8102797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7729292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7729292.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7729292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7729292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33245094</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20202387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BSR20202387</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cardiovascular System &amp; Vascular Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Diagnostics &amp; Biomarkers</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Host-Microbe Interactions</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Virology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="toc-heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Screening and validation of differentially expressed microRNAs and target genes in hypertensive mice induced by cytomegalovirus infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="Y">YunZhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names initials="D">DongMei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="X">XiaoNi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="N">Na</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Y">YongMin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="L">LaMei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names initials="H">Hua</given-names></name><email>156696992@qq.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="no"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5986-8398</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="F">Fang</given-names></name><email>fangf2002shz@126.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathophysiology/Key Laboratory of Education Ministry of Xinjiang Endemic and Ethnic Diseases, Medical College of Shihezi University, Shihezi, China</aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label>Second Department of Emergency and Critical Care Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital of Medical College of Shihezi University, Shihezi, China</aff><aff id="AFF3"><label>3</label>The Centre of Medical Functional Experiments, Medical College of Shihezi University, Shihezi, China</aff><aff id="AFF4"><label>4</label>Department of Geriatrics, The First Affiliated Hospital of Medical College, Shihezi University, Shihezi, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Hua Zhong (<email>156696992@qq.com</email>) or Fang He (<email>fangf2002shz@126.com</email>)</corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-12-10"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>12</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">369643</issue-id><elocation-id>BSR20202387</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted-manuscript"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-31 22:25:13.213"><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the .</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Introduction:</bold> Multiple studies have suggested an association between cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection and essential hypertension (EH). MicroRNAs (miRNAs) play a critical role in the development of EH by regulating the expression of specific target genes. However, little is known about the role of miRNAs in CMV-induced EH. In the present study, we compared the miRNA expression profiles of samples from normal and murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV)-infected C57BL/6 mice using high-throughput sequencing analysis. <bold>Methods:</bold> We collected the thoracic aorta, heart tissues, and peripheral blood from 20 normal mice and 20 MCMV-infected mice. We identified differentially expressed miRNAs in the peripheral blood samples and predicted their target genes using bioinformatics tools. We then experimentally validated them using quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) and the target genes with double luciferase reporter gene assay. <bold>Results:</bold> We found 118 differentially expressed miRNAs, among which 9 miRNAs were identified as potential MCMV infection-induced hypertension regulators. We then validated the expression of two candidate miRNAs, mmu-miR-1929-3p and mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p, using qRT-PCR. Furthermore, the dual-luciferase reporter gene assay revealed that the 3′-untranslated region (UTR) of endothelin A receptor (<italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>) messenger RNA (mRNA) contained a binding site for mmu-miR-1929-3p. Collectively, our data suggest that MCMV infection can raise the blood pressure and reduce mmu-miR-1929-3p expression in C57BL/6 mice. Moreover, we found that mmu-miR-1929-3p targets the 3′-UTR of the <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> mRNA. <bold>Conclusion:</bold> This novel regulatory axis could aid the development of new approaches for the clinical prevention and control of EH.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cytomegalovirus infection</kwd><kwd>essential hypertension</kwd><kwd>miRNA</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hypertension is one of the most common chronic diseases, affecting more than 1 billion people worldwide [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Chronically elevated blood pressure is a common cause of chronic renal failure, myocardial infarction, stroke, heart failure, and death [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Approximately 90‒95% of all the hypertension cases are classified as essential hypertension (EH) [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although the prevention and treatment of hypertension have made great progress in the past decade, the etiology and pathogenesis of hypertension have not been fully elucidated yet. A recent study showed that hypertension is not only related to the interaction between genetic and environmental factors but also with viral infections and non-coding RNAs, such as microRNA (miRNA) [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Another population association study showed that the human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) and miRNAs encoded by HCMV are correlated to hypertension [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. HCMV is a member of the cytomegalovirus (CMV) genus, and the prevalence of HCMV infection has been estimated in the 40–100% range [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Moreover, a European study has shown an independent correlation between HCMV infection and blood pressure [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, at present, the relationship between HCMV infection and hypertension remains unclear. Some studies suggested that the mechanism of CMV infection-induced hypertension may be correlated to oxidative stress and endothelial dysfunction [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Alternatively, HCMV could promote hypertension through developmental and metabolic disorders to vascular smooth muscle cells [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Due to the high prevalence of hypertension and widespread HCMV infection, it is particularly important to clarify the role of HCMV in hypertension pathogenesis.</p><p>HCMV is a ubiquitous β herpes virus that has the largest known genome among human herpesviruses (230 kb) encoding a variety of factors that modulate the host immune response [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. HCMV infection can cause latent infection and toxic lytic infection, depending on the host’s response to the infection. In latent infection, the virus does not replicate, although the viral genome and proteins remain in the host cells. When the immune system is normal, HCMV infection will not cause any uncomfortable symptoms [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, when the host defenses are impaired—in fetuses, infants, young children, and people with low immunity—the virus immediately gets activated, causing a toxic lytic infection which can lead to extensive damage [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A recent study has shown that HCMV infection is associated with increased systolic blood pressure (SBP) in healthy old people [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV) has been also associated with an increase in blood pressure. Interestingly, MCMV infection increased the expression of renin in renal cells, suggesting that the renin-mediated increase in the blood volume may contribute to hypertension [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The molecular mechanisms underlying the correlation between HCMV infection and elevated blood pressure have not been elucidated. We hypothesized that miRNAs, including virus-encoded miRNA, could be involved in HCMV-mediated hypertension.</p><p>MiRNAs are highly conserved, single-stranded, non-coding small RNAs (19‒25 nucleotides in length) that negatively regulate the expression of their target genes at the post-transcriptional level, by directly binding to the 3′-untranslated region (UTR) or 5′-UTR of their target messenger RNAs (mRNAs) [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Previous studies have shown that several miRNAs are involved in the development of primary hypertension [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Inhibition of miRNA-126 leads to bleeding, suggesting that miRNA-126 is involved in the maintenance of vascular endothelium integrity [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Moreover, miRNA-155 is up-regulated in the plasma of hypertensive subjects, where it inhibits the angiotensin II type I receptor [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Notably, Cai et al<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> have shown that the HCMV-encoded miRNA hcmv-miR-UL112 was up-regulated in hypertensive patients, and the blood pressure of the mice significantly increased 9‒12 days after adenoviral transfection of hcmv-miR-UL112 [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It has been reported that HCMV can encode at least 26 different mature miRNAs (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org">www.mirbase.org</ext-link>) [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and can change the miRNA expression profile in the host [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Given that hypertension is regulated by a complex miRNA-gene network, it is implausible that hcmv-miR-UL112 is the only miRNA involved in HCMV-mediated regulation of hypertension. Thus, further efforts are needed to identify novel miRNAs involved in HCMV-mediated hypertension.</p><p>Our previous studies found that HCMV infection is associated with EH in patients of Kazakh and Han ethnicity in Xinjiang, and is associated with EH progression and target organ damage in patients of Han ethnicity, further supporting the correlation between HCMV and hypertension [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We thus hypothesized that MCMV may be correlated to hypertension in mice through similar miRNA-induced mechanisms. Therefore, in the present study, we screened differentially expressed miRNAs in mice infected with MCMV, identified the miRNAs potentially involved in hypertension, and experimentally validated our findings to elucidate the role of MCMV in the pathogenesis of hypertension.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Mice</title><p>All experiments in the present study were carried out in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The animal model was established as previously reported. A total of 40 C57BL/6 mice (4 weeks of age) were provided by the Institutional Animal Research Committee of Shihezi University School of Medicine. All mice were housed under pathogen-free conditions in individually ventilated cages, placed in a temperature-controlled environment with a 12-h day/12-h night cycle. Mice received food and water <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>, and were kept at the Shihezi University School of Medicine animal facility. After adaptive feeding for 1 week, the mice were divided into the following two groups: the MCMV infection group (1 × 10<sup>5</sup> pfu/ml, 1 ml, intraperitoneal injection) and the control group (equivalent volume of saline solution, intraperitoneal injection). All animal experiments were conducted at the Medical College of Shihezi University and performed according to the protocols approved by the Animal Experimental Ethical Inspection of First Affiliated Hospital, Shihezi University School of Medicine (approval number: A2018-038-01).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Virus and cell culture</title><p>MCMV was maintained in NIH 3T3 cells. NIH 3T3 cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% calf serum and 1% antibiotic solution (100 U/ml of penicillin and 100 µg/ml of streptomycin). The virus was collected from the supernatant of infected NIH 3T3 (infection rate: 100%) by centrifugation (15000×<italic toggle="yes"><bold>g</bold></italic> for 20 min) and then further purified with ultracentrifugation (20000 rpm for 1 h) through a 15% sucrose cushion in a virus standard buffer (VSB, 50 mM Tris/HCl pH 7.8, 12 mM KCl, and 5 mM EDTA). The virus pellet was resuspended in 0.5–1.0 ml of VSB, aliquoted, and stored at −80°C. Viral titers were determined with standard plaque assay in NIH 3T3 cells. Both the MCMV Smith strain and NIH 3T3 cells were donated by the Department of Neurovirology, Wuhan Institute of Virology (Hubei, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Blood pressure measurement</title><p>The mice were anesthetized using sodium pentobarbital (P3761, Sigma–Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.) through intraperitoneal injection (30 mg/kg), after which they were fixed on the operating table. An incision was made along the midline of the neck and the neck tissues were separated to expose the common carotid artery. The vagus nerves surrounding the carotid artery were separated carefully. A silicone tube (internal diameter: 0.3 mm) was implanted near the artery (diameter: ∼0.5 mm) and a cannula was ligated using 6-0 silk threads to monitor the blood pressure. Then, the carotid artery was put back into position. Finally, the mice were killed by decapitation under pentobarbital anesthesia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>RNA isolation and sequencing</title><p>The total RNA was isolated from thoracic aorta samples using miRNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Germany, 217004). The total RNA isolation from peripheral blood monocytes for sequencing and validation analysis was performed using the miRcute miRNA isolation kit with the enrichment for small RNAs, following the manufacturer’s instructions (TIANGEN, DP501). RNA quality was measured using the Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, U.S.A.). Paired-end libraries were synthesized by using the QIAseq miRNA Library Kit (Qiagen, Germany) following the QIAseq miRNA Library Kit Guide. The products were then purified and enriched by PCR to create the final cDNA library. Purified libraries were quantified by Qubit® 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, U.S.A.) and validated using the Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, U.S.A.) to confirm the insert size and calculate the library concentration. A cluster was generated by cBot with the library diluted to 10 pM and then sequenced on the Illumina Hiseq Xten (Illumina, U.S.A.).</p><p>The library construction and sequencing were performed by Sinotech Genomics Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Small RNA-seq data analysis and target prediction</title><p>After removing the adoptor sequences and the contaminated reads, the clean reads were processed for letter anlysis. Sequence files (fastq) were mapped to the reference genome (GRCm38) using Bowtie. Small RNA was classified by Unitas software. The miRNA abundance was expressed as counts of exon model per million mapped reads. Differential expression analysis for mRNA was performed using DESeq software. A minimum of two-fold difference between groups and a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value ≤0.05 were used as criteria for the identification of differentially expressed miRNA genes. We then performed gene ontology (GO) enrichment analysis to annotate gene functions, according to three categories: biological process (BP), cellular component (CC), and molecular function (MF). Next, we performed an enrichment analysis using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) to systematically analyze, annotate, and visualize gene functions. Potential targets of the differentially expressed miRNAs were predicted using miRanda (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microrna.org/microrna/home.do">http://www.microrna.org/microrna/home.do</ext-link>), miRDB (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirdb.org/">http://www.mirdb.org/</ext-link>), and TargetScan (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</ext-link>). Only the genes identified by all three software were selected as target genes.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction</title><p>The integrity and purity of total RNA samples were evaluated using PCR and agarose gel electrophoresis. Total RNA samples of suitable quality were reverse transcribed into cDNA using the miRcute Plus miRNA First-Strand cDNA kit (TIANGEN, KR211). The qPCR conditions were the following (Supplementary Table S1): 95°C for 15 min; 5 cycles at 94°C for 20 s, 65°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 34 s; 45 cycles at 94°C for 20 s and 60°C for 34 s. All primers were synthesized by Shanghai Living Creature (China) (Supplementary Table S2). Gene expression levels were calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔ<italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub>t</sub></sup> method [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Plasmid construction and dual-luciferase activity assay</title><p>The full-length 3′-UTR of the endothelin A receptor (<italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>) gene was amplified by PCR and cloned downstream the pmirGLO Luciferase (Shanghai GenePharma Co., Ltd, China) multiple cloning site by digestion with the SpeI and HindIII restriction enzymes. The resulting construct was called pEdnra-wild-type (Wt). The miR-1929-3p binding site on the Ednra mRNA was mutated and cloned in the pmirGLO Luciferase plasmid to create the pEdnra-Mutant (Mut) vector. The Wt and Mut vectors were each transfected with and without miR-1929-3p into the HEK293 cells. Additionally, a dual-luciferase reporter gene assay was performed using the dual-luciferase reporter assay system (Shanghai GenePharma Co., Ltd, China).</p><p>The mmu-miR-1929-3p mimics, corresponding negative control and siRNA targeting Ednra were synthesized from GenePharma (Shanghai GenePharma Co., Ltd, China). Ednra sense 5′-CCTGGCAGGAAACAATGTCAAAGTGGCCAAATGAGCTGATTGTGTTAAGTGAGATGTAGTTACACC-3′ antisense 5′-TCGAGGTGTAACTACATCTCACTTAACACAATCAGCTCATTTGGCCACTTTGACATTGTTTCCTGCCAGGAGCT-3′; si-Ednra sense 5′-CGCAGAACAUCAAAGAAGATT-3′, antisense 5′-UCUUCUUUGAUGUUCUGCGTT-3′; negative control siRNA sense 5′-UUCUCCGAACGUGUCACGUTT-3′, antisense 5′-ACGUGACACGUUCGGAGAATT-3′.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The SPSS 21.0 statistical software (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, U.S.A.) was used for statistical analysis. Data were presented throughout the study as mean ± standard deviation. The <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for comparing the differences between the two groups. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt;0.05 indicated a statistically significant difference.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>MCMV infection raises blood pressure in C57BL/6 mice</title><p>To confirm the MCMV infection, we measured with quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) the MCMV IE1 gene expression in the thoracic aorta of mice infected with the virus (MCMV IE Forward primer: 5′-ATC AAT CAG CCA TCA ACT CTG CTA CCA CAC-3′; MCMV IE Reverse primer: 5′-ATG GTG AAG CTA TCA AAG ATG TGC ATC TCA-3′). The results confirmed that the infection was successful (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). Then, we measured the blood pressure and observed that it was significantly higher in mice infected with MCMV after 10 weeks (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B–D). However, the heart rate and weight were not significantly different between the two groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>E,F).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The MCMV infection raised blood pressure in C57BL/6 mice</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) PCR analysis of MCMV IE gene in the thoracic aorta of male C57BL/6 mice. NC, negative control group. PC, positive control group. M, marker. 1∼4, thoracic aorta of different mice infected with MCMV for 21 days. (<bold>B</bold>) SBP. (<bold>C</bold>) Diastolic blood pressure. (<bold>D</bold>) Mean arterial pressure. (<bold>E</bold>) Heart rate. (<bold>F</bold>) Weight. The data are expressed as the means ± SEM, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=15), *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 vs. the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387-g1.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Differential miRNA expression upon MCMV infection</title><p>We compared miRNA expression profiles in the peripheral blood of mice infected with MCMV with uninfected mice using a high-throughput sequencing approach. We found 118 significantly differentially expressed miRNAs, of which 91 were up-regulated and 27 were down-regulated (absolute value fold-change ≥ 1, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A and Supplementary Table S3). Scatter plots and volcano plots of the standardized expression data showed the miRNA expression trend between the two groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B,C). The GO function enrichment analysis and the KEGG enrichment analysis of the top 20 target genes regulated by differentially expressed miRNAs are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D (Supplementary Table S8) and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>E (Supplementary Table S9), respectively.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>MiRNA expression changes by MCMV infection and bioinformatics analysis</title><p>x-axis: Sample.ID. the gray lines represent a log2 difference of 1 in the 2C. (<bold>A</bold>) Heat map of all 118 significantly changed miRNAs in the peripheral blood identified by sequencing (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=6). A2∼A7: MCMV group; B1∼B7: Control group. Red (up) and green (down) indicate relative fold-changes for each comparison. (<bold>B</bold>) Scatter plot of mean expression between MCMV group and control group. (<bold>C</bold>) Volcano map of differentially expressed miRNAs. (<bold>D</bold>) Top 20 genes for GO function enrichment analysis of target genes regulated by differential miRNAs. (<bold>E</bold>) KEGG Pathway enrichment analysis of hypertension-related target genes (top 20).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387-g2.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Screening of hypertension-related miRNAs and target genes prediction</title><p>We further analyzed the small RNA-seq data to identify differentially expressed miRNAs involved in hypertension. After removing the unknown and weak signal samples from each group, we performed cluster analysis and found a cluster containing 36 up-regulated and 11 down-regulated miRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A and Supplementary Table S4). Then, we predicted the miRNA target genes using bioinformatics methods. We found 90 hypertension-related target genes that were potentially targeted by 32 differentially regulated miRNAs, among which 26 were up-regulated and 6 down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B) (Supplementary Table S5). The GO function and the KEGG pathway enrichment analysis of the top 30 hypertension-related target genes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C,D and Supplementary Table S6).</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Screening of hypertension-related miRNAs and prediction of target genes</title><p>x-axis: Sample.ID. (<bold>A</bold>) Heat map of all 47 significantly changed miRNAs in the peripheral blood identified by sequencing (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=6). A2∼A7: MCMV group; B1∼B7: Control group. Red (up) and green (down) indicate relative fold-changes for each comparison. (<bold>B</bold>) Venn diagrams of target genes and mouse hypertension-related genes predicted by three databases of differentially expressed miRNAs. (<bold>C</bold>) Top 30 genes for GO function enrichment analysis of hypertension-related target genes regulated by differentially expressed miRNAs. (<bold>D</bold>) KEGG Pathway enrichment analysis of hypertension-related target genes (top 30). (<bold>E</bold>) MCMV-induced hypertension-related differential expression of miRNAs and target gene network regulation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387-g3.jpg"/></fig><p>To further identify miRNAs closely related to hypertension, we performed a ranking analysis between genes correlated with hypertension and high blood pressure with 29 miRNAs, 2 of them of CMV origin (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Then, we built an miRNA–mRNA regulatory interaction network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E and Supplementary Table S7) and selected 9 candidate miRNAs for experimental validation of their role in MCMV-induced hypertension (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Interaction analysis of MCMV-induced hypertension-related differential expression mRNA target genes and GCBI (top 20 diseases)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up-regulated miRNAs</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down-regulated miRNAs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-211-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-328-3p</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-379-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-486a-3p</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-204-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-1929-3p</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-183-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-143-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-133b-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-182-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-411-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-1a-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-203-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-429-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-3473c</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-145a-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-145a-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-200b-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-709</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-206-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-9-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-148a-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-200a-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-133a-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-let-7f-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-let-7i-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-let-7a-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mcmv-miR-m88-1-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviation: GCBI, Gene-cloud of Biotechnology Information.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Interaction analysis of MCMV-induced hypertension-related mRNA target genes of differentially expressed miRNAs and GCBI</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up-regulated miRNAs</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target genes associated with hypertension</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down-regulated miRNAs</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target genes associated with hypertension</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-133b-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Agt</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-328-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nr3c1, Tcf7l2</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-143-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Asb4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-1929-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Ednra, Smad9</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-182-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Adra2a, Rgs2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-204-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nr3c1, Prkg1, Nedd4l</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmu-miR-211-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Nr3c1, Prkg1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Slc12a6</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mcmv-miR-m88-1-3p</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">KLHL3</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: Adra2a, adrenergic receptor, α 2a; Agt, angiotensinogen (serpin peptidase inhibitor, clade A, member 8); Asb4, ankyrin repeat and SOCS box-containing 4; <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>, endothelin receptor type A; GCBI, Gene-cloud of Biotechnology Information; KLHL3, Kelch-like 3; Nedd4l, neural precursor cell expressed, developmentally down-regulated gene 4-like; Nr3c1, nuclear receptor subfamily 3, group C, member 1; Prkg1, protein kinase, cGMP-dependent, type I; Rgs2, regulator of G-protein signaling 2; Slc12a6, solute carrier family 12 (potassium/chloride transporters), member 6; Smad9, SMAD family member 9; Tcf7l2, transcription factor 7 like 2, T-cell specific, HMG box.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Validation of miRNA differential expression with qRT-PCR</title><p>qRT-PCR was used to validate the expression levels of the nine differentially expressed miRNAs in independent samples from different tissues (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=10). We isolated monocytes by performing Ficoll density gradient centrifugation and found that in peripheral blood monocytes of mice infected with MCMV [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p increased, while mmu-miR-133b-3p, mmu-miR-1929-3p, and mmu-miR-204-5p decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). In the thoracic aorta, mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p increased and mmu-miR-1929-3p decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). In the cardiac tissue mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p increased, while mcmv-miR-m88-1-3p, mmu-miR-1929-3p, mmu-miR-328-3p, and mmu-miR-182-5p decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Thus, mmu-miR-1929-3p was the only host-derived miRNA consistently down-regulated in all three tissues. Moreover, we observed that the expression levels of mmu-miR-1929-3p in the peripheral blood monocytes were significantly higher than those in the thoracic aorta and cardiac tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). At the same time, in our experimental validation using MCMV to infect NIH3T3 cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, we still found that MCMV infection is able to down-regulate the expression of mmu-miR-1929-3p in infected cells (Supplementary Figure S1B).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The value of each group of differentially expressed miRNA in MCMV-infected C57BL/6 mice</title><p>Control: value observed with uninfected control. (<bold>A</bold>–<bold>C</bold>) Differential expression of miRNA in peripheral blood monocytes, cardiac tissue and the thoracic aorta by RT-qPCR. The value at each group was normalized to the value observed with control, which was set to 1. (<bold>D</bold>) mmu-miR-1929-3p expression in peripheral blood monocytes, cardiac tissue and the thoracic aorta by RT-qPCR. The value at each group was normalized to the value observed with peripheral blood monocytes, which was set to 1. The data are expressed as the means ± SEM, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=15), *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 vs. the control group or peripheral blood monocytes group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387-g4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title><italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> is a target of mmu-miR-1929-3p</title><p>Using a bioinformatics approach, we found that endothelin receptor type A (<italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>) could be a potential target of mmu-miR-1929-3p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). Dual-luciferase reporter assay showed that the luciferase activity significantly dropped when we transfected the mednra-miR1929-WT vector (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05), while no significant difference was observed upon transfecting the mednra-miR1929-MUT vector or an NC mimic (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). At the same time, we found that in vascular tissues, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> mRNA in the MCMV infection group was higher than that in the control group (Supplementary Figure S1A). Thus, we experimentally validated that <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> is a target of mmu-miR-1929-3p.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> is determined to be a target of mmu-miR-1929-3p</title><p>NC, negative control. (<bold>A</bold>) Sequences of the 3′-UTR of the <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> mRNA binding with mmu-miR-1929-3p. <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>, endothelin receptor type A. (<bold>B</bold>) Luciferase activity in the Ednra-WT and Ednra-MUT group. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05 vs. the mimics NC group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="bsr-40-bsr20202387-g5.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we observed that MCMV infection caused the differential expression of various miRNA, originating both from the host and the virus, which could play a role in the pathogenesis of hypertension. In particular, we found that the MCMV-encoded mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p miRNA increased, while the host-encoded mmu-miR-1929-3p miRNA decreased. However, as the target genes regulated by mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p did not rank among the top ten hypertension-related genes in the bioinformatic analysis, we focused on mmu-miR-1929-3p for the subsequent analysis. CMV infection is usually latent, although it undergoes periodic reactivation events, by bypassing the host immune response [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Although HCMV infection is usually asymptomatic, congenital HCMV infection can cause severe birth defects, including hearing loss, cognitive impairment, and microcephaly [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. As MCMV is a natural mouse pathogen, it is not necessary to manipulate the host. Thus, the study of MCMV provides a unique model for studying <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> the biological mechanism of viruses of the CMV genus. MCMV has been extensively used in cardiovascular studies [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Much of the information derived from studies using this model has been translated into clinical practice [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A previous study has shown that CMV infection causes an increase in arterial blood pressure [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Similarly, we reported that CMV infection may be correlated to hypertension in patients belonging to two different ethnicities living in the Xinjiang region [<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In this study, we infected C57BL/6 mice with MCMV to establish a model presenting elevated blood pressure. Our results confirmed that, after 10 weeks of infection, the blood pressure is significantly higher in infected mice than that in the uninfected mice.</p><p>It has been widely recognized that miRNAs play an important role in regulating cardiovascular functions [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Patients with coronary heart disease are characterized by a high serum level of miR-486, miR-92a, and miR-122 [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Moreover, the level of circulating miR-126 is increased in patients with acute myocardial infarction and angina [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], while plasma miR-126 levels are down-regulated in patients with diabetes [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], heart failure [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and cancer [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Recently, miR-126 has been identified as an effective biomarker for endothelial cell detection and purification [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Many studies reported a functional role for miRNAs in hypertension. According to <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies, CMV-encoded miRNAs play an important regulatory role in viral replication, but the association between host-encoded miRNAs, HCMV-encoded miRNAs, and hypertension remain unclear. Here, we identified 118 differentially expressed miRNAs. Among them, the expression of two miRNA encoded by MCMV was up-regulated. These results suggest that both MCMV- and host-encoded miRNA may be involved in the insurgence of MCMV-mediated hypertension.</p><p>MiRNAs are known to be effective regulators of gene expression, by binding to target mRNA, blocking their translation by degrading the mRNA or inhibiting the translation process [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. ACE inhibitors and angiotensin 1 receptor blockers have been reported to partially reverse vascular dysfunction and normalize gene expression in miR-143/145-deleted mice [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Marques et al<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> demonstrated that miR-181a-5p binds to the 3′-UTR of the renin mRNA to reduce its gene expression. In hypertensive individuals, high expression of renin mRNA is accompanied by a decreased expression of miR-181a in the kidney [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In rats with hypertension complicated with heart failure, miR-16, miR-20b, miR-93, miR-106b, miR-223, and miR-423-5p circulating levels increases significantly [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. By inhibiting miR-208a, the circulating levels of these miRNA decrease, suggesting that plasma miRNA changes can be used as biomarkers of disease progression and manipulated to treat hypertension in the context of heart disease [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In this study, we validated with qRT-PCR the expression of mmu-miR-1929-3p and mcmv-miR-m01-4-5p in peripheral blood monocytes, blood vessels, and myocardial tissues samples. Although the exact role of viral-encoded miRNAs is not known in many cases, it has been proposed that they could be a common mechanism by which viruses modulate transcriptional changes in the host and their genome during toxic infection and/or incubation. For instance, the simian virus 40-encoded miR-s1 miRNA mediates the <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-degradation of cytotoxic t-antigen mRNA, which encodes for a major viral regulator, in a process thought to help to evade the host immune response [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The HCMV-encoded miR-ul112-3p targets the 3′-UTR of gene 72 (IE72), an early major <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>-activator gene. The removal of miR-ul112-3p target sites in the IE72 mRNA increased IE72 expression [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. One of the differentially expressed miRNAs detected in this study was mcmv-miR-m01-4, which is derived from a pre-miRNA located in the 3′-UTR of the m01 transcript and accumulates to detectable levels <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, we did not find any potential hypertension-related target genes. In contrast, for mmu-miR-1929-3p, we predicted a hypertension-related target gene, <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic>, and experimentally validated the finding with the dual-luciferase assay.</p><p>In mammals, the endothelin signaling system (ligand plus receptor) consists of three ligands (encoded by <italic toggle="yes">EDN1, EDN2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">EDN3</italic>) and two receptors (encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ednrb</italic>), belonging to the seven-fold transmembrane domain receptor family of G protein-conjugated receptors [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> gene spans over 40 kb and contains 8 exons and 7 introns [<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In hypertensive patients, <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> increases vasoconstriction tension and may be associated with an increase in endothelin-1 (ET-1) [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. ET-1 is the most effective vasoconstrictor in the human cardiovascular system and has very long-lasting effects. In the present study, we showed that mmu-miR-1929-3p targets <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> mRNA and thus might be involved in MCMV-induced hypertension. Future studies are required to identify potential biomarkers of CMV-mediated hypertension.</p><p>A previous study identified different virus- and host-encoded miRNAs whose target genes are related to the inflammatory response, vasoconstriction, and vascular remodeling (although their identified target genes are not among the top ten genes involved in the incidence of hypertension) [<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The discrepancy with our results can be explained by various factors, such as the use of different models, research objects, research methods, and CMV specificity in different species. However, both the present study and our support after the idea that MCMV infection promotes the development of hypertension through the miRNA-mediated regulation. Both studies also suggest that antiviral therapy can be a novel approach for the prevention and treatment of hypertension.</p><p>The present study presents some limitations. In particular, the effect of mmu-miR-1929-3p in the occurrence and development of hypertension and target organ damage still need to be further validated <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and elucidated at the cellular and molecular level.</p><p>In conclusion, we identified mmu-miR-1929-3p as a novel miRNA down-regulated in mice infected with MCMV. We also experimentally validated that <italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic> may be the target gene of mmu-miR-1929-3p. Thus, mmu-miR-1929-3p can be promising drug targets and/or potential biomarkers for the prevention and management of hypertension.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure S1 and Tables S1-S9</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="BSR-2020-2387_supp.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec5"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data associated with the present paper are stored in NCBI SRA (accession number: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/PRJNA679174">PRJNA679174</ext-link>). Other data that were used to support the findings of the present study are included within the supplementary information files.</p></sec><sec id="sec6" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China [grant number 31760291]; and the Shihezi University independently funded scientific research projects [grant number ZZZC201804A].</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>S.Y.S., F.H., and D.M.X. conceived and designed the experiments. S.Y.S., D.M.X., and H.Z. performed the experiments. S.Y.S., N.T., Y.M.L., L.M.W., and Y.T. analyzed the data. S.Y.S., X.N.Z., H.Z., and F.H. wrote or modified the paper. All authors contributed to and approved the final draft of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Ethics Approval</title><p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Shihezi Medical University (Shihezi, China) (approval number: A2018-038-01).</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="G1">ACE</term><def><p>angiotensin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">CMV</term><def><p>cytomegalovirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3"><italic toggle="yes">Ednra</italic></term><def><p>endothelin A receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">EH</term><def><p>essential hypertension</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">ET-1</term><def><p>endothelin-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">GO</term><def><p>gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">HCMV</term><def><p>human cytomegalovirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8">KEGG</term><def><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9">MCMV</term><def><p>murine cytomegalovirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10">miRNA</term><def><p>microRNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11">mRNA</term><def><p>messenger RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12">PFU</term><def><p>plaque forming unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">qRT-PCR</term><def><p>quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G14">UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G15">VSB</term><def><p>virus standard buffer</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oscullo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Resistant/refractory hypertension and sleep apnoea: current knowledge and future challenges</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Med.</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm8111872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6912579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31694223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romaine</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charchar</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaszewski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Circulating microRNAs and hypertension–from new insights into blood pressure regulation to biomarkers of cardiovascular risk</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coph.2015.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pausova</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adarichev</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adaricheva</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Hypertension: genes and environment</article-title>. <source>J. Hypertens.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004872-199816040-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9797185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carretero</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Oparil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Essential hypertension. Part I: definition and etiology</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.101.3.329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10645931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zicha</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The interaction of genetic and environmental factors in the etiology of hypertension</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Res.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>S33</fpage>–<lpage>S41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.33549/physiolres.931913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20131935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemecz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandru</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanko</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Georgescu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Role of MicroRNA in endothelial dysfunction and hypertension</article-title>. <source>Curr. Hypertens. Rep.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-016-0696-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27837398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Signature microRNA expression profile of essential hypertension and its novel link to human cytomegalovirus infection</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.012237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21690488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Review of cytomegalovirus seroprevalence and demographic characteristics associated with infection</article-title>. <source>Rev. Med. Virol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rmv.655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20564615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haarala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Relation of high cytomegalovirus antibody titres to blood pressure and brachial artery flow-mediated dilation in young men: the Cardiovascular Risk in Young Finns Study</article-title>. <source>Clin. Exp. Immunol.</source>
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2011.04513.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22236008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3278698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samaranayake</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Is human cytomegalovirus infection associated with hypertension? The United States National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 1999-2002</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e39760</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3388091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Human cytomegalovirus infection and coronary heart disease: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Virol. J.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-018-0937-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29409508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5801777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Coding potential of laboratory and clinical strains of human cytomegalovirus</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>14976</fpage>–<lpage>14981</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2136652100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC299866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatherer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-resolution human cytomegalovirus transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>19755</fpage>–<lpage>19760</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1115861108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22109557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3241806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogalski</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins-McMillen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Yurochko</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Overview of human cytomegalovirus pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>1119</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-62703-788-4_2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24639215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pass</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boppana</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Britt</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Stagno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Congenital cytomegalovirus infection following first trimester maternal infection: symptoms at birth and outcome</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Virol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2005.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schleiss</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Congenital cytomegalovirus infection: new prospects for prevention and therapy</article-title>. <source>Pediatr. Clin. North Am.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pcl.2012.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3807860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Cytomegalovirus infection is associated with an increase in systolic blood pressure in older individuals</article-title>. <source>QJM</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qjmed/hcw026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27071749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5027953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Cytomegalovirus infection causes an increase of arterial blood pressure</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>e1000427</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2673691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dewals</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs in large herpesvirus DNA genomes: recent advances</article-title>. <source>Biomol. Concepts</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/bmc-2016-0017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27544723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A viral microRNA down-regulates multiple cell cycle genes through mRNA 5¢UTRs</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e1000967</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2891821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spahis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bigras</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delvin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Borys</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>The epigenetic machinery in vascular dysfunction and hypertension</article-title>. <source>Curr. Hypertens. Rep.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11906-017-0745-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28540644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceolotto</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Interplay between miR-155, AT1R A1166C polymorphism, and AT1R expression in young untreated hypertensives</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hypertens.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajh.2010.211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20966899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meshesha</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The microRNA transcriptome of Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV)</article-title>. <source>Open Virol. J.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874357901206010038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22715351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3377890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>High anti-human cytomegalovirus antibody levels are associated with the progression of essential hypertension and target organ damage in Han Chinese population</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e0181440</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28837559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5570371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Unexpected role of the human cytomegalovirus contribute to essential hypertension in the Kazakh Chinese population of Xinjiang</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source>
<volume>38</volume>(<issue>3)</issue>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20171522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6019381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29752343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impact of human granulocyte and monocyte isolation procedures on functional studies</article-title>. <source>Clin. Vaccine Immunol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1065</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CVI.05715-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22552601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3393372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The pathogenicity of cytomegalovirus</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.1999.tb00408.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10422262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddehase</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Podlech</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Grzimek</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mouse models of cytomegalovirus latency: overview</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Virol.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>S23</fpage>–<lpage>S36</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1386-6532(02)00087-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang-Feldman</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV) infection upregulates P38 MAP kinase in aortas of Apo E KO mice: a molecular mechanism for MCMV-induced acceleration of atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>J. Cardiovasc. Transl. Res.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12265-012-9428-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23192592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4591060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crough</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Immunobiology of human cytomegalovirus: from bench to bedside</article-title>. <source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>, <comment>Table of contents</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00034-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2620639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Human cytomegalovirus infection is associated with essential hypertension in Kazakh and Han Chinese populations</article-title>. <source>Med. Sci. Monit.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2508</fpage>–<lpage>2519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25448630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12659/MSM.892861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4262054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viereck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Circulating noncoding RNAs as biomarkers of cardiovascular disease and injury</article-title>. <source>Circ. Res.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.308434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28104771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pervasive roles of microRNAs in cardiovascular biology</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>469</volume>, <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21248840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3073349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niculescu</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>MiR-486 and miR-92a identified in circulating HDL discriminate between stable and vulnerable coronary artery disease patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0140958</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26485305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4617647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Circulating miR-17-5p, miR-126-5p and miR-145-3p are novel biomarkers for diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Front. Physiol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2019.00123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30833907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6387945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The role of circulating microRNA-126 (miR-126): a novel biomarker for screening prediabetes and newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>10567</fpage>–<lpage>10577</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms150610567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24927146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4100169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Plasma levels of microRNA-21, -126 and -423-5p alter during clinical improvement and are associated with the prognosis of acute heart failure</article-title>. <source>Mol. Med. Rep.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>4736</fpage>–<lpage>4746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29344661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/mmr.2018.8428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>miR-126: a novel regulator in colon cancer</article-title>. <source>Biomed. Rep.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/br.2015.549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26893826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4734020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Efficient detection and purification of cell populations using synthetic microRNA switches</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>711</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2015.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boettger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Acquisition of the contractile phenotype by murine arterial smooth muscle cells depends on the Mir143/145 gene cluster</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source>
<volume>119</volume>, <fpage>2634</fpage>–<lpage>2647</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI38864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19690389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2735940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>F.Z.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profiling reveals renin mRNA overexpression in human hypertensive kidneys and a role for microRNAs</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1093</fpage>–<lpage>1098</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.180729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22042811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Plasma microRNAs serve as biomarkers of therapeutic efficacy and disease progression in hypertension-induced heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Heart Fail.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>650</fpage>–<lpage>659</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurjhf/hft018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23388090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grundhoff</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tevethia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SV40-encoded microRNAs regulate viral gene expression and reduce susceptibility to cytotoxic T cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>435</volume>, <fpage>682</fpage>–<lpage>686</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15931223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A human cytomegalovirus-encoded microRNA regulates expression of multiple viral genes involved in replication</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>e163</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17983268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2048532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dölken</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mouse cytomegalovirus microRNAs dominate the cellular small RNA profile during lytic infection and show features of posttranscriptional regulation</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>13771</fpage>–<lpage>13782</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01313-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2168864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Organization, structure, chromosomal assignment, and expression of the gene encoding the human endothelin-A receptor</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>18797</fpage>–<lpage>18804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1326535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campia</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cardillo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Panza</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ethnic differences in the vasoconstrictor activity of endogenous endothelin-1 in hypertensive patients</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>3191</fpage>–<lpage>3195</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000130590.24107.D3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15148269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>