
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1821</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">mtna</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101581621</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7933600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7933600.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7933600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7933600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33738132</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2020.11.022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2162-2531(20)30379-6</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Separation-related rapid nuclear transport of DNA/RNA heteroduplex oligonucleotide: unveiling distinctive intracellular trafficking</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names initials="D">Daisuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asada</surname><given-names initials="K">Ken</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yui</surname><given-names initials="D">Daishi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaue</surname><given-names initials="F">Fumika</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names initials="K">Kotaro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names initials="T">Tetsuya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names initials="T">Takanori</given-names></name><email>tak-yokota.nuro@tmd.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology and Neurological Science, Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences and Center for Brain Integration Research, Tokyo Medical and Dental University, 1-5-45 Yushima, Bunkyo-Ku, Tokyo 113-8519, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author: Takanori Yokota, Department of Neurology and Neurological Science, Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, Tokyo Medical and Dental University, 1-5-45 Yushima, Bunkyo-Ku, Tokyo 113-8519, Japan. <email>tak-yokota.nuro@tmd.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">370012</issue-id><fpage>1360</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-03-19 16:16:24.740"><day>19</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>DNA/RNA heteroduplex oligonucleotide (HDO), composed of DNA/locked nucleic acid (LNA) antisense oligonucleotide (ASO) and complementary RNA, is a next-generation antisense therapeutic agent. HDO is superior to the parental ASO in delivering to target tissues, and it exerts a more potent gene-silencing effect. In this study, we aimed to elucidate the intracellular trafficking mechanism of HDO-dependent gene silencing. HDO was more preferably transferred to the nucleus after transfection compared to the parental ASO. To determine when and where HDO is separated into the antisense strand (AS) and complementary strand (CS), we performed live-cell time-lapse imaging and fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) assays. These assays demonstrated that HDO had a different intracellular trafficking mechanism than ASO. After endocytosis, HDO was separated in the early endosomes, and both AS and CS were released into the cytosol. AS was more efficiently transported to the nucleus than CS. Separation, endosomal release, and initiation of nuclear transport were a series of time-locked events occurring at a median of 30 s. CS cleavage was associated with efficient nuclear distribution and gene silencing in the nucleus. Understanding the unique intracellular silencing mechanisms of HDO will help us design more efficient drugs and might also provide insight into innate DNA/RNA cellular biology.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fx1.jpg"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0020"><p>DNA/RNA heteroduplex oligonucleotide (HDO) is a newly developed antisense therapy. Here, Ono et al. demonstrated HDO was separated in and released from early endosomes and was efficiently transported into the nucleus. The double-stranded structure of HDO has dramatically changed the intracellular mechanism compared with its parent antisense oligonucleotide.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>DNA:RNA hybrids</kwd><kwd>endosomal escape</kwd><kwd>cytosolic release</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Antisense oligonucleotide (ASO) is a single-stranded therapeutic oligonucleotide that modulates RNA functions by binding to the targeted RNA through Watson-Crick base pairing.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> ASO is typically designed as a “gapmer” structure, where wings of chemically modified nucleotides flank both sides of a central portion of DNA. ASO gapmer with phosphorothioate (PS) backbone is highly potent and has recently been applied to clinical settings.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">We recently developed a novel highly efficient oligonucleotide, DNA/RNA heteroduplex oligonucleotide (HDO), which is composed of an antisense gapmer (DNA nucleotides flanked by LNAs) and complementary RNA (cRNA).<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> HDO showed improved delivery to the target tissue by conjugating tocopherol to the cRNA strand. Additionally, Toc-HDO presented 4.8 times higher gene silencing effect than parental ASO, revealed after measuring the delivered oligonucleotide content.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> MicroRNA-targeting HDO (HDO-antimiR) displayed high potency in cleaving the target microRNA, whereas the parental ASO exerted its potency via a steric blocking (not cleaving) mechanism.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Additionally, HDO-antimiR conjugated with GalNAc was more potent in the liver than the parent ASO conjugated with GalNAc, where delivery efficiency of HDO was comparable to that of ASO.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> These findings suggested that HDO may have a distinct intracellular trafficking pathway and processing machinery different from the single-stranded ASO.</p><p id="p0020">Intracellular trafficking pathways of oligonucleotides are diverse and depend on their structures, such as chemical modifications, ligand conjugations, and association with nanocarriers.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> For therapeutic applications, intracellular trafficking of ASO gapmers with PS backbones (referred to as PS-ASOs) has been intensely investigated.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Cells internalize PS-ASOs by endocytosis; they are trafficked from early endosomes to late endosomes, and finally to lysosomes.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> PS-ASOs have to be released from those endocytic vesicles into the cytosol and nucleus, where they bind to the target mRNA and cleave it by RNase H1.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">In our previous study, we investigated the intracellular mechanism of HDO.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> From the imaging studies <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, we suspected that the antisense strand (AS) of HDO was more robustly distributed into the nucleus compared with the parental ASO. Therefore, we hypothesized that an effective gene silencing by HDO could be attributed not only to the efficiency of cellular uptake but also to the distinctive intracellular localization patterns. Unlike single-stranded ASO, double-stranded HDO has to be separated into AS and complementary strand (CS) in the cell in order for AS to bind to the target RNAs and exert antisense activity. For the elucidation of these intracellular trafficking mechanisms of HDO, there are technical limitations—a conventional snapshot imaging cannot detect the time and site of HDO separation. To tackle this problem, we performed live-cell time-lapse imaging utilizing fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) assay and demonstrated a unique intracellular silencing mechanism by HDO.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Efficient gene silencing of HDO in the nucleus after cytosolic delivery</title><p id="p0030">To address our hypothesis that HDO is more efficiently transferred into the nucleus, we designed ASO and HDO molecules that targeted the intron region of <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> pre-mRNA (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A), which is localized in the nucleus.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> We evaluated how a spatially specifically introduced HDO or ASO can regulate nuclear expressing target pre-mRNA in human hepatocellular carcinoma Huh-7 cells transfected using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX, which effectively delivers small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) or single-stranded nucleotides into the cytosol.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> expression was measured 24 h after transfection, using quantitative real-time PCR. Our results showed a dose-dependent nuclear silencing effect of HDO, whereas no significant effect was observed with the parent ASO (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Efficient gene silencing of HDO in the nucleus after cytosolic delivery</p><p>(A) Design of ASO and HDO, targeting intron region of <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> pre-mRNA. The ASO is the 16-mer gapmer in which 10 DNA oligonucleotides are flanked by 3 LNA oligonucleotides, and all internucleotide linkages were modified by phosphorothioate (PS) substitution. In HDO, the complementary RNA strand is flanked by PS-modified 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-methyl RNAs, which are complementary to LNA.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> (B) Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of relative <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> mRNA levels was normalized to those of <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> mRNA 24 h after transfection of intron-targeting HDO or ASO (∗∗p &lt; 0.01 versus Lipofectamine [LFN] control; n = 3; mean ± SEM). (C) Representative images 24 h after transfection of the cells with 50 nM ASO or HDO. AF647 labels the antisense strand (AS) of HDO, and AF488 labels the complementary strand (CS), where FRET does not occur. AF647 signals (red) were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF488 signals (cyan) were excited by a 488 nm laser and detected through a 525 (500–550) nm filter. Dotted lines represent nuclear or plasma membrane outlined by differential interference contrast (DIC) images. Bar, 10 μm. (D) Percentage of cells with uniform nuclear distribution 24 h after transfection with 50 nM ASO or HDO. (E) Mean intensities of AS-AF647 in the nucleus or cytosol 24 h after transfection with 50 nM ASO or HDO, presented as absolute values normalized to background levels. (∗∗p &lt; 0.01; NS, not significant; n = 3 images for each 50 cells).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0035">Next, to visualize the nuclear distribution of HDO, we labeled AS with the fluorophore AF647 (excitation/emission: 650/665 nm), and CS with AF488 (490/525 nm), where excitation wavelengths are so far that the FRET phenomenon seldom occurs. Imaging results 24 h after HDO transfection showed a completely different distribution pattern compared to ASO (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C). An intense and well-demarcated nuclear signal of AS was observed in almost all HDO-transfected cells. Additionally, a dotted signal of CS, accumulated dominantly in the cytosol, was detected. Meanwhile, the same dose of ASO presented just a diffused or partly dotted weak distribution throughout the cells.</p><p id="p0040">Before the time-lapse imaging we will show in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, we defined the uniform and well-demarcated nuclear AS signals as “nuclear transport” and counted them (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). HDO showed a high uniform nuclear distribution rate, which was concordant with its potency (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B). We then quantified the mean intensity in both the nucleus and cytosol (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>E). HDO presented strong preference for the nucleus. On the other hand, ASO was distributed to the nucleus and cytosol without significant preference. Thus, we supposed that the uniform and well-demarcated nuclear localization was a distinctive character of HDO, associated with nuclear potency.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Separation and rapid transport of HDO into the nucleus</p><p>(A) Design of dye-conjugated HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> with FRET system. AF647 labels the AS of HDO, and AF568 labels the CS, where CS-AF568 signals become quenched. (B) Sequential changes in the percentage of cells with uniform nuclear distribution after 50 nM transfection of HDO or ASO. (n = 50). (C) Representative live-cell images within 2 h after transfection with 50 nM HDO or ASO, presented as merged images of DIC and AS-AF647 (red). AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. Bar, 10 μm. (D) Live-cell time-lapse images of the HDO-releasing vesicle (arrowhead). As shown in the bottom scheme, AF568 signal (green) represents separated CS, and AF647 signal (red) corresponds to the AS signal from the wound or isolated form. Therefore, newly observed yellow signal (colocalization of red and green) means separation of HDO. Dotted circles and squares represent nuclear and cytosolic areas, respectively, which are shown in (E). Images were acquired just after transfection with 50 nM HDO, every 30 s. AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570–620) nm filter. Bar, 10 μm. (E) Sequential changes of AS-AF647 (red) and CS-AF568 (green) signals in the nucleus, cytosol, and the HDO-releasing vesicle of the cell shown in (D). Mean intensities of each region are presented as relative values (0–1), with 0 being the background intensity and 1 being the highest intensity value for each object (except for the cytosol using the highest intensity of the nucleus). (F and G) Mean relative intensity of AS-AF647 and CS-AF568 in HDO-releasing vesicles (F) and nuclei (G). <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 is set just before the releases started. (F, n = 26; G, n = 10 G; ± SEM, shaded areas). Results were pooled from three experiments per condition in (F).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0045">Additionally, in co-transfection experiments with HDO and ASO, we confirmed that HDO was also superiorly distributed compared to ASO (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref>). Fluorescent dyes transfected without the oligonucleotide conjugation were not detectable in the cells (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3</xref>). To evaluate delivery methods other than lipid transfection, we performed gymnotic (free uptake) delivery of ASO or HDO, but it presented no significant nuclear distribution (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Separation and rapid transport of HDO into the nucleus</title><p id="p0050">To observe the separation of HDO, we designed an HDO composed of AF647-labeled AS and AF568-labeled CS and applied the FRET mechanism<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A). Excitation/emission wavelengths of these dyes are 650/665 and 578/603 nm, respectively, which are close enough for FRET to occur. In the double-stranded wound form, the energy absorbed by CS-AF568 after excitation with a 560 nm laser was transferred to AS-AF647. In other words, CS-AF568 signal became quenched, and AS-AF647 produced a signal through FRET. If HDO was separated, the isolated CS-AF568 could not transfer the energy to AS-AF647, and thus the CS-AF568 signal would increase and become dequenched. We confirmed the FRET and dequenching signals in our experimental system by measuring the fluorescence intensity of dye-conjugated HDO in solution without cell or transfection reagent (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">Live-cell time-lapse imaging was performed every 30 s for 120 min (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Uniform nuclear distribution of AS was observed in 98% of HDO- and only 2% of ASO-transfected cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>B). We repeated the experiments and deduced the following reproducible results. Immediately after the transfection, ASO-containing liposomes were visualized in the background, and a few of them were endocytosed. Cloud-like weak ASO signals were observed without preference to the nucleus or cytosol, which presented no remarkable change within 2 h (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>C).</p><p id="p0060">HDO-containing liposomes were also visualized in the background, where the majority of CS-AF568 signal was quenched by FRET. A few minutes after the transfection, several liposomes were endocytosed into the cell and transported from the periphery toward the perinuclear region of the cytosol. Then, in one of the endocytosed HDO vesicles, a sudden appearance of the CS-AF568 signal was detected with a transient increase of the AS-AF647 signal. Almost simultaneously, both AS and CS were released into the cytosol and subsequent nuclear transport started (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>D and 2E; <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video S1</xref>).</p><p id="p0065"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Video S1. Separation, cytosolic release, and rapid nuclear transport of HDO</title><p>Live cell time-lapse images of the HDO-releasing vesicle presented in Figure 2D, E. Images were taken, every 30 sec, just after transfection with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>, composed of antisense strand-AF647 (red) and complementary strand-AF568 (green). AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663-738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570-620) nm filter. Bar = 10 μm.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc2.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p><p id="p0070">We considered the transient increase of the AS-AF647 signal in the vesicle at the moment of the release as cancellation of self-quenching. Densely packed fluorophores, such as in liposomes, quench themselves, and this self-quenching is cancelled by the release from the vesicles.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> We subsequently defined the HDO release as a sudden increase of the AS signal in the cytosol and identified an HDO-releasing vesicle by the transient increase of the AF647 signal. We traced and measured subsequent changes of signal intensities in the HDO-releasing vesicles and nuclei, where <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 was reset just before the release, and the mean relative intensity was calculated with reference to the previous study (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>F and 2G).<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> The increase of the AS-AF647 signal was transient and corresponded to the cancellation of the self-quenching. The sudden and sharp increase of CS-AF568 signal just after the HDO release was reproducibly observed. Then, we confirmed that this newly generated CS-AF568 signal meant dequenching of the FRET signal, as a result of the HDO separation (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S6</xref>).</p><p id="p0075">Cytosolic signal from the AS was weak and transient, which was swallowed up into the nucleus soon after and depleted within a few minutes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>D and 2E; <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video S1</xref>). The nuclear distribution of both strands was almost homogeneous, which corresponded to the uniform nuclear distribution observed 24 h after the transfection, as mentioned above (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref>C and 1D). Further release from other vesicles followed, whereas the second release from the same vesicle was seldom observed. If we increased the sensitivity of fluorescence detection settings, the inflow signal from the releasing vesicles was observed (<xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Videos S2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc4" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S7</xref>). These sequential events—the separation, release, and nuclear transport of both strands—always occurred in that order. The separation occurred at a median of 27 min, and the median interval of separation to initiation of nuclear distribution was as short as 30 s (n = 50). The same phenomena were observed with 10 nM HDO, which was a comparable dose to 50 nM ASO (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S8</xref>). We also obtained similar results with other sequences of HDO, targeting the intron <italic toggle="yes">SNCA</italic> mRNA (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S9</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref>A–S10G) and a sequence without any target gene (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S11</xref>A–S11G).</p><p id="p0080"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Video S2. Inflow signals from HDO-releasing vesicles</title><p>(A, B) Live cell time-lapse images of cells which showed inflow signals from HDO-releasing vesicles, Images were taken in a high sensitivity setting compared to experiments in Figure 2, every 30 sec, just after transfection with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>, composed of antisense strand-AF647 (red) and complementary strand-AF568 (green). AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663-738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570-620) nm filter. Bar = 10 μm.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc3.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p><p id="p0085"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Video S3. Inflow signals from HDO-releasing vesicles</title><p>(A, B) Live cell time-lapse images of cells which showed inflow signals from HDO-releasing vesicles, Images were taken in a high sensitivity setting compared to experiments in Figure 2, every 30 sec, just after transfection with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>, composed of antisense strand-AF647 (red) and complementary strand-AF568 (green). AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663-738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570-620) nm filter. Bar = 10 μm.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc4.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Release of HDO from early endosomes</title><p id="p0090">Cells expressing GFP-labeled endosome markers were transfected with HDO, and subsequent live-cell imaging was performed to identify the nature of the HDO-releasing vesicle. At the time of the separation, strong but transient co-localization of the releasing vesicle with RAB5A, the early endosome marker, was observed (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>A–3C; <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video S4</xref>). In contrast, RAB7A, a late endosome marker, was gradually co-localized with the releasing vesicle several minutes after the separation (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>D–3F; <xref rid="mmc6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Video S5</xref>). These observations were reproducibly confirmed by two additional sequences and the other cell line (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S10</xref>H, S10I, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S11</xref>H, and S11I). Therefore, we considered that HDO was separated in and released from early endosomes.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Release of HDO from early endosomes</p><p>(A and D) Live-cell time-lapse images of the HDO-releasing vesicle (arrowheads). Cells expressing GFP-labeled RAB5A (A–C) or RAB7A (D–F) (cyan) were transfected with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> (AS-AF647, CS-AF568). Dotted circles represent nuclei outlined by DIC images. Images were taken just after transfection, every 1 min (A–C and F) or 2 min (D and E). GFP signals were excited by a 488 nm laser and detected through a 525 (500–550) nm filter. AF647 signals (red) were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF568 signals (green) were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570–620) nm filter. Bar, 10 μm, except the second row of (A), which is 1 μm. (B and E) Sequential changes of AF647 (red), AF568 (green), and RAB5A (B) or RAB7A (E) (cyan) signals in the HDO-releasing vesicles and the nucleus of the cell shown in (A) or (D), respectively. Mean intensities of each region were presented as relative values. (C and F) Mean relative intensity of RAB5A (C) or RAB7A (F) in HDO-releasing vesicles. <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 is set just before the release started. (C, n = 20; F, n = 46; ± SEM shown as shaded areas). Results were pooled from three experiments per condition.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0095"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Video S4. Co-localization of HDO vesicle foci with early endosomes</title><p>Live cell time-lapse images of the HDO releasing vesicle presented in Figures 3A and 3B. Cells expressing GFP-labeled <italic toggle="yes">RAB5A</italic> (cyan) were transfected with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> (antisense strand-AF647 (red), complementary strand-AF568 (green)). GFP signals were excited by a 488 nm laser and detected through a 525 (500-550) nm filter. AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663-738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570-620) nm filter. Images were taken just after transfection, every 1 min. Bar = 10 μm.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc5.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p><p id="p0100"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Video S5. Co-localization of HDO vesicle foci with late endosomes</title><p>Live cell time-lapse images of the HDO releasing vesicle presented in Figure 3D and 3E. Cells expressing GFP-labeled <italic toggle="yes">RAB7A</italic> (cyan) were transfected with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> (antisense strand-AF647 (red), complementary strand-AF568 (green)). GFP signals were excited by a 488 nm laser and detected through a 525 (500-550) nm filter. AF647 signals were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663-738) nm filter. AF568 signals were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570-620) nm filter. Images were taken just after transfection, every 2 min. Bar = 10 μm.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc6.flv" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Accumulation of AS in the nucleus and CS in lysosomes</title><p id="p0105">To evaluate HDO trafficking after the endosomal release, we labeled lysosomes with RFP-lysotracker. HDO composed of AS-AF647/CS-AF488 or reverse pair AS-AF488/CS-AF647 was imaged at 24 h (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). Signal intensities in nuclei or lysosomes were measured and presented as the mean of absolute values so that we could compare AS and CS by the same fluorescent dye (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4</xref>B and 4C). Both dyes presented the same tendency that more AS accumulated in nuclei than in lysosomes and more CS accumulated in lysosomes than in nuclei.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Accumulation of AS in the nucleus and CS in lysosomes</p><p>(A) Representative images 24 h after transfection with 50 nM HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>, composed of AS-AF647 and CS-AF488 (left), or CS-AF647 and AS-AF488 (right). Lysosomes were labeled with lysotracker-RFP (green), which were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570–620) nm filter. AF647 signals (red) were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF488 signals (cyan) were excited by a 488 nm laser and detected through a 525 (500–550) nm filter. Bar, 10 μm. (B and C) Mean signal intensities of AF647 (B) or AF488 (C) in nuclei and lysosomes. Measurements from the experiment (A) presented as absolute values normalized to background levels. (∗p &lt; 0.05, ∗∗p &lt; 0.01; n = 3 images for each 50 cells, or 150 lysosomes; mean ± SEM).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>CS cleavage and efficient gene silencing in the nucleus</title><p id="p0110">To evaluate the significance of CS cleavage for gene silencing in the nucleus, we applied the RNase-resistant 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-methyl sugar modification (2′-OMe). We confirmed that CS composed of full 2′-OMe was not cleaved <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S12</xref>A), which is in accordance with a previous <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> study.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> In the present study, HDO with a modified full 2′-OMe CS (2′-OMe-HDO) showed a much lower gene silencing effect in the nucleus than the default HDO (RNA-HDO) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>A; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S12</xref>B and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S13</xref>). To discriminate whether HDO was wound or separated, we generated mono-labeled-HDO (CS-AF568) without FRET, as well as dual-labeled HDO (AS-AF647/CS-AF568) with FRET (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>B). Mono-labeled AF568 signals reflected the amount of CS in both wound and separated forms, whereas in dual-labeled HDO, AF568 signal was quenched in the wound form but observed in the separated form.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Cleavage of CS and efficient gene silencing in the nucleus</p><p>To evaluate the effect of CS degradation, we used RNase-resistant full 2′-OMe-strand as CS. (A) Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of relative <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> mRNA levels normalized to <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> mRNA 24 h after transfection with 50 nM ASO, RNA-HDO, or 2′-OMe-HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> (∗∗p &lt; 0.01 versus LFN control; n = 4; mean ± SEM). (B) Designs of dye-conjugated HDOs, where RNA or full 2′-OMe was labeled with AF568, and AS was labeled with AF647 (dual-labeling with FRET) or not labeled (mono-labeling without FRET). (C) Images 24 h after transfection with 50 nM HDOs. AF647 signals (red) were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF568 signals (green) were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570–620) nm filter. Images were obtained by weaker sensitivity settings than those of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> to maximize a slight difference of nuclear signals between RNA-HDO and 2′-OMe-HDO. Bar, 10 μm. (D and E) Mean nuclear intensities of AS-AF647 (D) or CS-AF568 (E) presented as absolute values normalized to background levels (∗∗p &lt; 0.01; NS, not significant; n = 3 images for each 50 cells; mean ± SEM).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0115">Imaging and subsequent measurements of nuclear intensity were performed (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>C–5E). 2′-OMe-HDO presented a less intense distribution of AS into the nucleus 24 h after transfection (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>D) than RNA-HDO. Nuclear distribution of CS from RNA-HDO was relatively less than that of AS (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), and most of the CS existed in the separated form, because nuclear intensities of CS from RNA-HDO showed no difference between mono- and dual-labeled groups (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>E). On the contrary, the difference in the CS from 2′-OMe-HDO signals between mono- and dual-labeled groups was significantly large (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>E). Therefore, we considered that most of the AS from 2′-OMe-HDO in the nucleus was in a wound form and then exerted much less potency there (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>A; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S12</xref>B). At 24 h post-transfection, more AS from 2′-OMe-HDO accumulated in the nucleus than 2′-OM-CS and both strands did in lysosomes (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S14</xref>). This observation suggested a distinctive nature of HDO, in which AS was more efficiently transported to the nucleus than CS, even if CS was not cleaved.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Decreased separation and nuclear transport in cleavage-resistant 2′-OMe-HDO</title><p id="p0120">Time-lapse imaging of RNA-HDO and 2′-OMe-HDO was performed (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>) to quantify the effects of CS cleavage in the early stage of HDO intracellular trafficking. Similar to RNA-HDO (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>A and 6D), HDO separation just after the cytosolic release and subsequent nuclear distribution were also observed in 2′-OMe-HDO (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>B and 6E). However, comparison of their peak dequenching levels showed that cleavage-resistant 2′-OMe-HDO presented a lesser CS dequenching than RNA-HDO (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>C). 2′-OMe-HDO also showed a lesser nuclear AS signal than RNA-HDO 90 min after the release (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>F). We therefore derived that cleavage-independent separation and subsequent nuclear distribution existed with 50 nM 2′-OMe-HDO but was not sufficient for nuclear antisense activity.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Decreased separation and nuclear transport in cleavage-resistant 2′-OMe-HDO</p><p>Time-lapse imaging was performed after transfection with 50 nM RNA-HDO or 2′-OMe-HDO targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>, where RNA or full 2′-OMe was labeled with AF568, and AS was labeled with AF647 to quantify the effects of CS cleavability in the early stage of HDO intracellular trafficking. Images were acquired just after transfection for 120 min, every 1 min. <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 was set just before the releases started. AF647 signals (red) were excited by a 646 nm laser and detected through a 700 (663–738) nm filter. AF568 signals (green) were excited by a 560 nm laser and detected through a 595 (570–620) nm filter. Images were obtained by weaker sensitivity settings than those of <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> to maximize a slight difference of nuclear signals between RNA-HDO and 2′-OMe-HDO. (A and B) Sequential changes of CS-AF568 in HDO-releasing vesicles presented as absolute values normalized to background levels. (n = 10; ± SEM shown as shaded areas). (C) Mean intensities of CS-AF568 in HDO-releasing vesicles at peak levels (5.5 min after the releases) presented as absolute values normalized to background levels (∗p &lt; 0.05; n = 10; mean ± SEM). (D and E) Sequential changes of AS-AF647 signals in nuclei presented as absolute values normalized to background levels. (n = 20; ± SEM shown as shaded areas). (F) Mean intensities of AS-AF647 in nuclei at 90 min after the releases presented as absolute values normalized to background levels (∗∗p &lt; 0.01; n = 20; mean ± SEM).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Distinctive intracellular trafficking of HDO</title><p id="p0125">Here, we found a distinctive intracellular trafficking and processing mechanism of HDO, which is different from those of ASO or siRNA especially in two viewpoints: (1) separation-related rapid nuclear transport, and (2) cytosolic release from early endosomes. The results were reproduced using three other sequences and two cell lines. We also demonstrated the difference of intracellular trafficking between HDO and ASO by effective HDO versus non- or less-effective ASO (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S9</xref>), both highly effective HDO versus ASO (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S10</xref>), and non-target sequence (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S11</xref>). Furthermore, the equivalently transfected oligos presented the different effects and distributional patterns between HDO and AS (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S1</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>, and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S8</xref>). Therefore, we concluded that HDO and ASO showed different intracellular behaviors, and these were not attributed to ineffective transfection or differences in the transfection efficiencies.</p><sec id="sec3.1.1"><title>Separation-related rapid nuclear distribution</title><p id="p0130">In this study, separation, release into the cytosol, and initiation of nuclear transport always occurred in this order and within a short period (median, 30 s). These strong relationships suggested that separation of HDO triggered its endosomal release and subsequent nuclear transport. Rapid release from endocytic vesicles has been previously visualized with other oligonucleotides.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Lipid-formulated siRNA released from late endosomes into the cytosol has been demonstrated; however, the release is not triggered by the separation of double-strand RNA, and its nuclear distribution is either unobservable or transient.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Therefore, separation-related rapid nuclear transport is the distinctive character of HDO. We additionally observed inflow signals from the HDO releasing endosomes in this study (<xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Videos S2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc4" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>; <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S7</xref>). A similar phenomenon has not been documented. Although the biological implication is unclear, this phenomenon is indicative of an unveiled intracellular structure, perhaps a “molecular tunnel” for DNA/RNA heteroduplex.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2"><title>Cytosolic release from early endosomes</title><p id="p0135">Independent of the delivery method (free uptake, ligand conjugation, or lipid formulation), oligonucleotides are mostly internalized by endocytosis and then trafficked through endosomal compartments,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> where their cytosolic release is an essential step to exert their gene silencing activity in the cytosol or nucleus.</p><p id="p0140">The current study showed HDO was released from the vesicles which transiently expressed the early endosomal marker at the moment of release. Thereafter, the vesicles gradually expressed the late endosomal marker. In a previous study, Annexin 2 facilitates PS-ASO trafficking from early to late endosomes, where it may also contribute to PS-ASO release.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Lipid-formulated siRNAs are released from the late endosome, which is functionally related to the cholesterol transport protein NPC1.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> HDO-binding protein has not been identified, but it might exist in the early endosome and mediate cytosolic release.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Cleavage of CS and efficient gene silencing in the nucleus</title><p id="p0145">Our experiments with 2′-OMe-HDO revealed that cleavage-independent separation existed (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>), but it resulted in less nuclear distribution, where a larger amount of AS was in the wound form (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>), and more HDO was needed for gene silencing (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S12</xref>B). Therefore, the cleavability of CS was associated with the efficient gene silencing in the nucleus.</p><p id="p0150">In a previous study, we examined the cleavage site of CS <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> using northern blotting and concluded that CS is cleaved by unidentified enzymes, most unlikely by RNase H1.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> As we discussed above, HDO separation in early endosomes triggered the cytosolic release and subsequent nuclear transport. Once CS was cleaved, melting temperature dramatically decreased, and separation would have been accelerated. Therefore, it is reasonable to consider that CS was cleaved in early endosomes by unidentified RNases. On the contrary, we cannot exclude the possibility that cleavage-independent separation of default RNA-HDO could also occur in early endosomes. A relatively low melting temperature of RNA-HDO compared to 2′-OMe-HDO might support this idea. The identification of binding and cleaving proteins of HDO and elucidation of its cleaving mechanism are needed, which would aid in designing more effective drugs, by balancing the extracellular RNase-resistance and intracellular cleavability.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Innate DNA/RNA biology</title><p id="p0155">We showed that the exogenously administered short DNA/RNA heteroduplex had a distinctive trafficking pathway from early endosomes into the nucleus via cytosol. Regarding the exogenous origin, pathogen-derived RNA/DNA heteroduplex has been well investigated, and it induces interferon-related immune response via nucleotide sensor proteins like Toll-like receptor 9 (TLR9).<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> On the contrary, endogenous DNA/RNA heteroduplex has been mainly described in nuclear functions such as RNA primer of Okazaki fragments,<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> ribonucleotide incorporation<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> during DNA replication, R-loops,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and G-quadruplexes<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> during transcription. Recently, several studies proposed its extra-nuclear function. DNA/RNA heteroduplex of R-loop structure in the nucleus is cleaved and exported to cytosol,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> where the heteroduplex binds to Ago2 and regulates miRNA,<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> or single-stranded DNA functions as natural antisense after RNA cleavage by RNase H and TREX1.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Formulation of DNA and RNA into extracellular vesicles was also reported in cancer cells.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Although we must be cautious not to mix our findings obtained using the modified oligonucleotides, with innate biology, our findings of intracellular trafficking of HDO might help to understand innate biology of the DNA/RNA heteroduplex.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Limitations</title><p id="p0160">The results of our study are primarily based on lipid transfection experiments. We observed that gymnosis (free uptake) did not induce an effective delivery in our experimental system (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref>). The observations of our study need to be generalized and applied to <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies in the future for advancing to therapeutic application.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0165">Here, we presented the intracellular trafficking of HDO. Understanding this unique mechanism will help us design more efficient drugs and also provide more insight into innate DNA/RNA cellular biology.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Design and synthesis of oligonucleotides</title><p id="p0170">A series of oligonucleotides were synthesized by Gene Design (Osaka, Japan). The sequences targeting intron <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> mRNA were as follows: ASO, 5′-<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>t</underline>∗c∗c∗c∗a∗c∗c∗a∗c∗a∗t∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>-3′; cRNA, 5′-<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗AUGUGGUGGG∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>-3′; full 2′-OMe CS, 5′-<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>AUGUGGUGGG</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>-3′. Lower case letters represent DNA, lower case underlined letters represent LNA (<underline>c</underline> denotes LNA 5-methylcytosine), upper case letters represent RNA, upper case underlined letters represent 2′-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-methyl sugar modification, and ∗ indicates phosphorothioate linkage. The other sequences used were as follows: exon <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic>: AS, 5′-<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗a∗t∗t∗g∗g∗t∗a∗t∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>-3′; CS, 5′-<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗AUACCAAU∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>-3′.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref>
<italic toggle="yes">SNCA-1</italic>: AS, 5′-<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>t</underline>∗c∗c∗c∗a∗a∗g∗a∗g∗a∗c∗<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>-3′; CS, 5′-<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗GUCUCUUGGG∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>-3′. <italic toggle="yes">SNCA-2</italic>: AS, 5′-<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>g</underline>∗a∗a∗t∗c∗a∗a∗t∗t∗g∗c∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>-3′; CS, 5′-<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗GCAAUUGAUU∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>-3′.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Scramble sequence (no target): AS, 5′-<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>g</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗c∗a∗a∗t∗a∗c∗g∗c∗c∗g∗<underline>t</underline>∗<underline>c</underline>∗<underline>a</underline>-3′; CS, 5′-<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗ <underline>CGGCGUAUUG</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>-3′.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> siRNA targeting <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic>: sense, GUAUGACAACAGCCUCAAGtt; antisense, CUUGAGGCUGUUGUCAUACtt.<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> Full 2′-OMe CS targeting mouse <italic toggle="yes">Malat</italic>: <underline>G</underline>∗<underline>C</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>UUCAGUGAAC</underline>∗<underline>U</underline>∗<underline>A</underline>∗<underline>G</underline>. Alexa Fluor 488, Alexa Fluor 568, or Alexa Fluor 647 was covalently bound to the 5′ end of antisense or 3′ end of the CS, as mentioned in the text. Equimolar concentrations of antisense and complementary strands in nuclease-free water (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) were heated at 95°C for 5 min and annealed at room temperature (20°C–25°C) for over 1 h to generate HDO.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Cell Transfection</title><p id="p0175">Huh-7 cells, cultured in DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% penicillin/streptomycin (P/S) at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, were seeded in 24-well plates at 25,000–50,000 cells/well (depending on the time frame of the assay) 12 h before transfection. Oligonucleotides in 100 μL Opti-MEM (Life Technologies) and 1 μL Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (Life Technologies) were mixed at room temperature for 20 min and then added to cells in 400 μL DMEM (FBS+ P/S−) and incubated for 4 h. Transfection medium was then replaced with fresh DMEM (FBS+ P/S+) for subsequent experiments.</p><p id="p0180">In co-transfection experiments, two kinds of oligonucleotides were mixed initially in Opti-MEM, to which 1 μL Lipofectamine RNAiMAX was added. In gymnotic delivery experiments, oligonucleotides in 100 μL Opti-MEM were added to cells in 400 μL DMEM (FBS+ P/S−) and incubated for 24 h. We could not evaluate the gymnotic delivery longer than 24 h because cells died. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">ACTB</italic> was used as the internal control in this experiment because we were afraid that a large number of oligos affected the expression of <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic>. HEK293T cells were utilized only for the experiments presented in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S9</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S10</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR assay</title><p id="p0185">Total RNA was extracted with Isogen II (Nippon Gene, Tokyo, Japan) and was reverse-transcribed with PrimeScript RT Master Mix (Takara Bio, Kusatsu, Japan). The cDNAs were amplified using the LightCycler 480 II (Roche Diagnostics, Rotkreuz, Switzerland). Gene expression values were calculated using the comparative delta <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>t method, normalized by the expression of the housekeeping gene, <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">ACTB</italic>, as previously described.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> TaqMan primers (Applied Biosystems, Life Technologies) used in this study were as follows: <italic toggle="yes">APOB</italic> (Hs00181142_m1), <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic> (Hs99999905_m1), <italic toggle="yes">SNCA</italic> Hs01103383_m1), and <italic toggle="yes">ACTB</italic> (forward: 5′-CGGACTATGACTTAGTTGCGTTACA-3′; reverse: 5′-GCCATGCCAATCTCATCTTGT-3′; probe: 5′-FAM-CCTTTCTTGACAAAACCTAACTTGCGCAGA-TAMRA-3′).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>Live-cell imaging</title><p id="p0190">For live-cell imaging, Huh-7 cells were seeded in 35 mm Cell Imaging Dishes (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany) at 12,500 cells/well 12 h before transfection or transduction of labeled endosomes. In endosomal co-localization experiments, cells were transduced with GFP-labeled early or late endosomes 24 h before their transfection with oligonucleotides, using BacMam 2.0 CellLight Early endosome-GFP or Late endosome-GFP (Life Technologies), respectively, as previously described.<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> Cells were treated with LysoTracker Red DND-99 (Life Technologies) 1 h before the imaging, according to the manufacturer’s instructions, to visualize lysosomes.</p><p id="p0195">Transfection mixture containing dye-conjugated oligonucleotides and 1 μL Lipofectamine RNAiMAX in 100 μL Opti-MEM was prepared and stored at room temperature for 20 min. One minute after culture medium was replaced with the transfection mixture and 400 μL phenol red-free DMEM (FBS+ P/S−) (FluoroBrite, Life Technologies) on the stage of the microscope, time-lapse imaging was initiated. The medium was replaced with phenol red-free DMEM (FBS+ P/S+) 4 h after transfection, depending on the time frame of experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Microscope settings</title><p id="p0200">All images in this study were obtained using a live-cell imaging system (Nikon A1R laser scanning confocal microscopy, Nikon NIS elements AR software ver. 4.5, Tokyo, Japan) and stage top incubator (INUG2H-TIZSH, Tokai Hit, Fujinomiya, Japan). Instruments were warmed up, and cells and medium were incubated in the chamber for more than 1 h before imaging to stabilize the conditions in the chamber (37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 100% humidity).</p><p id="p0205">A preliminary experiment determined that the thickness of Huh-7 cells was less than 7 μm by <italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-section imaging at high magnitude. Therefore, the microscopic settings were adjusted accordingly to enable the detection of all intracellular signals. In this setting (10× objective and 10 ocular lenses; pinhole 28 μm), the calculated thickness of optical sections was 11 μm, and time-lapse imaging was obtained at a single plane, which was focused using differential interference contrast (DIC) imaging at initiation and autoregulated by Nikon Perfect Focus System. Depending on each experiment, 3 × 3 to 4 × 4 tailing images of each fluoresce and DIC were acquired every 30–120 s for 120 min. Imaging parameters, like laser intensity and exposure time, were uniformly set in the same experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Measuring imaging data</title><p id="p0210">The fluorescence intensity of HDO in releasing vesicles, nucleus, and cytosol were analyzed using Nikon NIS elements AR software ver. 4.5 (Nikon). As mentioned earlier, HDO release was defined as the sudden increase of cytosolic AS signal, and a releasing vesicle was identified by a transient increase of AF647 signal in the vesicle (except AF488 signal in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S6</xref>C), which meant the cancellation of self-quenching.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> We also defined the uniform and well-demarcated nuclear signals as nuclear transport and counted them accordingly.</p><p id="p0215">Nuclear and plasma membranes were identified with DIC imaging and manually traced, blinded by other fluorescent signals. Lysosomes were identified when lysotracker signals localized. Intensity values were presented as absolute values, differences between actual signals and background levels, to compare the signals from the same dye.</p><p id="p0220">In time-lapse imaging, the vesicles that released HDO first in individual cells were traced and mean signal intensity of each fluorophore was obtained. Relative values were calculated as previously described.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Namely, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0 was set just before the nuclear distribution started. Each fluorescence intensity was normalized to 0–1, with 0 being the background intensity and 1 being the highest intensity value for each object, in order to adjust various expression levels of each object. Here, we defined the background level as the mean intensity of an arbitrary no-cell area in the same image at the given time,<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> instead of the mean intensity of untransfected cells,<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> because we needed to eliminate the fluorescence caused by the dye-containing medium (note that the optical section was as thick as 11 μm in our settings). Exceptionally, in GFP-labeled early or late endosome experiments, cytosolic regions without the target protein expression were used as background.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><title>RNase treatment assay</title><p id="p0225">Various oligonucleotides (40 pmol), of which AS and CS were labeled with AF647 and AF488, respectively, were incubated with 1 ng of RNase A (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) or 10 units of RNase H (Takara Bio) at 37°C for 1 h and then loaded on 20% polyacrylamide gel. After electrophoresis in TBE, fluorescence of each dye was imaged using ChemiDoc Touch MP (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0230">All experiments were performed at least three times. All data represent mean ± SEM, unless otherwise mentioned. Student’s t tests were used to compare results obtained from different groups and/or conditions using Microsoft Excel. A p value of less than 0.05 was considered significantly significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swayze</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA targeting therapeutics: molecular mechanisms of antisense oligonucleotides as a therapeutic platform</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20055705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.010909.105654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kole</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA therapeutics: beyond RNA interference and antisense oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrd3625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4743652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raal</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marais</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charng</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cromwell</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachmann</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chasan-Taber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mipomersen, an apolipoprotein B synthesis inhibitor, for lowering of LDL cholesterol concentrations in patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolaemia: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>375</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60284-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiriboga</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vajsar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vivo</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of infantile-onset spinal muscular atrophy with nusinersen: a phase 2, open-label, dose-escalation study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>388</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>3017</fpage><lpage>3026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27939059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31408-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida-Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujino</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuhara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA/RNA heteroduplex oligonucleotide for highly efficient gene silencing</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>7969</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26258894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncomms8969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4918363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunieda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida-Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujino</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly efficient silencing of microRNA by heteroduplex oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>7321</fpage><lpage>7332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31214713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkz492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6698647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwahara</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida-Tanaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeniya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishina</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of blood-brain barrier function by a heteroduplex oligonucleotide in vivo</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>4377</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29531265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-018-22577-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5847588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular uptake and trafficking of antisense oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28244996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.3779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The delivery of therapeutic oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>6518</fpage><lpage>6548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkw236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5001581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular Trafficking and Endosomal Release of Oligonucleotides: What We Know and What We Don’t</article-title><source>Nucleic Acid Ther.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29708838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/nat.2018.0727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5994677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanisms of Antisense Oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acid Ther.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28080221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/nat.2016.0656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5372764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endosomal Escape of ASOs Internalized by Stabilin Receptors Is Regulated by Rab5C and EEA1 During Endosomal Maturation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acid Ther.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29437530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/nat.2017.0694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5899299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnane</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edbrooke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiarparin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revenko</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential uptake, kinetics and mechanisms of intracellular trafficking of next-generation antisense oligonucleotides across human cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>4375</fpage><lpage>4392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30927008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkz214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6511877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanowitz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Annexin A2 facilitates endocytic trafficking of antisense oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>7314</fpage><lpage>7330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27378781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkw595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5009748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crooke</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase H1-Dependent Antisense Oligonucleotides Are Robustly Active in Directing RNA Cleavage in Both the Cytoplasm and the Nucleus</article-title><source>Mol. Ther.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2075</fpage><lpage>2092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28663102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ymthe.2017.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5589097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipofectamine RNAiMAX: an efficient siRNA transfection reagent in human embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Mol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18327560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12033-008-9043-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warashina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harashima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small-sized, stable lipid nanoparticle for the efficient delivery of siRNA to human immune cell lines</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>37849</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27892533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep37849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5124971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veedu</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic screening of commonly used commercial transfection reagents towards efficient transfection of single-stranded oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2564</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules23102564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6222501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30297632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sevick-Muraca</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurements of FRET in a Glucose-sensitive Affinity System with Frequency-domain Lifetime Spectroscopy</article-title><source>Photochem. Photobiol.</source><volume>81</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1386</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1562/2005-02-14-RA-440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dye selection for live cell imaging of intact siRNA</article-title><source>Biol. Chem.</source><volume>393</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22628296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/BC-2011-256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Live cell imaging of duplex siRNA intracellular trafficking</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>43</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>4650</fpage><lpage>4660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25870407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkv307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4482072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Järve</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fricker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massing</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalpke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance of siRNA integrity by FRET imaging</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>e124</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17890733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkm694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2094076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raemdonck</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remaut</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demeester</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Smedt</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ analysis of single-stranded and duplex siRNA integrity in living cells</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>45</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>10614</fpage><lpage>10623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16939213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/bi060351b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittrup</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trifonova</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charisse</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchhausen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visualizing lipid-formulated siRNA release from endosomes and target gene knockdown</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>870</fpage><lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26192320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.3298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4663660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tansi</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rüger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabenhold</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiniger</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilger</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Liposomal encapsulation of a near-infrared fluorophore enhances fluorescence quenching and reliable whole body optical imaging upon activation in vivo</article-title><source>Small</source><volume>9</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>3659</fpage><lpage>3669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23650267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/smll.201203211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ur Rehman</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuhorn</surname><given-names>I.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of polyplex- and lipoplex-mediated delivery of nucleic acids: real-time visualization of transient membrane destabilization without endosomal lysis</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><volume>7</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>3767</fpage><lpage>3777</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23597090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/nn3049494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Querbes</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alabi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eltoukhy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurenko</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karagiannis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoncu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficiency of siRNA delivery by lipid nanoparticles is limited by endocytic recycling</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23792629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nbt.2614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3814166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leitch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reijns</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundie</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revuelta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diebold</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA:DNA hybrids are a novel molecular pattern sensed by TLR9</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24514026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/embj.201386117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3989650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kailasan Vanaja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathinam</surname><given-names>V.A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atianand</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skehan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial RNA:DNA hybrids are activators of the NLRP3 inflammasome</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>111</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>7765</fpage><lpage>7770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24828532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.1400075111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4040571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct visualization of RNA-DNA primer removal from okazaki fragments provides support for flap cleavage and exonucleolytic pathways in eukaryotic cells</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>292</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>4777</fpage><lpage>4788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M116.758599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5377794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khristich</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-DNA hybrids promote the expansion of Friedreich’s ataxia (GAA)n repeats via break-induced replication</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>3487</fpage><lpage>3497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29447396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gky099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5909440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nick McElhinny</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lundström</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chabes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome instability due to ribonucleotide incorporation into DNA</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20729855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nchembio.424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2942972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimprich</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>R-Loops as Cellular Regulators and Genomic Threats</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>73</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30735654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molcel.2019.01.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6402819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maizels</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic roles for G4 DNA in the biology of eukaryotic cells</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17146462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nsmb1171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>C.X.G.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobiyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBert</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatoo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoshi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA polymerase III regulates cytosolic RNA:DNA hybrids and intracellular microRNA expression</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>290</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>7463</fpage><lpage>7473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25623070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M115.636365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4367256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yui</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagaya</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytosolic Genomic DNA functions as a Natural Antisense</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>8551</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-018-26487-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5986806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaj</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breakefield</surname><given-names>X.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skog</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumour microvesicles contain retrotransposon elements and amplified oncogene sequences</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21285958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ncomms1180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3040683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Straarup</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisker</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedtjärn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindholm</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbohm</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarup</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ørum</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J.B.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short locked nucleic acid antisense oligonucleotides potently reduce apolipoprotein B mRNA and serum cholesterol in mice and non-human primates</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>7100</fpage><lpage>7111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20615897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkq457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2978335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallajosyula</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>MODULATION OF ALPHA SYNUCLEN EXPRESSION. International patent WO/2012/068405A2</chapter-title><year>2012</year><comment>filed 17 Nov 2011 / published 24 May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mccaleb</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freier</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>ALLELE SPECIFIC MODULATORS OF P23H RHODOPSIN. International patent WO/2016/138353A1</chapter-title><year>2016</year><comment>filed 26 Feb 2016 / published 1 Sep 2016</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of siRNA-mediated silencing of myeloid cell leukelia-1 on the biological behaviors and drug resistance of gastric cancer cells</article-title><source>Am. J. Transl. Res.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>2397</fpage><lpage>2411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26807186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4697718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazebnik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid and facile quantitation of polyplex endocytic trafficking</article-title><source>J. Control. Release</source><volume>247</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28043862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jconrel.2016.12.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental information</title><p id="p0255"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1–S14</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S2. Article plus supplemental information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc7.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0245">We thank Dr. Punit P. Seth (Ionis Pharmaceuticals) for helpful suggestions and meaningful comments. This research was supported by the Basic Science and Platform Technology Programs for Advanced Biological Medicine (20am0401006h0002) to T.Y. from the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100009619</institution-id><institution>Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (AMED; Tokyo, Japan); a JSPS KAKENHI Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (S) (17H06109) to T.Y. and T.N. and (A) (19H01016) to T.N. and T.Y. from the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001700</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (MEXT) of Japan (Tokyo); and <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100008373</institution-id><institution>Takeda Pharmaceutical Company</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (2A308 to T.Y.).</p><sec id="sec5"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0235">D.O. conducted the experiments; D.O., K.A., F.S., K.Y., T.N., and T.Y. designed the experiments; D.O., K.A, and T.Y. wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec6"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0240">T.Y. collaborates with Daiichi Sankyo, Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma, Ono Pharmaceutical, Rena Therapeutics, Takeda Pharmaceutical, Nanocarrier Pharmaceutical, and Toray Industries and serves as an academic adviser for Rena Therapeutics. All other authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0250">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2020.11.022" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.omtn.2020.11.022</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>