
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Technol Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Technol Cancer Res Treat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3299</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">tct</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101140941</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TCT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1533-0346</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1533-0338</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8721398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8721398.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8721398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8721398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34939866</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15330338211064438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_15330338211064438</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Up-frameshift Protein 1 Promotes Tumor Progression by Regulating Apoptosis and Epithelial–Mesenchymal Transition of Colorectal Cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="B">Binlie</given-names></name><degrees>BM</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="fn1-15330338211064438" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="H">Huaiming</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1-15330338211064438" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="D">Danfeng</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaosheng</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiyan</given-names></name><degrees>BM</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6704-1403</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yongming</given-names></name><degrees>MM</degrees><xref rid="aff1-15330338211064438" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="corresp1-15330338211064438" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-15330338211064438">
<label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">485866</institution-id><institution content-type="university">The First Affiliated Hospital of Shantou University Medical College</institution></institution-wrap>, Shantou, People's Republic of China</aff><aff id="aff2-15330338211064438">
<label>2</label>Medical College, Shantou University, Shantou, Guangdong, People's Republic of China</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1-15330338211064438"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="corresp1-15330338211064438">Yongming Zeng, Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital of Shantou University Medical College, 57 Changping Road, Shantou, 515041, People's Republic of China. 
Email: <email>13809290171@163.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">372632</issue-id><elocation-id>15330338211064438</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-05-25 01:25:18.697"><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold>Background</bold>: Recently, accumulating evidence confirmed that up-frameshift protein 1 (UPF1) was aberrantly expressed in various cancers. However, the molecular mechanism mediated by UPF1 underlying colorectal carcinogenesis remains unclear. <bold>Method</bold>: Immunohistochemistry (IHC) and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction analysis were used to determine the expression level of UPF1 in colorectal cancer (CRC) tissues. CCK-8, EdU, transwell assay, and flow cytometry were performed to investigate the biological significance of UPF1. Epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT) and apoptosis associated markers were detected by western blotting. <bold>Results</bold>: We found that UPF1 expression was upregulated in CRC tissues and cell lines. Clinical analysis revealed that high UPF1 expression was positively correlated with advanced stage, lymph node metastasis and shorter survival. Knockdown of UPF1 suppressed cell proliferation and cell cycle progression. Functionally, UPF1 promotes tumor metastasis by inducing epithelial to mesenchymal transition. Further investigations revealed that knockdown of UPF1 promoted apoptosis through triggering DNA damage. <bold>Conclusions</bold>: Taken together, this research revealed that UPF1 plays an oncogenic role in CRC via regulating EMT and apoptosis and may be a potential therapeutic target for CRC.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>up-frameshift protein 1</kwd><kwd>epithelial–mesenchymal transition</kwd><kwd>DNA damage</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group id="award1-15330338211064438"><funding-source id="funding1-15330338211064438">
<institution-wrap><institution>Shantou Science and Technology Bureau</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-15330338211064438">No. 20200930339-6</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts19</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-15330338211064438"><title>Introduction</title><p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third frequent malignancy and is the second leading cause of cancer-related deaths worldwide.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup> Incident rates of CRC rose by 2.2% annually overall.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr2-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
</sup> Although screening and treatments of CRC get advanced recently, majority of patients hold a poor prognosis.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr2-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
</sup> Therefore, better understanding of potential prognosis biomarkers and therapeutic targets is needed to improve survival of CRC patients.</p><p>Up-frameshift protein 1 (UPF1), located at chromosome 19p13.2-p13.11, is a highly conserved and ubiquitously expressed phosphoprotein with RNA/DNA-dependent ATPase and RNA helicase activity.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr3-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
</sup> Depending on its ATPase and helicase activities,<sup><xref rid="bibr4-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bibr5-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> UPF1 serves as the core regulator of nonsense-mediated mRNA decay machinery, which is a RNA surveillance pathway protecting cells from damage by premature termination codons.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr6-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
</sup> Also, UPF1 is involved in cell proliferation and differentiation.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> In addition, UPF1 is required for S phase progression and genome stability, which is essential for DNA damage repair.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> Previous studies have clarified the exact activities of UPF1 in hepatocellular cancer<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup> and gastric cancer,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup> however, UPF1 exact biological activities in human CRC are poorly understood.</p><p>DNA damage is the well-known trigger of the intrinsic apoptosis pathway. Signaling to intrinsic apoptosis due to DNA damage stimuli the release of cytochrome C and activate BCL-2 family, promoting the formation of apoptosome.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Then, procaspase 9 is activated, which in turn activates the executioner apoptosis cleaved caspase 3, leading to the death of cells.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr13-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
</sup> Double strand breaks (DSB) are wildly recognized to be among the most deadly forms of DNA damage, causing genomic unstability.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup> H2AX is considered to be the hallmark of DNA damage and DSB, its phosphorylation is tightly linked to DNA damage repairs.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr15-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
</sup> According to reports, the expression of H2AX is increased in UPF1-depleted cells.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> These observations arise our interest to explore whether and how UPF1 and H2AX are involved in tumorigenesis of CRC and the underlying mechanism driving the relationships with apoptosis.</p><p>In this study, we demonstrated that UPF1 was significantly upregulated in CRC tissues compared with adjacent normal tissues. Subsequently, we investigated the contribution of UPF1 to the proliferation and metastasis of CRC as well as its effect on DNA damage and apoptosis, which provides a new sight for clinical diagnosis and treatment of CRC.</p></sec><sec id="section2-15330338211064438"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section2A-15330338211064438"><title>Colorectal Clinical Specimens and Cell Lines</title><p>Forty-eight pairs of CRC specimens and paired adjacent noncancer tissues were collected from patients of The First Affiliated Hospital of Shantou University Medical College. Tumor staging relies on eighth American Joint Committee on Cancer Tumor-node-metastasis classification (AJCC TNM-8). All the patients who participated in this study had signed the written informed consent voluntarily. The present study was approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of The First Affiliated Hospital of Shantou University Medical College.</p><p>The FHC human normal colorectal epithelial cell line and 4 human CRC cell lines (SW480, SW620, RKO, Caco-2) were cultured with DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Australia origin) in a water-saturated environment at 37 °C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. All the cell lines (FHC, SW480, SW620, RKO, Caco-2) were donated by General surgery laboratory of Southern Medical University.</p></sec><sec id="section2B-15330338211064438"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>Immunohistochemical staining of 48 pairs of CRC tissues and paired normal tissues was performed on 4 μm thick paraffin sections. All the procedures were referred to manufacturer's protocol using an UltraSensitiveTM S-P kit and DAB (Maixinbio, China). Antibody UPF1(dilution of 1:10000, ab109363, abcam) was applied. Cytoplasm stained with brownish yellow is considered positive. The staining paraffin sections were imaged with microscope (200× magnification). Image J software was used to evaluate the immunohistochemistry (IHC) staining. The percent positively stained areas were scored as “1” (0-25%), “2” (26-50%), and “3” (≥50%). The staining intensity was scored as “0” (no staining), “1” (weak), “2” (moderate), and “3” (strong). Then we calculated the sum of the 2 scores. The total score ≤3 was defined as negative expression, while the total score ≥4 was defined as positive expression. All specimens were evaluated by 2 pathologists who were blinded to the patient identity and clinical outcome.</p></sec><sec id="section2C-15330338211064438"><title>Quantitative Real-Time Polymerase Chain Reaction</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from fresh tissue using EasyPure RNA Kit (TransGen) and was reverse-transcribed into cDNA using a PrimeScript RT Master Mix (TaKaRa). Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was performed using SYBR Premix Ex Taq II Kit (TaKaRa) on CFX Connect. β-actin was used as an internal control. The relative expression was evaluated using 2<sup>−ΔΔct</sup> method. The primers used are as follows: β-actin (5’-TGGCACCCAGCACAATGAA-3’; 5’-CTAAGTCATAGTCCGCCTAGAAGCA-3’); UPF1 (5’-AGAGCCTCATGCAGTTCAGCAA-3’; 5’-GGCATCATACATGGCTGTGGTC-3’).</p></sec><sec id="section2D-15330338211064438"><title>Plasmid Constructions and Transfection</title><p>UPF1-shRNAs were designed and synthesized by GeneCopoeia. The sequence of shRNAs used are as follows UPF1-shRNA #1: 5’-GCAGCCACATTGTAAATCACC-3’; UPF1-shRNA #2: 5’-GCGTGGTTTACTGTAATACCA-3’; UPF1-shRNA #3: 5’-CCTATTACACGAAGGACCTCC-3’. CRC cell lines SW620 and RKO were transfected using Lipofectamine 3000 Transfection Reagent (Thermo Fisher). At 48 h after transfection, qRT-PCR and western blotting were used to confirm the expression of UPF1.</p></sec><sec id="section2E-15330338211064438"><title>Cell Proliferation Assay</title><p>CCK-8 assay was used to examine cell proliferation. SW620 and RKO cell lines with UPF1 knockdown were seeded on the 96-well plates at a concentration of 3 × 10<sup>3</sup> of RKO while 5 × 10<sup>3</sup> of SW620 per well with 100 μl DMEM containing 10% CCK-8 solution (CCK-8, Dojindo). Then, each well was cultured for 24, 48, 72, and 96 h. Cells with CCK-8 reagent were incubated for 4 h at 37 °C. Finally, the absorbance value (OD) of 450 nm was read on the microplate reader (Bio-Rad).</p><p>EdU staining was also used to assess cell proliferation. CRC cells seeded in each well of 24-well plates at a density of 4 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well of RKO while 6 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well of SW620 were stained using Meilun EdU cell proliferation Kit with Alexa Fluor 488 (Meilun, Dalian) referring to manufacturer's protocol. Lastly, the cells were imaged with inverted microscope (100× magnification).</p></sec><sec id="section2F-15330338211064438"><title>Transwell Assay</title><p>The migration and invasion of cells were assessed using transwell chamber (0.8 mm) with Matrigel-coated or not. Transfected RKO cells (4 × 10<sup>4</sup>) and SW620 cells (6 × 10<sup>4</sup>) were separately seeded in upper chamber with 100 μl serum-free medium. The lower chamber was filled with 500 μl medium containing 20% FBS. After 48 h, cells trapped in the chamber membrane surface were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min, stained using 0.1% crystal violet for 15 min and imaged with microscope (400× magnification). Migrated and invaded cells of each sample were counted in 5 random fields for statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="section2G-15330338211064438"><title>Flow Cytometric Analyses</title><p>Transfected RKO cells and SW620 cells were collected 48 h after transfection and then stained using cell cycle detection kit (MultiSciences) following the manufacturer's instructions. The percentage of cells in the cell cycle stages was analyzed by a FACSCanto II flow cytometer (BD Biosciences). For the cell apoptosis assays, transfected cells were analyzed using Annexin V-FITC/PI apoptosis detection kit (4A Bio) according to the manufacturer's instructions, cell apoptosis rate was then evaluated by FACSCanto II flow cytometer.</p></sec><sec id="section2H-15330338211064438"><title>Western Blotting</title><p>Total proteins in cells were extracted by radio-immunoprecipitation assay buffer (RIPA) and the proteins concentration was measured using the bicinchoninic acid (BCA) protein assay kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The targeted proteins were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) (5% stacking and 12% separating gels) and transferred onto PVDF membranes which were blocked with 5% bovine serum albumin (BSA) solution for 1 h. Then the polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes with targeted proteins were incubated with primary antibody including UPF1 (dilution of 1:10000, ab109363, abcam), β-actin (dilution of 1:1000, 4ab000001, 4A Biotech), E-cadherin (dilution of 1:1000, #3195, cell signaling), Vimentin (dilution of 1:1000, #5741, cell signaling), H2AX (dilution of 1:1000, #7631, cell signaling), Bax(dilution of 1:1000, #5023, cell signaling), Bcl-2 (dilution of 1:1000, Ab32124, abcam), Caspase3 (dilution of 1:1000, #14220, cell signaling), Cleaved Caspase3 (dilution of 1:1000, #9661, cell signaling), and paired secondary antibody goat anti-rabbit/mouse IgG H&amp;L (HRP) (dilution of 1:2000, SA00001-1/ SA00001-2, Proteintech). Finally, the proteins bands were detected using ECL chemiluminescence system.</p></sec><sec id="section2I-15330338211064438"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All experiments were repeated at least 3 times and the data were expressed as the means ± standard deviation. The data were evaluated using Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and <italic toggle="yes">X</italic><sup>2</sup>-test. And <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 was considered to be significant. Statistical graphs were performed using GraphPad Prism software.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section3-15330338211064438"><title>Results</title><sec id="section3A-15330338211064438"><title>UPF1 Expression is Significantly Upregulated in 
CRC and Correlates with Patients’ Prognosis</title><p>To evaluate the expression and clinical significances of UPF1 in CRC, we first measured its expression level in 48 CRC patients using IHC staining. The results showed that UPF1 was significantly upregulated in CRC tissues compared to adjacent normal tissues (<xref rid="fig1-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A and B</xref>). qRT-PCR was further performed to examine the expression of UPF1 in 48 CRC patients. As shown in <xref rid="fig1-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>, UPF1 expression was higher in CRC tissues than in adjacent normal mucosa. Next, we separated these patients into UPF1 high (n = 23) and low (n = 25) group according to median value. Clinical data showed that aberrant expression of UPF1 was positively associated with the positive lymph node metastasis and TMN stage (<xref rid="fig1-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E and F</xref>, <xref rid="table1-15330338211064438" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Then, we downloaded the data containing 597 patients from the TCGA-COAD dataset. Kaplan-Meier and log-rank test analyses showed that patients with higher expression of UPF1 had significantly shorter overall survival (OS) (<xref rid="fig1-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>UPF1 expression is upregulated in CRC tissues compared to adjacent normal tissues. (A,B) The protein expression level of UPF1 was detected in 48 pairs of CRC and adjacent normal tissues via IHC staining (200×). (C) Kaplan-Meier curves showed that CRC patients with higher expression of UPF1 had worse overall survival (<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .05, log-rank test). (D) The mRNA expression level of UPF1 was measured in 48 pairs of CRC and adjacent normal tissues via RT-qPCR. (E) Correlation between UPF1 mRNA expression level in CRC patients and clinical TNM stage. (F) Correlation between UPF1 mRNA expression level in CRC patients and lymph node metastasis. *<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .05, **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-fig1.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Relation Between Clinicopathological Features and UPF1 Expression in CRC Patients (n = 48).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-table1.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cases</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">UPF1 expression</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low (n = 25)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High (n = 23)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">.153</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ＜60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">.263</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> I + II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">.007*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III + IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ＜5 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">.571</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥5 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphatic status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">.008*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-15330338211064438"><p>*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;.05</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section3B-15330338211064438"><title>Knockdown of UPF1 Inhibits CRC Cell Proliferation 
and Cell Cycle Progression</title><p>Similarly, qRT-PCR showed that UPF1 expression was higher in a group of CRC cell lines compared with FHC cell line, which is an immortalized normal human colorectal cell line (<xref rid="fig2-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Western blotting further proved the higher expression of UPF1 in CRC cell lines (<xref rid="fig2-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>), especially in SW620 and RKO. Therefore, these 2 cell lines were employed to confirm the oncogene role of UPF1 in vitro. To further investigate the biological function of UPF1, we knocked down UPF1 in SW620 and RKO cells by transfecting specific shRNA against UPF1. The results showed that the mRNA and protein levels were significantly reduced in 2 CRC cells transfected with sh-UPF1-1 and sh-UPF1-2 (<xref rid="fig2-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C and D</xref>). CCK8 and EdU proliferation assays revealed that silencing UPF1 inhibited cell proliferation relative to the negative control (NC) groups (<xref rid="fig3-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>-D). In addition, the cell cycle assays showed that silencing of UPF1 increased the proportion of cells in S phase (<xref rid="fig3-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E and F</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>UPF1 is upregulated in CRC cell lines. (A, B) UPF1 expression level was upregulated in CRC cell lines, especially in RKO and SW620. (C, D) Knockdown efficiency of UPF1 was confirmed via RT-qPCR. N.S., not significant. **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-fig2.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Knockdown UPF1 inhabited cell proliferation and cell cycle of CRC cell lines. (A, B) EdU staining showed that UPF1 depletion inhabited cell growth in RKO and SW620 cells (100×). Scale bar = 200 μm. (C, D) CCK8 assay showed that UPF1 depletion inhabited cell growth in RKO and SW620 cells. (E, F) Flow cytometry analysis showing the proportion of CRC cells in the G1, S, and G2/M phases when UPF1 was silenced in RKO and SW620 cells. **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-fig3.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section3C-15330338211064438"><title>Knockdown of UPF1 Inhibits Cell Migration, 
Invasion, and EMT in CRC Cells</title><p>To further examine the effects of UPF1 on tumor metastasis, we evaluated the biological activity of UPF1 in regulating migration and invasion through transwell assays. As shown in <xref rid="fig4-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, silencing of UPF1 repressed the migration and invasion abilities of SW620 and RKO cells (<xref rid="fig4-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A and B</xref>). As EMT is well known for tumor metastasis, the protein level of EMT markers was evaluated by western blotting. Silencing of UPF1 increased the expression of epithelial marker E-cadherin, while repressed the expression of mesenchymal marker vimentin (<xref rid="fig4-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C and D</xref>). Taken together, our results revealed that knockdown of UPF1 inhibits cell migration, invasion, and EMT in CRC.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Knockdown UPF1 inhabited cell migration, invasion, and EMT in CRC cell lines. (A, B) The ability of cell migration and invasion was inhibited when UPF1 was silenced in RKO and SW620 cells (400×). Scale bar = 200 μm. (C, D) UPF1 depletion upregulated E-cadherin expression while downregulated the expression of N-cadherin and vimentin. **<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .01, ***<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-fig4.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="section3D-15330338211064438"><title>Knockdown of UPF1 Promotes Apoptosis by Inducing DNA Damage in CRC</title><p>According to the study by Azzalin and his colleagues, UPF1 was essential to DNA stability, and DNA damage might be triggered by silencing of UPF1.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr16-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup> Previous studies had demonstrated that UPF1 was involved in apoptosis regulation,<sup><xref rid="bibr10-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> however, whether UPF1 could regulate apoptosis through triggering DNA damage promotes us to explore the underlying mechanism in CRC cells. As shown, the expression of DNA damage marker H2AX was significantly upregulated when UPF1 was silenced in SW620 and RKO cells (<xref rid="fig5-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C and D</xref>). Then, apoptosis flow cytometry analysis (FACS) showed that UPF1-knockdown induced apoptosis in the 2 cells (<xref rid="fig5-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A and B</xref>). We also evaluated the expression of apoptosis markers in cells transfected with UPF1-shRNA. The results showed that knockdown of UPF1 increased the pro-apoptosis marker BAX protein expression while decreased the anti-apoptosis marker Bcl-2 protein expression. In addition, cleaved caspase 3 were upregulated in UPF1-knockdown CRC cells compared to control cells, while the protein levels of procaspase 3 were not significantly altered (<xref rid="fig5-15330338211064438" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C and D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5-15330338211064438" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Knockdown UPF1 promoted cell apoptosis by triggering DNA damage. (A, B) Knockdown UPF1 induced apoptosis in RKO and SW320. (C, D) Western blotting analysis of H2AX protein expression and apoptosis marker proteins following transfection of UPF1-shRNA. ***<italic toggle="yes">P </italic>&lt; .001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_15330338211064438-fig5.jpg"/></fig><p>In addition, DNA mismatch repair (MMR) is also implicated in apoptosis after DNA damage.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr17-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
</sup> In order to explore the relationship between UPF1 and MMR proteins, we performed analysis using GEPIA database. As shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/15330338211064438" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Figure S1</ext-link>, expression of UPF1 was positively correlated with MMR proteins including MLH1, MSH2, MSH6, and PMS2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/15330338211064438" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Fig. S1 A-D</ext-link>). Therefore, we concluded that knockdown of UPF1 caused damage to DNA, and consequently promoted apoptosis in CRC cells.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section4-15330338211064438"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study showed that UPF1 was upregulated in CRC tissues and cell line. Moreover, high expression promoted cell growth and metastasis of malignant CRC cells, which agreed with the clinicopathological parameter. The expression of UPF1 was associated closely with TMN stages and lymphatic penetration in CRC. Therefore, our data demonstrated that UPF1 has a potential to act as a prognostic biomarker for CRC. However, more samples should be included to determine the clinical value of UPF1 in CRC.</p><p>EMT is recognized to be a crucial mechanism that plays an important role in cancer invasion and metastasis.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr16-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</sup> In this process, cells which lose epithelial characteristics gain migratory and invasive properties.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr18-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</sup> Our study elucidated that knockdown of UPF1 increased expression E-cadherin with reduced expression of Vimentin. These data suggested that UPF1 could activate process of EMT in CRC, leading to the enhanced metastasis. Tumor budding is a highly aggressive subpopulation of tumor cells with migratory and invasive capacities.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr19-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</sup> According to researches of Gurzu et al., EMT was associated with the tumor-budding degree in CRC. Budding degree could be used to evaluate EMT in CRC.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bibr21-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> However, whether UPF1 was correlated with tumor budding and the mechanism behind EMT are unclear, which should be further investigated in the following research.</p><p>Previous studies have demonstrated that UPF1 was essential in various biological processes including embryonic and brain development.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr22-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</sup> In Drosophila melanogaster, UPF1 loss-of-function suppressed cell growth and triggered apoptosis.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> However, dysfunction of UPF1 also contributed in tumorigenesis through regulating apoptosis. Actually, how UPF1 inducing apoptosis still remains unclear. As Azzalin and his colleagues mentioned, UPF1 was necessary to genome stability and UPF1-depletion might trigger DNA damage.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> In our study, we found that UPF1 silencing induced DNA damage response and increased the proportion of cells in S phase. Intriguingly, apoptotic rate in UPF1-depleted cell was significantly increased. It is known that intrinsic apoptosis pathway signal could arise from DNA damage.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr12-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
</sup> Taken together, we concluded that UPF1-depletion regulated apoptosis through inducing DNA damage. However, more downstream functional experiments still determine to be clarified in the following research.</p><p>Actually, the function of UPF1 is required for genome stability and is dual in tumorigenesis. Chang et al. clarified that UPF1 could suppress HCC invasion, migration, and proliferation through activating the TGF-β/Smad pathway by eliminating LncRNA SNHG6.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr25-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
</sup> Whereas, Shao and his colleagues demonstrated that UPF1 increased cell viability and promoted metastasis via enhancing the stability of Linc-00313 in glioma.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr26-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</sup> Our results showed that knockdown of UPF1 suppressed the malignant biological behaviors of CRC cells via triggering DNA damage. It seems that UPF1 phosphorylated by different kinases lead to different DNA or RNA metabolism processes. On the one hand, phosphorylated by SMG-1, UPF1 recognizes targeted mRNA and then works with UPF2/UPF3 to trigger the decay of aberrant RNA.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> On the other, modified by ATR phosphorylation, UPF1 is essential in DNA stability.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr24-15330338211064438" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</sup> Herein, we elucidated regulatory roles of UPF1 in CRC. However, whether DNA damage caused by UPF1 knockdown was induced by ATR phosphorylation in CRC cells should be further investigated in the future.</p></sec><sec id="section5-15330338211064438"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study suggested that the upregulation of UPF1 in tumor tissues was significantly correlated with poor prognosis. Furthermore, UPF1 depletion was involved in CRC progression through activated apoptosis and EMT progression. All the results indicated that UPF1 played an important role in CRC carcinogenesis and may serve as a potential target for CRC diagnosis and therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" specific-use="figshare"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material id="supp1-15330338211064438" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-1-tct-10.1177_15330338211064438 - Supplemental material for Up-frameshift Protein 1 Promotes Tumor Progression by Regulating Apoptosis and Epithelial–Mesenchymal Transition of Colorectal Cancer</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-1-tct-10.1177_15330338211064438.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-1-tct-10.1177_15330338211064438 for Up-frameshift Protein 1 Promotes Tumor Progression by Regulating Apoptosis and Epithelial–Mesenchymal Transition of Colorectal Cancer by Binlie Chen, Huaiming Wang, Danfeng Li, Xiaosheng Lin, Zhiyan Ma and Yongming Zeng in Technology in Cancer Research &amp; Treatment</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to all the patients who participated in this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors received funding through the Shantou Science and Technology Bureau (No. 200624155260702).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval and informed consent:</bold> The present study was authorized by the Research Ethics Review Board of The First Affiliated Hospital of Shantou University Medical College (No. 2020-102). All the patients who enrolled in this research had signed the written informed consent voluntarily.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Yongming Zeng <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6704-1403" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6704-1403</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Supplemental Material:</bold> Supplemental material for this article is available online.</p></fn></fn-group><glossary content-type="abbr"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ATR</term><def><p>ataxia telangiectasia mutated and RAD3-related</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAX</term><def><p>bcl-2-associated X protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BCL-2</term><def><p>B-cell lymphoma-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRC</term><def><p>colorectal cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSB</term><def><p>double strand breaks</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMT</term><def><p>epithelial–mesenchymal transition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FACS</term><def><p>flow cytometry analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCC</term><def><p>hepatocellular cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LncRNA</term><def><p>long noncoding RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MALAT1</term><def><p>metastasis-associated lung adenocarcinoma transcript 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMD</term><def><p>nonsense-mediated mRNA decay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OS</term><def><p>overall survival</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTC</term><def><p>premature termination codons</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SMG-1</term><def><p>suppressor with morphogenetic effect on genitalia-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNHG6</term><def><p>small nucleolar RNAs host gene 6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TGF-β</term><def><p>transforming growth factor beta</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UPF2/UPF3</term><def><p>up-frameshift protein 2/3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZFX</term><def><p>zinc finger protein X</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>53BP1</term><def><p>p53-binding protein 1.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-15330338211064438"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33538338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-15330338211064438"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goding Sauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Colorectal cancer statistics, 2020</article-title>. <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32133645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-15330338211064438"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Applequist</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jäck</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cloning and characterization of HUPF1, a human homolog of the <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> nonsense mrna-reducing UPF1 protein</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>814</fpage>-<lpage>821</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9064659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/25.4.814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC146496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-15330338211064438"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brogna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>mcleod</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Petric</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The meaning of NMD: translate or perish</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>407</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27185236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tig.2016.04.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-15330338211064438"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Neu-Yilik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kulozik</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonsense-mediated decay approaches the clinic</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>801</fpage>-<lpage>808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ng1403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-15330338211064438"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yepiskoposyan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Metze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zamudio Orozco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinschmidt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muhlemann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonsense-mediated mRNA decay in human cells: mechanistic insights, functions beyond quality control and the double-life of NMD factors</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19859661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-009-0177-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11115722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-15330338211064438"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jagannathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The RNA surveillance factor UPF1 represses myogenesis via its E3 ubiquitin ligase activity</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell.</source>
<year>2017</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>251.e6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28669802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.molcel.2017.05.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5536975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-15330338211064438"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Medghalchi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frischmeyer</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rent1, a trans-effector of nonsense-mediated mRNA decay, is essential for mammalian embryonic viability</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/hmg/10.2.99</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-15330338211064438"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Azzalin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lingner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The human RNA surveillance factor UPF1 is required for S phase progression and genome stability</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16488880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cub.2006.01.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-15330338211064438"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>The human RNA surveillance factor UPF1 modulates gastric cancer progression by targeting long non-coding RNA MALAT1</article-title>. <source>Cell Physiol Biochem</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2194</fpage>-<lpage>2206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28942451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000479994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-15330338211064438"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An APAF-1.cytochrome c multimeric complex is a functional apoptosome that activates procaspase-9</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>274</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>11549</fpage>-<lpage>11556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10206961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.274.17.11549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-15330338211064438"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Caspase regulation in Non–small cell lung cancer and its potential for therapeutic exploitation</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2097</fpage>-<lpage>2105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-04-1482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-15330338211064438"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Riedl</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Salvesen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The apoptosome: signalling platform of cell death</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>-<lpage>413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17377525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrm2153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-15330338211064438"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karagiannis</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>El-Osta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Double-strand breaks: signaling pathways and repair mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2137</fpage>-<lpage>2147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15338043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00018-004-4174-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11138614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-15330338211064438"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paull</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rogakou</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchgessner</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gellert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A critical role for histone H2AX in recruitment of repair factors to nuclear foci after DNA damage</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>886</fpage>-<lpage>895</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10959836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0960-9822(00)00610-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-15330338211064438"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thiery</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Acloque</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions in development and disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>139</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>871</fpage>-<lpage>890</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2009.11.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-15330338211064438"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tennen</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haye</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wijayatilake</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arlow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ponzio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gammie</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cell-cycle and DNA damage regulation of the DNA mismatch repair protein Msh2 occurs at the transcriptional and post-transcriptional level</article-title>. <source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23261051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dnarep.2012.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3749301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-15330338211064438"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Epithelial to mesenchymal transition correlates with tumor budding and predicts prognosis in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Surg Oncol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>764</fpage>-<lpage>769</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24975035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jso.23694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-15330338211064438"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zlobec</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lugli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epithelial mesenchymal transition and tumor budding in aggressive colorectal cancer: tumor budding as oncotarget</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>651</fpage>-<lpage>661</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.18632/oncotarget.199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3248128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-15330338211064438"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banias</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Immunohistochemical-based molecular subtyping of colorectal carcinoma using maspin and markers of epithelial-mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source>Oncol Lett</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1487</fpage>-<lpage>1495</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31966075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/ol.2019.11228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6956164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-15330338211064438"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banias</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gurzu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bara</surname><given-names>T</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nuclear maspin expression: a biomarker for budding assessment in colorectal cancer specimens</article-title>. <source>Pathol Res Pract</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>213</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1227</fpage>-<lpage>1230</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28780084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.prp.2017.07.025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-15330338211064438"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karousis</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nasif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Muhlemann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonsense-mediated mRNA decay: novel mechanistic insights and biological impact</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>661</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27173476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/wrna.1357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6680220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-15330338211064438"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente-Crespo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nashchekina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Drosophila Upf1 and Upf2 loss of function inhibits cell growth and causes animal death in a Upf3-independent manner</article-title>. <source>RNA</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>624</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1261/rna.2404211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3062174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-15330338211064438"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Azzalin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lingner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The double life of UPF1 in RNA and DNA stability pathways</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1496</fpage>-<lpage>1498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16861888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/cc.5.14.3093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-15330338211064438"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Upregulation of SNHG6 regulates ZEB1 expression by competitively binding mir-101-3p and interacting with UPF1 in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27702662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.canlet.2016.09.034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-15330338211064438"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>UPF1 Regulates the malignant biological behaviors of glioblastoma cells via enhancing the stability of linc-00313</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>629</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41419-019-1845-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6700115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-15330338211064438"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maquat</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cloning of a novel phosphatidylinositol kinase-related kinase: characterization of the human SMG-1 RNA surveillance protein</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>276</volume>(<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>22709</fpage>-<lpage>22714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.C100144200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-15330338211064438"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kashima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Binding of a novel SMG-1-Upf1-erf1-erf3 complex (SURF) to the exon junction complex triggers Upf1 phosphorylation and nonsense-mediated mRNA decay</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1101/gad.1389006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1361706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>