
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Manag Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Manag Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1404</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cancmanres</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101512700</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cmar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Management and Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8866986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8866986.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8866986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8866986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35221720</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S343602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">343602</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Enhanced Efficacy of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy with Nab-Paclitaxel and Platinum for Locally Advanced Cervical Cancer</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Yu et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Yu et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="XL">Xiao-Li</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="MF">Miao-Fang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="ft0001" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="L">Lin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names initials="SM">Shou-Min</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Malignant Tumor Epigenetics and Gene Regulation, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510120</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510120</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Gynecological Oncology, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510120</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Shou-Min Bai <institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <addr-line>510120</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country>
<phone>Tel/Fax +86-20-34070680</phone> Email baishm@mail.sysu.edu.cn</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">372600</issue-id><fpage>9297</fpage><lpage>9304</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>02</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-05-31 19:25:17.447"><day>31</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021 Yu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yu et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="cmar-13-9297.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Purpose</title><p>We aimed to determine the effect of neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of albumin-bound paclitaxel (“nab-paclitaxel”) and platinum (NACT-nPP) in patients with locally advanced cervical cancer (LACC).</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>Consecutive patients with newly diagnosed, non-metastatic LACC were recruited retrospectively between October 2016 and June 2020 in our hospital. All patients received concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) alone or neoadjuvant chemotherapy. We compared the complete response (CR) rate and 2-year progression-free survival (PFS) between patients receiving NACT-nPP and not receiving regimens or other regimens of neoadjuvant chemotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 195 patients were enrolled (78 in the NACT-nPP group and 117 in the control group). Upon chemoradiotherapy completion, 72 (92.3%) patients in the NACT-nPP group and 96 (82.1%) patients in the other group achieved CR (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042). For patients with squamous cell carcinoma, the NACT-nPP group had superior 2-year PFS than that of the control group (89.7% vs 74.1%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.027, HR = 2.486, 95% CI = 1.077–5.739) whereas for adenocarcinoma, 2-year PFS was 37.5% and 36.5%, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.863). In multivariate analysis, NACT-nPP and stage were independent prognostic factors (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046 and 0.012, HR = 2.357 and 2.499, 95% CI = 1.016–5.465 and 1.216–4.930, respectively). The acute hematological adverse events above grade 3 were manageable in the NACT-nPP group (46.2%, 36/78), and the rate was lower than that in the control group (55.6%, 65/117).</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Compared with CCRT alone, NACT-nPP followed by CCRT could improve the CR rate and 2-year PFS of patients with locally advanced cervical squamous cell carcinoma, and the toxicity was tolerable. NACT-nPP was an independent prognostic factor for 2-year PFS. However, further prospective studies are needed to confirm our results.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>neoadjuvant chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>cervical cancer</kwd><kwd>complete response</kwd><kwd>nab-paclitaxel</kwd><kwd>progression-free survival</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>is no funding</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>There is no funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="10"/><ref-count count="28"/><page-count count="8"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cervical cancer ranks the fourth most common and is the sixth leading cause of cancer-based death in women. Eighty-five percent of new patients are located in developing countries.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> For locally advanced cervical cancer (LACC), concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) is the main treatment modality.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref> However, residual tumor is common after treatment (especially for those with large masses) and imperils tumor control and patient survival. The 5-year overall survival rate of LACC is only 50–75%.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> How to reduce the residual tumor and improve the long-term survival of patients with LACC remain clinical challenges.</p><p>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy (NACT) has been demonstrated to increase the tumor-resection rate and improve the survival of patients with breast cancer and esophageal cancer.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, the role of NACT in treatment of cervical cancer is controversial. It has been reported that NACT can help to implement fertility-sparing surgery or improve the resection and survival rate in cervical cancer.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Conversely, some studies have demonstrated that NACT addition may be inferior to CCRT alone or surgery alone.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Thus, clarifying the effect of NACT on cervical cancer is important.</p><p>Most chemotherapy regimens used previously have been platinum combined with traditional paclitaxel or some non-preferred choice.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Albumin-bound paclitaxel (“nab-paclitaxel”) has several advantages over traditional paclitaxel: higher therapeutic dose, higher distribution in the tumor, and lower toxicity.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> The recommended dose of nab-paclitaxel is almost twice that of traditional paclitaxel. We observed that NACT consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum (NACT-nPP) obtained a higher tumor response rate than that for patients using other regimens.</p><p>Thus, in the present study, we compared the complete response (CR) rate and 2-year progression-free survival (PFS) between patients who underwent NACT-nPP and patients who received no or other regimens of NACT followed by CCRT, retrospectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Patient Characteristics</title><p>Between October 2016 and June 2020, all patients with newly diagnosed, non-metastatic cervical cancer who received radical radiotherapy (including external-beam radiotherapy (EBRT) and brachytherapy) were screened in our hospital. All clinical records were reviewed by the authors.</p><p>The inclusion criteria were: (i) the diagnosis of cervical cancer was confirmed with a biopsy; (ii) no distant metastasis was confirmed by gynecological and imaging examinations; (iii) stage IIA to IIIB; (iv) the radiation dose was not less than the recommended dose; (v) pathology was squamous cell carcinoma, adenocarcinoma, or adenosquamous carcinoma; (vi) age &gt;18 years.</p><p>The exclusion criteria were: (i) patients received surgery; (ii) presence of other cancer types; (iii) pregnant or lactating women; (iv) previous history of radiotherapy; (v) incomplete data on clinical treatment; (vi) imaging or gynecological examination showed obvious invasion of the inner wall of the bladder or rectum, but endoscopic biopsy was not confirmed.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Staging</title><p>All patients received systematic imaging examinations (chest radiography, computed tomography (CT) or ultrasonography of the abdomen, pelvic-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or whole-body <sup>18</sup>F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/CT) to exclude distant metastasis.</p><p>Two experienced gynecological oncologists (&gt;10 years of clinical experience) were consulted to determine disease staging, and disagreement was resoved through discussion. All patients had their disease staged according to the 2018 International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) classification.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Chemotherapy and Radiotherapy</title><p>Patients were divided into two groups. The test arm received NACT-nPP. The control arm received no or other regimens of NACT, such as cisplatin or carboplatin combined with traditional paclitaxel or liposomal paclitaxel. All patients received concurrent platinum-based chemotherapy. Before 2019, traditional paclitaxel combined with cisplatin was used primarily whereas, after 2019, the chemotherapy regimen changed gradually to nab-paclitaxel combined with platinum. Nab-paclitaxel and traditional paclitaxel was delivered, respectively, at a dose of 260 mg/m<sup>2</sup> and 135 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and the cisplatin dose was 50–75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p><p>All patients received EBRT and brachytherapy. Intensity-modulated radiotherapy was used for EBRT with a total dose of 45–50.4 Gy in 25–28 fractions at 1.8 Gy/fraction to the planning target volume. Grossly involved nodes were boosted with an additional 10–15 Gy of highly conformal (and reduced-volume) EBRT. All patients were treated with one fraction daily over 5 days per week.</p><p>Upon near completion of EBRT, a high dose rate of brachytherapy was given using an iridium-192 source. Three-dimensional (3-D) planning was used in the first three fractions, and the remainder was 2-D planning. For 3-D planning, the target volume was contoured on CT according to interstitial needles and intracavitary applicators. If vaginal involvement was over 1/2, the whole vagina was included, otherwise, the upper half of the vagina was contoured. The rectum, bladder, and sigmoid colon were delineated as the organs at risk. The prescription was delivered to the outer edge of the target volume for 3-D planning and point A for 2-D planning. Brachytherapy was applied at a total dose of 30–36 Gy in 5–6 fractions at 6 Gy/fraction, 1 fraction daily over 1–2 days per week.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Evaluation of Tumor Response</title><p>Upon CCRT completion, two experienced gynecological oncologists undertook a complete gynecological examination, respectively, to evaluate the tumor situation. Disagreement was resolved through discussion, and the results were documented. Ultrasound or enhanced CT/MRI of the pelvis were undertaken. According to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1, CR was assessed through gynecological examination and radiography after treatment completion.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Follow-Up and Statistical Analyses</title><p>All patients were evaluated every 3 months during the first 2 years, and every 6 months during the next 3 years, and annually thereafter. All patients were followed up until death or 15 July 2021. For those followed-up &gt;2 years, we collected data until 2 years after treatment initiation. “PFS” was defined as the time from first treatment to the date of disease progression or death as a result of any cause.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Patients who did not experience disease progression or death were censored at the time of the final follow-up.</p><p>Data were analyzed using SPSS 21.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). The <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic><sup>2</sup> test or Fisher’s exact test was used to compare ordinal variables and the CR rate between groups. PFS was estimated using the Kaplan–Meier method, and differences in survival curves were compared by the Log rank test. Univariate and multivariate analyses using the Cox proportional hazards model were undertaken to evaluate the independent significance of predictors. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 (two-tailed) was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Patient Characteristics</title><p>Between October 2016 and June 2020, 241 patients with non-metastastic cervical cancer received CCRT in our hospital. Forty-six patients were excluded due to the reasons listed in the exclusion criteria and 195 patients were enrolled. Of these, 78 patients received NACT-nPP (21, 36 and 21 patients received 1, 2, 3 cycles of NACT-nPP, respectively) and 117 in the control group (63, 22 and 3 patients received 1, 2, 3 cycles of NACT, respectively, and 29 patients received CCRT alone). Traditional paclitaxel or liposomal paclitaxel were the main chemotherapy regimens used in the control group.</p><p>In all patients, the median age was 55 years. At the time of the diagnosis, 132 patients were postmenopausal. The number of patients with stage-II and -III disease was 118 and 77, respectively. Ninety patients had complications, including cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, diabetes mellitus, or severe diseases of the liver, kidneys, or lungs. A total of 105 patients experienced chief complaint symptoms for &lt;3 months before treatment. The histology type included 178 squamous cell carcinomas and 17 adenocarcinomas. The serum level of antigens for squamous cell carcinoma was higher than the cutoff for the upper limit of normal in 139 patients. The distribution of the factors mentioned above was not significantly different between the two arms (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the 195 Patients with Cervical Carcinoma Enrolled in This Study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NACT- nPP<sup>a</sup> (n = 78)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other regimens<sup>b</sup> (n = 117)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.242</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menopausal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage (FIGO 2018)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> III</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complication(s)<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of complaint (months)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.769</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiotherapy duration (days)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in SCCA level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor type</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.147</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Squamous cell carcinoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Adenocarcinoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECOG PS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Patients received neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum followed by concurrent chemoradiotherapy. <sup>b</sup>Patients received concurrent chemoradiotherapy alone or following neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of traditional paclitaxel and platinum or other chemical agents. <sup>c</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values were calculated using the χ<sup>2</sup> test. <sup>d</sup>Including cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, diabetes mellitus, and severe diseases of the liver, kidneys, or lungs.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NACT-nPP, neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum; SCCA, squamous cell carcinoma antigen; ECOG PS, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status; FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>CR and 2-Year PFS</title><p>Through comprehensive assessment, we found that 72 (92.3%) achieved CR in the NACT-nPP group and 96 (82.1%) patients achieved CR in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of Complete Response Between Patients Who Did or Did Not Undergo NACT-nPP</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residual</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NACT- nPP<sup>a</sup> (n = 78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other regimens<sup>b</sup> (n =117)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: <sup>a</sup>Patients received neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum followed by concurrent chemoradiotherapy. <sup>b</sup>Patients received concurrent chemoradiotherapy alone or following neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of traditional paclitaxel and platinum or other chemical agents. <sup>c</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values were calculated using the χ<sup>2</sup> test.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NACT-nPP, neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum; CR, complete response; CCRT, concurrent chemoradiotherapy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Tumor progression occurred in 42 (21.5%) patients (9 in the NACT-nPP group and 33 in the control group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042)). Overall, 18 patients had isolated distant metastasis; 11 patients had local-regional recurrences and 13 patients had local-regional recurrences combined with distant metastases. There was significant difference in 2-year PFS (87.6% vs 70.4%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017, hazard ratio (HR) = 2.383, 95% confidence interval (CI) = 1.139–4.987) between the NACT-nPP group and control group (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). Further subgroup analysis was undertaken according to histology type. We found the NACT-nPP had superior 2-year PFS than that in the control group for squamous cell carcinoma (89.7% vs 74.1%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.027, HR = 2.486, 95% CI = 1.077–5.739 (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). However, this superiority was not observed for adenocarcinoma (37.5% vs 36.5%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.863) (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Two-Year PFS Among All Included Patients and Patients with Squamous Cell Carcinoma</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">NACT-nPP (N)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control Arm (N)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.6% (78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4% (117)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.383</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.139–4.987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup with SCC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7% (74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1% (104)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.077–5.739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subgroup with adenocarcinoma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5% (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5% (13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.237–5.565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.863</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PFS, progression-free survival; SCC, squamous cell carcinoma; NACT-nPP, neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Two-year PFS curve for all 195 patients (<bold>A</bold>), patients with squamous cell carcinoma (<bold>B</bold>) and pateints with adenocarcinoma (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="print-only" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="CMAR-13-9297-g0001.jpg"/></fig></p><p>We conducted univariate and multivariate analysis for 2-year PFS among patients with squamous cell carcinoma. In univariate analysis, only NACT-nPP and stage (FIGO 2018) were associated with PFS (P &lt; 0.05). These two factors and CR were analyzed further in multivariate analysis. NACT-nPP (HR = 2.357, 95% CI = 1.016–5.465, P = 0.046) and stage (FIGO 2018) (HR = 2.499, 95% CI = 1.216–4.930, P = 0.012) were significant independent indicators for PFS. Multivariate survival outcome analyses are summarized in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Multivariate Analysis for 2-Year PFS Among Patients with Squamous Cell Carcinoma</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Univariate Analysis (PFS)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Multivariate Analysis (PFS)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HR (95% CI)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NACT-nPP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.486 (1.077–5.739)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.357 (1.016–5.465)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage (FIGO 2018)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.568 (0.277–5.166)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.499 (1.216–4.930)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.021 (0.358–2.907)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899 (0.315–2.570)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.843</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of complaints</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813 (0.405–1.635)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.562</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiotherapy duration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.800 (0.381–1.681)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.058 (0.534–2.094)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menopause</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.847 (0.442–1.953)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.001 (0.504–1.986)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increase in SCCA level</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.082 (0.469–2.493)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.854</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECOG PS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700 (0.167–2.924)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.164 (0.587–2.309)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: PFS, progression-free survival; FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics; CR, complete response; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; NACT-nPP, neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum; ECOG PS, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Toxicity</title><p>Hematological and gastrointestinal adverse effects were the most common types of acute toxicity, and most events were manageable. Hematological toxicity of grade 3–5 was presented in 100 patients during the entire treatment (35 (44.9%) in the NACT-nPP group and 65 (55.6%) in the control group). One patient using liposomal paclitaxel and carboplatin died shortly after CCRT completion due to thrombocytopenia and hemorrhage. The incidence rate of hematological toxicity above grade 3 in the NACT-nPC group (35/78) was lower than that in the control group (65/117). One patient without hematological toxicity above grade 3 in the NACT-nPP group and control group, respectively, had an intestinal perforation, and recovered after care in the intensive care unit and systemic treatment. Late adverse events in the NACT-nPP group included one case of radiation proctitis and one case of ureteral obstruction. In the control group, one patient suffered a colonic fistula and four cases had a ureteral obstruction.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>CCRT is first-line treatment for patients with LACC,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–6</xref> but the tumor-control rate and long-term survival are unsatisfactory, especially for those with stage-IIIB or -IVA disease, many of whom have a residual tumor, tumor progression or even die shortly after CCRT.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Therefore, reducing the residual tumor and improving survival of such patients are urgent clinical problems that need resolution.</p><p>NACT can lessen the tumor load and involvement of the lymph–vascular space, and increase the sensitivity to radiation.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> For many locally advanced tumors, NACT has been shown to improve tumor control and patient survival, and has become an important part of standard treatment.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, the role of NACT in cervical cancer is unclear, and determination of the role and exploration of the optimal regimens of NACT for LACC are needed.</p><p>We found the patients who received NACT-nPP following by CCRT had a higher CR rate than others upon CCRT completion (92.3% vs 82.1%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.042). Initally, we attributed this observation to the higher therapeutic dose of nab-paclitaxel, the recommended dose of which is 260 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, which is nearly twice that of traditional paclitaxel (135 mg/m<sup>2</sup>). Hence, the advantage of a higher dose translated into a higher rate of tumor regression.</p><p>After treatment completion, the CR rate of the control group was 82.1%, similar to that of patients who received CCRT alone in a previous study.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> This observation could be explained by three main factors: (i) the control group in our study included some patients who underwent CCRT alone; (ii) NACT regimens in this group included traditional paclitaxel or liposomal paclitaxel combined with cisplatin, carboplatin, or other types of platinum, which have been reported to offer no advantage on survival for LACC;<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> (ii) the cisplatin dose intensity in our study was 17–25 mg/m<sup>2</sup>/week, lower than 25 mg/m<sup>2</sup>/week, which is the cutoff value that offers a benefit.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> However, a promising clinical CR rate of 92.3% in the NACT-nPP group was obtained. This value is higher than that reported previously: 56.3–86.54%.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Besides the advantage of a stronger dose intensity of nab-paclitaxel elaborated above, three other factors might also explain this observation: (i) NACT reduced the tumor volume, and a massive tumor has more chance to be covered completely with a radical radiation dose; (ii) NACT decreased the hypoxia of tumor cells and increased their radiation sensitivity;<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> (iii) the radiotherapy process from visiting the physician to CT simulation, delineation of the target volume, as well as planning, verification and starting radiotherapy took (on average) &gt;1 month. During this period, patients undergoing CCRT alone did not receive any treatment, whereas patients undergoing NACT received chemotherapy usually 1 week after the visit and started the radiotherapy process simultaneously. One-to-two cycles of NACT were carried out upon radiotherapy initiation. Therefore, patients with NACT followed by CCRT received treatment earlier than those who had CCRT alone.</p><p>The treatment response to NACT is an independent risk factor of the prognosis for patients with LACC.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> A meta-analysis involving 13 studies found that the clinical response to NACT was associated with longer overall survival (HR = 3.36, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) and disease-free survival (HR = 2.36, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.00001), and the pathological response also predicted favorable overall survival (HR = 5.45, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.00001) and disease-free survival (HR = 3.61, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.00001).<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In another study, 58.9% of patients with stage-IB2–IIA2 disease receiving platinum-based NACT achieved a response and 8.7% of patients achieved a pathologic CR. NACT responders showed significantly better overall survival (HR = 2.453, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024) and PFS (HR = 2.196, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.013).<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Unfortunately, in multivariate analysis, the improved CR was not an independent prognostic factor (HR = 0.899, 95% CI = 0.315–2.570, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.843). This inconsistency was explicable: the previous studies evaluated the treatment response to NACT before radical treatment, whereas we evaluated the treatment response upon CCRT completion. Thus, the CR rate was much higher than that in previous studies and reflected the combined effect of NACT and CCRT, but not the effect of NACT alone. Besides, most of the previous studies reported the pathological response, whereas we evaluated the clinical response.</p><p>Patients in the NACT-nPP group had superior PFS (87.6% vs 70.4%, P = 0.017). This result is in accordance with a meta-analysis of 18 randomized trials comparing NACT with radical radiotherapy alone. The authors found that NACT addition could improve survival for LACC in trials with chemotherapy cycle lengths ≤14 days or a cisplatin dose intensity ≥25 mg/m<sup>2</sup>/week (HR = 0.83, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046).<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> In another meta-analysis involving early or advanced cervical cancer, NACT addition could improve overall survival (HR = 0.77, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) and PFS (HR = 0.75, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008) of patients undergoing radical surgery.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Marita et al retrospectively analyzed the objective response, overall survival, and disease-specific survival of LACC patients. They found that NACT followed by CCRT resulted in higher response rates and improvements in disease-free survival and disease-specific survival compared with that using CCRT alone.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Conversely, some studies deemed NACT to be detrimental to patients. Da Costa et al found that, compared with CCRT alone, addition of NACT comprsing cisplatin and gemcitabine was associated with inferior 3-year PFS (40.9% vs 60.4%, HR = 1.84; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033) and overall survival (60.7% vs 86.8%; HR = 2.79; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.006), with even lower response rates discovered upon treatment cessation (56.3% vs 80.3%; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008).<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Upon subset analyses, the NACT-nPP group showed superior 2-year PFS in patients with squamous cell carcinoma (89.7% vs 74.1%, P = 0.027) but not adenocarcinoma (37.5% vs 36.5%, P = 0.863). In multivariate analysis, beside of the stage (FIGO 2018), the NACT-nPP (HR = 2.357, 95% CI = 1.016–5.465, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046) were the only two independent prognostic risk factors for 2-year PFS. This result is in accordance with a study that suggested CCRT benefits the survival of only postoperative patients with squamous cell carcinoma, but not those with adenocarcinoma.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The higher 2-year PFS rate of squamous cell carcinoma than that of adenocarcinoma may be due to the histopathological characteristics of greater malignancy. In addition, the small number of patients (n = 17) with adenocarcinoma may also have led to deviation of survival results.</p><p>The nab-paclitaxel dose was higher than that used for traditional paclitaxel, which improved the CR rate of the tumor but did not improve acute or chronic adverse events. Conversely, possibly because of preventive use of polyethylene glycol recombinant human granulocyte colony-stimulating factor, the hematological toxicity was lower. Besides hematological toxicity, grade-1–2 diarrhea was also common, which could be relieved after symptomatic treatment. In addition, NACT-nPP did not increase long-term toxicity.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Compared with CCRT alone, NACT-nPP followed by CCRT could improve the CR rate and 2-year PFS of patients with locally advanced cervical squamous cell carcinoma, and the toxicity was tolerable. NACT-nPP was an independent prognostic factor for 2-year PFS. However, further prospective studies are needed to confirm our results.</p></sec></body><back><sec id="s0006"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>LACC, locally advanced cervical cancer; NACT-nPP, neoadjuvant chemotherapy consisting of nab-paclitaxel and platinum; CCRT, concurrent chemoradiotherapy; NACT, neoadjuvant chemotherapy; CR, complete response; FIGO, International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics; EBRT, external beam radiotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s0008"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>The datasets for this study has been uploaded in the additional files section.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Ethics Approval</title><p>This retrospective study was approved by the Ethics Committees of Sun Yat-sen Memorial Hospital, Sun Yat-sen University, and the requirement to obtain informed consent was waived [SYSEC-KY-KS-2021-108]. All the data were analyzed anonymously. This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s0009"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors indicated no financial disclosures or potential conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>KD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname>
<given-names>HE</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2021</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CA Cancer J Clin</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33433946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferlay</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soerjomataram</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dikshit</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cancer incidence andmortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN2012</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>136</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E359</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.29210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25220842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bundy</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Concurrent cisplatin-based radiotherapy and chemotherapy for locally advanced cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1144</fpage>–<lpage>1153</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199904153401502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eifel</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pelvic radiation with concurrent chemotherapy compared with pelvic and para-aortic radiation for high-risk cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>340</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1137</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199904153401501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lanciano</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Calkins</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bundy</surname>
<given-names>BN</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Randomized comparison of weekly cisplatin or protracted venous infusion of fluorouracil in combination with pelvicradiation in advanced cervix cancer: a gynecologic oncology group study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>33</issue>):<fpage>8289</fpage>–<lpage>8295</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2004.00.0497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16230678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Chemoradiotherapy for Cervical Cancer Meta-Analysis Collaboration</collab>. <article-title>Reducing uncertainties about the effects of chemoradiotherapy for cervical cancer: asystematic review and meta-analysis of individual patient data from 18 randomized trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>5802</fpage>–<lpage>5812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2008.16.4368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2645100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Differences in the outcomes and complications between elderly and younger uterine cervical cancer patients treated by definitive radiotherapy - A propensity score-matched study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gynecol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2017.02.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28274568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>da Costa</surname>
<given-names>SCS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonadio</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>GabrielliF</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy with cisplatin and gemcitabine followed by chemoradiation versus chemoradiation for locally advanced cervical cancer: a randomized Phase II trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>33</issue>):<fpage>3124</fpage>–<lpage>3131</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.00674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31449470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mougalian</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soulos</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Killelea</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Use of neoadjuvant chemotherapy for patients with stage I to III breast cancer in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2544</fpage>–<lpage>2552</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.29348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sjoquist</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Smithers</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Survival after neoadjuvant chemotherapy or chemoradiotherapy for resectable oesophageal carcinoma: an updated meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>681</fpage>–<lpage>692</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70142-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21684205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfai</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kroep</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gaarenstroom</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Fertility-sparing surgery of cervical cancer &gt;2 cm (International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics 2009 stage IB1-IIA) after neoadjuvant chemotherapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Gynecol Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ijgc-2019-000647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31744889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fröbe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bokulić</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High-dose-rate brachytherapy and concurrent chemoradiotherapy followed by surgery for stage Ib-IIb cervical cancer: single institution experience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anticancer Res</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3861</fpage>–<lpage>3866</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24982415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Maheshwari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Parab</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy followed by radical surgery versus concomitant chemotherapy and radiotherapy in patients with stage IB2, IIA, or IIB squamous cervical cancer: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>1548</fpage>–<lpage>1555</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2017.75.9985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29432076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Roles of albumin-binding proteins in cancer progression and biomimetic targeted drug delivery</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chembiochem</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>1796</fpage>–<lpage>1805</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201800201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29920893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brachmann</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>XP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Albumin-bound nanoparticle (nab) paclitaxel exhibits enhanced paclitaxel tissue distribution and tumor penetration</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Chemother Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00280-015-2833-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4768222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhauer</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Therasse</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bogaerts</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>New response evaluation criteria in solid tumours: revised RECIST guideline (version 1.1)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2008.10.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Optimizing randomized phase II trials assessing tumor progression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Contemp Clin Trials</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cct.2006.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dancey</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recommendations for the assessment of progression in randomised clinical trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2008.10.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19097775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>McCormack</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kadalayil</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hackshaw</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A phase II study of weekly neoadjuvant chemotherapy followed by radical chemoradiation for locally advanced cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>108</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2464</fpage>–<lpage>2469</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.2013.230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23695016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3694233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy for locally advanced cervical cancer reduces surgical risks and lymph-vascular space involvement</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chin J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5732/cjc.011.10050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21880186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4013327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy for Locally Advanced Cervical Cancer Meta-analysis Collaboration</collab>. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy for locally advanced cervical cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of individual patient data from 21 randomised trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Cancer</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2470</fpage>–<lpage>2486</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-8049(03)00425-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14602133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acquired treatment response from neoadjuvant chemotherapy predicts a favorable prognosis for local advanced cervical cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>e0530</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000010530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29703026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5944488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Panici</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Scambia</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Greggi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and radical surgery in locally advanced cervical carcinoma: a pilot study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obstet Gynecol</italic></source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3 Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2450323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The efficacy and response predictors of platinum-based neoadjuvant chemotherapy in locally advanced cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Manag Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>10469</fpage>–<lpage>10477</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CMAR.S270258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33122946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7588671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rydzewska</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tierney</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vale</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy plus surgery versus surgery for cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>CD007406</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007406.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23235641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7175775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marita</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ordeanu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rancea</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term survival following neoadjuvant chemotherapy and concomitant radiochemotherapy in locally advanced cervical cancer: results of the oncology institute “Prof. Dr. Ion Chiricuta” experience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Life</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29696064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5909945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prognostic analysis of uterine cervical cancer treated with postoperative radiotherapy: importance of positive or close parametrial resection margin</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Radiat Oncol J</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3857/roj.2015.33.2.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26157680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4493422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dávila Fajardo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Os</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Post-operative radiotherapy in patients with early stage cervical cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gynecol Oncol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2014.04.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24784874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>