
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Anaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Anaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1246</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sjanaesth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101500601</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Journal of Anaesthesia</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1658-354X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0975-3125</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8477783</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8477783.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8477783</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8477783</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34658729</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/sja.sja_472_21</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJA-15-419</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A comparative study of the efficacy of Glidescope versus Macintosh direct laryngoscopy for intubation in pediatric patients undergoing cardiac surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zabani</surname><given-names initials="I">Ibrahim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlHarbi</surname><given-names initials="M">Mohammed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlHassoun</surname><given-names initials="A">Abdulkarim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names initials="S">Shafat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Amoudi</surname><given-names initials="D">Dareen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AlOtaibi</surname><given-names initials="S">Sultan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names initials="H">Hasan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Anesthesiology, King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Center, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ibrahim Zabani, Prince Saud Al Faisal, Ar Rawdah, Jeddah - 23433, KSA. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="izabani@gmail.com">izabani@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">390899</issue-id><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-08 21:25:12.860"><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2021 Saudi Journal of Anaesthesia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="SJA-15-419.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The Glidescope is a novel, portable, reusable video laryngoscope that has provided superior laryngeal visualization to facilitate tracheal intubation, especially in the management of difficult airways. In this study, we aimed to compare the efficacy of the Glidescope (video-laryngoscope) against the Macintosh direct laryngoscope.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methods:</title><p>Fifty patients were randomly selected via simple randomization using computer-generated random numbers, and sorted into two groups of 25 patients: the Glidescope group and the Macintosh group. We included pediatric patients undergoing cardiac surgery for the repair of congenital heart disease. Those with suspected difficult intubation, preterm babies with low body weight, and patients at risk of aspiration were all excluded.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Patients’ baseline demographic and clinical characteristics were found to be comparable in the two groups. The mean intubation time was 24.1 ± 13.6 s in the Glidescope group, as compared to 18.1 ± 5.9 s in the Macintosh group. Blade insertion was easy in 92% and 96% of the patients in the Glidescope and Macintosh groups, respectively. Tracheal intubation was considered easy in 84% of the Glidescope group, compared to 92% of the Macintosh group. There was a statistically significant correlation between the ease of tracheal intubation and the used intubation method (rho = –0.35; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014).</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Our findings indicate that the Glidescope can be used as an efficient modality for obtaining successful intubations with no complications. Ease of tracheal intubation was the only outcome that was found to be affected by the used modality. Further investigations with proper sample sizes are needed.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Airway</kwd><kwd>general anesthesia</kwd><kwd>intubation</kwd><kwd>laryngoscopy</kwd><kwd>pediatric</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Successful tracheal intubation is a very necessary skill for the management of critically ill patients. The glidescope has been developed to facilitate the tracheal intubation process with ease in all scenarios.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Previous studies reported superiority of the glidescope in comparison to the standard direct laryngoscope.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Furthermore, cardiac surgeries are usually associated with an increased risk of developing complications that can worsen the prognosis of the relevant patient and increase their risk of morbidity and mortality.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Therefore, reduced hospital stay and intensive care unit (ICU) admissions, in addition to early extubation and mobilization are encouraged in these patients to reduce the risk of the development of potential complications and to alleviate the economic burden.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Maintaining adequate and competent airways during intubation is a priority for anesthesiologists. A previous review by Cook <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] indicated that adverse events related to the management of airways during anesthesia for patients with cardiac arrests are the main cause for half of these cardiac events. Although most tracheal intubations are easily performed with no impairment of the airways, it has been reported that up to 8.5% of anesthesiologists may find it difficult to maintain proper airway management during intubation. This can lead to the development of serious complications such as mortality due to hypoxemic brain damage.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Other complications can also include laryngospasm, bronchospasm and dental damage as a result of fierce and repetitive intubation. Therefore, it was essential to address this experience of performing anesthesiologists and to enhance the quality of the equipment that is used for the delivery of the intubation process.</p><p>The Macintosh laryngoscope is commonly used for performing tracheal intubation and is often associated with difficult intubation in 1-4% of cases.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] As a result, the Glidescope video laryngoscope (GVL, Glidescope®, Saturn Biomedical Systems Inc.) has been developed for use in cases of difficult intubation processes.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Previous studies have shown its superiority over the Macintosh laryngoscope technique.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] However, the comparison between the two modalities in terms of intubation time is controversial. Previous studies have shown that the GVL can significantly increase the period of intubation.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] However, other investigations have reported that the intubation time difference between the two modalities is not significant,[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and some even reported that GVL may significantly reduce the intubation period.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] GVL is also not always affordable and cannot be obtained in the required sizes and shapes to suit all patients.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Few studies have investigated the differences between the Macintosh laryngoscope and GVL in pediatric cardiac surgeries. We aim to compare the efficacy of the Glidescope versus Macintosh direct laryngoscopy for intubation in pediatric patients undergoing cardiac surgery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Study design and population</title><p>This is a randomized control study that included 25 patients in each group to detect a difference of at least 12 s in intubation between the two groups with a significant level of 0.05, and a power of 80%. Data collection was conducted at King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Center in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. Fifty patients were randomly selected via simple randomization using computer-generated random numbers into two groups – the Glidescope group and the Macintosh group – with 25 patients in each group. The study was concluded upon the completion of the required sample size. We included pediatric patients undergoing cardiac surgery for the repair of congenital heart disease. The patient's body weight had to be within the range of 3 to 30 kg. Those with suspected difficult intubation, preterm babies with low body weight, and patients at risk of aspiration were all excluded. The study was reported using the CONSORT statement for randomized control trials.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Study procedures</title><p>The anesthetic techniques were standardized; patients were premedicated via midazolam 0.03 mg/kg IV. Induction of anesthesia was done via Ketamine 1.5- 2.5 mg/kg IV, Fentany l 5-10 μg/kg. Endotracheal intubation was performed using Rocuronium as a muscle relaxant with a dose of 0.5 mg/kg IV. Intubation was conducted by one senior anesthesiologist, to exclude variation in intubation skills, and the choice of the intubation device was dependent on the randomization program. The second operator was responsible for monitoring the time taken for intubation in seconds, the incidence of desaturation, incidence of airway injury, the ease of intubation, and recording the data in the excel spreadsheet alongside the patient medical number and name.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data was collected, coded, tabulated, and analyzed using the SPSS 26.0 statistical package. Continuous variables were represented as means and standard deviation and nominal variables were presented as counts and percentages. The skewness and Kurtosis tests were used for testing the normal distribution of continuous variables. To compare patients based on the intubation method used, the Chi-square test (or Fisher's exact test, when appropriate) was used for categorical data while an independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test was used for normally distributed continuous variables, and the Mann–Whitney H test was used for continuous variables not normally distributed. Moreover, the Spearman rank correlation coefficient (rho) was used to determine the relationship between the endotracheal intubation method and patient outcomes. Statistical significance was considered when the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> was &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Ethical consideration</title><p>The study was approved by King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Center Institutional Review Board (IRB) with approval number RC-J/483/40. An informed written consent was obtained from the guardian of the patients who were enrolled in the study to include their data in the study without revealing any personal information. All methods were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations Declaration of Helsinki 1975. In addition, the clinical trial was registered in the UMIN Clinical Trials Registry (UMIN-CTR) with registration number UMIN000044474.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>Patients’ baseline demographic and clinical characteristics were found to be comparable in two groups, with no statistically significant differences [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]. The mean age in the Glidescope group was 29.3 ± 37.0 months, as compared to 25.2 ± 30.6 months in the Macintosh group. Similarly, the mean BMI in the Glidescope group was 14.6 ± 2.3 Kg/m<sup>2</sup>, as compared to 13.9 ± 2.5 Kg/m<sup>2</sup> in the Macintosh group. All patients included in the study had a Class II Mallampati classification and most (Glidescope group = 88%; Macintosh group = 72%) did not have any anatomical abnormalities.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline demographic and clinical characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Treatment group</th><th align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">GlideScope</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Macintosh laryngoscope</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (months); mean±SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">29.3±37.0</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">25.2±30.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (Kg/m<sup>2</sup>); mean±SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">14.6±2.3</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">13.9±2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mallampati classification</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Class II</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical abnormalities</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior larynx</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.241</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Down syndrome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ellis-van Creveld syndrome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midface Hypoplasia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SD: Standard deviation</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All measured outcomes are summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The mean intubation time was 24.1 ± 13.6 s in the Glidescope group, as compared to 18.1 ± 5.9 s in the Macintosh group. Blade insertion was easy in 92% and 96% of the patients in the Glidescope and Macintosh groups, respectively. For ease of tracheal intubation, it was considered easy in 84% of the Glidescope group, compared to 92% of the Macintosh group. As for the quality of the view, it was excellent in most of the Glidescope group (84%), similar to the Macintosh group (88%). The Cormack–Lehane grade during laryngoscopy was I/II in 19/6 patients in the Glidescope group and was I/II in 16/9 patients in the Macintosh group. Intubation was attempted only once in the majority of the Glidescope group (96%) and most of the Macintosh group (88%). No complications were recorded in either group.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of outcomes among different intubation methods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Endotracheal intubation method</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">GlideScope</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Macintosh laryngoscope</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intubation time (seconds); mean±SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">24.1±13.6</td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">18.1±5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ease of blade insertion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Easy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ease of tracheal intubation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Easy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficult</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Challenging</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality of view</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excellent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cormack-Lehane grades</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade II</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of intubation attempts</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">One</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SD: Standard deviation</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The correlation analysis showed a statistically significant correlation between the ease of tracheal intubation and the intubation method used (rho = –0.35; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014). However, the correlation between other outcomes and the used intubation method did not reach statistical significance [<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Correlation between measured outcomes and different intubation methods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation results</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endotracheal intubation method</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intubation time (seconds)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.185</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ease of blade insertion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ease of tracheal intubation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality of view</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cormack-Lehane grades</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of intubation attempts</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spearman’s rho</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.537</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Statistically significant</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we evaluated the differences between Glidescope and Macintosh direct laryngoscopy for intubation in pediatric patients undergoing cardiac surgery, in terms of efficacy and clinical outcomes. Our results indicate that there are no apparent differences between the two groups in terms of complications, the number of intubation attempts, and ease of blade insertion. A previous study by Jafra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reported that the Glidescope group showed better laryngeal views and intubation difficulty scores when compared to the Macintosh laryngoscopy group in an adult population undergoing elective surgeries. Another randomized trial by Choi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] also reported that in the Glidescope group, the percentage of glottis opening was significantly increased when compared to the Macintosh laryngoscopy group. Moreover, the Glidescope group had a significantly lower visual analog score and reduced intubation time than the other group, which indicated the superiority of the modality. Similar findings were also reported by a randomized simulation trial by Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, no complications were noticed in the two groups. However, some cases have been previously published that report a possible incidence of laryngeal trauma, potential pharyngeal injury and infections.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] Previous studies have shown that the rate of successful intubation was similar between the two groups, ranging between 95.5 and 100% for both modalities.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] First attempts at successful intubation processes were also comparable between the two groups. Jafra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reported that the rate of first attempts was significantly higher in the Glidescope group. In contrast, Choi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] reported that similar rates of first successful intubation processes were found across the two groups. Ibinson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] also indicated that Glidescope was significantly more efficient at obtaining successful intubation rates from first attempts, as compared to the direct laryngoscopy group.</p><p>The results of the correlation analysis shown that ease of tracheal intubation may be the only factor that can significantly affect the success of intubation via either of the two modalities. A previous investigation by Ayoub <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] reported that more successful intubations could be obtained when using the Glidescope over the Macintosh laryngoscopy when both modalities were performed by inexperienced medical students. This indicates that the Glidescope may be easier to use to perform successful intubation processes. Previous reports have also shown that the Cormack–Lehane grading was significantly enhanced with the Glidescope group than the conventional group,[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] which is consistent with our findings.</p><p>We also found that the time of intubation was longer in the Glidescope group than the Macintosh direct laryngoscopy group. This finding is consistent with the findings of previous investigations.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] However, other reports have shown that the period may be similar between the two modalities,[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and further reports have even reported that using the Glidscope can significantly reduce the time needed for performing successful intubation.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] The difference in the findings of these various reports may be attributed to many factors. First, the difference of experience between the anesthesiologists that used both modalities in the different studies could be a potential factor, which indicates the need to recruit anesthesiologists that are adequately experienced in order to ensure a better and sufficient judgment. Second, the difference in the camera scope may also constitute a reason for the differences. Third, observing the monitor is essential to viewing the vocal cords when using the Glidescope, whereas it can be easily done via simple visualization when using the Macintosh laryngoscopy. The structure of the Macintosh blade is also different, which can raise some issues when performing intubation. These factors should be considered by future investigations for a better validation of the evidence and better judgment of the differences in efficacy between the two modalities.</p><p>Although no significant differences in the baseline characteristics were observed between the two groups, our study was limited by the small sample size of both groups, which prevented us from adequately validating our reported findings. Therefore, future investigations are encouraged to enroll adequate populations for better validation and estimation of the potentially correlated factors for the efficacy of both modalities. Moreover, we recommend that the previously discussed factors, including the experience of the performing anesthesiologists of both modalities, should also be considered for a better judgment on the efficacy of either modality.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our findings indicate that the Glidescope can be used as an efficient modality for obtaining successful intubations with no complications. However, we found that the intubation time was longer in the Glidescope group than the Macintosh laryngoscopy group. Ease of tracheal intubation was the only outcome that was found to be affected by the used modality. Further investigations with proper sample sizes are needed.</p><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabiner</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daswani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khine</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of GlideScope videolaryngoscopy to direct laryngoscopy for intubation of a pediatric simulator by novice physicians</article-title><source>Emerg Med Int 2013</source><year>2013</year><comment>407547</comment><comment>doi: 10.1155/2013/407547</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2013/407547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3833063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24288617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dexmedetomidine: A review of applications for cardiac surgery during perioperative period</article-title><source>J Anesth</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24913070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00540-014-1857-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doenst</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargenda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirov</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moschovas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tkebuchava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Safarov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac surgery 2018 reviewed</article-title><source>Clin Res Cardiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30929035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00392-019-01470-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast track cardiac surgery pathways: Early extubation, process of care, and cost containment</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1998</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9637632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-199806000-00002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittnacht</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hollinger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast-tracking in pediatric cardiac surgery--the current standing</article-title><source>Ann Card Anaesth</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0971-9784.62930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frerk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major complications of airway management in the UK: Results of the Fourth National Audit Project of the Royal College of Anaesthetists and the Difficult Airway Society. Part 1: Anaesthesia</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2011</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21447488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aer058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of difficult intubation</article-title><source>Eur J Anaesthesiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11270007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.0265-0215.2000.00777.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benumof</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of the difficult adult airway. With special emphasis on awake tracheal intubation</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>1991</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1087</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1824555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/00000542-199112000-00021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakles</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical and video laryngoscopes for emergency airway management</article-title><source>Intern Emerg Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18274712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11739-008-0101-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early clinical experience with a new videolaryngoscope (GlideScope) in 728 patients</article-title><source>Can J Anaesth</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03027728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serocki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dörges</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of the predicted difficult airway: A comparison of conventional blade laryngoscopy with video-assisted blade laryngoscopy and the GlideScope</article-title><source>Eur J Anaesthesiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19809328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/EJA.0b013e32832d328d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of ease of intubation with the GlideScope or Macintosh laryngoscope by anaesthetists in simulated easy and difficult laryngoscopy</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2005</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2044.2004.04038.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narang</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldeg</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medzon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of intubation success of video laryngoscopy versus direct laryngoscopy in the difficult airway using high-fidelity simulation</article-title><source>Simul Healthc</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SIH.0b013e318197d2e5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the GlideScope video laryngoscope and Macintosh laryngoscope in simulated tracheal intubation scenarios</article-title><source>Emerg Med J</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18434462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/emj.2007.052803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrzejowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the performance of four laryngoscopes in a high-fidelity simulator using normal and difficult airway</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19710072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aep232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirabayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GlideScope videolaryngoscope reduces the incidence of erroneous esophageal intubation by novice laryngoscopists</article-title><source>J Anesth</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20108005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00540-010-0872-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of traditional versus video laryngoscopy in out-of-hospital tracheal intubation</article-title><source>Prehosp Emerg Care</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20199237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/10903120903537189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanazi</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Alami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rameh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Khatib</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tracheal intubation following training with the GlideScope compared to direct laryngoscopy</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><year>2010</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20497150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2044.2010.06335.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the Airtraq (R) optical laryngoscope as a rescue airway device following failed awake flexible fiberoptic nasotracheal intubation of a patient with severe microsomia: A case report</article-title><source>Korean J Anesthesiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gombar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective randomized controlled study to evaluate and compare GlideScope with Macintosh laryngoscope for ease of endotracheal intubation in adult patients undergoing elective surgery under general anesthesia</article-title><source>Saudi J Anaesth</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/sja.SJA_543_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5875217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative study on the usefulness of the Glidescope or Macintosh laryngoscope when intubating normal airways</article-title><source>Korean J Anesthesiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21716906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4097/kjae.2011.60.5.339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3110292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications associated with the use of the GlideScope videolaryngoscope</article-title><source>Can J Anaesth</source><year>2007</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17197469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF03021900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The clinical assessment of Glidescope in orotracheal intubation under general anesthesia</article-title><source>Minerva Anestesiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kheterpal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brambrink</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine clinical practice effectiveness of the Glidescope in difficult airway management: An analysis of 2,004 Glidescope intubations, complications, and failures from two institutions</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2011</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21150569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/ALN.0b013e3182023eb7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warriner</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umedaly</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moult</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GlideScope video laryngoscope: Randomized clinical trial in 200 patients</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2005</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aei041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GlideScope video laryngoscopy versus direct laryngoscopy in the emergency department: A propensity score-matched analysis</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e007884</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2015-007884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4431126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25968006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibinson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezaru</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cormican</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangione</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GlideScope use improves intubation success rates: An observational study using propensity score matching</article-title><source>BMC Anesthesiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>101</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1186/1471-2253-14-101</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25400507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2253-14-101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4233079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maharaj</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harte</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffey</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized controlled trial of the Pentax AWS, Glidescope, and Macintosh laryngoscopes in predicted difficult intubation</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aep266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maharaj</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harte</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffey</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of Macintosh, Truview EVO2, Glidescope, and Airwayscope laryngoscope use in patients with cervical spine immobilization</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2008</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bja/aen231</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>