
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2992</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101672560</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9988470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9988470.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9988470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9988470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36895336</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e12149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(22)03437-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e12149</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effect of overall parental satisfaction on Chinese students' learning engagement: Role of student anxiety and educational implications</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oubibi</surname><given-names initials="M">Mohamed</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="G">Gaoyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fute</surname><given-names initials="A">Antony</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yueliang</given-names></name><email>zhouyl@zjnu.cn</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Teacher Education, College of Education and Human Development, Zhejiang Normal University, Jinhua, 321004, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Key Laboratory of Intelligent Education Technology and Application of Zhejiang Province, Zhejiang Normal University, Jinhua, 321004, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. College of Teacher Education, College of Education and Human Development, Zhejiang Normal University, Jinhua, 321004, China. <email>zhouyl@zjnu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">429787</issue-id><elocation-id>e12149</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-01 04:25:12.463"><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2022 Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Learning engagement is one of the important research contents of learning psychology. The level of learning engagement directly affects students' academic performance and future development. Based on the survey data of primary and secondary school parents and students collated at the beginning of 2019, control factors such as students' gender, school location, parents' education level, total annual family income, parental rearing methods, etc. The study found that parental overall satisfaction can significantly and positively predict students' learning engagement. Mediation effect analysis found that students' anxiety completely mediated the effect on parental overall satisfaction and students' learning engagement. Cultivate good parent-child relationships; Establish positive teacher-student relationships; Build a harmonious relationship with classmates. Families and schools should work together to create an atmosphere conducive to the healthy growth of students.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Parental satisfaction</kwd><kwd>Learning engagement</kwd><kwd>Student anxiety</kwd><kwd>Chinese students</kwd><kwd>Educational implications</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">According to many researchers of social cognition (Mahmoud et al., 2022; Schurz et al., 2021), environmental factors (such as parental satisfaction) can act on individual behaviors (such as learning engagement) through human internal factors (such as anxiety). Previous studies have found that students who experience more anxiety in learning have a lower level of learning engagement [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As a measure of a school's educational level and an indicator of a key factor in student learning, learning engagement has received more and more attention from scholars [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Mystkowska defined learning engagement as the degree of participation and effort of students in the learning process [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; Studies have shown a positive correlation between learning engagement and academic achievement [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The higher the learning engagement, the better the student's academic performance and the learning engagement will also affect mental health [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Under the premise of the level of students, it is of great practical significance to study the students' learning engagement.</p><p id="p0015">However, the family is an important environment that continuously affects the growth and development of individuals, and it is particularly necessary to examine the relevant factors and mechanisms that affect students learning engagement in the family context [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Among family factors, parents, as the closest relationship with their children, mainly through their demonstration and guiding role and children's identification with them [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. Therefore, the overall satisfaction held by parents may positively impact children's behavior, especially learning engagement, and it is necessary to pay attention to the impact of parents' overall satisfaction on learning investment [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In the research model of learning engagement, anxiety is often a mediating variable that impacts learning engagement [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>]. Therefore, this study will explore the relationship between parental satisfaction and students' learning engagement in China through the mediating role of students' anxiety.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Literature review</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Interactive determinism and overall parental satisfaction</title><p id="p0020">Due to the lack of research on the impact of overall parental satisfaction on students' learning engagement among family factors, this study will first analyze other family factors' impact on students' learning engagement. Existing studies have found that individuals' satisfaction positively impacts learning engagement [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. According to the research by Xiong, parental involvement in children's education has a significant positive impact on students' learning engagement and academic performance [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; if parents actively participate in children's learning related to These children's learning engagement may be improved [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; and Weian's research shows that when parents give their children respect, encouragement and support, the greater the student's investment in learning [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; then in the micro family system, the overall satisfaction of parents as an external Stimulation can generate children's inner cognition and have a positive impact on their behavior, that is, learning engagement [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Therefore, we hypothesize that overall satisfaction from parents positively impacts students' learning engagement.<statement id="enun_Hypothesis_1"><label>Hypothesis 1</label><p id="p0025">Parental overall satisfaction has a significant positive impact on students' learning engagement.</p></statement></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>The role of student anxiety</title><p id="p0030">At the beginning of the 20th century, anxiety attracted widespread attention from Western scholars [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. When people socialize, anxiety will inevitably appear, and there is an inevitable connection between the generation and development of self-consciousness and anxiety [<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Student anxiety is a negative emotional reaction produced by students in school situations and is a common psychological phenomenon in the development process of students. The performance of student anxiety is roughly derived from the negative evaluation of teachers, poor peer interaction quality, low learning self-efficacy, etc. As a negative emotion, it will impact learning engagement [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p id="p0035">In recent years, many psychological studies have gradually paid attention to the influence of family environmental factors on students' emotions and explored the correlation between families and individuals. Yuan Guangchao and others believed that family relationships, family quality, family atmosphere, and family education profoundly impact children's mental health. Influence at the same time, parental overprotection, harsh requirements, relationship estrangement, emotional warmth, and severe punishment are also closely related to children's physical and mental growth [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The research of Han Xiaopeng and other scholars has shown that the intimacy, entertainment, organization and resilience of the family environment, interpersonal assistance and family support factors are the protective factors for adolescents' anxiety and the contradiction and control of the family environment are the dangers of adolescents' anxiety factor [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This study will test Hypothesis 2 based on a larger sample.<statement id="enun_Hypothesis_2"><label>Hypothesis 2</label><p id="p0040">Parental overall satisfaction significantly negatively impacts student anxiety.</p></statement></p><p id="p0045">Learning engagement is the degree of participation in behavior, the quality of emotional experience, and the cognitive strategies students use in learning activities. It includes three dimensions: behavioral engagement, emotional engagement, and cognitive engagement [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Studies have shown that personal emotions affect learning engagement [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. For example, Ansong and other scholars have found that parental, peer, and teacher support can affect students' learning engagement [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. When students perceive the support of teachers, they will show a higher level of interest in learning and learning pleasure [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]; students who have a clearer experience of teachers' expectations, teachers' responses, and help will work harder and be more engaged in learning [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. It is also more durable [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. According to Bandura's theory of social cognition, environmental factors (such as parental satisfaction) can affect individual behaviors (such as learning engagement) through internal human factors (such as anxiety). Existing studies have found that students who experience more anxiety in learning have a lower level of learning engagement. In the research model of learning engagement, anxiety is often a mediating variable in learning engagement [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Therefore, we hypothesized that overall parent satisfaction was negatively correlated with student anxiety, and student anxiety was negatively correlated with learning engagement. Hypotheses 3 and 4 are proposed in this study.<statement id="enun_Hypothesis_3"><label>Hypothesis 3</label><p id="p0050">Student anxiety has a significant negative impact on students' learning engagement.</p></statement><statement id="enun_Hypothesis_4"><label>Hypothesis 4</label><p id="p0055">Student anxiety has a mediating effect between parental overall satisfaction and learning engagement.</p></statement></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Research model</title><p id="p0060">Some studies have found that different family factors have different predictive power on students' future planning exploration and investment [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and family SES (that is, Socioeconomic status, which usually includes parents' education level, parents' occupation, and family income) has a significant impact on parents' investment significantly affected. In families with different socioeconomic statuses, there are differences in the impact of parental involvement on students' learning engagement [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, when testing the above four hypotheses, this study uses family SES (parental education level, parental occupation, annual family income) and parenting style as the main control variables. We hypothesized that, after controlling for variables such as parental education level, parental occupation, annual income, and parenting style, this study explores the relationship between parental satisfaction and students' learning engagement in China through the mediating role of students’ anxiety. More details in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Research model of the effect of parental satisfaction on learning engagement and the mediating effect of student anxiety.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Research methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Data sources</title><p id="p0065">This study uses the data from the “Survey of Parents and Students in Primary and Secondary Schools” compiled in early 2019, which was carried out by the Teacher Education Research Center of Hubei Province. The survey was conducted by stratified cluster sampling. First, schools were selected, then classes were selected, and finally, all students and parents in the sampled classes were investigated by questionnaire. The sample covers 28 units (counties, districts and cities), one of China's most representative data in the field of education. All procedures performed in studies involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical committee of the local university, Zhejiang Normal university, College of Teacher Education (No. 20210069), and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration. The sampling map is shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>.<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Map of 28 units (counties, districts and cities) sampled.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0070">A total of 7419 questionnaires were collected from students and parents in this study. After data cleaning, 3298 completely matched parents' children survey samples were obtained. The sample covers three groups: primary school, middle school and high school. Among them, 1601 (48.5%) are male students, and 1697 (51.5%) are female students. The survey sample information is shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic information of the survey samples.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Level</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female （%）</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male （%）</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total（%）</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primary School</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">662（20.0）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">771（23.4）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1433（43.5）</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Middle School</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">707（21.4）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">685（20.8）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1392（42.2）</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High School</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">232（7.1）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">241（7.3）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">473（14.3）</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total（%）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1601（48.5）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1697（51.5）</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3298（100）</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Variable description</title><sec id="sec4.2.1"><label>4.2.1</label><title>Explained variables</title><p id="p0075">Learning engagement is the explained variable of this paper. The learning engagement scale was translated and revised by Li Xiying and others. Each item is scored on a 7-point Likert scale ranging from 1 to 7: never, hardly ever, rarely, sometimes, often, very often, and always. The higher the total score of the entire scale item, the higher the learning engagement [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The Cronbach's alpha coefficient of the 17 items is 0.96.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2.2"><label>4.2.2</label><title>Core explanatory variables</title><p id="p0080">The parents' overall satisfaction is the core explanatory variable of this paper, a survey of parents' overall satisfaction in the family. Parents' overall satisfaction can be measured in a single-dimensional way, from overall well-being, interpersonal relationships, socioeconomic status, life satisfaction, job satisfaction, confidence in the future life, and children's educational satisfaction. The total score indicates Overall parental satisfaction. Specifically, use “How do you think your happiness is now?” to measure overall happiness and score from the least happy to the happiest; use “How do you think you live in harmony with others?” To measure the quality of interpersonal relationships, scored on a 5-point scale from very poor to very good; measured perceived socioeconomic status on a 5-point scale from very low to very high using “What do you think your family's socioeconomic status is local?” How satisfied are you with your life, your work, and your current children's education?” Measure life satisfaction, work satisfaction, and children's education satisfaction, and score from very dissatisfied to very satisfied; Confidence in your future life is measured by “how confident you are in your future”, with a 5-point scale ranging from very low to very confident. The higher the score is, the higher the overall parental satisfaction. The Cronbach's alpha coefficient for 7 items is 0.82.</p><p id="p0085">This study also examined student anxiety's direct and mediating effects on learning engagement. Student anxiety refers to the emotions that students experience in the school environment. There are 13 items to measure students' anxiety levels: teacher-student relationship, peer relationship, academic performance, physical appearance, etc. Specifically, the teacher-student relationship dimensions are: the teacher does not like me, the teacher does not teach me well, the teacher criticizes me; the peer relationship dimension There are: unpopular with classmates, criticized by classmates, bullied by classmates, broken friendship with classmates, etc.; academic performance dimensions include: academic performance, study pressure, undeveloped potential, and inefficient learning methods; physical appearance dimensions include: appearance and body healthy. Each item is scored on a 5-point scale from 1 to 5: never, rarely, usually, often, always. The higher the score, the higher the anxiety level of the student. The Cronbach's alpha coefficient of the 13 items is 0.913.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2.3"><label>4.2.3</label><title>Control variables</title><p id="p0090">The control variables selected in this paper mainly come from students' individual and family levels. Student-level variables include gender and school location; Family-level variables include parents’ education level, occupational prestige, total annual family income, parenting styles, and annual family income.</p><sec id="sec4.2.3.1"><label>4.2.3.1</label><title>Student-level control variables</title><p id="p0095">The school location is a dichotomous variable: rural townships and cities; parents' educational level is divided into below junior college, college, and above. This study classifies parental occupations into two categories according to social capital and cultural capital: high social and cultural capital and low social and cultural capital. The former includes professional and technical personnel (such as doctors and engineers), responsible for party and government agencies or enterprises and institutions Persons, university teachers, primary and secondary school teachers, journalists or literary and artistic workers, and military personnel; the latter includes civil servants, workers, commercial and service workers, self-employed workers, unemployed, and others.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2.3.2"><label>4.2.3.2</label><title>Family level control variables</title><p id="p0100">The annual household income is obtained by asking parents, “what was your family's total income in the past year” in the questionnaire. In this study, parents' answers are compiled into two categories: less than 50,000 yuan and 50,000 yuan and above. Parenting Styles In the questionnaire of this study, the “Simple Parenting Style Questionnaire (s-EMBU-C)" revised by Jiang Xian et al., in 2010 was used [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The scale consists of three dimensions. Composition: emotional rejection, emotional support and overprotection, including 21 items. Each item is scored on a 4-point scale, with 1–4 never sometimes representing, often, and always. The Cronbach's alpha coefficient of the three dimensions of the paternal part and the maternal part of the scale was between 0.74 and 0.84, and it had good construct validity and criterion-related validity. More details regarding the study items in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>.<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Measurement tools and study items score.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0105">SPSS22.0 was used for descriptive statistics and regression analysis, and the multiple linear regression model was used to examine the relationship between parents' overall satisfaction and students' anxiety on learning engagement, to examine the direct effects of parents' overall satisfaction and students' anxiety on learning engagement; Amos and Its Bootstrap mediating effect test method analyzes the mediating effect of student anxiety on parents' overall satisfaction and learning engagement. . The significance level was set at 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><label>4.4</label><title>Study quality control</title><p id="p0110">Common method variation refers to the artificial co-variation between variables caused by the same data sources, raters, measurement environment, test item context, and test item characteristics, resulting in unstable results. To check whether there is common method bias in this study, we used Harman's univariate test and found that the maximum explanation ratio of the variance of the first common factor was 32.21%, indicating that the questionnaire method does not have a serious common method bias.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Results and discussions</title><sec id="sec5.1"><label>5.1</label><title>Descriptive statistics and correlations of parents’ overall satisfaction, learning engagement, and student anxiety</title><p id="p0115">To understand the status and relationship between parents' overall satisfaction, learning engagement, and students' anxiety, descriptive statistics were used to obtain each variable's mean and standard deviation, as well as the pairwise correlation matrix. The results are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlations of parents' overall satisfaction, learning engagement, student anxiety and other variables.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">V（n = 3298）</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1. Father's Education</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.Mother's Education</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.650∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.Father Occupation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.478∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.351∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4. Mother Occupation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.362∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.442∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.428∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5. Family Income</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.321∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.314∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.227∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.198∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6. Learning engagement</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.082∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.088∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.047∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.084∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7. Student Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.062∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.091∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.014</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.037∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.047∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.295∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.Overall satisfaction of parents</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.122∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.130∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.091∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.074∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.259∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.234∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.13∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average value</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.55∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.89∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.22∗∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.028</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.369</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.278</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.802</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.165</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.899</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.428</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: ∗∗at the 0.01 level (two-tailed), the correlation is significant; ∗at the 0.05 level (two-tailed), the correlation is significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0120">Learning engagement, one-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test with inspection value of 68, t = 52.309, p &lt; 0.001; student anxiety, one-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test with inspection value of 39, t = −32.202, p &lt; 0.001; overall parental satisfaction, with a one-sample <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test with a inspection value of 21, t = 67.739, p &lt; 0.001.</p><p id="p0125">From the research data in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, it can be concluded that parents' overall satisfaction in learning investment is significantly higher than their respective mean values, and students' anxiety is significantly lower than their test values. Emotions are generally low, and students' high engagement in learning is consistent with existing research and the reality of students. Students gradually realize the value of learning, and continuous learning can maintain their competitiveness in the future. Like learning, actively participate in various learning activities, be able to think seriously in the learning process, be diligent in using the brain when encountering difficult problems, dare to face learning difficulties, dare to accept learning challenges, and be willing to increase investment in learning to improve academic performance and obtain Learning competitive advantage, the vast majority of students can maintain a continuous and positive emotional state for learning; at the same time, the anxiety and negative emotions brought to students by the school environment are not always so prominent, which may be related to teachers' morality. Teachers' style and overall school atmosphere are good; parents’ overall satisfaction is relatively high, and parents can create a better family living space for their children.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><label>5.2</label><title>The influence of parents’ overall satisfaction and student anxiety on learning engagement</title><p id="p0130">To observe the changes in the impact of overall parental satisfaction on learning engagement after controlling for other variables, this study included the independent variable groups into the regression model in turn. Model 1 includes overall parental satisfaction, the variables in Model 2 add gender and school location, Model 3 adds annual family income, parent's education level, and parents' occupations, Model 4 adds parenting styles, and Model 5 adds student anxiety. <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presents the multiple linear regression analysis results, the dependent variable is learning engagement, and the regression coefficients in the table are all standardized coefficients.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Multiple linear regression analysis results.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Independent variable</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Regression Model<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall parent satisfaction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.234∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.224∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.119∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.107∗∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender （0-Male，1-Female）</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Location（0-rural，1-urban）</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.094∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.059∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.047∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Family Income</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Father Education（0-Under college，1-college and above）</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mother Education（0-Under college，1-college and above）</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Father's occupation (0-low social capital, 1-high social capital)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mother's occupation (0-low social capital, 1-high social capital)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.013</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parenting Styles - Parental Emotional Support</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.494∗∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.456∗∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parenting Styles - Parental Emotional Rejection</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.057∗∗</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.075∗∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parenting Styles - Overprotective Parents</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.036</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">student anxiety</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.196∗∗∗</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.055</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.064</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.064</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.272</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.306</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">after adjustment R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.055</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.063</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.062</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.270</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.304</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: The β coefficient values in the model are standardized coefficients; ∗p ​&lt; ​0.05, ∗∗p ​&lt; ​0.01, ∗∗∗p ​&lt; ​0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0135">It can be seen from <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> that without controlling for other factors, the overall satisfaction of parents has a significant positive impact on students' learning engagement; but in Model 2, Model 3, Model 4, and Model 5, gender, school location and, annual family income, parent's education level, parents' occupation, parents' rearing style, and students' anxiety, the effect of parents' overall satisfaction on students' learning investment are gradually weakening, but it still has a significant positive impact. Hypothesis 1 gets stronger support. When the student anxiety is further controlled in Model 5, overall parental satisfaction with students' learning engagement drops to 0.063, which means that part of its explanatory power affects learning engagement through the mediating variable of student anxiety. There is a mediating effect between satisfaction and learning engagement, and the mediating effect can be further tested. After controlling for other related factors, student anxiety has a significant negative impact on learning engagement, and Hypothesis 3 proposed in this paper is largely supported.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><label>5.3</label><title>The mediating effect of student anxiety</title><p id="p0140">This paper explores the mediation of student anxiety (representing four sub-dimensions: teacher-student relationship, peer relationship, academic performance, and physical appearance) on overall parental satisfaction (X) and learning engagement (Y), represented by M1, M2, M3, and M4. <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows the structural equation model established using Amos26.0 and the analyzed path coefficients and significance test results. The solid line arrows in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> are the standardized regression coefficients of the previous variables to the latter variables, and the numbers in brackets of the dotted arrows are the standardized regression coefficients of X to Y (p &lt; 0.001); X and M1, M2, M3, M4 pair Standardized regression coefficient for Y (p &lt; 0.001).</p><p id="p0145">Note: M1 represents the sub-dimension 1 Teacher-student relationship in students' anxiety; M2 represents the sub-dimension 2 peer relationship in students' anxiety; M3 represents the sub-dimension 3 Academic performance in students' anxiety; M4 represents the sub-dimension 4 Physical appearances in students' anxiety.</p><p id="p0150">As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, overall parental satisfaction significantly negatively impacts student anxiety (teacher-student relationship, peer relationship, academic performance, and physical appearance), and Hypothesis 2 is supported.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Test model for the mediating effect of student anxiety.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0155">To verify the multiple mediating effects of the above four dimensions of student anxiety, this paper uses the bias-corrected (Bias-corrected) nonparametric percentile Bootstrap procedure in AMOS to test the mediating effect. A random sampling method was used in AMOS to draw 5000 Bootstrap samples from the original data to generate an approximate sampling distribution with 95% confidence intervals for the mediation effect estimated with the 2.5th percentile and 97.5th percentile. If the 95% confidence interval for the indirect effect does not include 0, the mediating effect is statistically significant; if the 95% confidence interval for the direct effect includes 0, it indicates a full mediating effect. <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> is the Bootstrap test results of the mediating effect of student anxiety.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Bootstrap test results of the mediating effect of student anxiety.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">BootSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">BootLLCI</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">BootULCI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X-M1-Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.032</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X-M2-Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.008</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.032</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X-M3-Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.117</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.075</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.165</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X-M4-Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.019</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X-M-Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.161</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.117</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.208</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0160">It can be seen from <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> that the confidence interval for the total effect of parental satisfaction (X) on learning engagement (Y) is 0.017∼-0.208, indicating that there is a significant mediating effect. There is a mediating effect between overall satisfaction and learning engagement.</p><p id="p0165">A detailed analysis of each dimension of learning anxiety shows that the confidence intervals of teacher-student relationship (M1) and academic performance (M3) are: −0.865–0.067, 0.075–0.165, respectively, indicating that the teacher-student relationship and academic performance in students' anxiety are two The mediating effect of the indicator exists significantly; while the confidence interval of peer relationship (M2) and physical appearance (M4) passes through 0, indicating that the mediating effect of peer relationship in student anxiety does not exist significantly, that is, there is a complete mediating effect.</p><p id="p0170">The study concluded that student anxiety played a partial mediating role in parental overall satisfaction and learning engagement. Overall, parental satisfaction positively impacts learning engagement through the direct path and positively impacts learning engagement through the mediating variable of student anxiety.</p><p id="p0175">The study found that overall parental satisfaction was positively correlated with learning engagement. The external environment affected by learning engagement mainly includes the school and family environments. Existing studies have confirmed the impact of school and family environments on learning engagement [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In addition to the family's economic and social status, family upbringing, and social support, the family environment is more important to the overall satisfaction level of the parents, which also has a positive effect on the child's learning engagement level.</p><p id="p0180">The study also found that overall parental satisfaction buffering effect student anxiety. The higher the overall parental satisfaction, the lower the anxiety children experience in the school environment. Consistent with the research hypothesis, one item of overall parental satisfaction involves “satisfaction with their children's current education”. Too much pressure makes children feel more pressure to study. Studies have shown that educational satisfaction relieves students' anxiety/reasonable educational expectations, positively affecting children's learning behavior [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Studies have found that anxiety can hinder students' learning engagement from personal factors that affect learning engagement. Therefore, when parent satisfaction is higher, the anxiety and negative emotions children experience in the school environment will be alleviated, and the reduced anxiety and negative emotions will promote an increase in learning engagement. According to Bronfenbrenner's [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] ecosystem theory, individuals' growth, development, and environment are considered [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The family is the earliest, most direct and most profound micro-system that affects children as a micro-system. With infrequent and in-depth interactions, parents have a dominant position in influencing their children due to their innate advantages and thus become important to others. The personality traits, behavioral models, and overall satisfaction that parents reveal will affect their children's Behavior, especially learning engagement. Therefore, overall parental satisfaction positively impacts learning engagement through the direct and indirect routes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>6</label><title>Conclusions and recommendations</title><p id="p0185">This paper explores the impact of parents' overall satisfaction on students' learning engagement. The empirical results show that: (1) parents' overall satisfaction has a positive impact on students' learning engagement; (2) parents' overall satisfaction has a positive impact on students' learning engagement; Overall satisfaction has a significant negative impact on student anxiety; (3) Student anxiety has a significant negative impact on students' learning engagement. (4) Student anxiety has a mediating effect between parents' overall satisfaction and learning engagement. Parents' overall satisfaction positively impacts learning investment through the direct and indirect paths.</p><p id="p0190">In general, the influencing factors that affect students' learning engagement can be considered from two aspects: individual factors and environmental factors. On the one hand, in terms of individual factors and improving learning ability, improving learning methods, etc., negative emotional factors should also be taken into account to alleviate the frequency of negative emotional experiences. On the other hand, regarding environmental factors, creating a good learning atmosphere, improving the quality of teacher-student and peer relationships, and reducing campus bullying, family factors should also be considered to reshape the overall family satisfaction, which creates a good family living space.</p><p id="p0195">Based on the conclusions of this study, this paper proposes the following measures to promote learning engagement.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>(1)</label><p id="p0200">Develop a good parent-child relationship.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0205">Parents should create a warm family atmosphere for their children, actively communicate and interact with their children, continuously enhance the parent-child relationship, and at the same time try to reduce the incidence of family conflicts; The key content of education is that students should learn to be grateful to their parents, understand their parents, and be filial to their parents; Finally, if parents and teachers find that students have adverse emotional reactions, they should take timely measures to intervene and guide them.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0015"><list-item id="o0015"><label>(2)</label><p id="p0210">Establish a positive teacher-student relationship.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0215">School educators should create a safe psychological atmosphere in the classroom, take the initiative to solve problems for students’ study and life after class, and be good teachers and friends of students; then, teachers have heart-to-heart conversations, actively participate in students activities, home visits, etc. to strengthen the contact between teachers and students, and increase the intimacy between teachers and students; Finally, teachers should pay attention to the signs of tension between teachers and students, and conduct education and guidance in time to reduce the occurrence of conflicts between teachers and students.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0020"><list-item id="o0020"><label>(3)</label><p id="p0220">To build a harmonious relationship with classmates.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0225">Teachers must establish a scientific concept and correctly understand the importance of classmate relationships to the healthy growth of students; Schools must create an environment conducive to the communication of students, such as creating a campus culture that is helpful to others, creating a solidarity and fraternity classroom atmosphere and dormitory atmosphere, etc.; Teachers should timely find students who have difficulty interacting with their classmates and help them. They can invite professional psychological teachers to assist or contact parents for home-school cooperation; Students should actively learn interpersonal knowledge and master interpersonal skills and communication skills, and constantly improve their personality charm.</p><p id="p0230">In a word, families and schools should work together to create a humanistic environment that is conducive to the healthy growth of vocational students, form a synergy of influences from all parties, improve college students’ sense of learning gain and the overall quality of higher education teaching, and truly enable students to learn To achieve and continue to promote the deepening of the development of learning to promote teaching, and constantly optimize the learning engagement structure of college students and constantly improve the current situation of students' anxiety.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>7</label><title>Limitation</title><p id="p0235">There are still some deficiencies in this study. Firstly, the “Parent Overall Satisfaction Questionnaire” is self-designed. Although the reliability and validity of the questionnaire have been tested when it is used, it needs further strict verification. Secondly, students' anxiety in this study is only a general indicator. In the future, internal indicators can be further subdivided to specifically investigate what aspects of students' anxiety are affected by external factors. Thirdly, this study is the data collated in early 2019, and the research conclusion may be different from that after Covid-19. We have collected various data after Covid-19, and in the future, we will further study the differences in students' learning anxiety before and after Covid-19.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec8.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0240">Mohamed Oubibi; Gaoyu Chen Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper. Antony Fute: Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data. Yueliang Zhou: Performed the experiments; Conceived and designed the experiments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec8.2"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0245">Data included in article/supp.material/referenced in article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec8.3"><title>Declaration of interest's statement</title><p id="p0250">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chinese adolescents' achievement goal profiles and their relation to academic burnout, learning engagement, and test anxiety</article-title><source>J. L., Diff. I.</source><volume>83</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101945</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of scientific self-efficacy and cognitive anxiety on science engagement with the “question-observation-doing-explanation” model during school disruption in COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J. J. o. S. E., Technol.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10956-020-09877-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7641485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33169057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang Mingkai</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiaoli</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An empirical study on the relationship between college students' learning engagement and learning self-efficacy</article-title><source>Educ. Acad. Month.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fredricks</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumenfeld</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>School engagement: potential of the concept, state of the evidence</article-title><source>J. R. o. e. r</source><volume>74</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chevrier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lannegrand</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between academic motivation and basic psychological needs within the freshman year context: a longitudinal person-oriented approach</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-021-00569-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between student engagement and academic achievement: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>J. S. B., J. P. a. i.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>528</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngussa</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitriyah</surname><given-names>F.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diningrat</surname><given-names>S.W.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between Facebook use, mental health and learning engagement: a case of universities in Surabaya City, Indonesia</article-title><source>J. T. O. J. o. D. E.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>245</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Descals-Tomás</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocabert-Beut</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abellán-Roselló</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Artiga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doménech-Betoret</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of teacher and family support on university student motivation and engagement</article-title><source>J. I. j. o. e. r., Health</source><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2606</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph18052606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7967384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33807813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antelm-Lanzat</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cacheiro-González</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Navío</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of family support on student engagement: Towards the prevention of dropouts</article-title><source>J. P. i. t. S.</source><volume>58</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Gómez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Araujo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer-Ortíz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pena-Ruiz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gender perspective of parental role model influence on nascent entrepreneurs: Evidence from Colombia</article-title><source>J. E. R. o. M. Econ.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100156</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qunito Romani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parental behaviour and children's sports participation: Evidence from a Danish longitudinal school study</article-title><source>J. S., Educ. Soc.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>347</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soleimanof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Following the footsteps that inspire: Parental passion, family communication, and children’s entrepreneurial attitudes</article-title><source>J. J. o. B. R.</source><volume>128</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>461</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putarek</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlin-Bernardić</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of self-efficacy for self-regulated learning, achievement goals, and engagement in academic cheating</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-019-00443-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O</surname><given-names>I.R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Investigation of the Relationships Among Educational Application (APP) Quality, Computer Anxiety and Student Engagement</part-title><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-l.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.J.C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The Effect of Learning Adaptability on Chinese Middle School Students' English Academic Engagement: the Chain Mediating Roles of Foreign Language Anxiety and English Learning Self-Efficacy</part-title><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardasheva</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contributions of (de) motivation, engagement, and anxiety to English listening and speaking</article-title><source>J. L., Diff. I.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101856</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sayad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Md Saad</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurasamy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How higher education students in Egypt perceived online learning engagement and satisfaction during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J. J. o. C. i. E.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>550</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parental involvement in adolescents' learning and academic achievement: Cross-lagged effect and mediation of academic engagement</article-title><source>J. J. o. Y., Adolesc.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1811</fpage><lpage>1823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10964-021-01460-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34117608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer-Gembeck</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Parental support, peer support and school connectedness as foundations for student engagement and academic achievement in Australian youth</part-title><source>Handbook of Positive Youth Development</source><year>2021</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>236</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weian</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>The Relationship between Parental Support and Learning Involvement of Junior Middle School Students</part-title><year>2020</year><publisher-name>Shandong Normal University</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.27280/d.cnki.gsdsu.2020.001689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dompnier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pansu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A latent profile analysis of teachers' causal attribution for academic success or failure</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-021-00551-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li Xing-bao</surname><given-names>Z.T.-t.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>According to the factors influencing learning anxiety in virtual learning community</article-title><source>J. Distance Educ.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15881/j.cnki.cn33-1304/g4.2016.06.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mollo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacelli</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The worlds' game: collective language manipulation as a space to develop logical abilities in a primary school classroom</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-018-0401-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes of student anxiety during simulation: What the literature says</article-title><source>J. C. S. i. N.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>e507</fpage><lpage>e512</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>G.C.Z.Y.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>R Qiang</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the correlation between depression, resilience and family environment in junior high school students</article-title><source>Psychol. Month.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19738/j.cnki.psy.2022.03.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han Xiaopeng</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between anxiety and family environment and resilience in adolescents</article-title><source>J. Clin. Exp. Med.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>2652</fpage><lpage>2655</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving student engagement</article-title><source>J. C. i. i. e.</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewaele</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher enthusiasm and students' social-behavioral learning engagement: The mediating role of student enjoyment and boredom in Chinese EFL classes</article-title><source>J. L. T. R.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>922</fpage><lpage>945</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reschly</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huebner</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appleton</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antaramian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engagement as flourishing: The contribution of positive emotions and coping to adolescents' engagement at school and with learning</article-title><source>J. P. i. t. S.</source><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>431</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Affuso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zannone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><x xml:space="preserve">…</x><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacchini</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of teacher support, parental monitoring, motivation and self-efficacy on academic performance over time</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-021-00594-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okumu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisensmith</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of parent, classmate, and teacher support in student engagement: Evidence from Ghana</article-title><source>J. I. J. o. E. D.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oubibi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parents' educational anxiety under the “double reduction” policy based on the family and students' personal factors</article-title><source>Psychol. Res. Behav. Manag.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2067</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35983019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/PRBM.S370339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9379115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oubibi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fute</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceived organizational support and career satisfaction among Chinese teachers: the mediation effects of job crafting and work engagement during COVID-19</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>623</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fute</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oubibi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing teaching compassion, work engagement and compassion fatigue among teachers during the pandemic</article-title><source>Psychol. Res. Behav. Manag.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2561</fpage><lpage>2571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36124334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/PRBM.S383292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9482458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R.-D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher support and math engagement: roles of academic self-efficacy and positive emotions</article-title><source>J. E. P.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donche</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fostering cognitive and affective-motivational learning outcomes for high-ability students in mixed-ability elementary classrooms: a systematic review</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-022-00606-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang Ling-ling</surname><given-names>Z.W.-x.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Family socioeconomic status, parenting, parent-child communication and adolescent future planning Journal of Shandong Normal University</article-title><source>Soc. Sci. Ed.</source><volume>66</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>G.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effect of parental participation on children's academic achievement in families with different socioeconomic status</article-title><source>Educ. Dev. Res.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14121/j.cnki.1008-3855.2018.20.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.Y.H.R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Revision of UWES-S scale for college students</article-title><source>Psychol. Res.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhengrong</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Bijing</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preliminary revision of the Chinese version of the simplified parenting style questionnaire</article-title><source>Psychol. Dev. Educ.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16187/j.cnki.issn1001-4918.2010.01.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Students home alone—profiles of internal and external conditions associated with mathematics learning from home</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-021-00590-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoury-Kassabri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Female teachers' coping styles with negative emotions in student aggression</article-title><source>Eur. J. Psychol. Educ.</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10212-021-00573-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronfenbrenner</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Ecological Systems Theory</part-title><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Jessica Kingsley Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>